
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="brief-report"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.2.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art520.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_MMCR126 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Med Mycol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Med Mycol Case Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Medical Mycology Case Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2211-7539</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4246399</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2211-7539(14)00047-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mmcr.2014.10.001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Disseminated Scedosporium prolificans infection in a Labrador retriever with immune mediated haemolytic anaemia </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>Amanda</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Talbot</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bennett</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>Patricia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Makara</surname><given-names>Mariano</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barrs</surname><given-names>Vanessa R.</given-names></name><email>vanessa.barrs@sydney.edu.au</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005">Faculty of Veterinary Science, University of Sydney, Sydney NSW 2006, Australia</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +61 2 9351 3437; fax: +61 2 9351 7436. <email>vanessa.barrs@sydney.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Disseminated scedosporiosis is rare in dogs and is usually reported in German Shepherds with suspected heritable immunodeficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This is the first report of disseminated scedosporiosis due to Scedosporium prolificans in a Labrador retriever dog that was receiving immunosuppressive drug therapy for treatment of immune-mediated haemolytic anaemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Despite cessation of immunosuppressive medications and an initial response to aggressive treatment with voriconazole and terbinafine the dog developed progressive disease with neurological signs necessitating euthanasia six months from diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights"><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Highlights </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>•Disseminated scedosporiosis due to Scedosporium prolificans is described in a dog.•Chronic prednisolone and cyclosporine therapy preceded disseminated scedosporiosis.•Combination therapy with oral voriconazole and terbinafine was prescribed.•Despite an initial response progressive disease occurred. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Canine</kwd><kwd>Scedosporiosis</kwd><kwd>Invasive fungal infection</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0005"><label>1</label><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Infections caused by fungi belonging to the Scedosporium/Pseudallescheria complex (SPCF) in dogs are restricted to a small number of cases including localised infections involving the skin, upper respiratory tract and eyes and disseminated disease [1]. Scedosporium prolificans and Scedosporium apiospermum (teleomorph Pseudallescheria boydii) are the medically significant species in the SPCF [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We report the first case of disseminated mycosis due to S. prolificans in a Labrador retriever dog that was receiving immunosuppressive drug therapy for treatment of immune mediated haemolytic anaemia (IMHA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CASE"><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Case </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>A four-year-old male desexed Labrador retriever was referred to the University Veterinary Teaching Hospital, Sydney (UVTHS) with a four week history of right hind limb lameness and a one week history of multiple ulcerated skin lesions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Ten months previously the dog had been diagnosed with primary immune mediated haemolytic anaemia (IMHA) and was treated with immunosuppressive medication (prednisolone 1.5 mg/kg PO every 12 h; azathioprine 1.25 mg/kg PO every 24 h), and antiplatelet therapy (aspirin 0.6 mg/kg PO every 24 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Following tapering of immunosuppressive medication, the dog represented to the UVTHS three months after initial diagnosis (day −176) with severe recurrent IMHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Prednisolone (1 mg/kg PO every 12 h) and azathioprine (1.25 mg/kg PO every 24 h) were again prescribed with the addition of cyclosporine (5.5 mg/kg PO every 24 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The dog responded well and all drug dosages were tapered slowly over the following seven months (prednisolone 0.125 mg/kg PO every second day; azathioprine 1.25 mg/kg PO every other day). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Cyclosporine was discontinued three months (day −97) prior to presentation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>On presentation to the UVTHS on day 0 the dog weighed 39.7 kg, was in good body condition and had a normal heart rate, respiratory rate and rectal temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>It was lame (grade III/V) on the right hind limb and had multiple ulcerated skin lesions with draining sinus tracts over the head, neck and body (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Pain was elicited on manipulation of the right coxo-femoral joint and mid thoracic spine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Pitting oedema was present distal to the right hock. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Mild bilateral elbow effusion was detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The left pre-scapular and popliteal lymph nodes were palpably enlarged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Given the clinical presentation and previous history of IMHA, differential diagnoses included disseminated bacterial or fungal infection, immune mediated polyarthropathy and dermatopathy as an indication of multisystemic autoimmunity, or systemic lupus erythematous. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>A complete blood count (CBC) and serum biochemistry were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>There was a mild non-regenerative anaemia (haematocrit 0.32 L/L; reference interval: 0.37–0.55 L/L), moderate leucocytosis (23.4×109 /L; reference interval: 7–12×109 /L) primarily due to a neutrophilia (18.95×109 /L; reference interval: 4.06–9.36×109 /L) with a left shit (bands 0.23×109 /L; reference interval: 0–0.24×109 /L) and a mild monocytosis (1.64×109 /L; reference interval: 0.21–0.96×109 /L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Mild elevations in alkaline phosphatase (ALP 261 U/L; reference interval: &lt;110 U/L), alanine transaminase (ALT 86 U/L; reference interval: &lt;60 U/L), total protein (72.8 g/L; reference interval: 50–70 g/L) and phosphate (2.02 mmol/L; reference interval: 0.8–1.6 mmol/L) were noted on serum biochemistry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In addition, total serum calcium (3.43 mmol/L; reference interval: 2.1–2.9 mmol/L) was elevated and ionised calcium was normal (1.28 mmol/L; reference interval: 1.25–1.5 mmol/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>An antinuclear antibody (ANA) titre was negative (&lt;1:25). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Abdominal ultrasound demonstrated increased, but homogeneous echogenicity of the pancreas, consistent with chronic pancreatitis and mild bilateral renal pelvis dilation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>On urinalysis short septate branching fungal hyphae were detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Whole body computed tomography (CT) on day 2 revealed multiple productive bone lesions in the distal portion of the third and eight ribs; lysis of the opposing endplates at thoracic vertebrae 5–6 and sternebrae 2–3 with surrounding bone sclerosis; and irregular periosteal new bone formation associated with the metatarsal and tarsal bones of the right hind limb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The right liver lobes had irregular borders and diffusely heterogeneous post-contrast enhancement in the arterial phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In addition, generalised abdominal, sternal and peripheral lymphadenopathy was seen (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Cytological examination of joint fluid from the right hock and carpus was unremarkable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Fine-needle aspirate biopsies from rib and sternebrae lesions, and impression smears of multiple skin lesion biopsies showed marked pyogranulomatous inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Fungal hyphae were identified in skin lesions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Itraconazole (5 mg/kg PO twice daily) was prescribed on day 3 whilst awaiting fungal culture results and the dog was discharged from hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Immunosuppressive medication doses were reduced then stopped after 5 days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>A suede-like black pigmented fungus was cultured on Sabouraud׳s dextrose agar on day 7 at 28 °C from urine, bone and skin, but not from joint fluid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>On microscopic examination, septate hyphae had basally inflated flask shaped conidiophores with small clusters of conidia consistent with S. prolificans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>A PCR targeting the partial β-tubulin gene was performed using DNA extracted from fungal culture material, as previously described [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The molecular identity was S. prolificans (99% homology with GenBank accession number AJ889591.1) [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The isolate was submitted to the Australian Reference Laboratory in Medical Mycology, Adelaide for susceptibility testing (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Histopathology of skin revealed multifocal pyogranulomatous dermal inflammation with brown pigmented periodic acid-Schiff (PAS) positive irregularly septate hyphae occasionally branching at 90° within inflammatory foci. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Over a three week period the skin lesions improved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Terbinafine (30 mg/kg PO once daily) was added to the treatment regimen on day 16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Following antifungal susceptibility testing results, voriconazole (5 mg/kg PO twice daily), obtained from a veterinary compounding pharmacy was substituted for itraconazole (day 35). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The dog was continued on voriconazole and terbinafine with no clinical side effects noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>After 6 weeks of treatment, all skin lesions had resolved and the hind limb lameness had improved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The dog׳s haematocrit had increased from 0.31 to 0.37 L/L indicating that the IMHA was in remission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Repeat serum biochemistry was unremarkable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The dog was readmitted to hospital approximately 3 months (day 101) later for a repeat CT evaluation, CBC, serum biochemistry and urine culture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>At this time, despite resolution of the right hind limb lameness, the dog had lost 6.7 kg since diagnosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The haematocrit (0.49 L/L) and leucocyte count (9.0×109 /L) were normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>There was moderate hypoalbuminaemia (19.7 g/L; reference interval: 23–43 g/L) with normal total protein (61.5 g/L; reference interval: 50–70 g/L) and globulins (41.8 g/L; reference interval: 27–44 g/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>On repeat CT, bone, liver and lymph node lesions were unchanged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Repeat urine culture was positive for S. prolificans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>A urine protein creatinine ratio was normal (0.2; reference interval: 0.2–0.5), as were pre- and post-prandial bile acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Hypoalbuminaemia was attributed to gastrointestinal losses due to mycotic involvement or concurrent inflammatory bowel disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The owner was reluctant to pursue further diagnostic investigations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Antifungal drugs were continued and the dog was transitioned to a hypoallergenic diet. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The dog remained clinically well for another seven weeks before representing three times over a five week period for recurrent inappetence, pyrexia, dehydration and altered behaviour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>On each occasion, the dog was treated conservatively with intravenous fluids and discharged within 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Repeat biochemistry indicated worsening hypoalbuminaemia (13.8 g/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>During this time the owner sought a second opinion at another small animal specialist practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>A rectal scape demonstrated the presence of fungal hyphae, further mycotic involvement of the gastrointestinal tract. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Six months (day 183) following diagnosis, the dog represented with inappetence and lethargy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Twelve hours following admission, the dog׳s neurological status rapidly deteriorated with abnormalities suggestive of a C1–T2 spinal cord segment or brain stem lesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>It became obtunded, hyperthermic, tachycardic and developed an erratic breathing pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Given the rapid deterioration and poor prognosis, the owners elected to humanly euthanase the dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>A full post mortem was not conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Cerebrospinal fluid collected immediately following euthanasia indicated a mild mononuclear pleocytosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Fungal culture was negative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s0015"><label>3</label><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>This is the first report of disseminated mycosis due to S. prolificans in a Labrador retriever dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Previous reports of disseminated scedosporiosis in dogs have been restricted to German Shepherd dogs (GSD) [5–9], and were due to S. apiospermum infection [5,6,8] except in one case of S. prolificans infection [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>There is a single case reported of disseminated S. prolificans (previously S. inflatum) infection in another breed; a Beagle with osteomyelitis and pulmonary involvement [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Scedosporiosis is considered an emerging disease in human medicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In contrast to S. apiospermum, which is commonly found in soil, sewage and polluted waterways, S. prolificans is more commonly isolated from soil and potted plants and has a more restricted geographical distribution with the majority of cases in humans reported in Australia and Spain [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, one of the two previously reported cases of disseminated S. prolificans infection in dogs also occurred in Australia [7], with the other occurring in New York [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Scedosporiosis in humans represents a broad spectrum of clinical disease including local cutaneous and subcutaneous infection (eumycetoma) that occur secondary to penetration wounds; saprobic involvement of a previously damaged bronchopulmonary tree; invasive pulmonary disease; sinopulmonary and central nervous system infection associated with near drowning׳s in polluted water ways contaminated with P. boydii; and disseminated infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Except for eumycetomas and near drowning׳s infection occurs in people with immune suppression or immune dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>More specifically, disseminated infections are most commonly reported in humans with disorders in innate immunity such as chronic granulomatous disease or in those receiving immunosuppressive drug therapy as a result of haematopoietic malignancies and bone marrow or solid organ transplants [2]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>GSD have an increased susceptibility to disseminated fungal infections, including aspergillosis and scedosporiosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Abnormalities in IgA regulation and function, and dysfunction of cell mediated immunity is suspected [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>No such immune deficiency has been identified in Labrador retrievers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In the Beagle with disseminated scedosporisosis, no underlying immune deficiency or history of immune suppressive medication was noted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>In our case, it is likely that immune suppression induced by treatment for IMHA allowed for opportunistic infection with S. prolificans. The use of glucocorticoids is a well-documented risk factor for developing invasive fungal infections [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Glucocorticoids therapy results in global immune suppression and the risk of infection increases with increasing dose and duration of treatment beyond 21 days [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A history of corticosteroid use and persistent profound neutropenia have been identified as risk factors in developing disseminated S. prolificans infection in humans [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Cyclosporine also has potent immunosuppressive activity, acting by interrupting intracellular signalling, resulting in significant negative effects on T-cell function and cell medicated immunity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Invasive fungal infections are a common complication in humans treated with cyclosporine following solid organ transplant [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In our case, the dose of prednisolone was low at the time of presentation; however the prolonged duration of therapy, initial high doses and combination therapy with azathioprine and cyclosporine, likely contributed to significant immunosuppression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>A similar recent case report from Australia describes a 2 year male desexed Rhodesian Ridgeback dog that developed lymphocutaneous lesions due to S. apiospermum infection whist receiving cyclosporine, azathioprine and prednisolone for IMHA and immune mediated polyarthritis [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In contrast to our case, once immunosuppressive medication was discontinued, the dog was able to clear the infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The route of infection in our case is not clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Humans with disseminated S. prolificans have a high rate of fungaemia that results in fungal embolization of multiple organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Haematogenous spread from primary pulmonary infection is the most common cause of fungaemia, although cutaneous lesions have been noted to precede dissemination in some cases [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>No clear route of infection has been identified in previously reported cases of disseminated disease in dogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>In several cases with osteomyelitis [5,6,9], a penetrating wound or foreign body was suspected but unproven. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>In our case, the dog had ulcerated skin lesion noted five months prior to presentation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The lesions were noted on the forelimbs associated with areas of pressure or wear and were considered likely due to the effects of prednisolone therapy on the skin namely thinning and increased fragility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The skin lesions had healed six weeks prior to initial presentation however this break in integument may have been the route of entry for the fungal infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The dog had no clinical sings attributable to pulmonary disease and mild changes noted on the CT scan of the thorax where more consistent with atelectasis rather than pneumonia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>It seems less likely that dissemination occurred from primary pulmonary disease however this cannot be excluded as previous case reports have only noted disease involving the lungs at the time of post mortem examination [7,9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Polyphagia and pica are common side effects seen in dogs receiving prednisolone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Given this, entry through the gastrointestinal tract as a result of indiscriminate eating patterns is also possible in this case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Gastrointestinal fungal involvement was demonstrated on rectal scape that would support this. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>There is little available information regarding successful treatment of disseminated scedosporiosis in dogs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Treatment with itraconazole was attempted in three previous cases with no success; two dogs were euthanaised within a few weeks of treatment due to lack of improvement [6,9] and the third dog died acutely 5 days after initiation of treatment [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The case of lymphocutaneous infection due to S. apiospermum was successfully treated with itraconazole and terbinafine and cessation of immunosuppressive medication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Success in this case may be due to several reasons; removal of the cause of immunosuppression in an otherwise immunocompetent individual; restriction of infection to the skin; and a less virulent, more anti- fungal responsive isolate, S. apiospermum. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Mortality rates as high as 90% are reported in human with disseminated S. prolificans infection [14]. S. prolificans has a high degree of antifungal resistance with high minimum inhibitory (MICs) values to the majority of available antifungal agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>However, combination therapy using terbinafine with voriconazole, itraconazole or miconazole has been shown to result in synergy in vitro against human clinical isolates of S. prolificans such that MIC values were reduced to clinically achievable levels [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In vitro synergy has also been reported with combinations of amphotericin B and micafungin [16], and voriconazole and micafungin [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Successful treatment has been reported in vivo in clinical cases using combination antifungal therapy with terbinafine and voriconazole [18–20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>However aggressive surgical debridement and/or immune modulation therapy was often used to complement antifungal therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Combination antifungal susceptibility testing is not easily available in Australia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Thus information was extrapolated from studies in humans and used to guide the choice of combination antifungal treatment prescribed in our dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Despite high in vitro MIC (&gt;16 mg/L) for itraconazole, significant and sustained clinical improvement occurred for six months after treatment with combination therapy using itraconazole then voriconazole, combined with terbinafine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>It is also possible that voriconazole, sourced from a compounding pharmacy, was not as efficacious as the non-generic formulation of the drug. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we present a novel case of a Labrador retriever that developed disseminated S. prolificans infection secondary to immunosuppressive drug therapy and demonstrate a partial clinical response to combination therapy with voriconazole and terbinafine. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="s0020"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>1EladD.Infections caused by fungi of the Scedosporium/Pseudallescheria complex in veterinary speciesVet J18712011334120580291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>2CortezK.J.RoilidesE.Quiroz-TellesF.MeletiadisJ.AntachopoulosC.KnudsenT.Infections caused by Scedosporium sppClin Microbiol Rev211200815719718202441 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>3GlassN.L.DonaldsonG.C.Development of primer sets designed for use with the PCR to amplify conserved genes from filamentous ascomycetesAppl Environ Microbiol614199513231330(April 1)7747954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>4GilgadoF.CanoJ.GenéJ.GuarroJ.Molecular phylogeny of the Pseudallescheria boydii species complex: proposal of two new speciesJ Clin Microbiol431020054930494216207945 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>5BaszlerT.ChandlerF.BertoyR.SmithC.WhiteleyH.Disseminated pseudallescheriasis in a dogVet Pathol Online25119889597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>6EladD.PerlS.YaminG.BlumS.DavidD.Disseminated pseudallescheriosis in a dogMed Mycol484201063563819886774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>7HaynesS.HodgeP.TyrrellD.AbrahamL.Disseminated Scedosporium prolificans infection in a German Shepherd dogAust Vet J901–22012343822256983 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>8HugnetC.MarrouB.DallyC.GuillotJ.Osteomyelitis and discospondylitis due to Scedosporium apiospermum in a dogJ Vet Diagn Investig211200912012319139512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>9SalkinI.CooperC.BartgesJ.KemnaM.RinaldiM.Scedosporium inflatum osteomyelitis in a dogJ Clin Microbiol30111992279728001452649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>10DayM.J.PenhaleW.J.An immunohistochemical study of canine disseminated aspergillosisAust Vet J681219913833861807243 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>11CutoloM.SerioloB.PizzorniC.SecchiM.E.SoldanoS.PaolinoS.Use of glucocorticoids and risk of infectionsAutoimmun Rev82200815315518703175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>12HadleyS.SamoreM.H.LewisW.D.JenkinsR.L.KarchmerA.W.HammerS.M.Major infectious complications after orthotopic liver transplantation and comparison of outcomes in patients receiving cyclosporine or FK506 as primary immunosuppressionTransplantation59619958518587535482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>13BrownJ.BennettP.LabucR.MerrettD.Lymphocutaneous infection with Scedosporium apiospermum in a dog on immuno-suppressant therapyAust Vet Pract39220095054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>14RevankarS.G.PattersonJ.E.SuttonD.A.PullenR.RinaldiM.G.Disseminated phaeohyphomycosis: review of an emerging mycosisClin Infect Dis3442002467476(February 15)11797173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>15MeletiadisJ.MoutonJ.W.MeisJ.F.VerweijP.E.In vitro drug interaction modeling of combinations of azoles with terbinafine against clinical Scedosporium prolificans isolatesAntimicrob Agents Chemother471200310611712499177 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>16YustesC.GuarroJ.In vitro synergistic interaction between amphotericin B and micafungin against Scedosporium spp.Antimicrob Agents Chemother49820053498350016048969 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>17HeynK.TredupA.SalvenmoserS.MüllerF-MC.Effect of voriconazole combined with micafungin against Candida, Aspergillus, and Scedosporium spp. and Fusarium solaniAntimicrob Agents Chemother491220055157515916304192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>18BhatS.V.PatersonD.L.RinaldiM.G.VeldkampP.J.Scedosporium prolificans brain abscess in a patient with chronic granulomatous disease: successful combination therapy with voriconazole and terbinafineScand J Infect Dis3912007879017366022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>19HowdenB.SlavinM.SchwarerA.MijchA.Successful control of disseminated Scedosporium prolificans infection with a combination of voriconazole and terbinafineEur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis222200311111312627286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>20WhyteM.IrvingH.O׳ReganP.NissenM.SiebertD.LabromR.Disseminated Scedosporium prolificans infection and survival of a child with acute lymphoblastic leukemiaPediatr Infect Dis J244200537537715818301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Ulcerated skin lesions with draining sinus tracts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>(a) Left antebrachium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>(b) Right lateral aspect of the neck. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Similar lesions were also seen on the left side of the neck, at the base of the right ear and at the lip commissures; and (c) medial aspect of right hind limb. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>CT images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>(a) Sagittal volume rendering maximum intensity projection reconstruction of the thorax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>On the right side of the thorax, a productive lesion, associated with irregular new bone formation can be seen affecting the distal aspect of the third and eight rib at the level of the costochondral junction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>(b) Sagittal reconstructed image of the thorax. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Lysis of the opposing end-plates of thoracic vertebrae 5–6 and sternebrae 2–3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>There is increased bone opacity surrounding the lytic end-plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Spondylosis deformans can be seen associated with the T5–6 lesion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>(c) Axial image of the abdomen at the level of the liver acquired during the arterial phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Right side of the liver presents heterogeneous enhancement and irregular contours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>A 15 mm hypoattenuating lesion can be seen in the caudate lobe during the arterial phase only. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t0005" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Antifungal susceptibility testing results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>R=resistant.</p><p>I=intermediate.</p><p>SDD=susceptible dose dependent.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tbl1fna"><label>a</label><p>S=susceptible.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
