
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4139276</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25141009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-14011</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological Tissue</subject><subj-group><subject>Epithelium</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biophysics</subject><subj-group><subject>Ion Transport</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Developmental Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Development</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytokines</subject><subj-group><subject>Interleukins</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Response</subject><subj-group><subject>Inflammation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Physiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Physiology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>IL-17A Induces Pendrin Expression and Chloride-Bicarbonate Exchange in Human Bronchial Epithelial Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">IL-17 Induces Pendrin in HBE Cells</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>Kelly M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>Valsamma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Spielman</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kolls</surname><given-names>Jay K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rubenstein</surname><given-names>Ronald C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>Gregory E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Noam A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kreindler</surname><given-names>James L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, Children's Hospital of Philadelphia, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Pediatrics, Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>School of Arts and Sciences, University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Departments of Pediatrics and Immunology, University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<addr-line>Department of Cell Biology, University of Miami Miller School of Medicine, Miami, Florida, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<addr-line>Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Perelman School of Medicine at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>Dominik</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Tübingen, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>kreindler@email.chop.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: James Kreindler and Noam Cohen are Academic Editors for PLOS ONE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>This does not alter the authors' adherence to PLOS ONE Editorial policies and criteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: KA VA JK JLK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: KA VA DS JK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: KA VA RR JLK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JK RR GC NC JLK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: KA JLK. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e103263</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Adams et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Adams et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The epithelium plays an active role in the response to inhaled pathogens in part by responding to signals from the immune system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Epithelial responses may include changes in chemokine expression, increased mucin production and antimicrobial peptide secretion, and changes in ion transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>We previously demonstrated that interleukin-17A (IL-17A), which is critical for lung host defense against extracellular bacteria, significantly raised airway surface pH in vitro, a finding that is common to a number of inflammatory diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Using microarray analysis of normal human bronchial epithelial (HBE) cells treated with IL-17A, we identified the electroneutral chloride-bicarbonate exchanger Pendrin (SLC26A4) as a potential mediator of this effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>These data were verified by real-time, quantitative PCR that demonstrated a time-dependent increase in Pendrin mRNA expression in HBE cells treated with IL-17A up to 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Using immunoblotting and immunofluorescence, we confirmed that Pendrin protein expression is increased in IL-17 treated HBE cells and that it is primarily localized to the mucosal surface of the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Functional studies using live-cell fluorescence to measure intracellular pH demonstrated that IL-17A induced chloride-bicarbonate exchange in HBE cells that was not present in the absence of IL-17A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, HBE cells treated with short interfering RNA against Pendrin showed substantially reduced chloride-bicarbonate exchange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that Pendrin is part of IL-17A-dependent epithelial changes and that Pendrin may therefore be a therapeutic target in IL-17A-dependent lung disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by National Institutes of Health K08 HL081080 and by funds from the Children's Hospital of Philadelphia. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. Data are in the Gene Expression Omnibus microarray accession code, GSE10240.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. Data are in the Gene Expression Omnibus microarray accession code, GSE10240.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>IL-17A plays a central role in multiple facets of the immune response of the lung. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Its activity is critical for host defense against extracellular bacteria including Haemophilus influenzae [1], [2] and Staphylococcus aureus [3], [4], [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>For example, in patients with Hyper-IgE syndrome, who lack ThIL-17 cells, Sa skin and lung infections are common [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In mice, loss of ThIL-17-mediated immunity after influenza infection predisposes to Sa pneumonia [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Notably, ThIL-17 cells, the main producers of IL-17A, are found in airways submucosa early in the course of cystic fibrosis (CF) [7], and IL-17A levels are increased in sputum during pulmonary exacerbations of CF and return to normal only after treatment [1], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In addition to a role in host defense, IL-17A and its related family members have a role in the pathophysiology of asthma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In particular, IL-17A is thought to contribute to the neutrophilic airways inflammation seen in severe asthmatics [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Therefore, IL-17A-mediated immune functions are potential targets for therapeutic manipulation in a number of respiratory diseases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Because of the importance of IL-17A in lung host defense, several studies have investigated its effects on airway epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The IL-17 receptor is highly expressed on human bronchial epithelial (HBE) cells [8], [10], in which IL-17A induces transcription of airway mucins [11], antimicrobial peptides [12], and pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines that favor production and influx of neutrophils into the lung [13], [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Epithelial ion transport is closely linked to mucin biology [15], [16], antimicrobial peptide function [17], and inflammation [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we hypothesized that IL-17A may alter epithelial ion transport properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We previously found that IL-17A induced CFTR-dependent HCO3 − secretion in HBE cells [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We also made the observation that IL-17A increased apical surface pH (pHASL) in the absence of exogenous stimuli and without affecting baseline short-circuit current, suggesting that it promoted an electroneutral mechanism that changed surface pH [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The simplest explanation for the observed increase in pHASL in IL-17A-stimulated HBE cells would be either decreased H+ secretion or increased HCO3 − secretion across the apical membrane of the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Microarray analysis had shown that IL-17A strongly upregulated Pendrin expression in HBE cells (data from this array were previously published [1]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Pendrin (SLC26A4) is an electroneutral, HCO3 −-secreting protein, and, thus, a good candidate to mediate the observed effect on pHASL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Pendrin is a member of the SLC26A family of Cl−-dependent anion transporters that are found at the apical plasma membrane of many epithelia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The SLC26A family of integral membrane proteins share common signal transduction and anti-sigma factor (STAS) domains that can interact with and regulate CFTR [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>SLC26A6 (PAT1) mediates CFTR-regulated HCO3 − secretion in the pancreas [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>SLC26A9 is expressed in human airways, but appears to primarily act as a Cl− channel rather than a Cl−/HCO3 − exchanger [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>While SLC26A3, which we do identify in HBE cells at the mRNA level, is reported to mediate CFTR-dependent Cl−/HCO3 − exchange in immortalized tracheal cells [24], others did not detect SLC26A3 mRNA outside of the gastrointestinal tract in ribonuclease protection assays [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, our data suggest that IL-17A reduces SLC26A3 expression, which would be expected to cause a decrease in net HCO3 − transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Therefore, SLC26A3 is not a good candidate to mediate the effects that we observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Pendrin is an electroneutral, Cl−/anion exchanger that can transport HCO3 − [26], [27], iodide (I−) [28], [29], and thiocyanate (SCN−) [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Within the Cl−/HCO3 − exchangers of the SLC26A family Pendrin is unique in its lack of a c-terminal PDZ domain [31], the absence of which may explain its CFTR independence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Pendrin is expressed in many epithelia, including those from lung, thyroid, inner ear, and kidney. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Genetic mutations in Pendrin cause Pendred syndrome (OMIM #274600), a disease characterized by congenital deafness, goiter, and thyroid hormone abnormalities [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The role of Pendrin in human lung physiology or pathophysiology is not yet known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>To date, lung disease has not been described in Pendred syndrome patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we tested the hypothesis that IL-17A specifically increased the expression and function of Pendrin in HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Cell culture </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Normal HBE cells purchased from Lonza (Walkersville, MD) were cultured to maturity at air-liquid interface as previously described (14) (17, 28, 59–60). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Epithelial cells were isolated from airways of CF patients at the time of transplant following protocols (Function and Differentiation of the Airway Epithelium) approved by the University of Miami Institutional Review Board. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Written informed consent was obtained prior to the collection of the samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>RNA was isolated using Qiagen's RNeasy Kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>cDNA was generated with Applied Biosystems High Capacity Reverse Transcription cDNA Kit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was performed using pre-designed primer-probe combinations with Taqman reagents (both Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed by comparative threshold cycle (CT) analysis using GAPDH as the control and normalizing all values to the mean of the control group [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s2b1"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>RNA-seq sample preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Total RNA from HBE cells (1–4 ug) that had or had not been stimulated with cytokines was used as starting material for deep sequencing using the Illumina TruSeq RNA Sample Preparation v2 Guide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Briefly, mRNA was purified with oligo-dT beads, fragmented with magnesium and heat-cataylzed hyrdolysis, and used as a template for first- and second-strand cDNA synthesis with random primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The cDNA 3′ ends were adenylated, followed by adaptor ligation and a 15-cycle PCR to enrich DNA fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Quantification of cDNA libraries was performed by using Kapa Biosystems primer premix kit with Illumina-compatible DNA primers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>For cluster generation, the TruSeq SR Cluster Kit v2-cBot-GA was used, and cDNA libraries were loaded onto the flow cell at a final concentration of 6pM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Single-read sequencing was performed on the Illumina Genome Analyzer II. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Vehicle or IL-17A stimulated HBE cells were lysed with RIPA buffer plus 10 mM Na Orthovandate, 1 mM PMSF, and protease inhibitors (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Lysates were sonicated on ice and centrifuged for clarification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>30 µg total protein were separated by PAGE then transferred to PVDF membranes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting was performed with the anti-Pendrin antibody H-195 (1∶500, Santa Cruz) followed by a HRP-linked goat anti-rabbit antibody (Santa Cruz). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>After detection of Pendrin, membranes were stripped and actin detected as a loading control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>HBE cells were fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde and permeabilized with 0.3% Triton-X100 prior to blocking (1% BSA/5% normal goat). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Primary antibody was applied overnight at 4°C (1∶500 Pendrin; 1∶1000 Type IV Tubulin: Abcam). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibody was applied for 1 h at RT (1∶500 goat anti-rabbit IgG Alexa fluor 594 (Pendrin) plus 1∶750 goat anti-mouse IgG Alexa fluor 488 (Type IV Tubulin). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst at 1∶1000. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>HBE cells loaded with the pH-sensitive dye SNARF-5/6 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) [20] were mounted in a specially designed holder (Bioptechs, Butler, PA) on the stage of an inverted fluorescence microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Cells were bathed on the serosal side and perfused on the mucosal side. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Mucosal solution changes were made using a pinch-valve system (Warner Instruments, Hamden, CT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Intracellular dye was excited with light from a xenon lamp filtered with a 480/20 nm band-pass filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The ratio of fluorescence emissions at 640 nm and 580 nm was captured every 10 or 20 s using a Hamamatsu ORCA-ER camera and SlideBook software (Intelligent Imaging Innovations, Inc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Data were stored on a computer hard drive and analyzed using Prism 5 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Conversion from F640/F580 was performed after calibration of intracellular pH (pHi) at 6.8, 7.2, and 7.6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>siRNA inhibition of Pendrin expression: siRNA duplexes were introduced into epithelial cells using a modification of previously published methods [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Chemicals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Recombinant human IL-17A (R&amp;D Systems) was dissolved in 4 mM HCl and used at 50 ng/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>DIDS (Invitrogen) and niflumic acid (Sigma) were dissolved in DMSO as 1000× stocks and added to the mucosal, chloride-free solution at 100 µM each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>NF-κB inhibitor II (JSH-23) was dissolved as a 1000× stock in DMSO and used at 20 µM. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Values are mean ± S.E.M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Statistical were analyzed with Prism 5, using Student's t-test, two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni posttests, or repeated measures ANOVA as appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Significance was defined as a p≤0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Data from Gene Expression Omnibus microarray accession code, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE10240">GSE10240</ext-link>, are referenced in the results section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>IL-17A directly and specifically induces Pendrin mRNA expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Our microarray data strongly suggested that IL-17A increased Pendrin expression in normal HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>To verify this by quantitative PCR, we stimulated HBE cells with IL-17A at 50 ng/ml for 48 h, which were the conditions used in the microarray and in our previously published data [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Following stimulation, real-time PCR was performed to quantify the relative change in Pendrin expression in IL-17A-treated cells compared with vehicle controls using GAPDH as the reference gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>These data confirmed that IL-17A significantly increased Pendrin mRNA expression (Figure 1a) in a time-dependent manner, with increases appearing by 6 h and maximal at 48 h, the longest time point measured (Figure 1b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0103263-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>IL-17A-dependent induction of Pendrin mRNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A. Mature, well-differentiated HBE cells were stimulated with IL-17A (50 ng/ml, 48 h) prior to collection of total RNA, reverse-transcription, and analysis of Pendrin mRNA expression by quantitative PCR (n = 5 inserts, ** p&lt;0.01). B. IL-17A increases Pendrin mRNA in a time-dependent fashion (Note logarithmic scale, n = 2 inserts per time point, one from each of 2 donors compared to its own control). C. HBE cells were stimulated with IL-17A (50 ng/ml, 48 h) or vehicle (PBS) after which conditioned media were collected and used to stimulate naïve cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Conditioned media were treated with either an IL-17A neutralizing antibody (NA) or an isotype control IgG (IgG) (n = 2 inserts per condition, one from each of two donors compared to its own vehicle control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Quantitative PCR for SLC26A3 (DRA) and SLC26A6 (PAT1) in the presence and absence of IL-17A (n = 3 inserts per condition). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0103263.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Previous data demonstrated that IL-17A can signal through autocrine/paracrine mechanisms to regulate mucin transcription [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To test if this mechanism was necessary for IL-17A-mediated Pendrin expression we performed an experiment in which naïve HBE cells were treated with conditioned medium from cells treated with IL-17A for 48 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Conditioned media were treated either with an IL-17A neutralizing antibody (317-ILB, R&amp;D Systems) or with an isotype control antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Naïve cells fed with conditioned medium treated with control (non-neutralizing) antibody demonstrated significant increases in Pendrin expression after 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Conversely, cells treated with IL-17A neutralized conditioned medium did not show significant increases in Pendrin expression (Figure 1c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Multiplex cytokine analysis of conditioned media confirmed that IL-17A induced G-CSF production [8], but failed to show increased IL-6 production in IL-17A-treated HBE cells (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Together, these data support the conclusion that IL-17A alone is sufficient for increased Pendrin expression under our experimental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Although IL-17A is sufficient to promote Pendrin expression in HBE cells, other cytokines including interferon-γ and IL-13 also appear to increase Pendrin RNA expression (Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Pendrin is a member of the SLC26A family of anion exchangers [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we wanted to investigate whether IL-17A increased the expression of other SLC26A Cl−/HCO3 − exchangers that are expressed in HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In cells treated with IL-17A for 48 h there was a significant decrease in SLC26A3 (DRA) expression and no significant change in SLC26A6 expression (Figure 1d), suggesting that the effect of IL-17A on Pendrin expression is not a non-specific effect seen across SLC26A family members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Additionally, because some members of the SLC26 family interact with the cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR), we measured changes in CFTR mRNA after 48 h of IL-17A stimulation (50 ng/ml). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>CFTR expression increased by an average of 1.8-fold (range 0.97–2.5) in IL-17A-treated cells relative to vehicle controls (n = 7 inserts, representing 2 donors; data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>IL-17A induces Pendrin protein expression at the apical membrane of normal HBE cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>To demonstrate that the observed increases in Pendrin mRNA correlated with increased protein expression, we performed immunoblotting using a commercially available anti-Pendrin antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Consistent with its effect on Pendrin transcription, IL-17A significantly increased Pendrin protein expression in a time-dependent fashion with Pendrin protein expression appearing to be greater at 48 h compared to 24 h (Figure 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Because the antibody we used identified a dominant band at the expected size for Pendrin [27], we performed immunofluorescence on mature, differentiated HBE cells treated with either vehicle or IL-17A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Confocal imaging confirmed greater Pendrin expression in IL-17A-treated cells and revealed that Pendrin is expressed at the mucosal surface of the cells (Figure 2b, right panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>This is best appreciated in the main XY image where Pendrin staining is present in the same 0.5 micron section as discreet cilia that are stained with Type IV Tubulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This is also demonstrated in the XZ sections, though it is more difficult to appreciate because these cell preparations were only about 10 microns thick. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Pendrin appeared to be expressed primarily in non-ciliated cells, i.e. those cells in Figure 2b that do not have Type IV Tubulin staining, which identifies cilia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Notably, vehicle controls did not demonstrate any immunofluorescence signal even in the presence of primary antibody (Figure 2b, left panel), nor did IL-17A-treated cells exposed only to secondary antibody (Figure S2, panel g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Similar results were obtained with two different, commercially available Pendrin antibodies (Figure S2, panels a–c and d–f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>For these antibodies, synthetic antigenic peptide was available, and co-incubation of the primary antibody with the peptide reduced immunofluorescence signal (Figure S2, panels c and f). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0103263-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>IL-17A induces Pendrin protein expression at the apical plasma membrane of normal HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>A. Immunoblot of Pendrin from total cell lysates at 24 h and 48 h of IL-17A stimulation. B. Confocal immunofluorescence images of vehicle and IL-17A stimulated HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Note that Pendrin (red) is only detected in IL-17A stimulated cells and is primarily localized to non-ciliated cells, which lack of Type IV Tubulin (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Images are z-stacks with 0.5 micron sections from the Transwell support to the tips of the cilia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>For each set of images, the main image is a single slice from the z-stack. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Below is an x–z projection and to the right is a y–z projection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The yellow lines indicate the location from which the projections are taken. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0103263.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>IL-17A induces CFTR-independent Cl−/HCO3 − exchange at the mucosal surface of HBE cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The finding of increased Pendrin expression at the apical membrane of HBE cells prompted us to look for functional evidence of its expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>To accomplish this goal, we loaded HBE cells with the pH-sensitive dye SNARF-5/6 and mounted them in a specially-designed perfusion apparatus that allowed for differential perfusion of the mucosal and serosal surfaces of the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>This apparatus was placed on the stage of an inverted fluorescence microscope for live-cell imaging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>To probe the HCO3 − exit pathway across the apical membrane, we established a Cl− gradient that promoted movement of Cl− out of the cell across the apical membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>To accomplish this, the apical membrane was initially perfused with solution containing both Cl− and HCO3 − (described in Methods S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>After a 2–3 minute period of stabilization during which fluorescence readings were made, the mucosal solution was changed to one in which Cl− salts were replaced with equimolar gluconate salts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>In IL-17A-treated cells this resulted in a rapid increase in pHi (Figure 3b) that was not seen in controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>By two-way ANOVA with Bonferroni post-test correction, there were no statistically significant differences at individual time points when comparing IL-17A-treated cells and controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>However, when the change in pHi from baseline was examined by subtracting the average pHi from time 0–2 minutes from that of the average pHi from time 5–6 minutes, there was a statistically greater change in the IL-17A-treated cells (0.13±0.02 pH units) than in controls (0.001±0.02 pH units). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0103263-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>IL-17A induces Cl−/HCO3 − exchange at the apical membrane of normal HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>A. Calibration curve of pHi versus F640/580. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>An insert of HBE cells was loaded with SNARF-5/6-AM and then incubated in high-potassium buffer (pH 6.8, 7.2, or 7.6) containing 20 µM each valinomycin and nigericin for 40 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Five serial measurements over 2 minutes were taken for each filter and the average used to calculate a single calibration point for each pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Linear fit was performed in Microsoft Excel. B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Intracellular pH changes in response to chloride removal from the apical perfusate (open circles: vehicle, n = 6 inserts; shaded circles: IL-17A (50 ng/ml for 48 h, n = 5 inserts). C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Intracellular pH changes in response to chloride removal from the apical perfusate in the absence of soluble HCO3 − and CO2 (only IL-17A treated cells are shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Please see the results section in the text for a complete discussion of two-way ANOVA applied to 3b. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0103263.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This change was dependent on the presence of HCO3 − in the bath solutions (Figure 3c), supporting the notion that the pH change was due to Cl−/HCO3 − exchange as opposed to changes in H+ transport, though we note in these experiments that the starting intracellular pH was significantly higher than in the presence of CO2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In fact, the baseline pH was close to the upper limit of linearity in our assay (Figure 3a), which may have limited our ability to detect a rise in pHi in the absence of HCO3 −. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>There was a small decrease in pHi when Cl− was replaced in the apical bath solution, consistent with loss of intracellular base equivalents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Pendrin, which we hypothesize is responsible for IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange, is a CFTR-independent exchanger [30], [35], as opposed to SLC26A3 and SLC26A6, which are CFTR-dependent [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>To explore whether IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange was CFTR-dependent or independent, we stimulated CF HBE cells with IL-17A (50 ng/ml, 48 h) and evaluated for both Pendrin expression and Cl−/HCO3 − exchange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Similar to results in normal HBE cells, IL-17A induced Pendrin expression (Figure 4a) and induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange (Figure 4b) in CF HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0103263-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>IL-17A increases Pendrin and Cl−/HCO3 − exchange in CF HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>A. Pendrin mRNA is increased in CF HBE cells treated with IL-17A (shaded bar) (n = 9 inserts from 2 donors, *** p&lt;0.01 compared to vehicle controls (open bar)). B. Consistent with the increase in Pendrin expression, apical membrane Cl−/HCO3 − is also increased in CF HBE cells treated with IL-17A (closed circles, n = 3 inserts). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0103263.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>siRNA inhibition of Pendrin expression reduces IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In order to test more directly the hypothesis that Pendrin expression is required for IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange, normal HBE cells were transfected with one of two siRNA molecules directed against Pendrin or with a non-targeting control siRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Each of the two siRNA sequences was tested in two tissue donors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Individually, siRNA treatment resulted in decreased Cl−/HCO3 − exchange in IL-17A-treated cells (Figure 5a and 5b) when compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Differences in baseline pHi between the two experiments made combining the raw data difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Therefore, pHi was normalized to the average of the pHi readings over the first minute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Data from the two experiments were then combined, and show a consistent and robust diminution of Cl−/HCO3 − exchange in siRNA-treated cells when compared with controls (Figure 5c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR (Figure 5d) and immunoblotting (Figure 5e) confirmed that siRNA treatment decreased Pendrin expression compared to controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0103263-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of Pendrin expression by siRNA reduces IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>A. and B. Normal HBE cells from two different donors were transfected with either non-targeting (scrambled) siRNA (closed circles) or one of two Pendrin-targeting siRNA from Invitrogen: HSS 107794 (siRNA 1, closed squares) and HSS 107796 (siRNA 2, open triangles). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>After 14 days, cells were tested for Cl−/HCO3 − exchange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Panels A and B represent data from the individual donor. C. To account for differences in baseline pHi, pH was normalized to the mean of the first minute (pHt0) and data were then combined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Normalized mean data encompassing both donors are shown in panel C. D. Quantitative PCR measuring Pendrin mRNA expression in targeting siRNA-treated cells compared with scrambled control siRNA-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Immunoblot comparing Pendrin protein expression in targeting siRNA-treated cells compared with scrambled control siRNA-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0103263.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>IL-17A induces Pendrin expression via NF-κB </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>IL-17A signals to HBE cells through a number of pathways, including canonical NF-κB signaling and through JAK signaling [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Because the IL-17A-induced epithelial changes in antimicrobial peptide production and mucin transcription are driven by NF-κB [12], [37], we hypothesized that airway epithelial Pendrin expression would also be dependent on NF-κB signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we pre-treated HBE cells with vehicle (DMSO) or NF-κB inhibitor II (20 µM, JSH-23, Calbiochem) for 1 h prior to stimulation with IL-17A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>DMSO-treated cells stimulated with IL-17A showed robust increases in Pendrin mRNA (Figure 6A) and protein (Figure 6B) expression, whereas NF-κB inhibitor II-treated cells stimulated with IL-17A were not different from unstimulated controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0103263-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0103263.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>IL-17A-induced Pendrin expression is dependent on NF-κB. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated with NF-κB inhibitor II (20 µM) for 6 hours and then with NF-κB inhibitor II and IL-17A (10 ng/ml) for 24 h prior to analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Quantitative PCR (A) and immunoblotting (B) from normal HBE cells demonstrating that inhibition of NF-κB prevents IL-17A induced Pendrin expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0103263.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>IL-17A has numerous effects on the biology and physiology of airway epithelial cells, including effects on ion transport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Previously, we demonstrated that IL-17A stimulated CFTR-dependent HCO3 − secretion [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>As part of those studies, we measured resting airway surface pH (pHASL) and observed that IL-17A increased pHASL in an electroneutral, CFTR-independent fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The current studies were undertaken to explore the mechanism by which IL-17A might have this effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that a rise in pHASL would reflect a change in net ion transport rather than changes in other buffering systems. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>This hypothesis was consistent with microarray data comparing vehicle-treated HBE cells with cells that were stimulated with IL-17A, IL-22, or a combination of the two that suggested IL-17A-stimulated HBE cells expressed more Pendrin, a HCO3 − secreting Cl−/HCO3 − exchanger, mRNA than did vehicle controls [1]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>We first confirmed our microarray observations using quantitative PCR, demonstrating that there is a time-dependent increase in Pendrin mRNA expression in IL-17A stimulated HBE cells without increases in mRNA expression of other SLC26A Cl−/HCO3 − exchangers expressed in HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>These findings are in agreement with others who have found that Th2 cytokines induce Pendrin expression, but not other SLC26A family members [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Associated with the increase in Pendrin mRNA that we observed, IL-17A stimulated HBE cells demonstrate a time-dependent increase in Pendrin protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Moreover, Pendrin protein expression can be localized by immunofluorescence to the apical domain of the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Although the Pendrin antibody used was not monospecific and, therefore, immunofluorescence results may represent nonspecific binding, we do not favor this interpretation because the dominant band detected in immunoblots was of the anticipated molecular weight and because multiple Pendrin antibodies produced similar results (Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we concluded that IL-17A increased Pendrin expression at the apical membrane in normal HBE cells, and we undertook experiments to test the hypothesis that IL-17A would also increase Cl−/HCO3 − exchange in these cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The experimental system we chose to investigate apical Cl−/HCO3 − exchange was one in which Cl− is rapidly replaced in the mucosal solution by gluconate, an impermeant anion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Cl− removal from the mucosal bath creates a large concentration gradient for Cl− from serosal (120 mM Cl) to mucosal (0 mM Cl) across the epithelium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in the presence of an apical membrane Cl−/HCO3 − exchanger one will see a rise in pHi as HCO3 − enters the cell in exchange for Cl−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>In the absence of a Cl−/HCO3 − exchanger, one would expect to see little or no change in pHi with mucosal Cl− removal because there is no HCO3 − transport pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Our data confirm that IL-17A induces a Cl−/HCO3 − exchange mechanism at the apical membrane of normal HBE cells that is not present in untreated cells as IL-17A-treated cells but not controls respond to removal of mucosal Cl− with a rise in pHi (Figure 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>As predicted, this change is reversible with replacement of mucosal Cl−. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>To test the hypothesis that this pathway required HCO3 −, we performed the same experiment in the absence of CO2/HCO3 − with solutions buffered to pH 7.4 using HEPES. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>In these experiments, there was no rise in pHi with Cl− removal, suggesting that HCO3 − entry was responsible for the observed rise in pHi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, we observed a small decrease in pHi with Cl− replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>One possible explanation for this change in pHi is that the IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange pathway can also exchange Cl− for OH−, as has been shown for Pendrin [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>We note that baseline pH in the CO2/HCO3 −-free conditions was higher than that in cells in the presence of CO2/HCO3 −, presumably because lack of CO2 entry into the cells resulted in less H+ generation from carbonic anhydrase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>It is also possible, therefore, that we did not see a rise in pHi with Cl− removal from the mucosal solution because the resistance to HCO3 − entry in the presence of elevated pHi was greater than the driving force for Cl− exit from the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>A second possibility is that the assay itself failed to detect a rise in pHi because the starting pHi was close to the top of the linear range of detection according to our calibration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>However, we note that SNARF dyes demonstrate fluorescence changes at up to pH 9 according to the support material (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://tools.lifetechnologies.com/content/sfs/manuals/mp01270.pdf">http://tools.lifetechnologies.com/content/sfs/manuals/mp01270.pdf</ext-link>).In either case above, our data would underestimate Cl−/HCO3 − exchange with Cl− removal and replacement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Because of these limitations, our data taken together are strongly suggestive of Cl−/HCO3 − exchange, but do not establish an absolute dependence on the presence of HCO3 −. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>To test the hypothesis that the IL-17A-induced Cl−/HCO3 − exchange pathway was Pendrin, we adapted a previously published method for siRNA inhibition of Pendrin expression [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We were successful at reducing, but not completely eliminating Pendrin mRNA and protein expression in anti-Pendrin siRNA-treated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>This residual expression is likely correlated with the small residual response in pHi to Cl− removal from the mucosal solution seen in the treated cells (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Despite our experimental paradigm, in which we manipulate the direction of Pendrin exchange to transport HCO3 − into the cell, we hypothesize that under physiological conditions in the airway Pendrin mediates HCO3 − secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>This is supported by our previous measurements of surface pH in IL-17A treated HBE cells [20] and by microelectrode impalement studies performed under physiological ionic conditions in which the resting membrane potential of HBE cells is close to the equilibrium potential for Cl− and more negative than that for HCO3 − [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Therefore, under physiological conditions one would anticipate that there would be a greater driving force for HCO3 − secretion compared with Cl− secretion and Pendrin would facilitate net HCO3 − secretion across the apical membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>This conclusion is also supported by the finding that pHASL is elevated during pathophysiological states where Pendrin has been found to be elevated, including chronic bronchitis and during viral infections [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that Pendrin is part of the airway epithelial response to IL-17A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Previously, Pendrin was shown to be part of the airway epithelial response to IL-13 [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>More recently it has been demonstrated that Th17 and Th2 skewed cytokine profiles are found in stable CF patients preceding the detection of Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>It remains to be seen whether Th17 and Th2 cytokines have a synergistic effect on Pendrin expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Our RNA sequencing data suggest little difference in the ability of IL-13 and IL-17 to promote Pendrin RNA expression in HBE cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>While such studies may provide further insight into the role of Pendrin under different inflammatory conditions, drawing conclusions with respect to relative potency may be quite difficult to control because of the multiple variables such as expression and density of receptors signaling machinery that would need to be accounted for, even while the system itself may be changing (see below). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Heterologous expression of Pendrin in fisher rat thyroid (FRT) cells confers cAMP-independent SCN− transport [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Such SCN− transport is linked to innate immunity through the activity of lactoperoxidase (LPO) that catalyzes the formation of the antibacterial compound hypothiocyanite (OSCN−) from SCN− and hydrogen peroxide (H2O2) [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Similarly, IL-4 increases SCN− transport in HBE cells [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Moreover, at least 2 different laboratories have established a direct link between HCO3 − and antibacterial defenses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>In particular, Sa grown in the presence of HCO3 − is significantly more susceptible to antimicrobial peptides than Sa grown in medium of the same pH that lacks HCO3 − [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in rat prostate, HCO3 − secretion, but not pH, is critical for bacterial killing [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these findings suggest that Pendrin may have a role in airways host defense. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Others have suggested that HCO3 − secretion is critical for the normal secretion and/or unfolding of secreted mucins [43], [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>This raises the hypothesis that Pendrin expression may be linked to mucin or mucus biology in airway epithelial cells, a hypothesis supported by data demonstrating the role of Pendrin in HCO3 − secretion from Calu-3 cells, a model of submucosal gland serous cells [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Others have shown in mice that virally-mediated over-expression of Pendrin in lung is sufficient for airways mucin production [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Our immunofluorescence data raise the possibility that in IL-17A treated cells Pendrin is predominantly, if not exclusively, expressed in non-ciliated cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Moreover, there appear to be fewer ciliated cells in IL-17A treated monolayers, though we did not undertake statistical analysis to determine if this is definitively the case. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Such an effect has been demonstrated previously for IL-13 [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these data are consistent with a role for Pendrin in the pathophysiology of mucus hyperplasia and metaplasia seen in chronic inflammatory disorders [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>There is growing evidence that Pendrin plays a role in the host response to infection and inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>However, many of the investigations have taken place in cultured epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>And while differentiated epithelial cells are a good representation of the native epithelium, one must use caution when extending in vitro findings to whole tissue, organ, and animal physiology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>An example for why such caution is warranted is the apparent lack of lung disease in Pendred syndrome patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>This may reflect either relatively low levels of Pendrin in the lung in the absence of inflammation, or the ability of other HCO3 − transporters, such as CFTR or other SLC26A family members, to compensate for lack of Pendrin in the airways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>This may also reflect that absence of Pendrin is protective against some forms of pulmonary disease, a suggestion for which there is evidence in the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>For example, Pendrin null mice demonstrate attenuated inflammatory responses and reduced airways reactivity in an allergen-induced model of asthma [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>This response was attributable to increased ASL depth in response to IL-13 stimulation of Pendrin-deficient airway epithelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>The precise mechanism of Pendrin regulation of ASL remains unknown and may be directly related to Pendrin, indirectly related to Pendrin through other ion transporters, or to some other effect of Pendrin deficiency not yet identified [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Further investigation in physiologically relevant Pendrin null model systems is warranted to determine what role, if any, Pendrin has in airways physiology or pathophysiology and the mechanisms by which it affects cell biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103263.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Relative potency of interferon-γ (Ifnγ), IL-13, and IL-17A to induce Pendrin in HBE cells. We note that each condition represents n = 2 donors, so statistical analysis is not appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>In these donors, IL-17 and IL-13 appear to induce Pendrin to a greater extent than does Ifn-γ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0103263.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103263.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence detection of Pendrin in IL-17A-treated HBE cells (50 ng/ml, 48 h). All images: Pendrin is pseudocolored red; Type IV Tubulin marking cilia is pseudocolored green. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Top row: Pendrin antibody, clone E-20 (Santa Cruz): A. Vehicle controls, B. IL-17A-treated cells, C. IL-17A-treated cells in the presence of blocking peptide (Santa Cruz, specific for clone). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Middle row: Pendrin antibody, clone G-19 (Santa Cruz): D. Vehicle controls, E. IL-17A-treated cells, F. IL-17A-treated cells in the presence of blocking peptide (Santa Cruz, specific for clone). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Bottom row: No Pendrin antibody: G. Secondary antibodies used alone (note: same secondary antibodies were used for immunofluorescence experiments). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0103263.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0103263.s003"><label>Methods S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>This section provides details on real-time PCR calculations, microscopy solutions and siRNA transfections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0103263.s003.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to acknowledge and thank Dr. Guoxiang Xiong for his assistance with immunofluorescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Portions of this work were published in a supplement to Pediatric Pulmonology as an abstract presented at the 2011 North American Cystic Fibrosis Conference. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0103263-Aujla1"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>1 AujlaSJ, ChanYR, ZhengM, FeiM, AskewDJ, et al (2008) IL-22 mediates mucosal host defense against Gram-negative bacterial pneumonia. Nat Med 14: 275–281.18264110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Happel1"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>2 HappelKI, ZhengM, YoungE, QuintonLJ, LockhartE, et al (2003) Cutting edge: roles of Toll-like receptor 4 and IL-23 in IL-17 expression in response to Klebsiella pneumoniae infection. J Immunol 170: 4432–4436.12707317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Cho1"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>3 ChoJS, PietrasEM, GarciaNC, RamosRI, FarzamDM, et al (2010) IL-17 is essential for host defense against cutaneous Staphylococcus aureus infection in mice. J Clin Invest 120: 1762–1773.20364087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Milner1"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>4 MilnerJD, BrenchleyJM, LaurenceA, FreemanAF, HillBJ, et al (2008) Impaired T(H)17 cell differentiation in subjects with autosomal dominant hyper-IgE syndrome. Nature 452: 773–776.18337720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Minegishi1"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>5 MinegishiY, SaitoM, NagasawaM, TakadaH, HaraT, et al (2009) Molecular explanation for the contradiction between systemic Th17 defect and localized bacterial infection in hyper-IgE syndrome. J Exp Med 206: 1291–1301.19487419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Kudva1"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>6 KudvaA, SchellerEV, RobinsonKM, CroweCR, ChoiSM, et al (2011) Influenza A inhibits Th17-mediated host defense against bacterial pneumonia in mice. J Immunol 186: 1666–1674.21178015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Tan1"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>7 TanHL, RegameyN, BrownS, BushA, LloydCM, et al (2011) The Th17 pathway in cystic fibrosis lung disease. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 184: 252–258.21474644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-McAllister1"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>8 McAllisterF, HenryA, KreindlerJL, DubinPJ, UlrichL, et al (2005) Role of IL-17A, IL-17F, and the IL-17 receptor in regulating growth-related oncogene-alpha and granulocyte colony-stimulating factor in bronchial epithelium: implications for airway inflammation in cystic fibrosis. J Immunol 175: 404–412.15972674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Aujla2"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>9 AujlaSJ, AlcornJF (2011) TH17 cells in asthma and inflammation. Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) - General Subjects 1810: 1066–1079.21315804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Kuestner1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>10 KuestnerRE, TaftDW, HaranA, BrandtCS, BrenderT, et al (2007) Identification of the IL-17 receptor related molecule IL-17RC as the receptor for IL-17F. J Immunol 179: 5462–5473.17911633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Fujisawa1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>11 FujisawaT, VelichkoS, ThaiP, HungL-Y, HuangF, et al (2009) Regulation of Airway MUC5AC Expression by IL-1{beta} and IL-17A; the NF-{kappa}B Paradigm. J Immunol 183: 6236–6243.19841186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Kao1"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>12 KaoCY, ChenY, ThaiP, WachiS, HuangF, et al (2004) IL-17 markedly up-regulates beta-defensin-2 expression in human airway epithelium via JAK and NF-kappaB signaling pathways. J Immunol 173: 3482–3491.15322213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Hwang1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>13 HwangS-Y, KimJ-Y, KimK-W, ParkM-K, MoonY, et al (2004) IL-17 induces production of IL-6 and IL-8 in rheumatoid arthritis synovial fibroblasts via NF-kappaB- and PI3-kinase/Akt-dependent pathways. Arthritis Res Ther 6: R120–R128.15059275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Kao2"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>14 KaoCY, HuangF, ChenY, ThaiP, WachiS, et al (2005) Up-regulation of CC chemokine ligand 20 expression in human airway epithelium by IL-17 through a JAK-independent but MEK/NF-kappaB-dependent signaling pathway. J Immunol 175: 6676–6685.16272323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Danahay1"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>15 DanahayH, AthertonHC, JacksonAD, KreindlerJL, PollCT, et al (2006) Membrane capacitance and conductance changes parallel mucin secretion in the human airway epithelium. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 290: L558–569.16227318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Garcia1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>16 GarciaMA, YangN, QuintonPM (2009) Normal mouse intestinal mucus release requires cystic fibrosis transmembrane regulator-dependent bicarbonate secretion. J Clin Invest 119: 2613–2622.19726884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Dorschner1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>17 DorschnerRA, Lopez-GarciaB, PeschelA, KrausD, MorikawaK, et al (2006) The mammalian ionic environment dictates microbial susceptibility to antimicrobial defense peptides. FASEB J 20: 35–42.16394265 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Danahay2"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>18 DanahayH, AthertonH, JonesG, BridgesRJ, PollCT (2002) Interleukin-13 induces a hypersecretory ion transport phenotype in human bronchial epithelial cells. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 282: L226–236.11792627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Gray1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>19 GrayT, CoakleyR, HirshA, ThorntonD, KirkhamS, et al (2004) Regulation of MUC5AC mucin secretion and airway surface liquid metabolism by IL-1beta in human bronchial epithelia. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 286: L320–330.14527933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Kreindler1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>20 KreindlerJL, BertrandCA, LeeRJ, KarasicT, AujlaS, et al (2009) Interleukin-17A induces bicarbonate secretion in normal human bronchial epithelial cells. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 296: L257–266.19074559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Ko1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>21 KoSB, ZengW, DorwartMR, LuoX, KimKH, et al (2004) Gating of CFTR by the STAS domain of SLC26 transporters. Nat Cell Biol 6: 343–350.15048129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>22 WangY, SoyomboAA, ShcheynikovN, ZengW, DorwartM, et al (2006) Slc26a6 regulates CFTR activity in vivo to determine pancreatic duct HCO3- secretion: relevance to cystic fibrosis. Embo J 25: 5049–5057.17053783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Bertrand1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>23 BertrandCA, ZhangR, PilewskiJM, FrizzellRA (2009) SLC26A9 is a constitutively active, CFTR-regulated anion conductance in human bronchial epithelia. J Gen Physiol 133: 421–438.19289574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Wheat1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>24 WheatVJ, ShumakerH, BurnhamC, ShullGE, YankaskasJR, et al (2000) CFTR induces the expression of DRA along with Cl(−)/HCO(3)(−) exchange activity in tracheal epithelial cells. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol 279: C62–71.10898717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Silberg1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>25 SilbergDG, WangW, MoseleyRH, TraberPG (1995) The Down regulated in Adenoma (dra) gene encodes an intestine-specific membrane sulfate transport protein. J Biol Chem 270: 11897–11902.7744840 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Royaux1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>26 RoyauxIE, WallSM, KarniskiLP, EverettLA, SuzukiK, et al (2001) Pendrin, encoded by the Pendred syndrome gene, resides in the apical region of renal intercalated cells and mediates bicarbonate secretion. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 98: 4221–4226.11274445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Soleimani1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>27 SoleimaniM, GreeleyT, PetrovicS, WangZ, AmlalH, et al (2001) Pendrin: an apical Cl{−}/OH{−}/HCO3{−} exchanger in the kidney cortex. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol 280: F356–364.11208611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Scott1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>28 ScottDA, WangR, KremanTM, SheffieldVC, KarniskiLP (1999) The Pendred syndrome gene encodes a chloride-iodide transport protein. Nat Genet 21: 440–443.10192399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Dossena1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>29 DossenaS, RodighieroS, VezzoliV, BazziniC, SironiC, et al (2006) Fast fluorometric method for measuring pendrin (SLC26A4) Cl-/I- transport activity. Cell Physiol Biochem 18: 67–74.16914891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Pedemonte1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>30 PedemonteN, CaciE, SondoE, CaputoA, RhodenK, et al (2007) Thiocyanate Transport in Resting and IL-4-Stimulated Human Bronchial Epithelial Cells: Role of Pendrin and Anion Channels. J Immunol 178: 5144–5153.17404297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Lohi1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>31 LohiH, KujalaM, MakelaS, LehtonenE, KestilaM, et al (2002) Functional Characterization of Three Novel Tissue-specific Anion Exchangers SLC26A7, -A8, and -A9. J Biol Chem 277: 14246–14254.11834742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Schmittgen1"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>32 SchmittgenTD, LivakKJ (2008) Analyzing real-time PCR data by the comparative C-T method. Nature Protocols 3: 1101–1108.18546601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Chen1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>33 ChenY, ThaiP, ZhaoYH, HoYS, DeSouzaMM, et al (2003) Stimulation of airway mucin gene expression by interleukin (IL)-17 through IL-6 paracrine/autocrine loop. J Biol Chem 278: 17036–17043.12624114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Mount1"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>34 MountDB, RomeroMF (2004) The SLC26 gene family of multifunctional anion exchangers. Pflugers Arch 447: 710–721.12759755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Garnett1"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>35 GarnettJP, HickmanE, BurrowsR, HegyiP, TiszlaviczL, et al (2011) Novel role for pendrin in orchestrating bicarbonate secretion in CFTR-expressing airway serous cells. Journal of Biological Chemistry  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Huang1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>36 HuangF, KaoCY, WachiS, ThaiP, RyuJ, et al (2007) Requirement for both JAK-mediated PI3K signaling and ACT1/TRAF6/TAK1-dependent NF-kappaB activation by IL-17A in enhancing cytokine expression in human airway epithelial cells. J Immunol 179: 6504–6513.17982039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Fujisawa2"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>37 FujisawaT, VelichkoS, ThaiP, HungLY, HuangF, et al (2009) Regulation of airway MUC5AC expression by IL-1beta and IL-17A; the NF-kappaB paradigm. J Immunol 183: 6236–6243.19841186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Kreindler2"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>38 KreindlerJL, JacksonAD, KempPA, BridgesRJ, DanahayH (2005) Inhibition of chloride secretion in human bronchial epithelial cells by cigarette smoke extract. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 288: L894–902.15626749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Fischer1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>39 FischerH, WiddicombeJH (2006) Mechanisms of acid and base secretion by the airway epithelium. J Membr Biol 211: 139–150.17091214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Tiringer1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>40 TiringerK, TreisA, FucikP, GonaM, GruberS, et al (2013) A Th17- and Th2-skewed cytokine profile in cystic fibrosis lungs represents a potential risk factor for Pseudomonas aeruginosa infection. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 187: 621–629.23306544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Conner1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>41 ConnerGE, Wijkstrom-FreiC, RandellSH, FernandezVE, SalatheM (2007) The lactoperoxidase system links anion transport to host defense in cystic fibrosis. FEBS Lett 581: 271–278.17204267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Xie1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>42 XieC, TangX, XuW, DiaoR, CaiZ, et al (2010) A host defense mechanism involving CFTR-mediated bicarbonate secretion in bacterial prostatitis. PLoS One 5: e15255.21151921 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Chen2"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>43 ChenEY, YangN, QuintonPM, ChinWC (2010) A new role for bicarbonate in mucus formation. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 299: L542–549.20693315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Muchekehu1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>44 MuchekehuRW, QuintonPM (2010) A new role for bicarbonate secretion in cervico-uterine mucus release. J Physiol 588: 2329–2342.20478977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Garnett2"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>45 GarnettJP, HickmanE, BurrowsR, HegyiP, TiszlaviczL, et al (2011) Novel role for pendrin in orchestrating bicarbonate secretion in cystic fibrosis transmembrane conductance regulator (CFTR)-expressing airway serous cells. J Biol Chem 286: 41069–41082.21914796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Nakao1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>46 NakaoI, KanajiS, OhtaS, MatsushitaH, ArimaK, et al (2008) Identification of pendrin as a common mediator for mucus production in bronchial asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease. J Immunol 180: 6262–6269.18424749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Atherton1"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>47 AthertonHC, JonesG, DanahayH (2003) IL-13-induced changes in the goblet cell density of human bronchial epithelial cell cultures: MAP kinase and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase regulation. Am J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol 285: L730–739.12794003 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Curran1"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>48 CurranDR, CohnL (2010) Advances in Mucous Cell Metaplasia. American Journal of Respiratory Cell and Molecular Biology 42: 268–275.19520914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0103263-Nakagami1"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>49 NakagamiY, FavoretoSJr, ZhenG, ParkSW, NguyenvuLT, et al (2008) The epithelial anion transporter pendrin is induced by allergy and rhinovirus infection, regulates airway surface liquid, and increases airway reactivity and inflammation in an asthma model. J Immunol 181: 2203–2210.18641360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
