
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Open Forum Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Open Forum Infect Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ofid</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">ofids</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Open Forum Infectious Diseases</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2328-8957</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4281816</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ofid/ofu056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ofu056</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Major Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Low Multiplicity of HIV-1 Infection and No Vaccine Enhancement in VAX003 Injection Drug Users </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sterrett</surname><given-names>Sarah</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>Gerald H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Edlefsen</surname><given-names>Paul T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Haynes</surname><given-names>Barton F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>Beatrice H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>George M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bar</surname><given-names>Katharine J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>University of Alabama at Birmingham</institution>, <addr-line>Birmingham</addr-line></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Perelman School of Medicine</addr-line>, <institution>University of Pennsylvania</institution>, <addr-line>Philadelphia</addr-line></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><institution>Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center</institution>, <addr-line>Seattle, Washington</addr-line></aff><aff id="af4"><label>4</label><institution>Duke Human Vaccine Institute, Duke University Medical Center</institution>, <addr-line>Durham, North Carolina</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence: Katharine J. Bar, MD, 502D Johnson Pavilion, 3610 Hamilton Walk, Philadelphia, PA, 19104 (<email>bark@upenn.edu</email>).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>ofu056</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Infectious Diseases Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial reproduction and distribution of the work, in any medium, provided the original work is not altered or transformed in any way, and that the work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="ofu056.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain> We performed human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) transmitted/founder (T/F) virus analysis of the VAX003 vaccine efficacy trial participants to characterize the transmission bottleneck and test for vaccine-associated reduction or enhancement of infection in this injection drug user (IDU) cohort. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain> We performed single genome sequencing of plasma vRNA from 50 subjects sampled in early HIV infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Sequences were analyzed phylogenetically, T/F viruses enumerated, and a sieve analysis performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain> Eight of 19 (42%) placebo recipients were productively infected by more than 1 virus (range 1–5, median 1, mean 1.7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This frequency of multiple virus transmission was greater than reported for heterosexual cohorts (19%, P = .03) but not statistically different from vaccine recipients (22.6%, P &gt; .05), where the range was 1–3, median 1, and mean 1.3 (P &gt; .05 for all comparisons). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>An atypical sieve effect was detected in Env V2 but was not associated with reduction or enhancement of virus acquisition. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain> The number of T/F viruses in IDUs was surprising low, with 95% of individuals infected by only 1–3 viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>This finding suggests that a successful vaccine or other prevention modality generally needs to protect against only one or a few viruses regardless of risk behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>T/F analysis identified an atypical genetic sieve in the V2 region of Envelope and found no evidence for vaccine-mediated enhancement in VAX003. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>HIV transmission</kwd><kwd>VAX003</kwd><kwd>injection drug users</kwd><kwd>multiple virus transmission</kwd><kwd>genetic sieve</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The development of a safe and effective human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) vaccine is of critical importance in the fight against HIV/AIDS, with injection drug users (IDUs) representing a high-risk population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>IDUs are significant drivers of the HIV epidemic, representing approximately 10% of HIV-infected individuals worldwide and more than 40% of new infections in some high-incidence regions, including eastern Europe and central Asia [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have demonstrated a stringent population bottleneck in heterosexual (mucosal) transmission of HIV-1, with approximately 80% of infections initiated by a single transmitted/founder (T/F) virus [2–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Biological and epidemiological considerations suggest that HIV-1 acquisition could differ substantially when occurring via injection rather than sexual activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Though employing high inocula, nonhuman primate studies of simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) infection demonstrate orders of magnitude differences in the number of T/F viruses between intravenous and mucosal inoculation [5–8], and epidemiologic studies ascribe a higher per event transmission risk to parenteral exposures [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Direct examination of the HIV-1 transmission bottleneck in IDUs, however, has been limited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Just 2 small studies have quantified T/F viruses in IDUs, demonstrating a wide range in the number of T/F viruses (1–16) with conflicting results as to the mean (1.46 vs 3) and median (1 vs 3) number of T/F viruses in IDUs [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>A third study of a high-risk needlestick exposure found a minimum of 15 T/F viruses established infection despite post-exposure prophylaxis [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Thus, critical questions remain as to what extent the HIV-1 transmission barrier differs between injection and sexual cohorts and how the IDU transmission route might influence vaccine trial design and assessment and, ultimately, vaccine efficacy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>A single vaccine efficacy trial, VAX003, enrolled an IDU cohort [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>VAX003 was a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled trial of the AIDSVAX (recombinant gp120) B/E vaccine with an HIV-1 incidence of 3.4/100 person-years [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This trial demonstrated no vaccine efficacy (VE) in preventing HIV-1 acquisition [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>AIDSVAX B/E was subsequently used in conjunction with a canarypox-vector prime (ALVAC) in the RV144 trial conducted in Thai heterosexuals [15], where it demonstrated a 31.2% VE [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Post hoc analyses further identified increased VE in the lowest risk RV144 subjects, highlighting the possibility that higher risk modes of acquisition, such as IDU, may affect vaccine trial outcomes [14–16]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The molecular identification of discrete T/F genomes responsible for productive clinical infection by single genome sequencing (SGS) allows for a precise quantitative and qualitative analysis of HIV-1 transmission, including factors that might inhibit or enhance virus infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These include potential T-cell or antibody mediated pressures resulting in selective virus outgrowth (sieving)[17, 18] or enhancement [19, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="?"><plain>In the present study, we applied T/F analyses to the VAX003 trial to examine 3 key questions: (1) What is the multiplicity of HIV-1 infection in IDUs, ie, how high is the bar set for clinical vaccine protection? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="?"><plain>(2) Is there evidence of protection or enhancement of virus acquisition associated with an Env containing vaccine? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="?"><plain>(3) Is there evidence of vaccine-associated sieving of viruses leading to selective virus transmission? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Study Subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Deidentified plasma samples were obtained from Global Solutions for Infectious Diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The estimated date of infection was determined as midpoint between HIV-specific antibody positive and negative testing or 10 days prior to HIV viral RNA (vRNA) positive/antibody negative sampling [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>For 7 subjects, we had access to 2 samples obtained within the first 100 days of infection (subjects 3022, 3025, 3046, 3090, 3112, 3126, 3210). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>The VAX003 trial was conducted in accordance with the declaration of Helsinki and local institutional review boards [14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Viral RNA Extraction, cDNA Synthesis, SGS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Viral RNA extraction, complementary DNA (cDNA) synthesis, and SGS were performed to amplify gp41 or gp160 env as previously described [2, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Amplicons were directly sequenced and chromatograms were inspected for evidence of priming from multiple templates or introduction of polymerase chain reaction (PCR) error in early cycles [2, 22]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Sequences were aligned with ClustalW and hand-checked using MacClade 4.08. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The composite maximum-likelihood (ML) phylogenetic tree with ML bootstrap support was estimated using RAxML-HPC-SSE3 version 7.6.3 with a Γ model of rate heterogeneity and ML estimate of the α parameter [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>All other phylogenetic trees were generated by the neighbor-joining (NJ) method using ClustalW or ML method using PhyML v.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Sequences were analyzed by a previously described model of neutral virus evolution [2, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Under this model, low-diversity sequence lineages display a star-like phylogeny and a Poisson distribution of mutations and coalesce to an unambiguous T/F sequence [2, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Sequences with evidence of APOBEC3G-mediated hypermutation were removed from model calculations and figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All sequences were deposited in GENBANK (KJ952241–KJ953713). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Sieve Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Sieve analysis of the envelope V1V2 region followed a prespecified approach based on the RV144 analysis protocol using the EPIMAP site set [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>As per the RV144 analysis, we included only CRF01_AE sequences; a secondary analysis was performed excluding all but the first of phylogenetically linked infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Two subjects with only gp41 sequences were excluded (subjects 3054 and 3192); subject 3110 had additional plasma available for V1V2 sequence amplification and was included. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Multiplicity correction for site scanning methods used a Benjamini-Hochberg false discovery rate (q-value) threshold of 0.2 [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The prespecified analyses and associated multiplicity correction were conducted separately for each insert (A244 and MN) and statistical method [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Comparison Between Heterosexual and IDU Cohorts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>A review of the literature revealed 5 manuscripts using single genome methods to enumerate T/F viruses in subjects with documented IDU and heterosexual transmission risks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>These articles describe 174 heterosexuals[2–4] and 42 unvaccinated IDUs [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Subject Characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>T/F analysis requires samples obtained early in infection so that viral sequence evolution conforms to a model of random or near-random evolution [2, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Enumeration of T/F variants has been validated in samples obtained within approximately 100 days of infection [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We elected to study all VAX003 subjects with high-risk IDU practices and samples collected within 100 days of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Fifty (19 placebo- and 31 vaccine-recipients) out of a total of 211 HIV-infected subjects met these prespecified criteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Subjects were largely male (88%), with ages ranging from 21 to 53 years, and estimated time since HIV-1 infection of between 10 and 100 days (mean 58 days; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Plasma samples were analyzed by HIV-1 enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) and Western blot, and the Fiebig clinicopathological stage was determined [2, 21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In total there were 14 pre-antibody seroconversion samples and 36 post-seroconversion samples (Table 1) [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The placebo and vaccine groups had similar demographic and Fiebig stage composition, with 11% and 13% female representation, mean ages of 28.4 and 27.0 years, and 26% and 29% preseroconversion sampling, respectively; none of these characteristics differed statistically between groups.Table 1.Demographics and sequence analysis of VAX003 subjectsAbbreviations: HIV-1, human immunodeficiency virus type 1; T/F, transmitted/founder.a The estimated date of infection was determined as midpoint between HIV-specific antibody positive and negative testing or as 10 days prior to a HIV viral RNA positive/antibody negative sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>For subjects with 2 samples, estimated dates are listed for both.b Number of total sequences analyzed per subject. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>In subjects with 2 available samples obtained within the first 100 days of infection, the numbers of sequences analyzed from first and second timepoint are shown in parentheses.c Estimate of minimum number of T/F viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In subjects with multiple T/F viruses, initial model testing indicated a GOF P value &lt; .05 for the whole subject dataset, whereupon model analyses of maximum Hamming distance, Lambda, Goodness of Fit P value, MRCA days by Poisson, and Star phylogeny were conducted on the largest T/F lineage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>In subjects with 2 samples, analyses were performed on the earlier timepoint.d Maximum Hamming distance.e Goodness of Fit P value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Low P values (&lt;.05) indicate divergence from a Poisson distribution.f Number of days since most recent common ancestor as determined by Poisson distribution, with 95% confidence intervals in parentheses.g Star phylogeny defined as divergence of &lt;10% between observed and estimated convolution values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Near Star phylogeny indicates the sequence set meets this criterion upon removal of up to 3 sites of shared polymorphisms.h For subjects 3003 and 3110 additional sequences were generated spanning 1200 nucleotides of gp120, including the V1V2 region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic Analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>A total of 1473 env gp160 or gp41 sequences generated by SGS were obtained with a median of 26 per subject timepoint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Gp160 sequences were generated for 42 subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>In 8 subjects (3/19 [16%] placebo and 5/31 [19%] vaccine arm), viral loads were lower or the plasma sample was of poorer quality such that we chose to amplify gp41 to increase sequencing efficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The gp41 env sequences from all 50 subjects were analyzed together in a ML phylogeny along with relevant reference sequences (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Sequences from 43 subjects (86%) clustered unambiguously with Thai CRF01_AE reference viruses, 5 subjects clustered with Thai Subtype B viruses, 1 subject (Subject 3156) clustered with both Subtype B and CRF01_AE viruses, and 1 subject (Subject 3147) clustered with CRF15_01B viruses (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The use of SGS enabled detection of minority variants, including individuals infected with multiple subtypes (subject 3156; see Fig. 1 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ofid.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/ofid/ofu056/-/DC1">Supplementary material, Fig. S1</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In 7 subjects, there was phylogenetic evidence of epidemiologically closely related infections, including 2 likely “acute-to-acute” transmissions (subjects 3017 and 3212 and subjects 3017 and 3213; Fig. 1, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ofid.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/ofid/ofu056/-/DC1">Supplementary material, Figs S2 and S3</ext-link>). Fig. 1.ML tree of HIV-1 gp41 env sequences from the 50 VAX003 subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Each subject's sequence set is shown in a different color and labeled with the subject identifier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Reference sequences are shown in gray. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Forty-six subjects were infected by CRF01_AE viruses; CRF15_01B and subtype B clades are specifically indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Individual subject sequence sets with bootstrap values &gt;95% are annotated with an asterisk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>There are 8 individual subject sequence lineages with bootstrap values &gt;75%: the 2 acute-to-acute transmissions (subjects 3212 and 3017 and subjects 3184 and 3090), 3 subjects with related but distinct lineages (subjects 3189, 3111 and 3112), and subject 3156. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Subject 3156 (shown in mustard orange and annotated with a hashtag at the top and bottom of tree) has sequences clustering with CRF01_AE and subtype B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The single long branch in subject 3156's viral sequences at the top of the figure is a unique interlineage recombinant shown in greater detail in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ofid.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/ofid/ofu056/-/DC1">Supplementary material, Figure S1</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Genetic distance is indicated by the scale bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: HIV-1, human immunodeficiency virus type 1; ML, maximum-likelihood. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>T/F Analysis of Placebo Recipients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>To assess the stringency of the IDU transmission barrier, we analyzed the 19 placebo recipient's gp160 or gp41 env sequences from the first available timepoint to enumerate the viruses founding productive infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>For the placebo subjects, within-patient maximum env diversities ranged from 0.272% to 0.868%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Eleven of the placebo subjects' phylogenies demonstrated a single low-diversity lineage (maximum within-env diversity 0.27%–0.87%), as represented in Figure 2 and summarized in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>For all but 2 of these 11 subjects, the diversity was within that attainable in env within the first 100 days of infection (&lt;0.6%, 95% confidence interval [CI]: 0.54%–0.68%)[2]; 2 subjects sampled later in infection had marginally higher diversities in their single sequence lineages (0.71% and 0.868%; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This phylogenetic pattern of a single low-diversity lineage is characteristic of acute infection founded by 1 T/F virus, and the majority of these subjects' sequences conformed to a model of random virus evolution from a single template (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The sequences that did not conform to model predictions were sampled later (Fiebig stages V–VI) and deviated from model predictions due to few sites of shared mutations (Table 1) [2, 27]. Fig. 2.Single T/F virus transmission in VAX003 placebo recipients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>ML trees of HIV-1 gp160 env sequences for placebo subjects 3202 (A), 3046 (B), and 3022 (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>ML tree and Highlighter plot for gp160 env sequences from placebo subject 3126 from 2 timepoints (Fiebig stage II sample sequences shown in blue, Fiebieg stage IV sample sequences, estimated 67 days post-infection, shown in green) (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>All 4 subjects' phylogenies reveal initial single, low-diversity lineages consistent with productive clinical infection by a single virus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Later sequences from 3126 reveal evidence of selection at several positions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Genetic distances are indicated by the scale bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: HIV-1, human immunodeficiency virus type 1; ML, maximum likelihood; T/F, transmitted/founder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In 4 of the placebo subjects with a single T/F virus (subjects 3022, 3025, 3046, 3126), we had access to additional plasma samples obtained 20–60 days after the first sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>As illustrated by subject 3126 (Fig. 2D), who was sampled preseroconversion and 57 days later, the longitudinal sequences clustered together and demonstrated the expected accrual of genetic diversity over time [2, 24, 27–30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Importantly, in all 4 subjects, lineages remained discernible as single virus transmissions, although identification of exact T/F sequences was confounded by selection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Eight of the placebo subjects (8/19, 42.1%) demonstrated phylogenetic evidence of multiple virus transmission (MVT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>In these subjects, as represented by subjects 3090 and 3007 in Figure 3, 2 or more discrete low-diversity lineages were present, often with interlineage recombinant sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Maximum env diversities ranged from 0.901% to 22.6%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Seven subjects had maximum env diversities typical of the HIV quasispecies of an HIV-infected individual (0.901%–5.22%), whereas subject 3156 had &gt;20% env diversity due to the presence of sequences from both subtype B and CRF01_AE (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ofid.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/ofid/ofu056/-/DC1">Supplementary material, Fig. S1</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Despite the overall increased sequence diversity reflecting MVT, individual sequence lineages showed limited diversity and conformed to a model of random virus diversification from discrete T/F genomes, thus allowing for estimation the number of T/F viruses (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Importantly, these are minimum estimates of numbers of T/F viruses, with the sensitivity and precision of the estimates influenced by sequencing depth (see[2] for model predictions and power calculations). Fig. 3.Multiple T/F virus transmission in VAX003 placebo recipient subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>ML trees and Highlighter plots of HIV-1 gp160 env sequences from subject 3090 (A) and subject 3007 (B), each phylogeny revealing productive infection by at least 3 viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>T/F virus lineages are color-coded and labeled variant (V)1–3; recombinant (R) sequences shown in orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: HIV-1, human immunodeficiency virus type 1; ML, maximum likelihood; T/F, transmitted/founder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The range in the number of viruses initiating productive infection in the placebo recipients was 1–5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In total, 42% of the placebo recipients had HIV-1 infection founded by multiple viruses, with a mean of 1.7 T/F viruses per subject. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>When compared with 174 subjects from cohorts of sexual transmission analyzed by the same SGS methodology [2–4], this frequency of MVT is significantly higher than the 19% seen in heterosexuals (P = .03, Fisher exact test). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>T/F Analysis of the Vaccine Recipients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>We next analyzed each of the 31 vaccine recipients' sequences for overall diversity and evidence of random virus evolution [2, 24, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four of the 31 subjects exhibited a phylogenetic pattern of single low-diversity lineages (maximum within-env diversity of 0.769% to 0%), as shown in Figure 4A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Phylogenies from 22 of these sequence sets met model criteria for a Poisson distribution of mutations, and 19 had star-like or near star-like phylogenies (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Seven of the vaccine recipients' sequence sets had greater env diversity than predicted for single virus transmission (1.43%–4.96%) and phylogenies consistent with MVT, as exemplified by subject 3019 in Figure 4B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In total, 22.6% (7/31) of the vaccine recipients had infection founded by multiple viruses, with a mean of 1.3 T/F viruses per subject and a range of 1–3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Comparing the 2 study arms, there was no evidence of vaccine-associated enhancement leading to increased numbers of T/F viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Instead, there was a statistically nonsignificant trend toward a reduction in the number of viruses establishing clinical infection (mean 1.3 vs 1.7, P = .133, Wilcoxin test) and the overall frequency of MVT (22.6% vs 42.1%, P = 0.21, Fisher exact test) in vaccinees compared with placebo-recipients. Fig. 4.ML tree and Highlighter plots of gp160 env sequences from VAX003 vaccine recipient subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Subject 3153 (A) demonstrates single virus transmission, while subject 3019 reveals multiple virus transmission by at least 2 viruses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>T/F lineages are labeled and color-coded and recombinant sequences shown in orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: ML, maximum likelihood; T/F, transmitted/founder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Sieve Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>We next tested for genetic signatures of a vaccine effect through sieve analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Genetic sieve analyses look for sequence evidence that vaccine-induced immune responses selectively block the transmission of certain viruses [17, 18, 31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>This is accomplished by comparing the sequences of breakthrough viruses in the vaccine and placebo recipients to the vaccine insert(s) [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Sieve analysis of the RV144 trial demonstrated 2 sites in V2 with statistically different rates of amino acid mismatch (Env positions 169 and 181) [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Further, both a typical sieve effect (ie, greater mismatch in the vaccine-recipient sequences) at position 169 and an atypical effect (ie, greater mismatch in the placebo-recipient sequences) at position 181 were associated with increased VE [18, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Because RV144 and VAX003 tested identical Env immunogens (with or without ALVAC), we used the RV144 sieve analysis as a template. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>To maximize power, we employed a prespecified statistical plan to test only sites determined to be of likely importance based on structural and binding models, termed EPIMAP sites [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Our sieve analysis differed from RV144 in that we compared the T/F virus sequences and full SGS-derived sequence sets obtained in the first 100 days of infection, which enabled us to mitigate some post-acquisition selection effects possible in studies evaluating all breakthrough infections [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We performed 2 predetermined analyses of V1V2 mismatching; the first tested the signals seen in the RV144 analysis, and the second examined EPIMAP sites [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Each sample was compared against the CRF01_AE and Subtype B Env inserts, thus restricting comparisons to between 5 and 7 sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We used the same 3 statistical methods to compare insert mismatches as did the RV144 analyses, (1) GWJ (a non-parametric T-test comparing insert mismatch in the major T/F sequence per subject), (2) MBS (a Bayesian model-based test comparing the major T/F sequence per subject), and (3) SMMB (a simplified bootstrap pairwise AA test using all the SGA-derived sequences) [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Analysis of the positions identified in the RV144 sieve analysis (Env 169 and 181) showed no evidence of selection in the VAX003 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The EPIMAP sites, however, revealed a sieve effect at Env position 170 in the V2 crown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>At this position, there was a greater frequency of insert mismatch with the placebo-recipient sequences than vaccinee sequences (37.5% [6/16] vs 5% [1/20]) (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>This atypical sieve effect was statistically significant (P = .0368 for GWJ method, .035 for MBS method, .015 for SMMB method) and met the multiplicity correction of q &lt; 0.2 for 4 of the 6 tests, with differences due to number of sites compared per insert (q = 0.258 and 0.184 for GWJ method, 0.245 and 0.1743 for MBS method, and 0.135 and 0.105 for SMMB method for comparison with the A244 and MN inserts, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A secondary analysis excluding linked transmissions revealed similar trends (P = .053 for GWJ method, .051 for MBS, and .020 for SMMB) and (q = 0.355 and 0.253 for MBS, and 0.374 and 0.267 for GWJ, and 0.182 and 0.1414 for the SMMB for A244 and MN inserts, respectively). Fig. 5.Sieve analysis at Env position 170. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>95% (19/20) of T/F virus sequences from vaccine recipients matched the A244 and MN vaccine inserts at position 170 compared with 62.5% (10/16) of placebo recipient T/F virus sequences (P &lt; .05 for all tests performed). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Abbreviation: T/F, transmitted/founder. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>HIV-1 transmission in IDUs is an important but understudied subject with relevance to multiple prevention efforts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Here we identified and quantified the T/F viruses from 50 VAX003 subjects, enabling a robust characterization of the transmission bottleneck in IDUs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, we found only a modest increase in the multiplicity of infection in these IDUs compared with heterosexuals. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>HIV-1 transmission in heterosexuals is characterized by a strict genetic bottleneck, with 81% of subjects infected with a single T/F virus and the vast majority of the remainder infected with just 2 or 3 viruses (Fig. 6) [2–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The proportion of MVT in IDUs was higher in both the VAX003 placebo-recipients (n = 19, 42% MVT, P = .03, Fisher exact test) and in an aggregate of published unvaccinated IDUs with enumerated T/F viruses (n = 42, 43% MVT, P = .002), as shown in Figure 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Importantly, 43% MVT is also greater than the 21% MVT reported for the 52 HIV-infected heterosexual participants in the placebo arm of RV144 (P = .027) [25]. Fig. 6.Increased multiplicity of HIV-1 infection in IDUs compared with heterosexuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>HIV-1 infections founded by a minimum of 1, 2–3, 4–6, or &gt;6 T/F viruses from aggregated reports of heterosexuals (n = 174)[2–4] and unvaccinated IDUs (n = 42)[11, 12] analyzed by comparable single genome sequencing methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The frequency of MVT in IDUs (43%) is greater than in heterosexuals (19%, P = .002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Transmission of between 1 and 3 viruses occurred in 97% heterosexuals and 93% of IDUs, P &gt; .05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: HIV-1, human immunodeficiency virus type 1; IDU, injection drug user; MVT, multiple virus transmission. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Although the frequency of MVT in IDUs was approximately double that in heterosexuals, the actual number of viruses establishing productive infection was only slightly greater in IDUs than in heterosexuals (mean of 1.3 T/F viruses [range 1–6] in heterosexuals, mean of 1.7 [range 1–5] in VAX003 placebo-recipients, and mean of 2.1 [range 1–16] in all unvaccinated IDUs (n = 42), P &gt; .05 for both comparisons, unequal-variance t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Thus, as shown in Figure 6, the majority of HIV-1 infections in both heterosexuals and IDUs were founded by a single virus (81% and 57%, respectively), and the vast majority of infections were founded by between 1 and 3 viruses (98% and 93%, respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="?"><plain>What might be the explanation for the surprisingly low numbers of T/F viruses in IDUs and the clinical significance of a modest difference in the proportion of cases of MVT in IDUs compared with heterosexuals? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>People who inject drugs have concomitant injection and sexual risks for HIV acquisition [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Studies in VAX003 trial participants, however, found injection practices, not sexual behaviors, correlated with HIV-1 incidence [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Further, we selected only trial participants reporting high-risk IDU practices for this analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Despite our focus on a high-injection, low sexual-risk cohort, it is probable that some subjects were infected via sexual routes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Another possible contributor to the low T/F virus numbers is that injection practices of VAX003 participants generally led to the transfer of very small amounts of blood and a low virus inoculum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Plasma-associated factors in the infected partner (eg, neutralizing antibodies[35]) or in virus-naive recipients could similarly contribute. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Epidemiological studies have consistently shown HIV transmission to be a low-probability event, with a small fraction of HIV exposures via any route causing infection [9, 36–39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>While these data are consistent with our findings, they also suggest that a small increase in the number of T/F viruses could shift the outcome of an exposure and reduce the efficacy of a marginally effective vaccine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>This concept is consistent with the loss of vaccine efficacy seen in RV144 subjects with higher risks, suggesting that a higher risk challenge (eg, IDU or MSM exposures) may have overwhelmed the low-level immune responses elicited in RV144 [15, 16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>In the advent of more robust vaccines proven to be highly efficacious in heterosexual cohorts, however, the low multiplicity of infection of VAX003 IDUs shown here suggests such a vaccine is likely to be similarly successful in the majority of IDUs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Our second finding addresses the concern for antibody-mediated enhancement of infection, which may be relevant in vaccination strategies that induce lower potency antibody responses [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Multiple lines of in vitro evidence demonstrate antibody-mediated enhancement of HIV infection via interactions with low potency or low concentrations of antibodies [40, 41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>More recently, this concern was raised by 3 independent nonhuman primate studies suggesting antibody-dependent enhancement by weakly- or nonneutralizing antibodies administered via passive infusion or induced by vaccination strategies similar to VAX003 and RV144 [19, 20, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Because the VAX003 immunogen elicited a nonprotective response akin to in vitro and animal model experiments invoking enhancement [40, 42], we reasoned the VAX003 trial warranted assessment for vaccine-associated enhancement using T/F analyses [19, 20, 42, 43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>We found no evidence that antibodies elicited by the AIDSVAX vaccine led to enhancement of HIV-1 infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In fact, our T/F analysis of the VAX003 trial revealed a trend, albeit statistically nonsignificant, toward a vaccine-related reduction with lower frequency of MVT and numbers of T/F viruses in vaccinees compared with the placebo arm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Further, we saw no examples of vaccine recipients with high numbers of T/F viruses, with at most 3 T/F viruses establishing infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The lack of enhancement in virus acquisition measured by T/F analysis of VAX003 may reduce concerns that an ineffective antibody response may lead to enhancement of clinical infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Our last question was whether VAX003 subjects' T/F sequences had evidence of vaccine-associated selection, or a sieve effect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We chose to study T/F viruses rather than evolved virus populations represented later in infection (beyond 100 days) to focus on the earliest immune pressures present at or near the time of transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This strategy had an associated cost in statistical power that studying the entire VAX003 cohort may have increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Despite the restricted sample size, the VAX003 sieve analysis demonstrated modest evidence of an atypical sieve effect at Env position 170. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This signature of vaccine-associated selection corroborates and complements the RV144 analysis, which implicated typical and atypical sieve effects in the same V2 crown region, both of which were associated with increased VE and supported by biological correlates analyses [17, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Atypical (ie, greater mismatch in the placebo sequences) sieve effects are in some ways counterintuitive and provocative but are supported by the associated VE shown in the RV144 sieve analysis and merit further study [18, 44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>In summary, our analyses of the T/F viruses in 50 VAX003 subjects showed a surprisingly low multiplicity of HIV-1 infection in IDUs, indicating that a successful vaccine or other prevention modality generally needs to protect against only 1 or a few viruses regardless of mode of acquisition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The stringent HIV-1 transmission bottleneck in both mucosal (sexual) and nonmucosal (IDU) transmission suggests that formidable barriers to HIV transmission lie both within and outside of the genital mucosa. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health Center for HIV/AIDS Vaccine Immunology (U19AI067854), the Center for HIV/AIDS Vaccine Immunology and Immunogen Development (UM1AI100645), the Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation (grant 37874), and the W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Smith Charitable Trust. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_1_2_ofu056__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_ofu056_ofu056supp.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank Faruk Sinangil and Keith Higgins at Global Solutions for Infectious Diseases for sample coordination, Patricia Crystal for manuscript preparation, and the University of Pennsylvania Center for AIDS Research SGA Sequencing Core for sequencing support. They also acknowledge the Bangkok Vaccine Evaluation Group members and valued contributions of the VAX003 trial participants.</p><p><bold><italic>Conflict of Interest Statement:</italic></bold> None of the authors of the article have any commercial or other association that would pose a conflict of interest with this work.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="OFU056C1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>1(UNAIDS) JUNPoHAGlobal Report: UNAIDS report on the global AIDS epidemic 20132013In: Data WLC-i-P, ed. http://www.unaids.org/en/media/unaids/contentassets/documents/epidemiology/2013/gr/UNAIDS_Global_Report__en.pdf </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C2"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>2KeeleBFGiorgiEESalazar-GonzalezJFIdentification and characterization of transmitted and early founder virus envelopes in primary HIV-1 infectionProc Natl Acad Sci USA20081057552718490657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C3"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>3HaalandREHawkinsPASalazar-GonzalezJInflammatory genital infections mitigate a severe genetic bottleneck in heterosexual transmission of subtype A and C HIV-1PLoS Pathog20095e100027419165325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C4"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>4AbrahamsMRAndersonJAGiorgiEEQuantitating the multiplicity of infection with human immunodeficiency virus type 1 subtype C reveals a non-poisson distribution of transmitted variantsJ Virol20098335566719193811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C5"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>5GreenierJLMillerCJLuDRoute of simian immunodeficiency virus inoculation determines the complexity but not the identity of viral variant populations that infect rhesus macaquesJ Virol20017537536511264364 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C6"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>6KeeleBFLiHLearnGHLow-dose rectal inoculation of rhesus macaques by SIVsmE660 or SIVmac251 recapitulates human mucosal infection by HIV-1J Exp Med200920611173419414559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C7"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>7LiuJKeeleBFLiHLow-dose mucosal simian immunodeficiency virus infection restricts early replication kinetics and transmitted virus variants in rhesus monkeysJ Virol201084104061220686016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C8"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>8StoneMKeeleBFMaZMA limited number of simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) env variants are transmitted to rhesus macaques vaginally inoculated with SIVmac251J Virol20108470839520463069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C9"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>9BaggaleyRFBoilyMCWhiteRGRisk of HIV-1 transmission for parenteral exposure and blood transfusion: a systematic review and meta-analysisAIDS2006208051216549963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C10"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>10PowersKAPooleCPettiforAERethinking the heterosexual infectivity of HIV-1: a systematic review and meta-analysisLancet Infect Dis200885536318684670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C11"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>11BarKJLiHChamberlandAWide variation in the multiplicity of HIV-1 infection among injection drug usersJ Virol2010846241720375173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C12"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>12MasharskyAEDukhovlinovaENVerevochkinSVA substantial transmission bottleneck among newly and recently HIV-1-infected injection drug users in St Petersburg, RussiaJ Infect Dis2010201169770220423223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C13"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>13LiHBlairLChenYMolecular mechanisms of HIV type 1 prophylaxis failure revealed by single-genome sequencingJ Infect Dis2013208159860324023257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C14"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>14PitisuttithumPGilbertPGurwithMRandomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled efficacy trial of a bivalent recombinant glycoprotein 120 HIV-1 vaccine among injection drug users in Bangkok, ThailandJ Infect Dis200619416617117109337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C15"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>15Rerks-NgarmSPitisuttithumPNitayaphanSVaccination with ALVAC and AIDSVAX to prevent HIV-1 infection in ThailandN Engl J Med200936122092019843557 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C16"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>16RobbMLRerks-NgarmSNitayaphanSRisk behaviour and time as covariates for efficacy of the HIV vaccine regimen ALVAC-HIV (vCP1521) and AIDSVAX B/E: a post-hoc analysis of the Thai phase 3 efficacy trial RV 144Lancet Infect Dis201212531722652344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C17"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>17RollandMTovanabutraSdeCampACGenetic impact of vaccination on breakthrough HIV-1 sequences from the STEP trialNat Med2011173667121358627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C18"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>18RollandMEdlefsenPTLarsenBBIncreased HIV-1 vaccine efficacy against viruses with genetic signatures in Env V2Nature20124904172022960785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C19"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>19BurtonDRHessellAJKeeleBFLimited or no protection by weakly or nonneutralizing antibodies against vaginal SHIV challenge of macaques compared with a strongly neutralizing antibodyProc Natl Acad Sci USA201110811181621690411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C20"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>20SholukhAMByrareddySNShanmuganathanVPassive immunization of macaques with polyclonal anti-SHIV IgG against a heterologous tier 2 SHIV: outcome depends on IgG doseRetrovirology201411824444350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C21"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>21FiebigEWWrightDJRawalBDDynamics of HIV viremia and antibody seroconversion in plasma donors: Implications for diagnosis and staging of primary HIV infectionAIDS2003171871912960819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C22"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>22LiHBarKJWangSHigh Multiplicity Infection by HIV-1 in Men Who Have Sex with MenPLoS Pathog20106e100089020485520 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C23"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>23StamatakisARAxML-VI-HPC: maximum likelihood-based phylogenetic analyses with thousands of taxa and mixed modelsBioinformatics20062226889016928733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C24"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>24LeeHYGiorgiEEKeeleBFModeling sequence evolution in acute HIV-1 infectionJ Theor Biol20092613416019660475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C25"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>25RollandMLarsenBBEdlefsenPTSequence Analysis of HIV-1 Breakthrough Infections in the RV144 TrialAIDS Vaccine2011Bangkok, Thailand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Page 46 Abstract S07.02 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C26"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>26BenjaminiYHochbergYControlling the false discovery rate—a practical and powerful approach to multiple testingJ R Stat Soc Ser B-Stat Methodol199557289300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C27"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>27GiorgiEEFunkhouserBAthreyaGEstimating time since infection in early homogeneous HIV-1 samples using a poisson modelBMC Bioinformatics20101153220973976 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C28"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>28BarKJTsaoCYIyerSSEarly low-titer neutralizing antibodies impede HIV-1 replication and select for virus escapePLoS Pathog20128e100272122693447 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C29"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>29GoonetillekeNLiuMKSalazar-GonzalezJFThe first T cell response to transmitted/founder virus contributes to the control of acute viremia in HIV-1 infectionJ Exp Med200920612537219487423 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C30"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>30Salazar-GonzalezJFSalazarMGKeeleBFGenetic identity, biological phenotype, and evolutionary pathways of transmitted/founder viruses in acute and early HIV-1 infectionJ Exp Med200920612738919487424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C31"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>31GilbertPBWuCJobesDVGenome scanning tests for comparing amino acid sequences between groupsBiometrics20086419820717608781 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C32"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>32HaynesBFGilbertPBMcElrathMJImmune-correlates analysis of an HIV-1 vaccine efficacy trialN Engl J Med201236612758622475592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C33"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>33KralAHBluthenthalRNLorvickJSexual transmission of HIV-1 among injection drug users in San Francisco, USA: risk-factor analysisLancet2001357139740111356437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C34"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>34MartinMVanichseniSSuntharasamaiPDrug use and the risk of HIV infection amongst injection drug users participating in an HIV vaccine trial in Bangkok, 1999–2003Int J Drug Policy20102129630120079620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C35"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>35MaZMStoneMPiatakMJr.High specific infectivity of plasma virus from the pre-ramp-up and ramp-up stages of acute simian immunodeficiency virus infectionJ Virol20098332889719129448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C36"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>36BaggaleyRFWhiteRGBoilyMCHIV transmission risk through anal intercourse: systematic review, meta-analysis and implications for HIV preventionInt J Epidemiol20103910486320406794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C37"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>37BellDMOccupational risk of human immunodeficiency virus infection in healthcare workers: An overviewAm J Med19971029159845490 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C38"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>38WawerMJGrayRHSewankamboNKRates of HIV-1 transmission per coital act, by stage of HIV-1 infection, in Rakai, UgandaJ Infect Dis20051911403915809897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C39"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>39JinFJanssonJLawMPer-contact probability of HIV transmission in homosexual men in Sydney in the era of HAARTAIDS2010249071320139750 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C40"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>40GorlaniAForthalDNAntibody-dependent enhancement and the risk of HIV infectionCurr HIV Res201311421624191936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C41"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>41RobinsonWEJr.MontefioriDCMitchellWMA human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) infection-enhancing factor in seropositive seraBiochem Biophys Res Commun198714969393426595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C42"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>42PeguPVaccariMGordonSAntibodies with high avidity to the gp120 envelope protein in protection from simian immunodeficiency virus SIV(mac251) acquisition in an immunization regimen that mimics the RV-144 Thai trialJ Virol20138717081923175374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C43"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="?"><plain>43KijakGHKimJHTiming, adherence, resistance, and … persistence? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>New insight into the mechanisms of failure of HIV type 1 postexposure prophylaxisJ Infect Dis20132081542424023256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="OFU056C44"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>44EdlefsenPTGilbertPBRollandMSieve analysis in HIV-1 vaccine efficacy trialsCurr Opin HIV AIDS20138432623719202 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
