
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biomed Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biomed Res Int</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BMRI</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BioMed Research International</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2314-6133</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2314-6141</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4338376</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2015/168292</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Comparative Analysis of Quinolone Resistance in Clinical Isolates of Klebsiella pneumoniae and Escherichia coli from Chinese Children and Adults </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogutu</surname><given-names>James O.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Jiarui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Fengshu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>Yuhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Wenjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Zhiwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Wenli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Xiaobei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>Yingmei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Fengmin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor2">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Microbiology, Pathogenic Biology, Harbin Medical University, Harbin, Heilongjiang 150081, China</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Heilongjiang Provincial Key Laboratory of Immunity and Infection, Harbin, Heilongjiang 150081, China</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Harbin Children's Hospital, Harbin, Heilongjiang 150081, China</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Laboratory Diagnosis, Heilongjiang Provincial Hospital, Harbin, Heilongjiang 150081, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Yingmei Fu: <email>yingmeifu@foxmail.com</email> and </corresp><corresp id="cor2">*Fengmin Zhang: <email>fengminzhang@ems.hrbmu.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Teresa M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Coque </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>2015</volume><elocation-id>168292</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2015 Ying Huang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The objective of this study was to compare quinolone resistance and gyrA mutations in clinical isolates of Klebsiella pneumoniae and Escherichia coli from Chinese adults who used quinolone in the preceding month and children without any known history of quinolone administration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The antimicrobial susceptibilities of 61 isolates from children and 79 isolates from adults were determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>The mutations in the quinolone resistance-determining regions in gyrA gene were detected by PCR and DNA sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Fluoroquinolone resistance and types of gyrA mutations in isolates from children and adults were compared and statistically analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>No significant differences were detected in the resistance rates of ciprofloxacin and levofloxacin between children and adults among isolates of the two species (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The double mutation Ser83→Leu + Asp87→Asn in the ciprofloxacin-resistant isolates occurred in 73.7% isolates from the children and 67.9% from the adults, respectively (P = 0.5444). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Children with no known history of quinolone administration were found to carry fluoroquinolone-resistant Enterobacteriaceae isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The occurrence of ciprofloxacin resistance and the major types of gyrA mutations in the isolates from the children were similar to those from adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that precautions should be taken on environmental issues resulting from widespread transmission of quinolone resistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>It is widely accepted that overuse of antibiotics in hospitals and communities is one of the major contributing factors to bacterial resistance [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>However, it is worth noting that decreasing antibiotic use does not necessarily directly correspond to complete eradication of antimicrobial resistance in bacterial populations [2, 3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that drug resistance and its determinants could persist in the bacterium even in the absence of the corresponding antibiotics [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it has recently been shown that quinolone resistance also develops in the absence of antibiotic selective pressure [4, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we may postulate that the existence of antimicrobial-resistant isolates from clinical cases may not necessarily result from antimicrobial use. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Fluoroquinolones have been widely used in the treatment of a variety of infections due to their broader antimicrobial spectra and improved pharmacokinetic properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>However, the problem of quinolone resistance is becoming increasingly serious with the extensive use of the agents [6, 7]. Klebsiella pneumoniae and Escherichia coli are the two most common quinolone-resistant Enterobacteriaceae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Resistance to quinolones in enterobacteria is mainly due to mutations in the quinolone target enzymes (DNA gyrase and topoisomerase IV) encoded by gyrA and parC [8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Besides, plasmid-mediated quinolone resistance genes also confer low levels of quinolone resistance [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Due to their adverse effects on children's cartilage, the prescription of quinolones has been restricted from pediatric cases [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Thus, children can be considered as a population lacking exposure to quinolones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>With the purpose of investigating drug resistance among people with and without the history of fluoroquinolone administration within the same area, we collected the clinical isolates of K. pneumoniae and E. coli from both preschool children, who have no known history of quinolone administration, and adults, who used quinolone in the preceding month of the sample collection, in Harbin, Heilongjiang, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Fluoroquinolone resistance and types of gyrA mutation in the clinical isolates were detected and compared between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Bacterial Collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>During the period of March to December 2009, 77 K. pneumoniae and 63 E. coli nonrepetitive isolates were consecutively collected from three tertiary hospitals in Harbin city, the provincial headquarters of Heilongjiang province, Northeast China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Seventy-nine isolates came from adult patients while sixty-one isolates from children, comprising 21 infants (&lt;1 year), 20 toddlers (1–3 years), and 20 preschoolers (3–6 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The strains were isolated from stool, nasopharyngeal swabs, and sputum samples of in-patients in surgical wards, internal medicine wards, intensive care units, and pediatric wards. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>A questionnaire surveyed information about quinolone usage in children and adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The clinical strains were obtained only from children without the history of quinolone administration and adults who had taken quinolones in the four weeks preceding specimen collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>All the specimen providers or the children's guardians agreed to participate in the research projects and signed the informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The Institute Research Board of Harbin Medical University checked and approved the study (Report number HMUIRB20140009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Identification of the bacteria to species level was done through the API 20E system (BioMérieux, Marcy-I'Etoile, France). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>All isolates were confirmed as nonreplicate strains by Randomly Amplified Polymorphism DNA (RAPD) analysis (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Antimicrobial Susceptibility Test </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Minimum Inhibitory Concentrations (MICs) of ciprofloxacin were determined by the microdilution method according to Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute (CLSI) guidelines [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The susceptibility to other antimicrobial agents was determined using Kirby-Bauer disk diffusion test with antimicrobial agent discs (OXOID, UK) following the CLSI guidelines [13]. E. coli ATCC 25922 and K. pneumoniae ATCC 10031 were used as means of quality control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Isolates with reduced susceptibility to third generation cephalosporins were subjected to phenotypic detection of ESBL production by using cefotaxime (CTX) and ceftazidime (CAZ) discs and double-disk synergy (DDS) method as recommended by the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>AmpC production was detected using cefoxitin alone and in combination with boronic acid and confirmation was done by three-dimensional disk method. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Isolates with reduced susceptibility to cefoxitin were subjected to a modified three-dimensional extract test to confirm AmpC production [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Amplification and Sequencing of the gyrA Gene Fragments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>All isolates of K. pneumoniae and E. coli were used to determine the DNA sequence of QRDR of gyrA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotide primers used for amplification of fragments encompassing the QRDR were gyrA-F (5′-TGCGAGAGAAATTACACC-3′) and gyrA-R (5′-AATATGTTCCATCAGCCC-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The gyrA gene fragments were amplified from crude cell lysates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>PCR products were purified and then subjected to bidirectional sequencing using an automated DNA sequencer (ABI PRISM 373; Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) with the same primers used in the PCR amplification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequences and the deduced amino acids were compared to that of K. pneumoniae ATCC 13883 (GenBank DQ673325) and E. coli K-12 (GenBank NC_010473.1) using the online ClustalW2 multiple sequence alignment program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>All the experiments were performed in accordance with relevant guidelines and regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The partial sequences of the variant gyrA genes in the clinical isolates were submitted to GenBank under accession numbers EU430280 through EU430289 and JQ694717 through JQ694722. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Statistical Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Resistance rates among the isolates were analyzed with paired chi-square test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Comparisons of fluoroquinolone resistance and individual GyrA alterations between adults and children of all age groups were analyzed by Fisher's exact test or Pearson chi-square test (IBM SPSS 16.0 statistical package). P &lt; 0.05 was considered as statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Antimicrobial Resistance in K. pneumoniae and E. coli Isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>A comparison of antimicrobial agent susceptibility between isolates from children and adults in K. pneumoniae and E. coli was shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Among isolates of the two species, there were no significant differences in the resistance rates of ciprofloxacin and levofloxacin between children and adults (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>In K. pneumoniae, the MIC50, MIC90, and MIC range for ciprofloxacin in isolates from children and adults were 8 mg/L versus 2 mg/L, 256 mg/L versus 256 mg/L, and 0.5–256 mg/L versus 0.5–512 mg/L, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In E. coli isolates from children and adults, the ciprofloxacin MIC50 was 64 mg/L versus 64 mg/L, MIC90 was 128 mg/L versus 256 mg/L, and MIC range was 0.5–512 mg/L versus 1–512 mg/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of ciprofloxacin resistance in children varied with the age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Resistance to ciprofloxacin was found in 37.5% of the isolates from infants aged under 6 months, which was lower than the percentage observed in the other age groups (69.23% of 6-month to 1-year infants, 70.0% of 1- to 3-year toddlers, and 60.0% of 3- to 6-year preschool children). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 1, resistance rates to other classes of antimicrobial agents in E. coli isolated from children and adults were quite similar (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>However, in K. pneumoniae, the resistance rates for cefotaxime, ceftriaxone, and ceftazidime in children were statistically higher than those in adults (all P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Occurrences of the production of extended-spectrum beta-lactamases (ESBLs) isolates from children and adults were 57.9% and 38.5%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In contrast, cefoxitin resistance rate was significantly lower in the isolates from children (P = 0.0085). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Of note, the occurrence of AmpC in children was 7.9%, which is similar to that in adults (15.4%, the Fisher exact test P = 0.4806). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The amikacin resistance rate of K. pneumoniae in children is also higher than that of adults (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Among the resistant isolates from adults, 9 (23.1%) were found an absence of inhibition zone around the amikacin disc (diameter &lt;6 mm), while 25 (65.8%) of the isolates from children were observed to have this phenomenon (χ 2 = 14.2398, P = 0.0002, Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Resistance to Ciprofloxacin and gyrA Mutations in Isolates from Children and Adults </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>All the 140 isolates were investigated for QRDR mutations of gyrA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>46 of the 61 isolates (75.4%) from children were found to contain gyrA mutations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>A similar prevalence pattern of the gyrA mutation was also observed in the isolates of adult origin (64/79, 81.0%, P = 0.43). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Among the 38 isolates resistant to ciprofloxacin from children, 37 (97.4%, 37/38) were found to contain the gyrA mutation, which is quite similar to the prevalence in isolates from adults (55/56, 98.2%, P = 1.00). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table 2, the double mutation Ser83→Leu + Asp87→Asn was the most prevalent type of GyrA changes in antimicrobial-resistant isolates from both children and adults (73.7% versus 67.9%, P = 0.5444). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The single mutation Ser83→Ile was not detected in the isolates from children but was detected in 19.6% of the isolates from adults (P = 0.0026). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The single mutation Ser83→Leu was detected in 18.4% of the isolates from children but was not found in those from adults (P = 0.0012, Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>GryA mutation was also found in 18 isolates nonresistant to ciprofloxacin, including 9 isolates from children and 9 isolates from adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The mutation patterns were listed in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>GyrA Mutations in Children with Different Age Groups </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The 61 isolates from children were assigned into 4 groups according to physiological development and participation in social activities, namely, young infants (&lt;6 months), infants (6–12 months), toddlers (1–3 years), and preschoolers (age of 3–6 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>It was found that the mutations Ser83→Leu + Asp87→Asn, Ser83→Leu, Ser83→Thr, and Asp87→Asn were the common types of mutations in GyrA, and Ser83→Leu + Asp87→Asn was the most prevalent double mutation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In addition, there was no significant difference in terms of individual types of mutation in GyrA in children among different age groups (P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>There is a growing concern over antibiotics resistance as a result of antibiotics overuse in hospital and communities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Thus, restriction on the use of antibiotics has become one of the most important measures for control emergence and spread of drug-resistant bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This study involves clinical isolates obtained from children in the absence of fluoroquinolone usage history, as quinolones are not recommended for pediatric use due to the adverse effects on joints. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>However, our findings showed that children harbored quinolone-resistant isolates being similarly resistant to ciprofloxacin and levofloxacin compared with the isolates from adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Moreover, isolates from children were found to have similarly high ciprofloxacin MIC levels with those from adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>By sequencing the QRDRs of gyrA, we found that the double mutation Ser83→Leu + Asp87→Asn was similarly predominant among the quinolone-resistant isolates from both children and adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A previous study conducted in Spain found 5% resistance rate of ciprofloxacin in E. coli isolates from healthy children [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Other studies have also recorded quinolone-resistant Enterobacteriaceae from children in recent years [17, 18]. GyrA mutations involved in quinolone resistance in isolates from infants were most recently discovered in Spain [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The resistance rate to ciprofloxacin in children was up to 22% in these regions [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Compared to these regions, the ciprofloxacin resistance rate and the resistant level (MIC) found in the present study are notably higher. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In spite of the difference in resistance rate and resistant level, the findings in the present study and others demonstrated the quinolone resistance and the involved mutation mechanisms in nonexposed population under high antibiotic pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>It indicates that drug resistance may be transmitted and persist in people who are not exposed to the corresponding antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Various reports on the different aspects of resistance have revealed that persistence of resistance in human or animal populations relies more on the transmission of resistance in the public environment than on drug pressure [5, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Drug-resistant isolates of bacteria were detected even in remote mountainous areas of Amazon where antibiotics have never been used [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Presence of drug-resistant isolates in children might be attributed to their increased contact with adults and playmates in families, daycare, or school settings [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Among the environmental factors, food supply chain may be the major source of antibiotic resistance in “naïve” humans as an indirect consequence of overuse of antibiotics for curative and preventative purpose in stock farming and agricultural products. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In 2000, the use of antibiotics in raising animals was questioned [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Shortly after, antibiotic-resistant E. coli was detected in poultry products [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The situation of antibiotic-resistant bacteria from food chain sources has become a notable societal issue which should be worthy of attention [25–29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, pollution by antibiotic resistance genes from stock farming and antibiotics in manure and metabolites could increase the chances of resistance acquisition by human pathogens [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In summary, our data showed similar prevalence of quinolone resistance and type of gyrA gene mutation in E. coli and K. pneumoniae among children and adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The conclusion that there exists similarity in fluoroquinolone resistance rates between children and adults in a region under high community antibiotic pressure constrains us to pay close attention to the environmental and community reservoirs of resistance and take precautions to prevent perpetuating antibiotic-resistant isolates and their transmission and dissemination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by grants from National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC) (81101300, 31370164, J1103609, and J1210062), Heilongjiang Educational Agency (1155G34), Heilongjiang Provincial Science and Technology Innovation Team in Higher Education Institutes for Infection and Immunity, and Harbin Medical University. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>All authors declare that they have no conflict of interests.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title>Authors' Contribution</title><p>Ying Huang, Yingmei Fu, and Fengmin Zhang participated in the design, conduction, analysis, and interpretation of the study. Ying Huang, James O. Ogutu, and Jiarui Gu were involved in all phases of the experiment. Fengshu Ding, Yuhong You, and Yan Huo were involved in the manipulation of clinical isolates. Hong Zhao and Wenjing Li were involved in the DNA sequencing. Zhiwei Zhang, Wenli Zhang, and Xiaobei Chen conducted the statistical analysis. Ying Huang wrote the paper. Yingmei Fu and Fengmin Zhang reviewed the initial and final drafts of the paper. All authors read and approved the final paper.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>1JohnsenP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>J.TownsendJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>P.BøhnT.SimonsenG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>S.SundsfjordA.NielsenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>M.Factors affecting the reversal of antimicrobial-drug resistanceThe Lancet Infectious Diseases20099635736410.1016/S1473-3099(09)70105-72-s2.0-6564910228519467475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>2HennessyT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>W.PetersenK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>M.BrudenD.Changes in antibiotic-prescribing practices and carriage of penicillin-resistant Streptococcus pneumoniae: a controlled intervention trial in rural AlaskaClinical Infectious Diseases200234121543155010.1086/3405342-s2.0-003709763612032887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>3BarkaiG.GreenbergD.Givon-LaviN.DreifussE.VardyD.DaganR.Community prescribing and resistant Streptococcus pneumoniae Emerging Infectious Diseases200511682983710.3201/eid1106.0501982-s2.0-1934436231115963276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>4PallecchiL.BartoloniA.RiccobonoE.Quinolone resistance in absence of selective pressure: the experience of a very remote community in the Amazon forestPLoS Neglected Tropical Diseases201268e17902-s2.0-8486598517710.1371/journal.pntd.0001790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>5Quintana-HayashiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>P.ThakurS.Phylogenetic analysis reveals common antimicrobial resistant Campylobacter coli population in antimicrobial-free (ABF) and commercial swine systemsPLoS ONE201279e4466210.1371/journal.pone.00446622-s2.0-84866314918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>6Martínez-MartínezL.PascualA.JacobyG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>A.Quinolone resistance from a transferable plasmidThe Lancet1998351910579779910.1016/s0140-6736(97)07322-42-s2.0-0032515790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>7MontesM.TamayoE.OrdenB.LarruskainJ.Perez-TralleroE.Prevalence and clonal characterization of Streptococcus pyogenes clinical isolates with reduced fluoroquinolone susceptibility in SpainAntimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy2010541939710.1128/aac.00780-092-s2.0-7384910490919805559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>8HopkinsK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>L.DaviesR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>H.ThrelfallE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>J.Mechanisms of quinolone resistance in Escherichia coli and Salmonella: recent developmentsInternational Journal of Antimicrobial Agents200525535837310.1016/j.ijantimicag.2005.02.0062-s2.0-1764440506715848289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>9WeigelL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>M.StewardC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>D.TenoverF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>C. gyrA mutations associated with fluoroquinolone resistance in eight species of Enterobacteriaceae Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy19984210266126672-s2.0-00316874729756773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>10RobicsekA.JacobyG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>A.HooperD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>C.The worldwide emergence of plasmid-mediated quinolone resistanceLancet Infectious Diseases200661062964010.1016/s1473-3099(06)70599-02-s2.0-3374888524017008172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>11Committee on Infectious DiseasesThe use of systemic fluoroquinolonesPediatrics200611831287129210.1542/peds.2006-172216951028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>12Clinical and Laboratory Standards InstituteMethods for Dilution Antimicrobial Susceptibility Tests for Bacteria That Grow Aerobically20098thWayne, Pa, USACLSI(M07-A8) </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>13PfallerM.BoykenL.HollisR.Comparison of the broth microdilution methods of the European Committee on Antimicrobial Susceptibility Testing and the Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute for testing itraconazole, posaconazole, and voriconazole against Aspergillus isolatesJournal of Clinical Microbiology20114931110111210.1128/jcm.02432-102-s2.0-7995232038821209166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>14Clinical and Laboratory Standards InstitutePerformance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Twentieth informational supplementM100-S20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Wayne, Pa, USA: CLSI; 2010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>15Clinical and Laboratory Standards InstitutePerformance standards for antimicrobial susceptibility testing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Eighteenth informational supplement2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>16DomínguezE.ZarazagaM.SáenzY.BriñasL.TorresC.Mechanisms of antibiotic resistance in Escherichia coli isolates obtained from healthy children in SpainMicrobial Drug Resistance20028432132710.1089/107662902604695892-s2.0-003692655312523629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>17AyatollahiJ.ShahcheraghiH.AkhondiR.SolutiS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>S.Antibiotic resistance patterns of Escherichia coli isolated from children in shahid sadoughi hospital of YazdIranian Journal of Pediatric Hematology and Oncology201332788224575275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>18GarraffoA.MarguetC.ChecouryA.Urinary tract infections in hospital pediatrics: many previous antibiotherapy and antibiotics resistance, including fluoroquinolonesMedecine et Maladies Infectieuses2014442636810.1016/j.medmal.2013.12.0022-s2.0-8489673929724512734 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>19PonsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>J.MosquitoS.GomesaC.del ValleL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>J.OchoaT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>J.RuizJ.Analysis of quinolone-resistance in commensal and diarrheagenic Escherichia coli isolates from infants in lima, PeruTransactions of the Royal Society of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene20141081222810.1093/trstmh/trt1062-s2.0-8489128397624306130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>20Quintana-HayashiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>P.ThakurS.Longitudinal study of the persistence of antimicrobial-resistant Campylobacter strains in distinct swine production systems on farms, at slaughter, and in the environmentApplied and Environmental Microbiology20127882698270510.1128/aem.07723-112-s2.0-8486111900022307299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>21IsendahlJ.Turlej-RogackaA.ManjubaC.RodriguesA.GiskeC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>G.NauclérP.Fecal carriage of ESBL-producing E. coli and K. pneumoniae in children in Guinea-Bissau: a hospital-based cross-sectional studyPLoS ONE2012712e5198110.1371/journal.pone.00519812-s2.0-84871426389 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>22PiresR.ArdanuyC.RoloD.Emergence of ciprofloxacin-nonsusceptible Streptococcus pyogenes isolates from healthy children and pediatric patients in PortugalAntimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy20105462677268010.1128/aac.01536-092-s2.0-7795259420720350943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>23BywaterR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>J.CasewellM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>W.An assessment of the impact of antibiotic resistance in different bacterial species and of the contribution of animal sources to resistance in human infectionsJournal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy2000466p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>105210.1093/oxfordjournals.jac.a020886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>24JohnsonJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>R.SannesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>R.CroyC.Antimicrobial drug-resistant Escherichia coli from humans and poultry products, Minnesota and Wisconsin, 2002–2004Emerging Infectious Diseases200713683884610.3201/eid1306.0615762-s2.0-3425002100217553221 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>25BagheriM.GhanbarpourR.AlizadeH.Shiga toxin and beta-lactamases genes in Escherichia coli phylotypes isolated from carcasses of broiler chickens slaughtered in IranInternational Journal of Food Microbiology2014177162010.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2014.02.0032-s2.0-8489685750224590116 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>26CossiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>C.BurinR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>K.LopesD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>A.Antimicrobial resistance and virulence profiles of Salmonella isolated from butcher shops in minas gerais, BrazilJournal of Food Protection20137691633163710.4315/0362-028x.jfp-13-1192-s2.0-8488469142323992511 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>27ReichF.AtanassovaV.KleinG.Extended-spectrum beta-lactamase- and ampc-producing enterobacteria in healthy broiler chickens, GermanyEmerging Infectious Diseases20131981253125910.3201/eid1908.1208792-s2.0-8488070860723876576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>28MellataM.Human and avian extraintestinal pathogenic Escherichia coli: infections, zoonotic risks, and antibiotic resistance trendsFoodborne Pathogens and Disease2013101191693210.1089/fpd.2013.15332-s2.0-8488667948723962019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>29HolvoetK.SampersI.CallensB.DewulfJ.UyttendaeleM.Moderate prevalence of antimicrobial resistance in Escherichia coli isolates from lettuce, irrigation water, and soilApplied and Environmental Microbiology201379216677668310.1128/aem.01995-132-s2.0-8488693721623974140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>30MartinezJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>L.Environmental pollution by antibiotics and by antibiotic resistance determinantsEnvironmental Pollution2009157112893290210.1016/j.envpol.2009.05.0512-s2.0-6924920546519560847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Resistance of 140 K. pneumoniae and E. coli isolates to antimicrobial agents in children and adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>
<sup>*</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tab2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>GyrA mutations in Enterobacteriaceae isolated from children and adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>
<sup>*</sup>
<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
