<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4708984</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26752595</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-30974</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Engineering of a <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> Strain with High Neutral Protease Producing Capacity and Optimization of Its Fermentation Conditions</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Engineering of a <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> Strain with High Neutral Protease Producing Capacity</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Lian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ping</surname><given-names>Yanhai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>Yingguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Huiying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Huoqing</given-names></name><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Bin</given-names></name><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><addr-line>Key Laboratory for Feed Biotechnology of the Ministry of Agriculture, Feed Research Institute, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, P. R. China</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Shihui</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>National Renewable Energy Lab, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: HH BY. Performed the experiments: HW LY YP. Analyzed the data: HW YB HH. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HW LY HH HL. Wrote the paper: HW HH BY.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>huanghuoqing@caas.cn</email> (HH); <email>binyao@caas.cn</email> (BY)</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e0146373</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2016 Wang et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0146373.pdf"/><abstract><p>The neutral protease has high potential for industrial applications, and attempts to improve enzyme expression level have important application values. In the present study, a neutral protease-encoding gene, <italic>Banpr</italic>, was cloned from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain K11, and a genetic manipulation method specific for this difficult-to-transform strain was developed for the high-level expression of neutral protease. The recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> was constructed in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> strain WB600 and then transformed into strain K11 under optimized conditions. A positive transformant 110N-6 with the highest protease secreting capacity on skim milk plates and great genetic stability for more than 100 generations was selected for further study. Optimization of the fermentation conditions increased the enzyme activity of strain 110N-6 to 8995 &#177; 250 U/ml in flask culture and 28084 &#177; 1282 U/ml in 15-l fermentor, which are significantly higher than that of the native strain K11 and industrial strain <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398, respectively. The high expression level and extreme genetic stability make <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain 110N-6 more favorable for mass production of neutral protease for industrial uses.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was supported by the National Science and Technology Support Program of China (2013BAD10B01-2), and the National High Technology Research and Development Program of China (2013AA102803), and the National Science Foundation for Distinguished Young Scholars of China (31225026), and China Modern Agriculture Research System (CARS-42).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="14"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information file.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information file.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Microbial proteases are among the most important hydrolytic enzymes which dominate the worldwide enzyme market [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. <italic>Bacillus</italic> species are prolific producers of extracellular proteases with a wide range of applications, particularly in the detergent, food, pharmaceutical, leather and chemical industries [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Of the numerous proteases, neutral proteases from <italic>Bacillus</italic> spp. are zinc metalloproteinases with pH optima around 7, and are extensively used in nitrogen control, food industry to reduce the bitterness [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], fresh fish waste treatment [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], soy modification for use as flavors, milk protein modification and in animal feeds preparation [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Though extremely important in industry process, the expression level of neutral protease is only one-fifth to one-tenth of other proteases. The low yield results in relatively high price and consequently limits the wide use of neutral protease. Increasing yield would be of great significance in industrial production of neutral protease.</p><p>Overexpression of related gene by genetic engineering is an enabling technology for improving enzyme productivity. Since 1983, the first cloning and expression of the neutral protease structural gene from <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> CU-21 in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> was reported [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>], the period of gene modification on neutral protease improvement has begun. Up to now, numerous <italic>Bacillus</italic> neutral proteases have been characterized and genes encoding for these enzymes have been cloned and sequenced from <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], <italic>Bacillus thermoproteolyticus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], <italic>Bacillus nematocida</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], <italic>Bacillus caldolyticus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], etc. A number of these studies have undertaken expression of neutral proteases by multicopy plasmids or by modifying regulatory elements in heterologous hosts like <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> or <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic>. However, due to the toxicity of protease to heterologous host and slow processing of pro leader peptide, recombinant expression of neutral protease is very difficult and hampers its commercialization. Therefore, it will be highly efficient to express the multiple copies of a neutral protease gene in host strain by utilizing its own expression elements, allowing for appropriate post-translational modification and localization.</p><p><italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> strain AS.1398, an industrial strain widely used in China, was developed by traditional mutation breeding approaches including UV treatment and chemical mutagenesis and optimization of fermentation parameters and medium over the last century. The yield of neutral protease produced by this strain reached 8000&#8210;10000 U/ml. However, over the past two decades, the neutral protease-producing capacity of strain AS.1398 has not been further improved. Compared with <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> host, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> is also extremely important for commercial processes for exoenzymes as they frequently exhibit higher capacity of secreting proteins than <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic>. The high level production of extracellular enzymes makes <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> interesting particularly for an industrial microbiologist [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>], but <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> is genetically different from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic>. The shortage of efficient genetic transformation method has hindered applying recombinant DNA techniques to this organism.</p><p><italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain K11 shares extremely high sequence identity with strain 1398 and has high neutral protease-producing ability. However, traditional mutagenesis techniques have failed to improve its yield of neutral protease. In the present study, increased production of neutral protease from this difficult to transform strain was achieved by transforming <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 with recombinant construct pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> containing its native promoter, ribosomal binding site, initiation codon and signal sequence to overexpress neutral protease gene. In combination with optimization of fermentation process, the neutral protease yield was increased significantly in both shake flasks and fermentor.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Strains, plasmids and culture conditions</title><p><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> Trans1-T1 cells (TransGen) were routinely grown in LB medium supplemented with 100 &#956;g/ml ampicillin and used for gene cloning. Details of other bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study are listed in <xref rid="pone.0146373.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. <italic>Bacillus</italic> cells were cultured on LB medium at 37&#176;C supplemented with 20&#8722;30 &#956;g/ml kanamycin when necessary. To induce neutral protease production, strain K11 was cultured at 37&#176;C with constant agitation of 200 rpm in the seed medium containing (w/v) 1% tryptone, 1% beef extract and 0.5% NaCl. The fermentation medium consisted of (w/v) 4.0% corn meal, 3.0% wheat bran, 3.0% soybean meal, 0.4% Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, and 0.03% KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0146373.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146373.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0146373.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> Amp<sup>R</sup>, ampicillin resistance; Kan<sup>R</sup>, kanamycin resistance</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Molecular identification of strain K11</title><p>Genomic DNA of strain K11 was extracted according to the standard protocols using the TIANamp Bacteria DNA Kit (Beijing). PCR amplification of the 16S rRNA and <italic>gyrB</italic> genes were performed using bacterial universal primers 27F/1492R and degenerate primers UP-1S/UP-2Sr (<xref rid="pone.0146373.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), respectively. The PCR bands of 1.6 kb and 1.2 kb were purified using Gel extraction kit (Omega) and cloned into the pEASY-T3 vector for sequencing. The sequences were submitted to NCBI website for analysis.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0146373.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Primers used in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146373.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0146373.t002"/></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Quantitative assay of protease activity</title><p>Casein was used as the substrate for protease activity assay and prepared as follows: 1.0 g of casein was dampened with a few drops of 0.5 M NaOH, followed by addition of 80 ml of Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>-NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> buffer (6.02 g/l Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>&#8729;12H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.5 g/l NaH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, pH 7.5). The mixture was stirred constantly while boiled in water for 30 min until the casein was dissolved thoroughly. The mixture was then cooled to room temperature, and the pH and final volume were adjusted to 7.5 and 100 ml, respectively. The protease activity was determined by using the Folin-phenol method of the People's Republic of China GB/T 23527&#8211;2009. Briefly, 0.5 ml of 1% (w/v) casein solution was preheated at 30&#176;C for 10 min, followed by addition of 0.5 ml of 30&#176;C-preheated appropriately diluted enzyme solution. The reaction mixture was incubated at 30&#176;C for 10 min, and 1 ml of 400 mM trichloroacetic acid (TCA) was added to terminate the reaction. The reactions with enzyme addition after TCA were used as controls. After centrifugation at 13,000 g for 5 min, 1 ml of the supernatant was added into a test tube containing 5 ml of 400 mM Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub> and 1 ml of Folin-phenol reagent, followed by incubation at 30&#176;C for 20 min. The absorbance was measured at 680 nm. One unit of protease activity was defined as the amount of enzyme that hydrolyzed casein to produce 1 &#956;g of tyrosine per minute.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Expression vector construction in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic></title><p>To construct of expression vector in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic>, POE-PCR method [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] was employed to increase the ligation efficiency of recombinant plasmid. Primer pairs P1/P2 and P3/P4 (<xref rid="pone.0146373.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>) were used to amplify the vector backbone of pUB110 and <italic>Banpr</italic> gene, respectively. Both PCR products were gel purified and used as templates for the second cycle of PCR without primers. Through natural competence transformation [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], 1&#8722;10 &#956;l of the secondary PCR product was transformed into <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600 competent cells, and Kan-resistant transformants were selected on LB agar plates containing 20 &#956;g/ml kanamycin. Positive transformants were further confirmed by PCR amplification, restriction digest and protease activity detection on 3% (w/v) skim milk plates (forming halos).</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Production of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR in its parent strain</title><p>Recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> was then transformed into its parent strain to achieve overproduction of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR. To introduce foreign DNA into strain K11, a series of parameters, including screening of the optimal growth medium, optimization of electroporation buffers, changing of electroporation conditions, altering the type of DNA transformed (DNA extracted from <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> Tran1-T1, <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> EC135/pM.Bam and <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600), amount of DNA added (50&#8722;100 ng), were examined to prepare the electro-competent cells of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Ultimately, the competent cells of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 were prepared according to protocol following. Briefly, an overnight LB culture of strain K11 was diluted 100-fold with fresh LB medium and grown until the OD<sub>600</sub> reached 0.5. Penicillin of different concentrations (0&#8722;100 &#956;g/ml) was then added. The cultures were incubated overnight until the OD<sub>600</sub> values were 20&#8722;50% of that of controls without penicillin addition under the same conditions, followed by cooling on ice for 20 min. The cells were collected by centrifugation at 4&#176;C, 8000 g for 5 min, and washed three times with ice-cold electroporation buffer (500 mM sorbitol, 500 mM mannitol, and 10% glycerol). After resuspension in 1 ml of electroporation buffer, 80 &#956;l of competent cells were mixed with 5 &#956;l of plasmid pUB110 or pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> (~ 250 ng) extracted from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600. The mixture was kept on ice for 5 min, transferred to a pre-chilled 1 mm gap electroporation cuvette, and immediately electroporated via a Bio-Rad Gene Pulser. Right after the pulse delivery, the cells were diluted into 1 ml of LB medium containing 500 mM sorbitol and 380 mM mannitol (LBSM medium). After incubation at 37&#176;C for 3 h with agitation at 50 rpm, the cells were spread on LB plates containing 30 &#956;g/ml kanamycin for selection of positive transformants containing the episomal plasmids. The number of positive transformants was counted after overnight growth at 37&#176;C, and the copy numbers of <italic>Banpr</italic> were verified by PCR and restriction digest. Colonies with larger clearance zones on skim milk plates were picked up and grown in shake flasks.</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Fermentation of recombinant <italic>Ba</italic>NPR in shake flasks</title><p>The transformants selected above were cultured at 37&#176;C for 10&#8722;12 h with agitation at 200 rpm in seed medium containing 30 &#956;g/ml of kanamycin with the parent strain K11 as a control. Ten milliliters of the seed culture (20% inoculum volume) were inoculated into 500 ml of Erlenmeyer flasks containing 50 ml of fermentation medium and then aerobically grown at 37&#176;C for 2&#8722;3 days in a rotary shaker (200 rpm). The culture supernatants were collected at regular intervals and centrifuged at 13,000 g for 10 min for protease activity assay and electrophoresis analysis on SDS-PAGE. The bands of neutral protease were then excised from the gel for protein identification by matrix assisted laser desorption/ionization time of flight (MALDI-TOF) mass spectrometry at institute of apicultural research of Chinese Academy of Agritual Sciences. The transformant exhibiting the highest enzymatic activity was selected for optimization of culture conditions.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Optimization of fermentation conditions for <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production</title><p>Extracellular protease production is greatly influenced by physical factors such as pH, temperature and incubation time and by others factors such as media composition and presence of metal ions [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The main fermentation factors, including temperature (30 to 37&#176;C), initial pH (6.0 to 8.0), loading volume of culture medium (50 to 200 ml) and inoculum size (2 to 20%), were optimized for maximum production of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR. Moreover, the effect of amino acids (0.05% of methionine, lysine and histidine) and metal ions (0.1% or 0.2% of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, Mg<sup>2+</sup> and Zn<sup>2+</sup>) on <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production were also tested.</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Genetic stability of recombinant strain of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR</title><p>Continuous passage cultivation was conducted to monitor the segregation stability of recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11. The recombinant strains were streaked onto the seed medium agar plates supplemented with 30 &#956;g/ml kanamycin and incubated at 37&#176;C for 12 h. One colony was picked and cultivated in the liquid seed medium containing 30 &#956;g/ml kanamycin for 12 h. The culture was then diluted 10<sup>4</sup>-fold to 10<sup>6</sup>-fold and plated on seed medium agar plates containing antibiotic for growth of 14&#8722;16 h. The colony numbers in each diluted-fold plates were counted, and one hundred colonies were picked randomly and dotted on seed medium agar plates with and without 30 &#956;g/ml kanamycin simultaneously. The number of colonies on each plate was counted and compared to determine the frequency of plasmid loss. The dilution process was repeated at 10-generation intervals for 10 times.</p><p>Enzyme digestion of the recombinant plasmids was conducted to determine the structural stability of pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6. The plasmid extracted from the 100 generations (plasmid B) and the plasmid constructed originally (plasmid A) were digested with multiple restriction enzymes (<italic>Bgl</italic>II/<italic>Nco</italic>I, <italic>EcoR</italic>I and <italic>Bgl</italic>II/<italic>Eco</italic>RV) to confirm the presence of the recombinant plasmid and to examine its structural stability. Plasmid B was then re-transformed into <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 to detect the production of neutral protease. The plasmid from the newly constructed strain <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-N3 (plasmid C) was extracted and digested with the same enzymes above.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Large-scale fermentation of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR in fermentor</title><p>Enhanced neutral protease production by the engineered <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain was scaled up from flask to 15-l bioreactor (Bioengineering) containing 10-l of fermentation medium under batch fermentation conditions with industrial strain <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398 as controls. The fermentation medium was sterilized <italic>in situ</italic> at 121&#176;C for 20 min and inoculated with 300 ml [3.0% (v/v)] of incubated seed culture under OD<sub>600</sub> = 0.4&#8722;0.6. The agitation speed was set to 750 rpm and compressed air was sparged at a flow rate of 1.0 vvm. The initial pH of the fermentation medium was adjusted to 7.0 with NaOH and was monitored but not controlled during fermentation. The fermentor temperature was controlled by the following thermal gradient program: started and maintained at 32&#176;C for initial 3 hours; increased at a rate of 1&#176;C/h until 40&#176;C; decrease at a rate of 1.5&#176;C/h until 32&#176;C; isotherm at 32&#176;C until the end of fermentation. Samples were collected at variable intervals, and the neutral protease activity was estimated. Fermentation was performed in three fermentors simultaneously, and the fermentation procedures were repeated for three times.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Nucleotide sequence accession numbers</title><p>The nucleotide sequences for the 16s rRNA, <italic>gyrB</italic> gene and neutral protease gene (<italic>Banpr</italic>) of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 were deposited in the GenBank database under accession number KM603513, KM603514 and KM603515, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec014"><title>Identification of neutral protease high producing strain</title><p>Phylogenetic analysis of the 16s rDNA gene of strain K11 against known sequences indicated that strain K11 is affiliated with the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic>. <italic>gyrB</italic> encodes the subunit B protein of DNA gyrase and has been proved to be a better molecular marker than the 16S rDNA gene for the study of phylogenetic and taxonomic relationships at specie levels of <italic>Bacilus</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The <italic>gyrB</italic> gene of strain K11 had the highest identity of 99% to that of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> Y2, thus strain K11 was termed as <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic>. It was deposited at Agricultural Culture Collection of China under registration No. ACCC19735.</p></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Cloning and sequence analysis of <italic>Banpr</italic> from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11</title><p>By using the primer set npr-F/npr-R (<xref rid="pone.0146373.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), a gene fragment of 2533 bp was amplified from strain K11, including a 519-bp upstream fragment, a 1563-bp open reading frame (ORF) of <italic>Banpr</italic> and a 448-bp downstream fragment. A possible terminator sequence was found immediately downstream of the ORF in the 3&#8242;-non-coding region. Compared with the corresponding gene sequence of strain Y2, <italic>Banpr</italic> had 12 nucleotide substitutions: 2 occurred in the promoter region, 2 in terminator region, and 8 in the ORF region.</p><p>Multiple alignment of the deduced amino acid sequence of <italic>Banpr</italic> with other neutral proteases is shown in <xref rid="pone.0146373.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>. Deduced <italic>Ba</italic>NPR exhibited 100%, 96%, and 83% sequence identity with the neutral proteases from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> Y2, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398, and <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> strain 168 [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], respectively. It consists of a signal peptide of 27 residues, a pro-region of 194 residues, and a structural region of 300 residues. The calculated molecular mass was predicted to be 32.7 kDa. Modeled <italic>Ba</italic>NPR shows the typical structure of metalloproteinase: the pro-peptide, the catalytic domain, and the haemopexin-like C-terminal domain. Two histidine residues (His 143 and His 147) and catalytic glutamate residue (Glu 144) in the zinc-binding motif sequence and one glutamate residue (Glu 167) chelating the active-site Zn<sup>2+</sup> were also identified in the putative tertiary structure.</p><fig id="pone.0146373.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Multiple amino acid sequence alignment of NPR.</title><p>Amino acid sequence alignment of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 with the NPR from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> Y2, NPRE from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> (<italic>Bacillus velezensis</italic>) (P06832), NPRE from <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> 168 (P68736), NPRE from <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic> (P05806), THER from <italic>Bacillus thermoproteolyticus</italic> (P00800), and NPRE from <italic>Bacillus caldolyticus</italic> (P23384) using the ClustalW program. Two histidine residues in active site are indicated by asterisks.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146373.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec016"><title>Heterologous expression in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic></title><p>Due to the low transformation efficiency using <italic>Bacillus</italic> as the expression host, many shuttle plasmids have been developed to carry out the initial cloning steps in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> and then the recombinant plasmids were transferred into <italic>Bacillus</italic> strains. To facilitate vector construction, we initially attempted to construct the shuttle expression vector of <italic>Banpr</italic> in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>. Only a few ligation mixtures of <italic>Banpr</italic> and linearized shuttle vectors were successfully transformed into <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> Tran1-T1 competent cells as shown on screening plates, and nonsense mutations existed in all colonies. Similar phenomenon also occurred in the report of Tran <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Wang <italic>et al</italic>. [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] had ascribed the lytic effect of <italic>nprE</italic> gene product on <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> cells and removed the ribosome binding site (RBS) of <italic>nprE</italic> to achieve expression and secretion. Therefore, we constructed a recombinant plasmid harboring its original promoter, SD sequence, coding sequence and terminator sequence of <italic>Banpr</italic> in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600, instead of in <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>. These elements are very efficient for expression of <italic>Bacillus</italic> genes that are toxic to <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>.</p><p>By using the POE-PCR method introduced by You et al. [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> was successfully constructed in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600. The positive transformants were verified by PCR amplification, and the accuracy was confirmed by enzyme digest and sequencing. The colonies harboring pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> showed clear halos on skim milk plates, while the controls (protease-deficient <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600 carrying empty plasmid pUB110) did not. It revealed that <italic>Banpr</italic> with its original expression elements was functionally expressed in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600.</p></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>Transformation of recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> into <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11</title><p>It is quite difficult to incorporate foreign DNA into <italic>Bacillus</italic> cells due to the lack of efficient gene transformation system and the existence of R-M systems [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Optimization of hypertonic agents, pulse voltage, and electroporation buffers have been reported to improve the transformation efficiencies; however, these protocols are highly species or strain specific, and the efficiency is relatively variable among strains even using the same protocol [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> has much thicker cell wall. Modifying the cultivation conditions, growth conditions, or amending electroporation parameters such as applied voltage and capacitance and the quality of DNA had no effect on transformation of strain K11. Zhang et al. [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] reported that the walls of vegetative cells grown in semi-complex NCM medium are relatively loose and easy to form pore during electroporation, and consequently more accessible by exogenous plasmid. However, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 showed no growth in NCM medium. Cell-wall-weakening agents gly and DL-thr of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> TA208 [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] did not improve the transformation efficiency in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11, either. The reason might be that the cell-wall carbohydrates varied in the glycosyl compositions of strains TA208 and K11 or different chemical dosages were used. Strain K11 was obtained with the ampicillin concentration up to 100 &#956;g/ml, which is much higher than the previously reported level [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. The different mode of restriction-modification between <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> and <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> makes the transformation of recombinant plasmid extracted from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subilis</italic> WB600 much easier into strain K11 than those from <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>. Recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> was extracted from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> WB600 and transformed into <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 via optimized electroporation method. The positive transformants acquired kanmycin-resistant characteristic were selected on LB plates containing 30 &#956;g/ml of kanamycin and subsequently verified by PCR amplification and enzyme digest.</p></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Overproduction of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11</title><p>Five transformants harboring pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> showed apparent transparent zones on skim milk plates and were further cultivated in shake flasks. Great variance was detected on the protease-producing ability of transformants and parental strain K11 (<xref rid="pone.0146373.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The transformant 110N-6 showed distinguished neutral protease producing capacity (7460 &#177; 51 U/ml) over the parental strain (2694 &#177; 49 U/ml). Because vector pUB110 is an autonomously replicating plasmid, the different levels of protease production should be attributed to the various damages occurred during the electroporation process. The increase of protease productivity in transformant 110N-6 is likely ascribed to the increased copy numbers of <italic>Banpr</italic> and high transcriptional levels.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0146373.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Production of recombinant <italic>Ba</italic>NPR by <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> harboring pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> in shaker flasks<xref rid="t003fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146373.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0146373.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> All data are shown as mean &#177; SD (n = 3)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>A protein band with a molecular mass of about 37 kDa was observed in the culture supernatants of all strains as shown in SDS-PAGE (<xref rid="pone.0146373.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The apparent molecular weight of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR was a little larger than its calculated value (32.7 kDa). Further MALDI-TOF analysis of the band verified the identity of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR and revealed complete incision of the signal peptide (<xref rid="pone.0146373.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). The slow mobility of expressed protein on the SDS gel also has been reported in other neutral and alkaline proteases [<xref rid="pone.0146373.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0146373.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. The similar phenomenon might be ascribed to certain modifications of the expressed protein in host cells.</p><fig id="pone.0146373.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>SDS-PAGE analysis of recombinant <italic>Ba</italic>NPR in <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11.</title><p>Lane: M, the molecular mass standards; 1&#8211;3 and 5&#8211;7, the different transformants harboring pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic>; 4, the transformant harboring the empty vector pUB110.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146373.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>Genetic stability of recombinant plasmid</title><p>As shown in <xref rid="pone.0146373.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, the recombinant plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 kept constant during the serial passage process. One hundred colonies were randomly picked up from generations up to 100, and no clone lost in the media with or without antibiotic (<xref rid="pone.0146373.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>). The restriction patterns of plasmid DNA were identical as shown in <xref rid="pone.0146373.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>, suggesting that neither rearrangement nor deletion occurred, and nor obvious spontaneous mutation of DNA sequence generated during the long sequential replication in transformant 110N-6. The neutral protease activity of the newly constructed <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliqefaciens</italic> 110N-N3 at generation 100 reached 7983 U/ml at 72 h in flasks, further confirmed the stability of the plasmid. All the results above proved that the hereditary stability of pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> in <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 was excellent for industrial application. Because it is impractical to add antibotic in large-scale fermentation, plasmid stability is an important factor for industrial applications without selective pressure.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0146373.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Segregation stability of pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> in recombinant <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 by continuous passage cultivation<xref rid="t004fn001" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0146373.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0146373.t004"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p><sup>a</sup> All data are shown as mean &#177; SD (n = 3)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>There are two possible mechanisms to underlie plasmid stability, i.e. segregation stability and structural stability. Under normal circumstances, the structural stability of a plasmid can be achieved by the rigorous selection of host strains. Segregation instability accounts for the majority of plasmid instability. Due to the variations of host&#8217;s metabolic load and copy numbers caused by defective partitioning, cells without plasmid are produced. Adverse environmental conditions and growth competition from the cells without plasmid may further promote the instability of the plasmid. The copy number of the recombinant plasmid represents an important factor to affect plasmid stability. When the cell divides, the plasmids are randomly assigned to the daughter cells. The higher copy number the plasmid has, the lower probability the plasmid-free cells and the more stable the plasmid.</p><p>In this study, the growth curves of recombinant strain 110N-6 and parent strain K11 showed no difference (data not shown), and two recombinant plasmids pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> and pKan300-<italic>Banpr</italic> were constructed simultaneously. Recombinant <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> F20 harboring pKan300-<italic>Banpr</italic> was genetically instable under the same conditions as recombinant <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 containing pKan300-<italic>Banpr</italic>, and lost all recombinant plasmid pKan300-<italic>Banpr</italic> after 8 generations (data not shown). The only difference between these two plasmids is that the <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> expression elements existed in the pKan300-<italic>Banpr</italic> vector of <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> F20. Therefore we speculate that it is the <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> expression elements that cause plasmid instability in <italic>Bacillus</italic> hosts. Therefore, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 with distinguished genetic stability was selected for further optimization and large-scale fermentation.</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Optimization of the culture conditions for <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production</title><p>The optimal conditions for <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production by transformant 110N-6 were investigated in 500 ml shake flasks. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0146373.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>, the optimal fermentation conditions of 110N-6 were determined as initial pH at 6.0, 30&#176;C, 200 rpm/min, 60&#8722;72 h, 50 ml of working volume, and 5% inoculum capacity (<xref rid="pone.0146373.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A&#8722;3D</xref>). Under the optimized conditions, the yield of r-<italic>Ba</italic>NPR increased significantly to 8995 &#177; 250 U/ml, while that of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR only reached 2739 &#177; 472 U/ml (<xref rid="pone.0146373.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4A</xref>). Some amino acids are known to induce protease production. Thus the effect of methionine, lysine and histidine on <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production was also tested. Addition of lysine and histidine had no effect on <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production, but methionine enhanced the production at 48 h (<xref rid="pone.0146373.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3E</xref>). Moreover, the enzyme production was slightly inhibited by Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup>, and completely suppressed by Zn<sup>2+</sup> (<xref rid="pone.0146373.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3F</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0146373.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Optimization of culture conditions for <italic>Ba</italic>NPR production in <italic>Bacillus amyloliqufaciens</italic> 110N-6.</title><p>a Effect of temperature on enzyme production. b Effect of pH on enzyme production. c Effect of working volume on enzyme production. d Effect of inoculum size on enzyme production. e Effect of different amino acids on enzyme production. f Effect of different metal ions on enzyme production. Each value in the panel represents the means &#177; SD (n = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146373.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone.0146373.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146373.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Comparison of the production of neutral protease in shake flasks and fermentors.</title><p>a The enzyme activity of r-<italic>Ba</italic>NPR and <italic>Ba</italic>NPR produced by <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 and <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 on flask level under optimized conditions. b The enzyme activity of r-<italic>Ba</italic>NPR and <italic>Bs</italic>NPR produced by <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> 1398 on large-scale batch production in the fermentor. Each value in the panel represents the means &#177; SD (n = 3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0146373.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Large-scale fermentation of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR</title><p><italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398 has been used for production of neutral protease for several decades in industries. To justify whether the engineered strain 110N-6 with high activity and excellent genetic stability was contestable for industrial production of neutral protease, both recombinant strain <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 and industrial strain <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398 were subjected to large-scale fermentation. As shown in <xref rid="pone.0146373.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4B</xref>, the neutral protease production by <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398 and <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 reached the maximum of 9218 &#177; 754 U/ml and 28084 &#177; 1282 U/ml at about 26 h and 68 h, respectively, and declined after that. Although the rapid production of neutral protease by <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398 is desirable, combined analysis of the yield and fermentation duration reveals that <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 is more efficient (413 U/ml&#183;h vs. 355 U/ml&#183;h) in the production of neutral protease. Therefore, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 constructed in this study with high yield of neutral protease and excellent genetic stability will overcome the bottlenecks (low yield and high price) of neutral protease production, and has the potential to replace <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398 as the industrial strain for neutral protease production.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec022"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In conclusion, a neutral protease-encoding gene, <italic>Banpr</italic>, was cloned from <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> K11 and engineered for overexpression in its native host. By optimization of the fermentation conditions, the <italic>Ba</italic>NPR yield of engineered strain K11 harboring the <italic>Bacillus</italic> expression vector pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic> reached 28084 U/ml in a 15-l fermentor, which is much higher than that of the widely used industrial strain <italic>B</italic>. <italic>subtilis</italic> AS.1398. Moreover, <italic>B</italic>. <italic>amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6 showed excellent genetic stability. All these properties indicate r-<italic>Ba</italic>NPR represents a valuable neutral protease candidate for economic mass-production and industrial applications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec023"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0146373.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Peptides of <italic>Ba</italic>NPR identified by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry.</title><p>(EPS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0146373.s001.eps"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0146373.s002"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Colonies of <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> strain 110N-6 after subcultivation of 100 generations.</title><p>a Seed medium agar plate without kanamycin. b Seed medium agar plate with 30 &#956;g/ml kanamycin.</p><p>(EPS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0146373.s002.eps"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0146373.s003"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Enzyme digestion profile of plasmid pUB110-<italic>Banpr</italic>.</title><p>Lanes: M, the molecular mass standards; 1&#8211;3, plasmid A (the originally constructed plasmid) digested with enzymes <italic>Bgl</italic>II/<italic>Nco</italic>I, <italic>EcoR</italic>I and <italic>Bgl</italic>II/<italic>EcoR</italic>V, respectively; 4&#8211;6, plasmid B (the plasmid extracted from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-6) digested with the same enzymes; 7&#8211;9, plasmid C (the plasmid extracted from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> 110N-N3) digested with the same enzymes.</p><p>(EPS)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0146373.s003.eps"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0146373.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanksale</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghatge</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deshpande</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular and biotechnological aspects of microbial proteases</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <year>1998</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>597</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>635</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 9729602?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9729602</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Horikoshi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Alkaliphiles: some applications of their products for biotechnology</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>750</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10585964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10585964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Proteolytic enzymes</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Pergamon Press</publisher-name>
<year>1985</year>; <fpage>789</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>818</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sandhya</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sumantha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Szakacs</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashok</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparative evaluation of neutral protease production by <italic>Aspergillus oryzae</italic> in submerged and solid-state fermentation</article-title>. <source>Process Biochem</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>2689</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2694</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bhaskar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mahendrakar</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Protein hydrolysate from visceral waste proteins of Catla (<italic>Catla catla</italic>): Optimization of hydrolysis conditions for a commercial neutral protease</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source>. <year>2008</year>; <volume>99</volume>: <fpage>4105</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4111</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17933524?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17933524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>OP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nature of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cell lysis by culture supernatants of <italic>Bacillus</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1893</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1898</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1892379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1892379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aiba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular cloning of a thermostable neutral protease gene from <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> in a vector plasmid and its expression in <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic> and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1983</year>; <volume>154</volume>: <fpage>831</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>837</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 6302083?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6302083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Takagi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aiba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Nucleotide sequence and promoter region for the neutral protease gene from <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1985</year>, <volume>163</volume>: <fpage>824</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>831</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2993245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2993245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning and expression of a novel protease gene encoding an extracellular neutral protease from <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>173</volume>: <fpage>6364</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6372</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1917867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1917867</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Devenish</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> neutral protease gene (<italic>nprE</italic>) in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic></article-title>. <source>J Gener Microbiol</source>. <year>1993</year>; <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>343</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>347</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning of the neutral protease gene of <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and the use of the cloned gene to create an in vitro-derived deletion mutation</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1984</year>; <volume>160</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 6090407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6090407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Honjo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manabe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mita</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furutani</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning and expression of the gene for neutral protease of <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Biotechnol</source>. <year>1984</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>265</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>277</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vasantha</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagle</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Filpula</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genes for alkaline protease and neutral protease from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> contain a large open reading frame between the regions coding for signal sequence and mature protein</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1984</year>; <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>819</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 6090391?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6090391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wetmore</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roche</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>. <article-title>The role of the pro-sequence in the processing and secretion of the thermolysin-like neutral protease from <italic>Bacillus cereus</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>1992</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1604</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1495388?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1495388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning and nucleotide sequence of the highly thermostable neutral protease gene from <italic>Bacillus stearathermaphilus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Gen Micrabial</source>. <year>1988</year>; <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>1883</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1892</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mansfeld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Petermann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D&#252;rrschmidt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ulbrich-Hofmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>The propeptide is not required to produce catalytically active neutral protease from <italic>Bacillus stearothermophilus</italic></article-title>. <source>Protein Expr Purif</source>. <year>2005</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>219</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>228</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15642473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minoda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sakurama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hashida</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Extracellular production of recombinant thermolysin expressed in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, and its purification and enzymatic characterization</article-title>. <source>Protein Expr Purif</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>255</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16169746?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16169746</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O'Donohue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roques</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning and expression in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> of the <italic>npr</italic> gene from <italic>Bacillus thermoproteolyticus</italic> Rokko coding for the thermostable metalloprotease thermolysin</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>. <year>1994</year>; <volume>300</volume>: <fpage>599</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>603</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 8002967?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8002967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Niu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A neutral protease from <italic>Bacillus nematocida</italic>, another potential virulence factor in the infection against nematodes</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>185</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>448</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16775750?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16775750</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van den Burg</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Enequist</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Haar</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eijsink</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stulp</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Venema</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>A highly thermostable neutral protease from <italic>Bacillus caldolyticus</italic>: cloning and expression of the gene in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and characterization of the gene product</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>173</volume>: <fpage>4107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4115</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1905714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1905714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Priest</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Extracellular enzyme synthesis in the genus <italic>Bacillus</italic></article-title>. <source>Bacteriol Rev</source>. <year>1977</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>753</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 334155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">334155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>ZP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A mimicking-of-DNA-methylation-patterns pipeline for overcoming the restriction barrier of bacteria</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002987</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002987</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23028379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <article-title>Wong, SL. Engineering a <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> expression-secretion system with a strain deficient in six extracellular proteases</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1991</year>; <volume>173</volume>: <fpage>4952</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4958</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1907264?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1907264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Simple Cloning: direct transformation of PCR product (DNA multimer) to <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> and <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>78</volume>: <fpage>1593</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1595</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.07105-11</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22194286?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22194286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anagnostopoulos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spizizen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Requirements for transformation in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1961</year>; <volume>81</volume>: <fpage>741</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>746</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16561900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16561900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Holo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nes</surname><given-names>IF</given-names></name>. <article-title>High-frequency transformation, by electroporation, of <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic> subsp. <italic>cremoris</italic> grown with glycine in osmotically stabilized media</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>55</volume>: <fpage>3119</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3123</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16348073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16348073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nagane</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Improvement of the electro-transformation efficiency of facultatively alkaliphilic <italic>Bacillus pseudofirmus</italic> OF4 by high osmolarity and glycine treatment</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>. <year>2001</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>2773</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2775</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11826976?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11826976</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vehmaanper&#228;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Transformation of <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> by electroporation</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source>. <year>1989</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>169</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2599355?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2599355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dalrymple</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name>. <article-title>High osmolarity improves the electro-transformation efficiency of the gram-positive bacteria <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> and <italic>Bacillus licheniformis</italic></article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Methods</source>. <year>1999</year>; <volume>34</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>191</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Enhancing electro-transformation competency of recalcitrant <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> by combining cell-wall weakening and cell-membrane fluidity disturbing</article-title>. <source>Anal Biochem</source>. <year>2011</year>; <volume>409</volume>: <fpage>130</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>137</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2010.10.013</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20951110?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20951110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Construction of engineered <italic>Arthrobacter simplex</italic> with improved performance for cortisone acetate biotransformation</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>. <year>2013</year>; <volume>97</volume>: <fpage>9503</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9514</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-013-5172-7</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24037307?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24037307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thys</surname><given-names>RCS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guzzon</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cladera-Olivera</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adriano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Optimization of protease production by <italic>Microbacterium</italic> sp. in feather meal using response surface methodology</article-title>. <source>Process Biochem</source>. <year>2006</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>73</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparison of <italic>gyrB</italic> gene sequences, 16S rRNA gene sequences and DNA-DNA hybridization in the <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> group</article-title>. <source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source>. <year>2007</year>; <volume>57</volume>: <fpage>1846</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1850</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17684269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17684269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ekkel</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Devenish</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Expression in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> of the <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> neutral protease gene (NPRE) lacking its ribosome binding site</article-title>. <source>Biochem Int</source>. <year>1990</year>; <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>1085</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1093</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 2128597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2128597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pridmore</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Juillerat</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Purification and characterization of proteases from <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> isolated from traditional soybean fermentation starter</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>. <year>2003</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>7664</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7670</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14664526?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14664526</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0146373.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Henner</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Estell</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning, sequencing, and secretion of <italic>Bacillus amyloliquefaciens</italic> subtilisin in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic></article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>1983</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>7911</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7925</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 6316278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6316278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>