<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4482717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26114434</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-15-08303</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
<italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> MifS-MifR Two-Component System Is Specific for &#945;-Ketoglutarate Utilization</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">MifS-MifR Dependent &#945;-Ketoglutarate Utilization</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tatke</surname><given-names>Gorakh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>Hansi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001">
<sup>&#164;a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Silva-Herzog</surname><given-names>Eugenia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff002">
<sup>&#164;b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramirez</surname><given-names>Lourdes</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mathee</surname><given-names>Kalai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="currentaff001">
<sup>&#164;a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological Sciences, College of Arts &amp; Sciences, Florida International University, Miami, Florida, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff002">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Molecular Microbiology and Infectious Diseases, Herbert Wertheim College of Medicine, Florida International University, Miami, Florida, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of North Dakota, UNITED STATES</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: GT KM. Performed the experiments: GT HK EH LR. Analyzed the data: GT KM HK. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KM. Wrote the paper: GT KM.</p></fn><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff001"><label>&#164;a</label><p>Current address: Department of Human and Molecular Genetics, Herbert Wertheim College of Medicine, Florida International University, Miami, Florida, United States of America</p></fn><fn fn-type="current-aff" id="currentaff002"><label>&#164;b</label><p>Current address: Department of Molecular, Cellular and Developmental Biology, University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, Colorado, United States of America</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>matheelabfor65roses@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e0129629</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2015 Tatke et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tatke et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0129629.pdf"/><abstract><p>
<italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is a Gram-negative, metabolically versatile opportunistic pathogen that elaborates a multitude of virulence factors, and is extraordinarily resistant to a gamut of clinically significant antibiotics. This ability, in part, is mediated by two-component regulatory systems (TCS) that play a crucial role in modulating virulence mechanisms and metabolism. MifS (PA5512) and MifR (PA5511) form one such TCS implicated in biofilm formation. MifS is a sensor kinase whereas MifR belongs to the NtrC superfamily of transcriptional regulators that interact with RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>). In this study we demonstrate that the <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> genes form a two-gene operon. The close proximity of <italic>mifSR</italic> operon to <italic>poxB</italic> (<italic>PA5514</italic>) encoding a &#223;-lactamase hinted at the role of MifSR TCS in regulating antibiotic resistance. To better understand this TCS, clean in-frame deletions were made in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 creating PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic>. The loss of <italic>mifSR</italic> had no effect on the antibiotic resistance profile. Phenotypic microarray (BioLOG) analyses of PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> revealed that these mutants were unable to utilize C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylate &#945;-ketoglutarate (&#945;-KG), a key tricarboxylic acid cycle intermediate. This finding was confirmed using growth analyses, and the defect can be rescued by <italic>mifR</italic> or <italic>mifSR</italic> expressed in <italic>trans</italic>. These <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants were able to utilize all the other TCA cycle intermediates (citrate, succinate, fumarate, oxaloacetate or malate) and sugars (glucose or sucrose) except &#945;-KG as the sole carbon source. We confirmed that the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants have functional dehydrogenase complex suggesting a possible defect in &#945;-KG transport. The inability of the mutants to utilize &#945;-KG was rescued by expressing <italic>PA5530</italic>, encoding C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylate transporter, under a regulatable promoter. In addition, we demonstrate that besides MifSR and PA5530, &#945;-KG utilization requires functional RpoN. These data clearly suggests that <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifSR TCS is involved in sensing &#945;-KG and regulating its transport and subsequent metabolism.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported in part by the National Institutes of Health &#8211; Minority Biomedical Research Support SCORE (SC1AI081376; to KM), National Science Foundation IIP-1237818 [PFI-AIR: CREST-I/UCRC-Industry Ecosystem to Pipeline Research] (to KM), Biomedical Research Initiative (BRI) student research award (NIH/NIGMS R25 GM061347; to GT), Florida International University (FIU) teaching assistantship (Biological Sciences; to GT), FIU research assistantship (Herbert Wertheim College of Medicine; to GT), MBRS-RISE fellowship (NIH/NIGMS R25 GM061347; to LR). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="14"/><table-count count="5"/><page-count count="31"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>
<italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> is a metabolically versatile, Gram-negative opportunistic pathogen that is well known for its extensive spatio-temporal distribution [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. It is a dominant nosocomial pathogen capable of causing acute and chronic infections in immunocompromised and immunosuppressed patients [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In particular, patients with AIDS, severe burn wounds, cystic fibrosis (CF), chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), non-CF bronchiectasis and neutropenia are predisposed to <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> infections [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> chronic pulmonary infections are characterized by intensive bronchial neutrophilic inflammation resulting in respiratory failure [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], a major cause of fatality in CF patients [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> is associated with keratitis [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and chronic suppurative otitis media [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] leading to visual impairment and deafness [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> possess numerous virulence factors, both cell-surface associated and secretory, which significantly contribute to its pathogenesis [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Effective treatment of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> infections is impeded by its extraordinary intrinsic and acquired resistance to numerous clinically important antibiotics [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Thus, antibiotic resistance and expression of multi-determinant virulence factors are two critical hallmarks in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> infections that make it an intimidating pathogen.</p><p>Successful infection and disease progression depends significantly on the ability of any pathogen to effectively utilize available nutrients that are essential for its growth and survival. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> is renowned for its extraordinary ability to utilize wide range of organic compounds such as carbohydrates, amino acids, fatty acids, mono- and polyalcohols, di- and tri-carboxylic acids as sources of carbon, nitrogen and energy [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, unlike other bacteria where glucose is the preferred carbon source [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>], <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> preferentially utilizes tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle intermediates [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], specifically, C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates of the TCA cycle such as malate, fumarate and succinate [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>The TCA cycle is an amphibolic pathway that serves two main purposes: energy-generation in aerobic organisms (catabolism), and the generation of intermediates to serve as biosynthetic precursors for fatty acid, amino acid and carbohydrate synthesis (anabolism) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. The metabolic intermediates of the TCA cycle consist of a group of organic anions that include C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates (succinate, fumarate, malate and oxaloacetate), C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylates (alpha-ketoglutarate (&#945;-KG)) and C<sub>6</sub>-tricarboxylates (citrate, isocitrate) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. However, the role of TCA cycle intermediates is not restricted to energy metabolism or to serve as biosynthetic precursors. In the recent years, TCA cycle intermediates, in-particular, succinate and/or &#945;-KG have gained significant importance as biological signaling molecules in variety of organisms including, bacteria [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], animals [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] and plants [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>].</p><p>Sensing the available nutrients is a prerequisite for mobilizing the uptake systems. Bacterial <underline>t</underline>wo-<underline>c</underline>omponent <underline>s</underline>ystems (TCSs), involving a membrane-bound histidine sensor kinase (HK) and a cytoplasmic response regulator (RR) play an integral part in bacteria&#8217;s ability to sense physiological cues. In response to stimuli, the sensor autophosporylates at a conserved histidine residue at the C-terminus, and subsequently the phosphate is transferred to an aspartate residue at the N-terminus of the RR [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. TCSs in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>, <italic>Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic>, <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>, <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic> and <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic> have been shown to regulate extracellular C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates and tricarboxylates transport [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Of these, DctB-DctD in <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> is an extensively studied TCS, which in coordination with sigma factor RpoN(&#963;<sup>54</sup>) regulates the extracellular transport of C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates succinate, fumarate and malate [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>Three TCS protein pairs in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> namely, PA5165/PA5166 (DctB/DctD), PA5512/PA5511 (MifS/MifR) and PA1336/PA1335 have been identified to be homologous to the <italic>Rhizobium</italic> C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylate transport regulatory DctB/DctD [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Amongst the three, very little is known of PA1336/PA1335. The PA5165/PA5166 (DctB/DctD) TCS has been demonstrated to regulate the transport of C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates, succinate, fumarate and malate in coordination with the sigma factor RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The SK MifS (65.3 kDa) and RR MifR (49.6 kDa) share 51% and 69% sequence identity to the <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> DctB and DctD, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The RR MifR is involved in regulating the maturation stage of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> biofilm formation as <italic>mifR</italic> deficient mutants fail to form microcolonies [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Later studies reported the interdependence of pyruvate fermentation and functional MifR in supporting microcolony formation [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. However, the mechanism by which MifR is activated in this process remains obscure and no relation with HK MifS has been established. Using clean in-frame deletion mutants of the <italic>mifS</italic>, <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> genes we show that MifSR TCS regulates <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#945;-KG transport and requires functional RpoN.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec002"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec003"><title>
<italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> are a part of a two-gene operon</title><p>In eubacteria, the genes that encode a HK and its cognate RR are often linked and are co-transcribed [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Our sequence analysis of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 genome revealed that <italic>mifS</italic> (<italic>PA5512)</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> (<italic>PA5511</italic>) are adjacent to each other, in the same orientation. The predicted translation start site of <italic>mifR</italic> ORF overlaps with <italic>mifS</italic> translation termination codon indicating that they are cotranscribed (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A and 1B</xref>). To determine if these two genes form an operon, cDNA across the intergenic regions spanning <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> was amplified using GDT_cotransF1-R1 and GDT_cotransF2-R2 primers (see <xref rid="sec016" ref-type="sec">Materials and Methods</xref>). As expected, 200 bp and 100 bp products were detected when using primers that span the overlapping region (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>, Lane 3 and Lane 4). These results confirm that <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> are a part of a two-gene operon. As controls, the <italic>mifSR</italic> genes were also amplified (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>, Lane 2).</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Genome organization of the <italic>mifSR</italic> gene locus.</title><p>In <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 the <italic>mifR</italic> (<italic>PA5511</italic>) ORF has a translation start codon (ATG) overlapping the <italic>mifS</italic> (PA5512) termination codon (TGA), denoted in red (B), suggesting that the <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> genes are physically linked. The cDNA amplification of the intergenic region spanning the <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> genes using GDT_cotrans F1-R1 and GDT_cotrans F2-R2 primers (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) confirm that the two genes <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> are co-transcribed and form an operon (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Loss of <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> did not affect antibiotic resistance</title><p>To identify the role of MifSR TCS, clean in-frame deletion mutants of <italic>mifS</italic>, <italic>mifR and mifSR</italic> were constructed in the prototypic <italic>P</italic>. aeruginosa PAO1. Henceforth they will be referred to as PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic>, respectively. For complementation studies, recombinant plasmids containing the entire <italic>mifR</italic>, <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> genes were constructed. The complementing plasmids with the genes are called pMifS, pMifR and pMifSR. These plasmids were introduced into the respective mutant strains.</p><p>Previous studies in our lab postulated that the MifSR TCS system, found 81-bp upstream of the <italic>pox</italic> operon, may contribute to <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#223;-lactam resistance [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] as the genes regulated by TCS tend to be co-located on the chromosome [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. However, MIC analyses using E-test and micro-dilution methods showed that the loss of these genes did not affect the antibiotic resistance profile when compared to the parent strain, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1(Data not shown). Further, qRT-PCR studies showed that deletion of <italic>mifS</italic>, <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> had no effect on the expression of <italic>poxB</italic> compared to the parent PAO1 (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Expression of <italic>poxB</italic> (<italic>PA5514</italic>) in <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants.</title><p>Expression of <italic>poxB</italic> (<italic>PA5514</italic>) was tested in <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants relative to PAO1. Data was normalized to expression in PAO1. Bars above or below the line represents up- and down-regulation, respectively and the bars indicate standard errors. The <italic>clpX</italic> gene (<italic>PA1802</italic>) was used as the housekeeping control. There was no statistically significant difference (<italic>p</italic>-value &gt; 0.05) between the wild type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutant strains as determined by one-way ANOVA and student&#8217;s unpaired <italic>t</italic> test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>
<italic>mifS</italic>, <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants failed to grow in the presence of &#945;-KG</title><p>The PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> mutants exhibited no discernible phenotype compared to the parent PAO1 when tested for growth, swimming, swarming, twitching motility (LB media), pyocyanin production (LB &amp; King&#8217;s A media), pyoverdine production (LB &amp; King&#8217;s B Media), congo red binding assay (CR media) and antibiotic resistance (MH media) (Data not shown). Hence, a comparative phenotypic microarray analysis was performed with the wild-type PAO1, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> mutants (BioLOG Inc.). Out of approximately 2000 metabolic and chemical sensitivity assays tested, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> exhibited four gain-of-function and 29 loss-of-function phenotypes whereas PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> exhibited two gain-of-function and 23 loss-of-function phenotypes (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3A</xref>). A single gain of function phenotype shared between PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, was the ability to utilize L-methionine. When metabolism and chemical sensitivity were compared, the mutants appear more sensitive to various antibiotics (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). However, none of these were reproducible in the lab in the MH media. The loss of <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> resulted in differential phenotype in the presence of six metabolites, amongst which, two were common to both <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> mutants (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). The shared metabolic phenotypes involved the utilization of L-methionine and &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3C</xref>). Compared to the parent PAO1, the mutants did not exhibit any growth increase when provided with L-methionine (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). This could be simply due to the difference in culture conditions and BioLOG proprietary media.</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>
<italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> dependent phenotypes.</title><p>To identify the role of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa mifSR</italic> TCS, comparative phenotypic microarray of PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> mutants and wild-type PAO1 strain was performed at BioLOG Inc. (Hayward, CA, USA). Venn diagram of differentially regulated phenotypes of the mutants compared to their isogenic parent PAO1, showing gain of function or loss of function phenotypes (A). Phenotypic differences were further classified based on metabolic and chemical sensitivity properties (B). The phenotypes common to both <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> mutants are listed (C).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g003"/></fig><fig id="pone.0129629.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Growth curve analysis in the presence to methionine.</title><p>Growth curves of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> wild-type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants in M9 minimal media supplemented with glucose (30 mM) and methionine (5 mM) as carbon and nitrogen source.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g004"/></fig><p>The inability to utilize &#945;-KG by PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5A</xref>) and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5B</xref>) in the BioLOG assay was reproduced in M9 minimal media supplemented with 30 mM &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5C</xref>). In fact, all three mutant strains, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> failed to grow in the presence of &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5C</xref>). To rule out potential toxicity, the wild-type <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 and the mutants were cultured in M9 minimal media with varying concentrations of &#945;-KG, ranging from 1 to 80 mM (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). The mutants exhibited no growth in the presence &#945;-KG after 24 h at 37&#176;C, whereas the wild-type PAO1 exhibited an increase in growth that was proportional to &#945;-KG concentration (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6B</xref>). All subsequent experiments were done with 30 mM &#945;-KG. The growth defect exhibited by PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> could be restored to the wild-type levels by introducing <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> genes into the respective mutants (Figs <xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">5D</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0129629.g007" ref-type="fig">7A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Phenotypic microarrays of PAO&#916;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#916;<italic>mifR</italic> mutants.</title><p>The loss of <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> results in a growth deficient phenotype in the presence of &#945;-KG as a sole carbon source, as depicted by BioLOG plate PM1, well D6 (A and B). Loss of growth phenotype was confirmed by growing PAO1, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> mutants in M9 minimal media with &#945;-KG (30 mM) for 18 to 24 h at 37&#176;C (C). The growth defect was rescued by expressing <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> genes (D) and the gene encoding the &#945;-KG specific transporter PA5530 (E) in <italic>trans</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g005"/></fig><fig id="pone.0129629.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Growth profile in the presence of varying concentrations of &#945;-KG.</title><p>PAO1 and its isogenic <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants, PAO&#916;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#916;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#916;<italic>mifSR</italic> were grown in M9 minimal media with varying concentrations of &#945;-KG (1 to 80 mM) as the sole carbon source. Growth was monitored by measuring absorbance at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) over a period of 24 h at 37&#176;C. OD<sub>600</sub> at 0 h (A) and 24 h (B) is plotted against &#945;-KG concentration. Results shown are mean with standard deviation of three biological replicates. Statistically significant difference between the wild type and mutants as determined by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni&#8217;s post-hoc test, ** <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g006"/></fig><fig id="pone.0129629.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Rescue of &#945;-KG-dependent growth phenotype of <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants.</title><p>Growth curves of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> wild-type PAO1, <italic>mifSR</italic> single and double deletion mutants and its complimenting clones (A) and in the presence of pPA5530 (B) in M9 minimal media with &#945;-KG (30 mM).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g007"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>
<italic>mifSR</italic> mutants exhibit &#945;-KG dependent growth defect</title><p>&#945;-KG is a key TCA cycle intermediate (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>) and plays an important role in regulating carbon and nitrogen metabolism [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. It has been previously shown that <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> preferentially utilizes TCA cycle intermediates as a carbon source over other compounds [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. To test if the growth defect exhibited by the loss of <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> is restricted to &#945;-KG utilization, the mutants and the complementing strains were grown in the presence of TCA cycle intermediates citrate, succinate, fumarate, malate and oxaloacetate at 30 mM each. No difference in growth was observed between wild type PAO1 and its isogenic mutants in the presence of other TCA cycle intermediates except for &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This is not surprising as <italic>P</italic>. aeruginosa can use the glyoxylate shunt pathway to bypass the need for &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Furthermore, no difference in the growth profile of the wild type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants was observed when grown in the presence of sugars, glucose and sucrose (30 mM each) (Data not shown). To reconfirm that the presence of &#945;-KG is not toxic, the cells were grown in the presence of citrate and succinate combined in equal concentration with &#945;-KG. The mutants and the wild type shared similar early exponential growth (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g009" ref-type="fig">Fig 9</xref>). However, the mutants reached stationary phase earlier as compared to the parent strain PAO1. This suggests that the presence of excess carbon source in the form of &#945;-KG further contributes to the growth of PAO1. These analyses indicate that <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants are only defective in &#945;-KG utilization.</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title>Tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle and its related reactions.</title><p>Enzymes converting iso-citrate to &#945;-KG (iso-citrate dehydrogenase: Icd, Idh), &#945;-KG to succinyl-coA (&#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex: SucA, SucB, Lpd3) and those involved in the glyoxylate shunt (isocitrate lyase (AceA) and malate synthase G (GlnB)) are shown in bold. Green boxes indicate the amino acid biosynthetic precursors of &#945;-KG involved in the anaplerotic reaction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g008"/></fig><fig id="pone.0129629.g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g009</object-id><label>Fig 9</label><caption><title>Growth curves in presence of &#945;-KG in combination with succinate and citrate.</title><p>To determine if &#945;-KG is toxic to the cells, wild-type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants were grown in the presence of &#945;-KG in combination with succinate (A) and citrate (B) at 30 mM each. In comparison to the wild-type PAO1, <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants shared a similar exponential phase but reached stationary phase earlier, suggesting that it has depleted usable C-source. This suggests that PAO1 can efficiently utilize excess carbon source in the form of &#945;-KG contributing to its increased growth.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g009"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0129629.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Growth properties of <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants in presence of TCA cycle intermediates.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0129629.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0129629.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>+++, growth;---, no growth</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>Growth of the wild type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants was tested in M9 minimal media supplemented with different TCA cycle intermediates at 30 mM each, as the sole carbon source. Cells were cultured for 18 to 24 h at 37&#176;C and their growth was monitored by measuring the absorbance at 600 nm. No difference was observed in the growth rate of <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants compared to the parent PAO1 strain. Data is represented in terms of growth and no growth phenotype.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>
<italic>mifSR</italic> mutants are defective in &#945;-KG transport</title><p>The absence of growth in the presence of exogenous &#945;-KG could be due to either failure to enter the cells or loss of the mutants&#8217; ability to convert &#945;-KG to succinate. The latter is likely if the mutants failed to express a functional &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex. The ability of <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants to grow effectively in the presence of citrate and succinate suggests that these mutants are likely to harbor a functional &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex, unless the mutants bypass it using the glyoxylate shunt (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>). The former is likely as qPCR analysis of genes encoding isocitrate dehydrogenase (<italic>idh</italic>, <italic>icd)</italic> and &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex (<italic>sucA</italic>, <italic>sucB</italic>, <italic>lpd3)</italic> revealed no difference in the expression levels in the wild-type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g010</object-id><label>Fig 10</label><caption><title>Quantification of <italic>rpoN</italic>, <italic>acnA</italic>, <italic>idh</italic>, <italic>icd</italic>, <italic>sucA</italic>, and <italic>Ipd3</italic> mRNA by qRT-PCR.</title><p>RNA was isolated from cells grown in M9 minimal media supplemented with citrate (30 mM), reverse transcribed to cDNA and the presence of specific transcripts was analyzed by qPCR using gene-specific primers (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). The expression of genes encoding aconitate hydratase 1 (<italic>acnA</italic> (<italic>PA1562</italic>)) isocitrate dehydrogenase (<italic>idh</italic> (<italic>PA2623</italic>)) isocitrate dehydrogenase, &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex (<italic>icd</italic> (<italic>PA2623</italic>)), <italic>sucA</italic> (<italic>PA1585)</italic> and <italic>lpd3</italic> (<italic>PA4829</italic>), and &#963;<sup>54</sup> (<italic>rpoN</italic> (<italic>PA4462</italic>)) were analyzed in <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants relative to PAO1 (log<sub>10</sub> RQ = 1). Bars above or below the line represents up- and down-regulation, respectively and the bars are standard errors. The <italic>clpX</italic> (<italic>PA1802</italic>) gene was used as the housekeeping control. Statistically significant difference between the wild type and mutants as determined by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni&#8217;s post-hoc test. Difference in the expression levels of genes is not statistically significant at <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g010"/></fig><p>&#945;-KG is a hub for anaplerotic reactions, a process for replenishing TCA cycle intermediates. In this process glutamate, glutamine, proline and arginine act as precursor molecules for &#945;-KG synthesis [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Growth studies in the presence of these amino acids would serve as another indirect measure to test the functionality of &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex in <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants. To test this hypothesis, PAO1, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> mutants were cultured in the presence of glutamate, glutamine, proline and arginine (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The parent PAO1 and the isogenic mutants exhibited similar growth phenotype. From the expression studies and growth analyses we deduce that the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants are impaired in &#945;-KG transport.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0129629.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Growth profile analysis of the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants in presence of amino acids.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0129629.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0129629.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t002fn001"><p>+++, growth;---, no growth</p></fn><fn id="t002fn002"><p>Cells were grown in the M9 minimal media with the indicated amino acids (30 mM each). Data is represented in terms of growth and no growth phenotype.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>
<italic>mifSR</italic> TCS genes regulate extracellular &#945;-KG transport</title><p>In a recent study using transposon mutagenesis; PA5530 was identified as the functional &#945;-KG transporter [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. To confirm the role of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa PA5530</italic> in &#945;-KG uptake and identify the role of <italic>mifSR</italic> genes, the gene was amplified and subcloned downstream of the inducible P<sub><italic>lacUV5</italic></sub> promoter. The plasmid pPA5530 was introduced into PAO1 and the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants. Expression of <italic>PA5530</italic> in <italic>trans</italic> in PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> mutants restored their growth to a level similar to the wild-type PAO1 in M9 minimal media with &#945;-KG (30 mM) as the sole carbon source (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7B</xref>). Expression of an extra copy of <italic>PA5530</italic> gene in the wild-type PAO1 did not affect its growth (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5E</xref>). This finding suggests that expression of <italic>PA5530</italic> is likely regulated by MifSR and/or &#945;-KG. In fact, expression of <italic>PA5530</italic> is regulated by &#945;-KG, as seen in qRT-PCR analysis when PAO1 was grown in M9 media with varying amounts &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11A</xref>). The loss of <italic>mifS</italic>, <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> results in a significant decrease in <italic>PA5530</italic> expression as compared to the wild type PAO1 in the presence of &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11B</xref>). Thus, &#945;-KG-dependent <italic>PA5530</italic> expression requires MifS and MifR.</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g011" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g011</object-id><label>Fig 11</label><caption><title>Expression of <italic>PA5530</italic> in response to &#945;-KG.</title><p>
<italic>PA5530</italic> gene expression was determined in the wild type PAO1 with varying concentrations of &#945;-KG (1 h) (A). In addition, the expression of <italic>PA5530</italic> was tested in <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants relative to PAO1, with cells exposed to 30 mM &#945;-KG for 1 h (B). Data was normalized to expression in PAO1 under the respective conditions. Bars above or below the line represents up- and down-regulation, respectively and the bars indicate standard errors. The <italic>clpX</italic> gene (<italic>PA1802</italic>) was used as the housekeeping control. Statistically significant difference between the wild type and mutants as determined by one-way ANOVA with Bonferroni&#8217;s post-hoc test, ** <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g011"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) is required for &#945;-KG utilization</title><p>The closest <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifS and MifR homologs are <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> DctB and DctD [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In fact, MifR is 69% similar to <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> DctD that belongs to the Sigma 54 (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) dependent NtrC family of transcriptional regulators [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. Thus, it is likely that MifR has the conserved domains found among NtrC family of regulators, an N-terminal regulatory, a central &#963;<sup>54</sup> activation and a C-terminal DNA binding domains [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. MifR analysis using the simple modular architecture research tool (SMART) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and InterPro [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] revealed the presence of three domains: CheY-homologous receiver/regulatory, a central AAA<sup>+</sup> region required for &#963;<sup>54</sup> activation, and the DNA binding helix-turn-helix domains (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig 12A</xref>). The central AAA<sup>+</sup> domain contains seven conserved regions designated C1 to C7 [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] that are characteristic of &#963;<sup>54</sup>- dependent transcriptional regulators. Sequence analysis of MifR revealed the presence of all the seven conserved regions in the AAA<sup>+</sup> domain between amino acid residues 144 to 373 (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g012" ref-type="fig">Fig 12B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g012" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g012</object-id><label>Fig 12</label><caption><title>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifR domain organization and sequence alignment.</title><p>(A) MifR domain organization determined using the <underline>S</underline>imple <underline>M</underline>odular <underline>A</underline>rchitecture <underline>R</underline>esearch <underline>T</underline>ool (SMART) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. MifR is a sigma-54 dependent transcriptional activator [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. There are three functional domains, N-terminal receiver with the conserved aspartate residue at position 53 (Asp-53) (Purple), central AAA<sup>+</sup> ATPase, characteristic of sigma-54 dependent activation proteins (Green), and the C-terminal helix-turn-helix (HTH) DNA binding (Red) domains. (B) Sequence alignment of MifR with <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> DctD (PA5166), NtrC (PA5125) and <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> DctD. Vertical bars indicate conserved residues, asterisk (*) indicate residues are identical at that position. Key residues of the central AAA<sup>+</sup> domain (C1 to C7) are well conserved amongst sigma-54 dependent transcriptional activators. The horizontal arrow bars indicate HTH domain. Asp-53 indicates the conserved phosphorylation site of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifR. The alignment was generated using ClustalW2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</ext-link>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g012"/></fig><p>Since MifR exhibits high identity to &#963;<sup>54</sup>-dependent transcriptional regulators, we hypothesized that <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa rpoN</italic> mutants should exhibit a &#945;-KG-dependent phenotype, similar to the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants. To verify this hypothesis, we tested the ability of PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic> mutant to grow in the presence of &#945;-KG (30 mM) (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). As expected, PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic> failed to grow in the presence of &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). The growth of the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant was restored in PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic>::<italic>rpoN</italic> complementing strain. Further, in <italic>trans</italic> expression of <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> in PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic> mutant failed to restore their growth in the presence of &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This data confirms that MifR regulatory function requires functional RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0129629.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Growth properties of PAO1&#916;<italic>rpoN</italic> and its derivatives in the presence of &#945;-KG and LB.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0129629.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0129629.t003"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p>+++, growth;---, no growth</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p>Growth of PAO1&#916;<italic>rpoN</italic> mutant and its derivatives was tested in the M9 minimal media supplemented with &#945;-KG (30 mM) and in the LB media at 37&#176;C for 24h.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The small 81-bp <italic>mifSR</italic> promoter has no obvious RpoN sigma factor -12/-24 consensus sequence: 5&#8217;-TGGCACG-N4-TTGCW-3&#8217; in which W stands for either A or T (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13A</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. In fact, it appears to have a potential -10 (consensus: TATAAT) but lacked -35 (consensus: TTGACA) for sigma-70 promoter (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13A</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. On the other hand, the promoter region of <italic>PA5530</italic> is 315-bp long with strong -12 and -24 boxes upstream of the predicted transcription start site (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13B</xref>). We hypothesized that the inability of <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant to utilize &#945;-KG can be rescued by expressing PA5530 under a regulatable promoter P<sub><italic>lacUV5</italic>.</sub> As expected, the growth of the <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant was restored when the plasmid harboring the transporter PA5530 was expressed in <italic>trans</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This suggests that expression of PA5530 requires both MifSR TCS and RpoN.</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g013" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g013</object-id><label>Fig 13</label><caption><title>
<italic>In silico</italic> analysis of <italic>mifS</italic> (P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub>) and <italic>PA5530</italic> (P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub>) promoter sequences.</title><p>Motif search was done using the ensemble learning method SCOPE and GLAM2 (Gapped Local Alignment of Motifs) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. (A) Sequence analysis of the 81-bp (P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub>) (black) indicates a putative &#963;<sup>70</sup>-dependent -10 consensus (TATAAT). However, it lacks the -35 consensus (TTGACA) for &#963;<sup>70</sup> promoter [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Arrows represent the long 17-bp direct and inverted repeats in P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub> with a consensus GGAt/cAGCGACATCGGCG. (B) The 315-bp promoter region of <italic>PA5530</italic> showing strong -12 and -24 &#963;<sup>54</sup>-dependent promoter like element and the proposed transcription start site (+1). Dashed line (blue) depicts a common motif in P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub> and P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> suggesting a common regulatory mechanism (A and B). The three pairs of direct repeats in P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> are represented by green, blue and orange arrows<sub>.</sub> P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> possess the signature sequence (AAc/uAAc/uAA) for catabolite repression control (Crc) protein (brown box) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. The uncharacterized small antisense RNA (asRNA) identified in the P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> region [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>] is indicated by marked line.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g013"/></fig><p>The presence of a common motif, GATCGGCGGATt/gTCC, in the P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub> and P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13A and 13B</xref>) suggest that these two operons share some common regulatory mechanism. In addition, both promoters possess multiple motifs: P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub> has two sets of large overlapping inverted repeats, and P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> has three sets of direct repeats (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13A and 13B</xref>). However, the role of these motifs remains to be elucidated.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec010"><title>Discussion</title><p>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> pathogenicity relies significantly on its metabolic flexibility. However, establishment of successful infection and its progression requires more than just meeting nutritional demands. Precision in sensing environmental signals concomitant with a quick and appropriate response is the key to efficient bacterial adaptation and survival. An arsenal of TCSs encoded in its genome has furnished <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> with a sophisticated capability to regulate diverse metabolic and virulence processes, ensuring its success as a pathogen [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> genome encodes one of the largest groups of TCS proteins identified in any sequenced bacterial species [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Bacterial TCS&#8217;s sense and respond to a variety of external cues such as nutrient availability, osmolarity, redox state, temperature, and concentrations of other extracellular molecules [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. However, very few TCS signaling molecules have been identified to date. In this study we suggest that the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifSR TCS exclusively senses &#945;-KG, a C<sub>5</sub> dicarboxylate and a key component of TCA cycle.</p><sec id="sec011"><title>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> antibiotic resistance is independent of MifSR TCS</title><p>A common feature of bacterial genomes is a close association between the functionally related genes and their location on the chromosome [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Typically, genes encoding functionally related HKs and RRs are often physically linked and are co-transcribed as an operon [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. Indeed, our <italic>in silico</italic> analysis (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1A and 1B</xref>) and cDNA amplification (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1C</xref>) reveled that <italic>mifS</italic>-<italic>mifR</italic> genes are co-transcribed and form an operon. This also suggests that HK-MifS and RR-MifR are functionally related and work as a TCS pair. In addition, TCS proteins are known to regulate expression of genes in their immediate vicinity [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The <italic>mifSR</italic> genes are 81 bp upstream of the two-gene <italic>poxAB</italic> (<italic>PA5513-5514</italic>) operon. Due to the proximity of <italic>mifSR</italic> to <italic>poxB</italic> which encodes for a &#946;-lactamase, we postulated that <italic>mifSR</italic> TCS regulates antibiotic resistance. However, our initial results nullified this hypothesis in which comparative MIC&#8217;s (Data not shown) and qRT-PCR data (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>) showed no difference in antibiotic resistance profiles or <italic>poxB</italic> expression between the wild-type PAO1 and <italic>mifSR</italic> single and double deletion mutants.</p></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>MifSR TCS regulates <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginiosa</italic> &#945;-KG utilization</title><p>A previous transcriptome study of the wild-type PAO1 and a <italic>mifR</italic> deletion mutant cultivated under biofilm-specific conditions showed significant alteration in the expression of genes involved in regulating <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> metabolism, small molecule transport and amino acid biosynthesis [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The majority of the changes observed in phenotypic microarrays of the <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> mutant strains cultivated under planktonic conditions were associated with chemical sensitivity and not with metabolism (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3B</xref>). Only 12&#8211;16% of phenotypic changes were associated with metabolism. This confirms the significant metabolic differences in the rich planktonic versus anaerobic mode of biofilm growth in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>].</p><p>Petrova <italic>et al</italic>. (2012) have also demonstrated that genes involved in energy metabolism, including anaerobic metabolism and fermentative pathways using arginine (<italic>arcDABC</italic>) and pyruvate, were expressed significantly less in <italic>&#8710;mifR</italic> mutant biofilms as compared to its parent PAO1 [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Though pyruvate is needed for biofilm formation, it cannot compensate for the loss of <italic>mifR</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Interestingly, the biofilm phenotype associated with the loss of <italic>mifR</italic> can be complemented by <italic>ldhA</italic> encoding D-lactate dehydrogenase to wild type levels of biomass accumulation and microcolony formation [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. These findings suggest that MifR somehow regulates expression of <italic>ldhA</italic>, a second gene in a three-gene operon <italic>gacS</italic>-<italic>ldhA</italic>-<italic>PA0926</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. Importantly, analyses of the promoters reveal the presence of a shared motif in P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub> (GATCCGCCGATGTCC) and P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> (GATCGGCGGATTTCC) (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13</xref>) and P<sub><italic>gacS</italic></sub> (AATCCGCCGGGCTGC) suggesting a possible coordinate regulation, and that need to be verified.</p><p>Our phenotypic microarray analyses and growth experiments suggested that <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#945;-KG utilization requires MifS and MifR (Figs <xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">5</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0129629.g007" ref-type="fig">7A</xref>). The ability of PAO&#916;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#916;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#916;<italic>mifSR</italic> to grow in the presence of &#945;-KG was restored by in <italic>trans</italic> expression of <italic>mifR</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g007" ref-type="fig">Fig 7A</xref>). Interestingly, the PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> was complemented by pMifR and pMifSR (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5D</xref>) but not by pMifS alone. To rule out that gene expression may have been compromised, the <italic>mifS</italic> gene was cloned downstream of the inducible P<sub><italic>lacUV5</italic></sub> promoter. Though the expression of stable protein was visible in a protein gel, it failed to complement PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> mutant (data not shown). This suggests that cis-expression of <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> is critical for MifS-function. Other researchers have encountered similar problems involving histidine kinases [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Moreover, complementation of the PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> with pMifR suggests that either phosphorylation is not required or there is a potential crosstalk between MifR and other non-cognate HKs. Alternatively, phosphorylation of MifR can occur through small molecule phosphor-donors, like acetyl phosphate, carbamoyl phosphate and phosphoramidate [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Such phenomenon is observed with other TCS RRs [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. However, this has to be verified.</p><p>The C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylate &#945;-KG is an important intermediate in the energy-generating TCA cycle (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>) and plays a key role in regulating carbon and nitrogen metabolism [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Similar to other bacteria [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>], TCS&#8217;s in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> have been reported to regulate transport and utilization of TCA cycle intermediates such as succinate, fumarate, malate and citrate [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. The <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> DctB/DctD system is a well-characterized TCS that controls the transport of TCA cycle C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates succinate, fumarate and malate [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Though <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifS/MifR proteins are homologous to <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> DctB/DctD TCS proteins, the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants efficiently utilized citrate, succinate, fumarate, malate, oxaloacetate, sucrose and glucose but exclusively failed to grow in the presence of &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). This was further supported by another parallel study that shows that &#945;-KG utilization requires MifR [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Thus, the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> MifSR TCS is specifically and uniquely involved in C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylate &#945;-KG utilization.</p></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>MifSR TCS modulates <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#945;-KG transport</title><p>The inability to utilize &#945;-KG suggested that the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants either have a defective &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex (inability to convert &#945;-KG to succinyl-coA, <xref rid="pone.0129629.g008" ref-type="fig">Fig 8</xref>), or they are deficient in the transport of &#945;-KG into the cell. The former was ruled based upon multiple findings: unchanged expression levels of genes encoding &#945;-KG dehydrogenase, <italic>lpd3</italic> (<italic>PA4829</italic>) and <italic>sucA</italic> (<italic>PA1585</italic>) (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g010" ref-type="fig">Fig 10</xref>); the ability to use C<sub>4</sub> and C<sub>6</sub> dicarboxylates (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) and C5 family of amino acids such as arginine, proline, glutamine, and histidine (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The C5 family of amino acids act as biosynthetic precursors of glutamate that ultimately are converted to &#945;-KG by a transamination reaction or through the action of glutamate dehydrogenase [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. These findings strongly argued that the <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants were defective in their ability to transport &#945;-KG into the cell.</p><p>To date, among the identified carboxylate transporters, the C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylate transporters have been reasonably well characterized. Based on protein sequence similarity analysis, bacterial C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylate transporters are classified into five families, namely, dicarboxylate transport (DctA); dicarboxylate uptake (DcuAB), (DcuC) and (CitT) and the tripartite ATP-independent periplasmic (TRAP) families [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Amongst these, DctA transporters, a subgroup of the <underline>d</underline>icarboxylate/<underline>a</underline>mino <underline>a</underline>cid:<underline>c</underline>ation <underline>s</underline>ymporter (DAACS) family [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>], are extensively studied and are implicated in the transport of C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates in <italic>Echerischia coli</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>], <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>], <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>] and <italic>Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. As we were trying to identify the MifSR-dependent transporter Lundgren <italic>et al</italic>., reported that PA5530 is involved in &#945;-KG transport [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. As predicted, in <italic>trans</italic> expression of <italic>PA5530</italic> was able to restore the ability of <italic>mifR</italic>, <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants to grow in &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5E</xref>). This is further confirmed by the increase in <italic>PA5530</italic> expression in PAO1 in the presence of &#945;-KG (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g011" ref-type="fig">Fig 11A</xref>). PA5530 shares no homology with the <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylate transporter PA1183 (DctA). However, it does have conserved protein domain family PRK10406 implicated in &#945;-KG transport and shares ~70% homology to <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> and <italic>Erwinia</italic> spp. &#945;-KG permease KgtP [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref079" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>]. A common feature in the transport of C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates and other carbon sources in different bacteria is the involvement of TCS mediated regulatory mechanism. Involvement of TCSs, a stimulus-response coupled mechanism, in the transport of C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylates suggests a more profound role of &#945;-KG as a signaling molecule.</p></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#945;-KG transport requires functional RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>)</title><p>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) is involved in a myriad of functions including expression of virulence factors and nutrient uptake [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref080" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>]. Functional RpoN is reported to be critical for maintaining a carbon-nitrogen balance in <italic>Pseudomonads</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref081" ref-type="bibr">81</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref084" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>]. Sequence analysis of MifR indicated a requirement of functional RpoN in modulating <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#945;-KG utilization. Our study confirms that &#945;-KG utilization in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 requires functional RpoN (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>). This phenotype is not strain-specific as phenotypic microarray profiling (BioLOG) of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PA14 <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant exhibited a similar phenotype, a significant difference in the ability to utilize &#945;-KG as a carbon source as compared to the wild-type PA14 [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. An RpoN-dependent phenotype was also observed with citrate and 4-hydroxyphenylacetate utilization [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>]. Similarly, utilization of C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylates succinate, fumarate and malate in <italic>R</italic>. <italic>meliloti</italic> and <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> also requires the sigma factor RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].</p><p>The need for RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) to utilize &#945;-KG in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> can be bypassed by expressing <italic>PA5530</italic> encoding for the transporter under a regulatable promoter but not MifS and MifR. Consistent with the need for RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>), the promoter for <italic>PA5530</italic> has the requisite signature sequences (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13</xref>). Like most complex RpoN-dependent promoters [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>], the region is long with multiple motifs that include a signature sequence (AAc/uAAc/uAA) for catabolite repression control (Crc) protein, a post-transcriptional inhibitor that binds the mRNA preventing translation [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. Expression of <italic>crc</italic> is in-turn regulated by RpoN-dependent non-coding RNA CrcZ [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] whose absence in <italic>rpoN</italic> mutant can also lead to reduced expression of <italic>PA5530</italic>. Also, analysis of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PA14 transcripts indicates that the <italic>PA5530</italic> promotor is under a small non-coding antisense RNA (asRNA) regulation [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Though the role of Crc, CrcZ and the asRNA in &#945;-KG transport has to be verified experimentally, it suggests an additional layer of regulation superimposed on the need for MifS and MifR on the expression of the C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylate transporter PA5530.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In eukaryotic cells, the mitochondria serve as a hub and reservoir of the TCA cycle and its intermediates, respectively. Bacterial pathogens can be highly virulent intruders of the host tissue, causing significant damage leading to cellular aberrations and injury. Mitochondrial dysfunction, a consequence of cell injury, results in efflux of TCA cycle intermediates leading to an increase in their extracellular concentrations [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. It is known that TCA cycle intermediates (C<sub>4</sub>, C<sub>5</sub>, and C<sub>6</sub> dicarboxylates) are present at micromolar (&#956;M) concentrations in blood that increase with tissues damaged [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. &#945;-KG can also act as a reactive oxygen species scavenger, especially for hydrogen peroxide, protecting both host and pathogen [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref093" ref-type="bibr">93</xref>]. For pathogenic bacteria such as <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic>, efficient uptake of TCA intermediates from the host is crucial for its survival, especially when it is bombarded with host reactive oxygen species, and requires the activity of bacterial carboxylate transport proteins. The transport proteins could be specific for C<sub>4</sub>, C<sub>5</sub>, and C<sub>6</sub> intermediates and may use a cognate TCS. This study suggests a complex regulatory cascade in modulating <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> C<sub>5</sub>-dicarboxylate, &#945;-KG uptake involving the PA5530 transporter, the MifS/MifR TCS and the sigma factor RpoN (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g014" ref-type="fig">Fig 14</xref>). It appears that MifS senses the presence of &#945;-KG and signals MifR. The activated MifR in concert with RpoN initiates the transcription of &#945;-KG-specific transporter gene <italic>PA5530</italic>. Analyses of the published data suggests that the <italic>PA5530</italic> promoter is under several layers of regulation including catabolite repression mediated by Crc/CrcZ [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>] and the small non-coding asRNA [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>]. Though the asRNA has been identified [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>], it has not been characterized. It is not surprising that the <italic>PA5530</italic> expression is potentially regulated by Crc, as it would allow control of transporter(s) in response to the presence of carbon sources in the environment.</p><fig id="pone.0129629.g014" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.g014</object-id><label>Fig 14</label><caption><title>Proposed model for &#945;-KG utilization in <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic>.</title><p>HK-MifS senses the extracellular &#945;-KG to undergo phosphorylation. The phosphate is transferred to the RR-MifR. The phosphorylated MifR in coordination with RpoN (&#963;<sup>54</sup>) activates the expression of &#945;-KG specific transporter gene <italic>PA5530</italic>. PA5530 thus enables the influx of &#945;-KG to meet the metabolic and energy demands of the cells. <italic>PA5530</italic> promoter (P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub>) region has a Crc binding site (<xref rid="pone.0129629.g013" ref-type="fig">Fig 13</xref>), suggesting that it is under the catabolite repression control by Crc/CrcZ. The P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub> also shows the presence of another uncharacterized small non-coding asRNA indicating a multilayered and complex regulation of the &#945;-KG transport system.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0129629.g014"/></fig><p>In addition to MifSR (PA5512/PA5511), PA1336/PA1335 have been identified to be homologous to the <italic>Rhizobium</italic> C<sub>4</sub>-dicarboxylate transport regulatory DctB/DctD TCS [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. However, the role of PA1336/PA1335 remains to be elucidated. The <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> genome also encodes 19 other paralogs of PA5530 dicarboyxlate transporters, most of which have share less than 50% similarity except for PA0229 (PcaT). PA0229 and PA5530 have 73% similarity. Future studies will determine if the transporters are preferentially or hierarchically upregulated depending on the carbon source. It is also important to note that much of bacterial physiology, particularly of pathogens such as <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> remains a mystery. Metabolic versatility, expression of virulence factors and antibiotic resistance together makes <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> an portentous pathogen. Thus, understanding the physiological cues and regulation would provide a better stratagem to fight the often indomitable infections.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec016"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec017"><title>Strains, media and growth conditions</title><p>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> wild-type PAO1 [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] and its derivatives PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic> or <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> strain DH5&#945; were used in this study (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> strain InvSC1 (Invitrogen, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA) was used for <italic>in vivo</italic> homologous recombination [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref094" ref-type="bibr">94</xref>]. Briefly, all bacterial cultures were grown in Luria Bertani (LB) broth (5 g tryptone, 10 g sodium chloride, and 5 g yeast extract per liter) or agar (LB broth with 1.5% agar) (Difco, NJ, USA) or M9 minimal Media (64 g Na<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>-7H<sub>2</sub>O, 15 g KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4,</sub> 2.5 g NaCl, 5.0 g NH<sub>4</sub>Cl, 20 mM MgSO<sub>4,</sub> 1 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> per liter) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>] at 37&#176;C, unless specified otherwise. Yeast extract-peptone-dextrose media (YEPD: 20 g Bacto Peptone, 10 g yeast extract, 20 g dextrose per liter) was routinely used to culture <italic>S</italic>. <italic>cerevisiae</italic> and synthetic define agar-uracil media was used as selection media for pMQ30 yeast transformants [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> competent cells were prepared as previously described [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. For growth curve and complementation studies M9 minimal media supplemented with glucose, sucrose or TCA cycle intermediates including citrate, &#945;-KG, succinate, fumarate, malate or oxaloacetate were used as a sole carbon source at 30 mM each unless specified otherwise. Motility assays were performed in LB media (Difco, NJ, USA). For pyocyanin and proverdine production strains were cultivated in King&#8217;s A medium (Difco, NJ, USA) and King&#8217;s B medium [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Cation-adjusted Mueller Hinton broth and agar (Difco, NJ, USA) was used in MIC assays. For plasmid maintenance, antibiotics were added to growth media when appropriate, at the specified concentrations: <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic>: ampicillin (Ap) 100 &#956;g/ml, gentamycin (Gm) 15 &#956;g/ml, kanamycin (Km) 20 &#956;g/ml, <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic>: Gm 75 &#956;g/ml.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0129629.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Strains and plasmids used in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0129629.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0129629.t004"/></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>Genetic manipulations</title><p>Genetic manipulations were carried out using standard techniques [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>]. Primers were synthesized by Integrated DNA Technologies, Inc. (Coralville, IA, USA) and are listed in <xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. Plasmid DNA isolation was carried out using PureLink Hipure Plasmid Miniprep Kit (Invitrogen, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA) and agarose gel fragments were purified using Wizard SV Gel and PCR Clean-Up System (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). RNA and cDNA was made using RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen Inc. Venio, Limburg, Netherlands) and SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis System (Invitrogen, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA). Restriction endonucleases were from New England Biolabs (Ipswich, MA, USA) and DNA sequencing was carried out at Florida International University (FIU) DNA core and at GENEWIZ Inc (South Plainfield, NJ, USA). All other chemicals were purchased from SIGMA-ALDRICH (St. Louis, MO, USA), AMRESCO (Solon, OH, USA) and Fisher Scientific (Waltham, MA, USA).</p><table-wrap id="pone.0129629.t005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0129629.t005</object-id><label>Table 5</label><caption><title>Primers used in this study.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0129629.t005g" xlink:href="pone.0129629.t005"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t005fn001"><p>qRT in the primer name indicates that the primer was designed for qPCR. Broken and continuous lines below the primer sequence indicate ribosome binding and restriction sites respectively.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>Construction of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> &#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> mutant</title><p>An unmarked <italic>mifR</italic> clean in-frame deletion mutant of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> was generated by gene splicing [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref104" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>]. Upstream and downstream flanking regions of <italic>mifR</italic> were amplified by PCR (GC Rich PCR System, Roche, Indianapolis, IN, USA), using primers listed in <xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. A 754-bp P1 and a 720-bp P2 were amplified using upstream primers <italic>mifR</italic>UF1-<italic>Eco</italic>RI and <italic>mifR</italic>UR1-<italic>Nhe</italic>I and the downstream primers <italic>mifR</italic>DF1-<italic>Nhe</italic>I and <italic>mifR</italic>DR1-<italic>Hin</italic>dIII (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), respectively from PAO1 genomic DNA. After sequencing to ensure fidelity, P1 and P2 were spliced together to obtain a 1474-bp deletion fragment with a deletion of <italic>mifR</italic> containing stop codons at its junction (inserted as part of <italic>Nhe</italic>I site in the primer). This was then sequenced and subcloned into a <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> non-replicative plasmid pEXG2 [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>] as a <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Hin</italic>dIII fragment and moved into the wild-type PAO1 strain by allelic replacement [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref105" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>] using pRK600 and pRK2013 as the helper plasmids [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Clones were screened for Gm sensitivity (75 &#956;g ml<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) and sucrose resistance (8% sucrose) corresponding to a double cross-over recombination event and replacement of the target gene with the deletion product. The presence of the deletion in PAO&#916;<italic>mifR</italic> (PKM901) was confirmed by PCR amplification and sequencing of the deletion product (data not shown).</p></sec><sec id="sec020"><title>Construction of <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa mifS</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> mutants</title><p>The unmarked <italic>mifS and mifSR</italic> deletion in PAO1 was generated by using the yeast system of double-stranded gap repair and homologous recombination [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. Briefly, the <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> upstream and downstream flanking regions were amplified by PCR using primers listed in <xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>. To create a <italic>mifSR</italic> deletion, an upstream 933-bp P1 and a downstream 1115-bp P2 were amplified using primer pairs <italic>mifSR</italic>UF1-<italic>mifSR</italic>DF1 and <italic>mifSR</italic>UR1<italic>-mifSR</italic>DR1, respectively. Similarly, to create <italic>mifS</italic> deletion, an upstream 703-bp P1 and a downstream 653-bp were amplified using primer pairs HK<italic>mifS</italic>UF-HK<italic>mifS</italic>DF and HK<italic>mifS</italic>UR-HK<italic>mifS</italic>DR, respectively. HK<italic>mifS</italic>UF and <italic>mifSR</italic>UF1 primers had stretches of homologous DNA, 5&#8217;-GGAATTGTGAGCGGATAACAATTTCACACAGGAAACAGCT-3&#8217; and 5&#8217;-CCAGGCAAATTCTGTTTTATCAGACCGCTTCTGCGTTCTGAT-3&#8217;, respectively, to target recombination of the amplicons with pMQ30 vector. These primer pairs also had complementing sequences at the 3&#8217; end to facilitate joining to create the P3 fragment, as well as stop codons (CTAGTTAGCTAG) to prevent any run off translation. The pMQ30 vector has double selection markers <italic>URA3</italic> for yeast and gentamycin for <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Yeast cells were transformed with the P1, P2 and linearized pMQ30 (<italic>Bam</italic>HI digested) using standard protocols [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>] and colonies were selected on sucrose-uracil plates.</p><p>The yeast colonies were checked for the presence of P3 constructs for <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifSR</italic> deletions by amplification using upstream forward (<italic>mifSR</italic>UF1 and HK<italic>mifS</italic>UF, respectively) and downstream reverse (<italic>mifSR</italic>DR1 and HK<italic>mifS</italic>DR, respectively) primers. Yeast DNA was isolated from the positive colonies as described earlier [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref106" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>]. <italic>E</italic>. <italic>coli</italic> was transformed with the recombinant pMQ30 plasmids containing P3s and screened for gentamycin resistance. The amplified P3s from the recombinant plasmids were sequenced to ensure fidelity. The constructs were then moved into PAO1 strain using tri-parental mating and screened for single and double crossovers using counter selection with sucrose and gentamycin as described earlier [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref108" ref-type="bibr">108</xref>]. The presence of the gene deletions in all the mutants were confirmed using standard molecular methods (PCR and DNA sequencing of the locus). These strains are henceforth referred to as PAO&#916;<italic>mifS</italic> (PKM900) and PAO&#916;<italic>mifSR</italic> (PKM902).</p></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>Construction of complementing plasmids</title><p>DNA fragments from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 with <italic>mifS</italic> (~1.77 kb) and <italic>mifR</italic> (~1.35 kb) were PCR amplified using primer pairs HK_<italic>mifS</italic>F1-HK_<italic>mifS</italic>F1R1, GDT_<italic>mifR</italic>F1-GDT_<italic>mifR</italic>R1, respectively. In order to ensure expression of the genes, the primers are designed such that the ORF will juxtapose against a strong ribosome binding site [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. The PCR amplified products were cloned into pCR2.1 TOPO (Invitrogen, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA) using manufacturers protocol to generate plasmids pGDT001 and pGDT002, respectively. The fidelity of the PCR amplified product was confirmed by sequencing. The fragments carrying <italic>mifS</italic> and <italic>mifR</italic> were moved into a broad host range pPSV37-Gm plasmid [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>] as a <italic>Nhe</italic>I-<italic>Sac</italic>I fragments, downstream of an inducible P<sub><italic>lacUV5</italic></sub> promoter to generate plasmids pGDT003 and pGDT004, respectively. Henceforth, these plasmids are referred to as pMifS and pMifR.</p><p>DNA fragments from PAO1 with <italic>mifSR</italic> (~3.12 kb) and <italic>PA5530</italic> (~1.3 kb) were PCR amplified using primer pairs HK_<italic>mifS</italic>F1-GDT_<italic>mifR</italic>R1 and GDT_<italic>PA5530</italic>F1-GDT_<italic>PA5530</italic>R1 (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>), respectively. The PCR amplified products were cloned directly into pPSV37-Gm plasmid as <italic>Nhe</italic>I-<italic>Sac</italic>I fragments, downstream of an inducible P<sub><italic>lacUV5</italic></sub> promoter to generate plasmids pGDT005 and pGDT006, respectively. Sequence fidelity was confirmed by sequencing using the primers GDT_p37_SeqF-R, <italic>mifR</italic>_seqF-R, <italic>mifS</italic>_seqF-F2 and <italic>PA5530</italic>_seqF-R (<xref rid="pone.0129629.t005" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>). Henceforth, these plasmids are referred to as pMifSR and pPA5530.</p><p>These expression plasmids were then introduced into wild-type PAO1, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic> deletion mutants by electroporation [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>] and gentamycin resistant colonies were selected.</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>Phenotypic microarray</title><p>Comparative phenotypic microarray profiles of wild-type PAO1 with PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> mutant were performed at BioLOG Inc. (Hayward, CA, USA). Phenotypic profiling was carried out in triplicate and data analyses was done using OmniLog PM software.</p></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>Growth curves</title><p>
<italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> PAO1 and its derivatives were grown overnight at 37&#176;C in LB broth with or without antibiotics. Overnight cultures were washed with sterile 0.85% NaCl (wt/vol) solution to remove spent and residual media. Cultures were diluted in fresh M9 minimal media to obtain equal optical densities (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.025. Growth of the cultures was assessed in LB broth and in M9 minimal media supplemented with glucose (30 mM), sucrose (30 mM) or TCA cycle intermediates including citrate, &#945;-KG, succinate, fumarate, malate or oxaloacetate (at 30 mM, unless specified otherwise) as a sole carbon source in 48 and 96 well plates (Falcon). Growth was monitored by determining absorbance at 600 nm using BioTek Synergy HT (Winooski, VT, USA) plate reader for 18&#8211;24 h at 37&#176;C. All experiments were performed multiple times in triplicate.</p></sec><sec id="sec024"><title>Pyocyanin and pyoverdine production</title><p>Extracellular pyocyanin was quantified by extracting the pigment from culture supernatants using the chloroform-HCL method as described previously [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>]. Briefly, 5 ml culture supernatants from stationary-phase cultures (&#8764;18 h) grown in King&#8217;s A medium was extracted with 3 ml chloroform. Pyocyanin was then re-extracted into 1 ml of 0.2 N HCl, resulting in a pink color, indicating the presence of pyocyanin that was read at 520 nm. The concentration is expressed as &#956;g of pyocyanin produced per ml of culture (&#956;g/ml), by multiplying the optical density OD<sub>520</sub> by 17.072 [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref109" ref-type="bibr">109</xref>].</p><p>To measure pyoverdine production, cells were grown overnight at 37&#176;C in King&#8217;s B medium [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>]. Pyoverdine in the supernatant was read at 405 nm and normalized to the initial cell density (OD<sub>600</sub>). Pyoverdine levels were expressed as a ratio of OD<sub>405</sub>/OD<sub>600</sub> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref110" ref-type="bibr">110</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec025"><title>Minimum Inhibitory Concentration</title><p>MICs were determined using the E-test as per the manufacturers protocol (BioMerieux, USA) and/or by standard broth microdilution method [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref111" ref-type="bibr">111</xref>]. The assays were performed in triplicate, each with technical triplicate, for each antibiotic in cation-adjusted Mueller Hinton broth.</p></sec><sec id="sec026"><title>RNA isolation, cDNA synthesis and qRT-PCR</title><p>RNA was isolated from <italic>P</italic>. <italic>aeruginosa</italic> wild-type PAO1, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> strains grown in LB broth followed by 1 h treatment with 30 mM &#945;-KG. Briefly, overnight cultures grown in LB broth at 37&#176;C were washed with sterile 0.85% saline solution to remove spent media and were subcultured at 37&#176;C, 200 rpm in LB media. LB broth was used as a carbon source for initial growth of cultures since PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>rpoN</italic> strains exhibit growth defects in the presence of &#945;-KG alone. When the cells reached an optical density at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) of 0.6&#8211;0.7 all the cultures were treated with 30 mM &#945;-KG for 1 h. Post treatment, RNA was stabilized by addition of phenol-ethanol mixture [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref112" ref-type="bibr">112</xref>]. Stabilized RNA was then isolated using RNeasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Inc Venio, Limburg, Netherlands) as per manufacturer&#8217;s protocol. Residual genomic DNA contamination was removed using RQ1 Rnase-free DNase (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and RNA was repurified using Rneasy Mini Kit (Qiagen, Inc Venio, Limburg, Netherlands). Quality of purified RNA was assessed on a denaturing agarose gel (NorthernMax Gly, Ambion, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA) and quantified at 260 nm (BioTEK, Synergy HT, Winooski, VT, USA). cDNA was then synthesized by annealing NS5 random primers to total purified RNA and subsequent extension was carried out using SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA).</p><p>qRT-PCR to study expression levels of <italic>PA5530</italic> under &#945;-KG induction was performed using Applied Biosystems Step One cycler and detection system with PowerSYBR Green PCR MasterMix with ROX (Applied Biosystems, Life Technologies, Carlsbard, CA, USA). In addition RNA was isolated from PAO1, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifR</italic>, PAO&#8710;<italic>mifS</italic> and PAO&#8710;<italic>mifSR</italic> strains grown in M9 Minimal media supplemented with citrate (30 mM) without &#945;-KG treatment, as described previously. qRT-PCR to study expression levels of genes encoding sigma-54 <italic>rpoN</italic> (<italic>PA4462</italic>), iso-citrate dehydrogenase (<italic>idh</italic> (<italic>PA2623</italic>) and <italic>icd</italic> (<italic>PA2624</italic>)), &#945;-KG dehydrogenase complex (<italic>sucA</italic> (<italic>PA1585)</italic> and <italic>lpd3</italic> (<italic>PA4829</italic>)) were done essentially as described above. The cycling conditions used were 95&#176;C/2 minutes (holding); 40 cycles of 95&#176;C/15 sec, 60&#176;C/1 min (cycling); 95&#176;C/15 sec, 60&#176;C/1 min, 95&#176;C/15 sec (0.6&#176;C ramp) (melt curve). Expression was normalized to <italic>clpX</italic> (<italic>PA1802</italic>), whose expression was determined to remain constant between the samples and conditions tested [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref107" ref-type="bibr">107</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec027"><title>Bioinformatic Analyses</title><p>Sequence analyses and domain organization studies were performed using the <underline>S</underline>imple <underline>M</underline>odular <underline>A</underline>rchitecture <underline>R</underline>esearch <underline>T</underline>ool (SMART) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>] and InterPro domain prediction database [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. <italic>mifS</italic> (P<sub><italic>mifS</italic></sub>) and <italic>PA5530</italic> (P<sub><italic>PA5530</italic></sub>) promoter analyses and motif search was done using the ensemble learning method SCOPE and GLAM2 (Gapped Local Alignment of Motifs) [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref113" ref-type="bibr">113</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref114" ref-type="bibr">114</xref>]. Multiple sequence alignment was generated using ClustalW2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/msa/clustalw2/</ext-link>) and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pseudomonas.com">www.pseudomonas.com</ext-link> [<xref rid="pone.0129629.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec028"><title>Statistical Analyses</title><p>All data were analyzed for statistical significance using the Student&#8217;s <italic>t</italic>-test on GraphPad or Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) with post-hoc testing when appropriate, on IBM SPSS Statistics 22.0 statistical analysis software. Differences were considered to be significant at <italic>p</italic>- values &lt; 0.05.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors thank the following individual for their intellectual input: Kyle Martins and Jeremy Chambers (Florida International University), Deepak Balasubramanian (Harvard Medical School), Lars Dietrich (Columbia University), and Elaine Newman (Concordia University, Canada). We would like to thank Dr. D. Haas from UNIL, Switzerland for kindly providing PA0&#916;<italic>rpoN</italic> and PA0&#916;<italic>rpoN</italic>::<italic>rpoN</italic>.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0129629.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <source>Pseudomonas</source>. <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Kluwer Academic/Plenum</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ledizet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Puttagunta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slade</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quagliarello</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kazmierczak</surname><given-names>BI</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The ability of virulence factor expression by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> to predict clinical disease in hospitalized patients</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e49578</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049578</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23152923?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23152923</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Everett</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trivedi</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rumbaugh</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whiteley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Requirements for <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> acute burn and chronic surgical wound infection</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genetics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e1004518</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1004518</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25057820?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25057820</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Furukawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuchma</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Keeping their options open: acute versus persistent infections</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>188</volume>: <fpage>1211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1217</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16452401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lyczak</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pier</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Establishment of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> infection: lessons from a versatile opportunist</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1051</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1060</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10967285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Valderrey</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pozuelo</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Macia</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rotger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chronic colonization by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> of patients with obstructive lung diseases: cystic fibrosis, bronchiectasis, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease</article-title>. <source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2010.04.008</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20727465?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20727465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Manfredi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nanetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiodo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Pseudomonas</italic> spp. complications in patients with HIV disease: an eight-year clinical and microbiological survey</article-title>. <source>Eur J Epidemiol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>111</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>118</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10845259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10845259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Emerson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rosenfeld</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNamara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramsey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and other predictors of mortality and morbidity in young children with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Pediatr Pulmonol</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>91</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>100</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12112774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12112774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cohen-Cymberknoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kerem</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ferkol</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elizur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Airway inflammation in cystic fibrosis: molecular mechanisms and clinical implications</article-title>. <source>Thorax</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>1157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1162</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/thoraxjnl-2013-203204</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23704228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23704228</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lyczak</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pier</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Lung infections associated with cystic fibrosis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>194</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>222</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11932230?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11932230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dart</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Seal</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Pathogenesis and therapy of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> keratitis</article-title>. <source>Eye</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>Suppl</issue>: <fpage>S46</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 3076156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3076156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Bacteriology of chronic suppurative otitis media&#8212;a multicenter study</article-title>. <source>Acta Otolaryngol</source>
<volume>127</volume>: <fpage>1062</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1067</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17851935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17851935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Karmakar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramadan</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>TLR4 and TLR5 on corneal macrophages regulate <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> keratitis by signaling through MyD88-dependent and-independent pathways</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>185</volume>: <fpage>4272</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4283</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1000874</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20826748?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20826748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Prevatt</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sedwick</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gajewski</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antonelli</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Hearing loss with semicircular canal transection and <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> otitis media</article-title>. <source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source>
<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>248</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>252</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15365544?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15365544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A dynamic and intricate regulatory network determines <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> virulence</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1039</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23143271?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23143271</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Fraimow</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nahra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Resistant Gram-negative infections</article-title>. <source>Crit Care Clin</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>895</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>921</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ccc.2013.06.010</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24094384?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24094384</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>WF</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Magasanik</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>1967</year>) <article-title>Glucose-lactose diauxie in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>93</volume>: <fpage>1397</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1401</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 5340309?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5340309</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stulke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hillen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of carbon catabolism in <italic>Bacillus</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>54</volume>: <fpage>849</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>880</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11018147?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018147</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Collier</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hager</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phibbs</surname><given-names>PV</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name> (<year>1996</year>) <article-title>Catabolite repression control in the Pseudomonads</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>
<volume>147</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>561</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9084769?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9084769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wolff</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eisenberg</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phibbs</surname><given-names>PV</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>Isolation and characterization of catabolite repression control mutants of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>173</volume>: <fpage>4700</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4706</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 1906870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1906870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1952</year>) <article-title>Utilization of carbohydrates by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>773</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>781</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 13011149?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13011149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kalhan</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The key role of anaplerosis and cataplerosis for citric acid cycle function</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>30409</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>30412</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12087111?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087111</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Frohman</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orten</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name> (<year>1951</year>) <article-title>Chromatographic determination of the acids of the citric acid cycle in tissues</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>193</volume>: <fpage>277</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>283</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14907714?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14907714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name> (<year>1940</year>) <article-title>The citric acid cycle and the Szent-Gyorgyi cycle in pigeon breast muscle</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>775</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>779</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16747218?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16747218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ninfa</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>PII signal transduction proteins: sensors of alpha-ketoglutarate that regulate nitrogen metabolism</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>173</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15802248?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15802248</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>He</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwandner</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Citric acid cycle intermediates as ligands for orphan G-protein-coupled receptors</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>429</volume>: <fpage>188</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>193</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15141213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Feria</surname><given-names>Bourrellier AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guillot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ambard-Bretteville</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hodges</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Chloroplast acetyl-CoA carboxylase activity is 2-oxoglutarate-regulated by interaction of PII with the biotin carboxyl carrier subunit</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>107</volume>: <fpage>502</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>507</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0910097107</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20018655?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20018655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Asai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baik</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kasahara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moriya</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the transport system for C4-dicarboxylic acids in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Microbiol</source>
<volume>146</volume>
<fpage>263</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Hoch</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Silhavy</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <chapter-title>Two-component signal transduction</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Washington, D.C.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ASM Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ninfa</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Protein phosphorylation and regulation of adaptive responses in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>490</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2556636?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2556636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dimroth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Regulation of anaerobic citrate metabolism in <italic>Klebsiella pneumoniae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>533</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>546</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8748036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8748036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brocker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schaffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mack</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bott</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Citrate utilization by <italic>Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic> is controlled by the CitAB two-component system through positive regulation of the citrate transport genes <italic>citH</italic> and <italic>tctCBA</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>191</volume>: <fpage>3869</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3880</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00113-09</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19376865?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19376865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sekiguchi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The CitST two-component system regulates the expression of the Mg-citrate transporter in <italic>Bacillus subtilis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>898</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>912</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10972810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Golby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of a two-component sensor-kinase and response-regulator system (DcuS-DcuR) controlling gene expression in response to C4-dicarboxylates in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>181</volume>: <fpage>1238</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1248</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9973351?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9973351</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Conservation between coding and regulatory elements of <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic> and <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum dct</italic> genes</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>171</volume>: <fpage>5244</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5253</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2793824?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2793824</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Roles of DctA and DctB in signal detection by the dicarboxylic acid transport system of <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>180</volume>: <fpage>2660</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2669</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9573150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9573150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ronson</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Astwood</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>Deduced products of C4-dicarboxylate transport regulatory genes of <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic> are homologous to nitrogen regulatory gene products</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>7921</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7934</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 3671068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3671068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Analysis of the C4-dicarboxylate transport genes of <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic>: nucleotide sequence and deduced products of <italic>dctA</italic>, <italic>dctB</italic>, and <italic>dctD</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>174</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>181</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2134335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2134335</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Valentini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Storelli</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lapouge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Identification of C(4)-dicarboxylate transport systems in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>193</volume>: <fpage>4307</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4316</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.05074-11</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21725012?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21725012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stover</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>XQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erwin</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mizoguchi</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warrener</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Complete genome sequence of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1, an opportunistic pathogen</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>406</volume>: <fpage>959</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>964</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10984043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10984043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Petrova</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A novel signaling network essential for regulating <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> biofilm development</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000668</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000668</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19936057?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19936057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Petrova</surname><given-names>OE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schurr</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schurr</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Microcolony formation by the opportunistic pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> requires pyruvate and pyruvate fermentation</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>819</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>835</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mmi.12018</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22931250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22931250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jayawardena</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Del Puerto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiehlmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laabs</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tummler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Characterization of <italic>poxB</italic>, a chromosomal-encoded <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> oxacillinase</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>358</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>92</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16120476?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16120476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Doucette</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwab</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wingreen</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rabinowitz</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>alpha-Ketoglutarate coordinates carbon and nitrogen utilization via enzyme I inhibition</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>894</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>901</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.685</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22002719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22002719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Runyen-Janecky</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maleniak</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hager</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacGregor</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zielinski-Mozny</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Effect of <italic>vfr</italic> mutation on global gene expression and catabolite repression control of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Microbiol</source>
<volume>148</volume>: <fpage>1561</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1569</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11988531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11988531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eagles</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name> (<year>1953</year>) <article-title>A deviation from the conventional tricarboxylic acid cycle in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>11</volume>: <fpage>594</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 13105691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13105691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kornberg</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>Anaplerotic sequences and their role in metabolism</article-title>. <source>Essays Biochem</source>: <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lundgren</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Villegas-Penaranda</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mottern</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boddy</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Genetic analysis of the assimilation of C5-dicarboxylic acids in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>196</volume>: <fpage>2543</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2551</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01615-14</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24794562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24794562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Osuna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soberon</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>A proposed architecture for the central domain of the bacterial enhancer-binding proteins based on secondary structure prediction and fold recognition</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>543</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>555</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9070437?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9070437</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Morett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Segovia</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The sigma 54 bacterial enhancer-binding protein family: mechanism of action and phylogenetic relationship of their functional domains</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>175</volume>: <fpage>6067</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6074</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 8407777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8407777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milpetz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>SMART, a simple modular architecture research tool: identification of signaling domains</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>5857</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5864</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9600884?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9600884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Apweiler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Attwood</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>InterPro in 2011: new developments in the family and domain prediction database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>D306</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkr948</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22096229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22096229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barrios</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valderrama</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morett</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Compilation and analysis of sigma(54)-dependent promoter sequences</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>4305</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4313</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10536136?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10536136</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Paget</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helmann</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The sigma70 family of sigma factors</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 12540296?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12540296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gooderham</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation of virulence and antibiotic resistance by two-component regulatory systems in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>279</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>294</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2008.00135.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19243444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19243444</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nishijyo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>The CbrA-CbrB two-component regulatory system controls the utilization of multiple carbon and nitrogen sources in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>917</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>931</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11401699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11401699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Winsor</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whiteside</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Pseudomonas Genome Database: improved comparative analysis and population genomics capability for <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> genomes</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>D596</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>600</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkq869</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20929876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20929876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barakat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ortet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jourlin-Castelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ansaldi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mejean</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitworth</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>P2CS: a two-component system resource for prokaryotic signal transduction research</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-10-315</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19604365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19604365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goudreau</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Two-component signal transduction</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Biochem</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>215</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10966457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10966457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huynen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Conservation of gene order: a fingerprint of proteins that physically interact</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>324</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>328</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9787636?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9787636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Overbeek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fonstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>D'Souza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pusch</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maltsev</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The use of gene clusters to infer functional coupling</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>2896</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2901</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10077608?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10077608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Evolutionary analysis of the two-component systems in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1</article-title>. <source>J Mol Evol</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>737</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15599505?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15599505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Waite</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paccanaro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papakonstantinopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saqi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Littler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Clustering of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> transcriptomes from planktonic cultures, developing and mature biofilms reveals distinct expression profiles</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>162</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 16800888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16800888</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bains</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hancock</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The sensor kinase CbrA is a global regulator that modulates metabolism, virulence, and antibiotic resistance in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>193</volume>: <fpage>918</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>931</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00911-10</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21169488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21169488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Deretic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leveau</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hibler</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>In vitro phosphorylation of AlgR, a regulator of mucoidy in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>, by a histidine protein kinase and effects of small phospho-donor molecules</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>2761</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2767</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 1435255?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1435255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lukat</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCleary</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Phosphorylation of bacterial response regulator proteins by low molecular weight phospho-donors</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>718</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>722</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 1731345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1731345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Varughese</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Molecular recognition of bacterial phosphorelay proteins</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>142</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>148</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11934609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11934609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilmes-Riesenberg</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Involvement of phosphotransacetylase, acetate kinase, and acetyl phosphate synthesis in control of the phosphate regulon in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>174</volume>: <fpage>2124</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2130</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 1551836?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1551836</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Janausch</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zientz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kroger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Unden</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>C4-dicarboxylate carriers and sensors in bacteria</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1553</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 11803016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11803016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Lehninger</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <chapter-title>Lehninger principles of biochemistry</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>W.H. Freeman</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>The IUBMB-endorsed transporter classification system</article-title>. <source>Mol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>253</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>262</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15247498?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15247498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The transporter classification (TC) system, 2002</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Biochem Mol Biol</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>337</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12449427?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12449427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Saier</surname><given-names>MH</given-names><suffix>Jr.</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barabote</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>TCDB: the Transporter Classification Database for membrane transport protein analyses and information</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>D181</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>186</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16381841?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381841</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Golby</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Omrani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broad</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guest</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Inactivation and regulation of the aerobic C(4)-dicarboxylate transport (<italic>dctA</italic>) gene of <italic>Escherichia coli</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>181</volume>: <fpage>5624</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5635</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 10482502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10482502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yarosh</surname><given-names>OK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charles</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Analysis of C4-dicarboxylate transport genes in <italic>Rhizobium meliloti</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>813</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>823</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2546011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2546011</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Finan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Succinate transport in <italic>Rhizobium leguminosarum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>148</volume>: <fpage>193</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>202</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 7287623?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7287623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Youn</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jolkver</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wendisch</surname><given-names>VF</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Characterization of the dicarboxylate transporter DctA in <italic>Corynebacterium glutamicum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>191</volume>: <fpage>5480</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5488</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00640-09</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19581365?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19581365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Marchler-Bauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Derbyshire</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chitsaz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geer</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>CDD: NCBI's conserved domain database</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>D222</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>226</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1221</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 25414356?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25414356</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref079"><label>79</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Seol</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shatkin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name> (<year>1991</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Escherichia coli kgtP</italic> encodes an alpha-ketoglutarate transporter</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>3802</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3806</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2053984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2053984</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref080"><label>80</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Potvin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanschagrin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levesque</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Sigma factors in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>38</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 18070067?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18070067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref081"><label>81</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Regulation of carbon and nitrogen utilization by CbrAB and NtrBC two-component systems in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>189</volume>: <fpage>5413</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5420</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17545289?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref082"><label>82</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rainey</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Dual involvement of CbrAB and NtrBC in the regulation of histidine utilization in <italic>Pseudomonas fluorescens</italic> SBW25</article-title>. <source>Genetics</source>
<volume>178</volume>: <fpage>185</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>195</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.107.081984</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18202367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18202367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref083"><label>83</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cases</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ussery</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>The sigma54 regulon (sigmulon) of <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>1281</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1293</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 14641574?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14641574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref084"><label>84</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kohler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cayrol</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>Nucleotide and deduced amino acid sequence of the RpoN sigma-factor of <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>10125</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 2602128?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2602128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref085"><label>85</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Behrends</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liebeke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cordes-Blauert</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Metabolite profiling to characterize disease-related bacteria: gluconate excretion by <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> mutants and clinical isolates from cystic fibrosis patients</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>288</volume>: <fpage>15098</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15109</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M112.442814</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23572517?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23572517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref086"><label>86</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ronson</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Albright</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name> (<year>1987</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Rhizobium meliloti ntrA</italic> (<italic>rpoN</italic>) gene is required for diverse metabolic functions</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>169</volume>: <fpage>2424</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2431</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 3034856?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3034856</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref087"><label>87</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Merrick</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>In a class of its own&#8212;the RNA polymerase sigma factor sigma 54 (sigma N)</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>903</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>909</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 7934866?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7934866</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref088"><label>88</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Browne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barret</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Gara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Computational prediction of the Crc regulon identifies genus-wide and species-specific targets of catabolite repression control in <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> bacteria</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>300</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-10-300</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21108798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21108798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref089"><label>89</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruiz-Manzano</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuste</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rojo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic> Crc global regulator is an RNA binding protein that inhibits translation of the AlkS transcriptional regulator</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>675</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 17462015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17462015</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref090"><label>90</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sonnleitner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Small RNA as global regulator of carbon catabolite repression in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>21866</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21871</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.pnas.0910308106</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20080802?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080802</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref091"><label>91</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wurtzel</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoder-Himes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dandekar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edelheit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The single-nucleotide resolution transcriptome of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> grown in body temperature</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002945</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002945</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 23028334?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23028334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref092"><label>92</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hebert</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Physiology: orphan detectors of metabolism</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>429</volume>: <fpage>143</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>145</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15141197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15141197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref093"><label>93</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Artefacts in cell culture: alpha-ketoglutarate can scavenge hydrogen peroxide generated by ascorbate and epigallocatechin gallate in cell culture media</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>406</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2011.01.091</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 21281600?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21281600</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref094"><label>94</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bascom-Slack</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>A physical assay for detection of early meiotic recombination intermediates in <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>
<volume>258</volume>: <fpage>512</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>520</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 9669333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9669333</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref095"><label>95</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <chapter-title>Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y.</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref096"><label>96</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caiazza</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hinsa</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toutain</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Saccharomyces cerevisiae-based molecular tool kit for manipulation of genes from Gram-negative bacteria</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>5027</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5036</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 16820502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16820502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref097"><label>97</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>A 10-min method for preparation of highly electrocompetent <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> cells: application for DNA fragment transfer between chromosomes and plasmid transformation</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Methods</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>397</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15987659?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15987659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref098"><label>98</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>EO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raney</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>1954</year>) <article-title>Two simple media for the demonstration of pyocyanin and fluorescin</article-title>. <source>J Lab Clin Med</source>
<volume>44</volume>: <fpage>301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>307</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 13184240?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13184240</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref099"><label>99</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Heurlier</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Denervaud</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pessi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reimmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Negative control of quorum sensing by RpoN (sigma54) in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> PAO1</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>185</volume>: <fpage>2227</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2235</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12644493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12644493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref100"><label>100</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kessler</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>A general system to integrate <italic>lacZ</italic> fusions into the chromosomes of gram-negative eubacteria: regulation of the Pm promoter of the TOL plasmid studied with all controlling elements in monocopy</article-title>. <source>Mol Gen Genet</source>
<volume>233</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>301</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 1318499?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1318499</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref101"><label>101</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Figurski</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Helinski</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>Replication of an origin-containing derivative of plasmid RK2 dependent on a plasmid function provided in <italic>trans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1648</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1652</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 377280?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">377280</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref102"><label>102</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rietsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vallet-Gely</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mekalanos</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>ExsE, a secreted regulator of type III secretion genes in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>8006</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8011</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 15911752?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15911752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref103"><label>103</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stopford</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svenson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rietsch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Control of effector export by the <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> type III secretion proteins PcrG and PcrV</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>75</volume>: <fpage>924</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>941</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.07027.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 20487288?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20487288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref104"><label>104</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>ZL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Gene splicing by overlap extension: tailor-made genes using the polymerase chain reaction</article-title>. <source>Biotechniques</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>528</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>535</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2357375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2357375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref105"><label>105</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Schweizer</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoang</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>An improved system for gene replacement and <italic>xylE</italic> fusion analysis in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Gene</source>
<volume>158</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 7789804?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7789804</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref106"><label>106</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shanks</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kadouri</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>MacEachran</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Toole</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>New yeast recombineering tools for bacteria</article-title>. <source>Plasmid</source>
<volume>62</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>97</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plasmid.2009.05.002</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19477196?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19477196</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref107"><label>107</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneper</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Merighi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lory</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The regulatory repertoire of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> AmpC ss-lactamase regulator AmpR includes virulence genes</article-title>. <source>PloS one</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e34067</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0034067</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 22479525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22479525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref108"><label>108</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balasubramanian</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zincke</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mathee</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>Role of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> AmpR on beta-lactam and non-beta-lactam transient cross-resistance upon pre-exposure to subinhibitory concentrations of antibiotics</article-title>. <source>J Med Microbiol</source>
<volume>63</volume>: <fpage>544</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>555</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.070185-0</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 24464693?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24464693</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref109"><label>109</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Essar</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eberly</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hadero</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Identification and characterization of genes for a second anthranilate synthase in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>: interchangeability of the two anthranilate synthases and evolutionary implications</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>172</volume>: <fpage>884</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>900</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 2153661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2153661</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref110"><label>110</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meldrum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poole</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>FpvA receptor involvement in pyoverdine biosynthesis in <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>
<volume>184</volume>: <fpage>3268</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3275</lpage>.
<?supplied-pmid 12029043?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029043</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref111"><label>111</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Methods for dilution antimicrobial susceptibility tests for bacteria that grow aerobically; Approved standards (2012). Wayne (Pennsylvania). Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute 32: M07-A09.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref112"><label>112</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Brencic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McFarland</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mogno</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dove</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The GacS/GacA signal transduction system of <italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> acts exclusively through its control over the transcription of the RsmY and RsmZ regulatory small RNAs</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>434</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>445</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2009.06782.x</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 19602144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19602144</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref113"><label>113</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chakravarty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Khetani</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>A novel ensemble learning method for de novo computational identification of DNA binding sites</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinform</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>249</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0129629.ref114"><label>114</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Frith</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>NF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Discovering sequence motifs with arbitrary insertions and deletions</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000071</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000071</pub-id>
<?supplied-pmid 18437229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18437229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>