
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4165761</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25226580</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-19060</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>DNA</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Computational Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Evolution</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Systematics</subject><subj-group><subject>Phylogenetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Phylogenetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytogenetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Cytogenetic Analysis</subject><subject>Karyotypes</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Animal Genetics</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Molecular Probe Techniques</subject><subj-group><subject>Probe Hybridization</subject><subj-group><subject>Fluorescent in Situ Hybridization</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Single Origin of Sex Chromosomes and Multiple Origins of B Chromosomes in Fish Genus Characidium </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Origin of Sex and B Chromosomes in <italic>Characidium</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pansonato-Alves</surname><given-names>José Carlos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Serrano</surname><given-names>Érica Alves</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Utsunomia</surname><given-names>Ricardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>Juan Pedro M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>da Costa Silva</surname><given-names>Guilherme José</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vicari</surname><given-names>Marcelo Ricardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Artoni</surname><given-names>Roberto Ferreira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>Cláudio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Foresti</surname><given-names>Fausto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Universidade Estadual Paulista (UNESP), Instituto de Biociências/IB, Departamento de Morfologia, Botucatu, São Paulo, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Universidad de Granada, Departamento de Genetica, Granada, Spain</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Universidade Estadual de Ponta Grossa, Departamento de Biologia Estrutural, Molecular e Genética, Ponta Grossa, Paraná, Brazil</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Stanyon</surname><given-names>Roscoe</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Florence, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>pansonato@ibb.unesp.br</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: JCPA EAS RU JPMC GJCS MRV RFA CO FF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: JCPA EAS RU GJCS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: JCPA ES RU GJCS JPMC MRV RFA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JPMC CO FF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: JCPA EAS RU GJCS JPMC MRV RFA CO FF. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e107169</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Pansonato-Alves et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Pansonato-Alves et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Chromosome painting with DNA probes obtained from supernumerary (B) and sex chromosomes in three species of fish genus Characidium (C. gomesi, C. pterostictum and C. oiticicai) showed a close resemblance in repetitive DNA content between B and sex chromosomes in C. gomesi and C. pterostictum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>This suggests an intraspecific origin for B chromosomes in these two species, probably deriving from sex chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>In C. oiticicai, however, a DNA probe obtained from its B chromosome hybridized with the B but not with the A chromosomes, suggesting that the B chromosome in this species could have arisen interspecifically, although this hypothesis needs further investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>A molecular phylogenetic analysis performed on nine Characidium species, with two mtDNA genes, showed that the presence of heteromorphic sex chromosomes in these species is a derived condition, and that their origin could have been unique, a conclusion also supported by interspecific chromosome painting with a CgW probe derived from the W chromosome in C. gomesi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Summing up, our results indicate that whereas heteromorphic sex chromosomes in the genus Characidium appear to have had a common and unique origin, B chromosomes may have had independent origins in different species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Our results also show that molecular phylogenetic analysis is an excellent complement for cytogenetic studies by unveiling the direction of evolutionary chromosome changes. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was funded by grants from the State of Sao Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP) to EAS (2013/02143-3), grants from National Council for Research and Development (CNPq) to FF (480449/2012-0), and by Coordenacao de Aperfeicoamento de Pessoal de Nıvel Superior (CAPES). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Supernumerary (B) chromosomes are extra elements found in many eukaryotic genomes in addition to the standard (A) complement of chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>They usually consist of highly repetitive DNA sequences, such as ribosomal DNA, satellite DNA, and mobile elements [1], [2], [3], while examples of B chromosomes carrying coding sequences [4], [5], [6], [7], functional ribosomal DNA [8], [9], and influencing sex determination [10] have recently been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>In some cases, DNA sequences in the B chromosomes resemble those in the A chromosomes of the same genome (intraspecific origin) whereas, in others, they are more similar to DNA sequences in the genome of a relative species (interspecific origin) [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>B chromosomes of intraspecific origin may be derived either from autosomes, as it is the case in Locusta migratoria [12], or from sex chromosomes, as in the frog Leiopelma hochstetteri [13], the fish Lithocromis rubripinnis [10] and the fly Drosophila albomicans [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In fact, sex and B chromosomes may share some features related to the distribution of chromatin, the accumulation of repetitive DNA and the loss of gene activity [11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The presence of B chromosomes has been reported in several fish species [15], [16], [17], [10], [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Morphologically, these chromosomes are highly variable and range in size from very small, as in Moenkhausia sanctafilomenae [19] and Prochilodus scrofa [20], to very large, as in Astyanax scabripinnis [21], [22] and Alburnus alburnus [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>In some cases, the repetitive sequences present on B chromosomes are shared with autosomal chromosomes, as in P. lineatus [23], [24] and A. scabripinnis [25], [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The B chromosomes of other species such as A. alburnus contain unique repetitive sequences [15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Among Neotropical fish, the genus Characidium (of the family Crenuchidae) provides an interesting model for cytogenetic and evolutionary studies, particularly because of the presence of differentiated sex chromosome systems [27] and supernumerary chromosomes [28], [29], [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Despite the conserved diploid number of 50 chromosomes in all species in this group [29], interspecific and interpopulational differences have been reported in relation to either sex chromosomes of the ZZ-ZW type [31], [32], the location and number of rDNA sites [27], the occurrence of natural triploidy [33], [34] and the presence of B chromosomes [28], [29], [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In Characidium, it has been postulated that the sex chromosome systems found in several species have a common origin and that the observed differences between the Z and W chromosomes in different species and populations were caused by a variety of structural rearrangements, mainly involving rDNA sites and heterochromatic regions [31], [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, though most species show a single rDNA-carrying chromosome pair, its chromosome location also shows variation [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Some species and populations are particularly interesting because they are highly differentiated: (i) the population of C. gomesi at Pardo River shows cells with up to four B chromosomes and lacks rDNA in the sex chromosomes [35]; (ii) the population of C. gomesi from the Tietê River has rDNA on the Z and W chromosomes and does not have any B chromosomes [30]; (iii) the population of C. oiticicai from the Paraitinga River has cells with up to 3 small extra chromosomes and shows NORs on the long arms of the W chromosome and on the short arms of the Z chromosome [29]; and (iv) a population of C. pterostictum from the Betari River exhibits cells with up to 3 small B chromosomes, NORs on the long arms of the W chromosome and on the short arms of the Z chromosome, and an acrocentric pair that is exclusive of this species [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Here we analyse the origin of B chromosomes in these three Characidium species by means of chromosome painting with DNA probes obtained from the B and W chromosomes, and infer the direction of chromosome changes by a mitochondrial DNA phylogeny built with these three Characidium species and six close relatives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The results have shown a unique origin for the sex chromosome systems in this genus, but multiple origins for B chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Samples were collected in accordance with Brazilian environmental protection legislation (collection permission MMA/IBAMA/SISBIO - number 3245), and the procedures for sampling, maintenance and analysis of the samples were performed in compliance with the Brazilian College of Animal Experimentation (COBEA) and was approved (protocol 595) by the BIOSCIENCE INSTITUTE/UNESP ETHICS COMMITTEE ON USE OF ANIMALS (CEUA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Origin of samples and cytogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>For the phylogenetic analysis, we assessed a population of Crenuchus spilurus as an outgroup and the ingroup was composed by C. zebra, C. gomesi, C. alipioi, C. lauroi, C. oiticicai, C. pterostictum, C. schubarti, C. lanei and Characidium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>(fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The animals were collected in accordance with Brazilian environmental laws (collection permission from MMA/IBAMA/SISBIO, number 3245). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The collection, maintenance and analysis of the animals were performed in accordance with the international regulations on animal experimentation followed by the University of the State of São Paulo (CEEAA/IBB/UNESP Protocol number 304). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>For the cytogenetic analysis, the animals were anesthetised and dissected, and the mitotic chromosomes were obtained from renal tissue and gills using the technique described by Foresti et al. [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>C-banding was performed following the protocol described by Sumner [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The samples to be analysed were identified, fixed and deposited in the fish collection of the Laboratório de Biologia e Genética de Peixes, Botucatu, São Paulo, Brazil (table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0107169-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Map showing collection localities for each Characidium species. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0107169.g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0107169-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Characidium species and populations analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0107169-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0107169.t001"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>LBP: Fish Collection of the Biology and Genetics Laboratory of Fish at Botucatu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>F: females, M: males, m: metacentric, sm: submetacentric, a: acrocentric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>rDNA: Chromosome pair carrying the 18S ribosomal DNA.Bs: B chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Microdissection and FISH </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>For the microdissection of B chromosomes, we utilised cell suspensions from C. gomesi (Pardo River, registration number 33637), C. pterostictum (Betari River - registration number 37903) and C. oiticicai (Tietê River, registration number 31212) whose metaphases possessed a single B chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>For the microdissection of the W chromosome, we used a cell suspension from C. gomesi (Tietê River - registration number 31099). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The B chromosomes were easily identified because they are smaller than the other chromosomes of the standard complement (A chromosomes) and have a distinct morphology (fig. 2B–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The W chromosome from the Tietê River C. gomesi population has a secondary constriction in its long arm (fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>The cell suspensions were dropped on 24 mm×60 mm glass coverslips and stained with 5% Giemsa for 5 minutes, and the microdissection was performed using a micromanipulator with a glass needle (Eppendorf-5171) coupled to an inverted microscope (Zeiss Axiovert 100). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Ten B chromosomes from each population and 12 W chromosomes from C. gomesi (Tietê River) were microdissected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>These chromosomes were placed in four different microtubes (0.2 mL) with 9 µL of ultrapure water, and the DNA was amplified using the GenomePlex Single Cell Whole Genome Amplification Kit (WGA4 - Sigma) [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The reaction products were visualised on agarose gels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>We generated probes for the B chromosomes (CgB - C. gomesi, CpB - C. pterostictum, CoB - C. oiticicai) and for the W chromosome (CgW - C. gomesi) from a re-amplification reaction of the amplified DNA and the GenomePlex WGA Re-amplification Kit (WGA3 - Sigma) using the modified nucleotide digoxigenin-11-dUTP (Roche Applied Science). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0107169-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Metaphase chromosome spreads after C-banding. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>a) C. gomesi (Alambari River), b) C. gomesi (Paranapanema River), c) C. pterostictum (Betari River), d) C. oiticicai (Paraitinguinha River). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The scale bar equals 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0107169.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent in situ hybridisation (FISH) experiments using probes specific to the B chromosomes were performed on four individuals per species, including B-carrying and B-lacking males and females. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The in situ hybridisation was performed as described by Pinkel et al. [39], under high stringency conditions (mix containing 200 ng of each probe, 50% formamide, 10% dextran sulphate, 2xSSC at 37°C overnight). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The chromosomes were counterstained with 4′, 6-diamidino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride (DAPI) and analysed using an optical photomicroscope (Olympus BX61). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The images were captured using the Image Pro plus 6.0 software (Media Cybernetics) and processed using the Adobe Photoshop CS2 program to improve their brightness and contrast. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Analysis of mitochondrial DNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>To extract DNA, the PromegaWizardGenomic DNA Purification Kit was used according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We used partial Cytochrome oxidase C subunit1 (COI) gene and Cytochrome B gene sequences (Cyt B) for molecular phylogenetic analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>For the amplification and sequencing of the gene segments, we used the primers FishF1 5′TCA ACC AAC CAC AAA GAC ATT GGC AC3′ and FishR1 5′TAG ACT TCT GGG TGG CCA AAG AAT CA 3′ [40] to COI and Cyt B L 14841 5′ CCA TCC AAC ATC TCA GCA TGA TGA AA 3′ and Cyt B H 15915b 5′ AAC CTC CGA TCT TCG GAT TAC AAG AC 3′ [41] to Cyt B. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The corresponding sequences were amplified by PCR in a total reaction volume of 12.5 µl with 35 cycles (240 s at 95°C, 45 s at 48–54°C, and 60 s at 72°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>For the PCR, we employed the Gotaq kit (Promega) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The PCR products were analysed on 1% agarose gel and purified using ExoSAP-IT reagent (USB Corporation) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The purified products were then used to assemble sequencing reactions with the BigDye TM Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing Ready Reaction Kit (Applied Biosystems) in accordance with the instructions provided in the user's manual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The reactions were purified, and the sequences were obtained using an ABI3130 Automated Capillary DNA Sequencer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The sequences were initially analysed using the ATGC program (Genetix Inc.) to obtain consensus sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The consensus sequences were aligned using the MUSCLE algorithm [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Each gene block was aligned separately and then concatenated into a single matrix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The matrix was partitioned into six partitions, one partition for each codon position of each gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>A matrix saturation test was conducted with the DAMBE program version 5.1.1 using the method described by Xia et al. [43] and in the same program by the transition/transversion rate graphic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The relationship between the sampled taxa using Maximum Likelihood (ML) analysis was performed using the ‘RAxML-HPC2onXSEDE’ tool [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>ML analyses were conducted under GTR+G since RAxML only applies this model [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>A bootstrap test with 1,000 pseudoreplicates [45] was used as a statistical test of the phylogeny, nodes with bootstrap values below 70% were collapsed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>An independent Bayesian analysis was conducted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Two independent MCMC chains were run with 5,000,000 replicates each, sampling one tree every 1000 steps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The search for the best model of nucleotide evolution for each partition was performed using the model test 3.6 [46] using the Akaike information criterion [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The distribution of log likelihood scores was examined to determine stationarity for each search and to decide if extra runs were required to achieve convergence, using the program Tracer 1.4 [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Initial trees estimated prior to convergence were discarded as part of a burn-in procedure, and the remaining trees were used to construct a 70% majority rule consensus tree in Paup* [49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We compared the prevalence of B chromosomes between males and females, in each species, by means of contingency chi square tests, with Yates' correction, using the GraphPad PRISM 5.1 software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The standard karyotype of all Characidium species hitherto analysed consists of 50 standard (A) chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In addition, the three species analyzed here (C. gomesi - Pardo River, C. oiticicai- Paraitinguinha River and C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Pterostictum- Betari River) harbour mitotically unstable B chromosomes, i.e. varying in number among the cells within a single individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>In all three species, the B chromosomes were the smallest members of the karyotype. C. gomesi and C. oiticicai showed very similar size groups for the A chromosomes, with 32 metacentric (m) and 18 submetacentric (sm) chromosomes, whereas C. pterostictum showed 32 m, 16 sm and 2 acrocentric (a) chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>All three species showed a ZZ/ZW sex chromosome system (Table 1), similar to most other Characidium species hitherto analysed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Only one of the four C. gomesi populations analyzed, collected in the Pardo River (Table 1) showed B chromosomes, with 72% of individuals carrying them (table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Likewise, only one of the five C. pterostictum populations analyzed, from the Betari River, carried B chromosomes (62% of B-carriers) (table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Finally, 50% of the individuals analyzed from the single C. oiticicai population sampled (Paraitinga River) carried B chromosomes (table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Contingency chi square tests failed to show significant differences in B chromosome prevalence between females and males, in any of the three species (table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0107169-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Proportion of individuals carrying B chromosomes (prevalence). </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0107169-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0107169.t002"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Proportion of individuals carrying B chromosomes (prevalence) in three species of fish genus Characidium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The B-carrying population in each species is indicated in Table 1. χ2 =  Yates's corrected contingency chi square test comparing the frequency of B-carrying (B+) and B-lacking (B−) females and males. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The C-banding technique revealed very similar patterns in the three species, especially for the W and B chromosomes, which were completely darkly C-banded in all three species (fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The Z chromosome showed a large pericentromeric C-band in all analysed populations of C. gomesi and C. oiticicai, but it showed an additional distal C-band in C. pterostictum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The autosomes showed pericentromeric C-bands in all three species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In C. pterostictum, there were also distal C-bands in the short arm of the submetacentric pair no. 22 and the long arm of the acrocentric pair no. 25. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Intraspecific chromosome painting with the probes obtained from B chromosome microdissection (table 3) showed remarkable differences between the species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In C. gomesi, the CgB probe hybridised with the B chromosomes, the pericentromeric region of the Z chromosome, and the entire W chromosome (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Likewise, in C. pterostictum, the CpB probe hybridised with the B chromosomes, the distal region of the Z chromosome long arm, the complete W chromosome and the distal region of the acrocentric pair no. 25 (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In C. oiticicai, however, the CoB probe only hybridised with the B chromosomes (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Hybridization signals near the telomere of some A chromosomes without a defined pattern have been observed in experiments with B chromosome probes for C. gomesi and C. oiticicai, presumably due to the presence, in the B-probes, of some repetitive DNAs being also present in some A chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0107169-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Karyotypes of Characidium species after chromosome painting with the CgW, CpB, CgB and CoB probes and counterstained with DAPI. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>m =  Metacentric; sm =  Submetacentric; a =  Acrocentric. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0107169.g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="pone-0107169-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Summary of in situ hybridisation experiments with the B and W chromosome probes. </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0107169-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0107169.t003"/></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Interspecific chromosome painting (table 3) with the CgB probe showed hybridisation with the B, Z, and W chromosomes and the acrocentric autosome pair no. 25 in C. pterostictum, but only with the sex chromosomes in C. oiticicai (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Likewise, the CpB probe showed hybridisation signals on the sex and B chromosomes in C. gomesi, but only on the sex chromosomes in C. oiticicai (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In high contrast, however, the CoB probe did not show any hybridisation signal on the C. gomesi and C. pterostictum chromosomes (table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Finally, the experiments using the CgW probe yielded the same results as those obtained with the CgB and CpB probes (fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>To infer the evolutionary direction of the observed chromosome changes, we build a molecular phylogeny for mitochondrial DNA using the Cyt B (GenBank acession numbers from KF914671 to KF914692) and COI (GenBank accession numbers from KF914693 to KF914710) genes on nine Characidium species and an outgroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We analysed a total of 1,694 nucleotides, 610 of which were variable, and 458 were parsimoniously informative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>There was no saturation since the Iss.c value was greater than the Iss value, and the information found in this matrix was used in the subsequent phylogenetic analysis [43], [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The graphic analysis of transition and transversion vs. genetic distance implemented by DAMBE 5.2.31 also indicated that the data were not saturated (R2 = 0.79 for transition; R2 = 0.90 for transversion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The best nucleotide substitution models selected for each partition after model test analysis are shown in Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The topologies yielded by ML and Bayesian analyses were very similar, with high statistical support and posterior probability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The final topology, resulting from the strict consensus between the topologies of both analyses (fig. 4), showed the existence of two main clades, a basal one including all populations of C. zebra (a species lacking sex chromosomes), and the other clade including the remaining species (all of them carrying sex chromosomes). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>This finding strongly suggests that the origin of sex chromosomes in these species was unique, and that their presence is a derived state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In addition, the tree in fig. 4 shows that C. gomesi belongs to a clade that is rather distant from the one including C. pterostictum and C. oiticicai. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>This result indicates that the B chromosomes in C. gomesi and C. pterostictum presumably showed independent origins despite the high resemblance in their DNA content suggested by chromosome painting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0107169-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0107169.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Consensus topology obtained by maximum likelihood and Bayesian analysis of the concatenated mtDNA dataset. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The two numbers over each node represent the percentage of bootstrap obtained by ML and the posterior probability for that split obtained in the Bayesian analysis, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>When one of these indices is equal to 100, it is replaced by an asterisk. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0107169.g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s4a"><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Sex chromosome evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The molecular phylogenetic analysis performed on the mtDNA of nine Characidium species revealed the existence of two main clades, with C. zebra (a species lacking sex chromosomes) constituting the basal clade, and a derived clade including eight species showing wide geographical distribution [27], [51], [29], [31], [32] and carrying ZW♀/ZZ♂ sex chromosomes (see fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>This suggests a unique origin for sex chromosomes in this genus, and this conclusion is reinforced by the fact that the CgW probe hybridized with the sex chromosomes of the three species analyzed here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The existence of the same repetitive DNAs in the Z and W chromosomes of, at least, the three Characidium species analyzed, thus suggests the possibility that these sex chromosomes arose in an ancestor species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A single origin has also been suggested in fish genus Triportheus [52], but other genera of Neotropical fish, such as Eigenmannia, exhibit the opposite situation, with different sex chromosome systems being observed in closely related species, with presumable different and recent origins [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The joint cytogenetic and phylogenetic analysis of more representatives of Characidium, and related genera, also including DNA probes obtained from the Z chromosome, would provide a more general picture on sex chromosome evolution in this group of species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>B chromosome evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The presence of B chromosomes in the genus Characidium appears to be limited to only a few populations in several species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Out of nine species with known cytogenetic data, B chromosomes have been found in a single population of C. gomesi (out of nine populations analysed), C. pterostictum (out of five populations analysed), C. zebra (out of seven populations analysed) and C. oiticicai (only one population analysed) [28], [33], [54], [55], [29], [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The B chromosomes observed in these species were all mitotically unstable, but exhibited some differences regarding shape and heterochromatin distribution [28], [30], as expected for genomic elements evolving in separate species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The DNA probes obtained from the B chromosomes of C. gomesi and C. pterostictum, and the W chromosome of C. gomesi, showed the same hybridisation pattern on the B, W and Z chromosomes of these two species, indicating that similar types of repetitive DNA make up their B and sex chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This probably reflects a descent relationship between these chromosomes and thus an intraspecific origin for these B chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>As our molecular phylogenetic analysis has clearly shown, sex chromosomes were present in eight species constituting a well-defined clade, whereas B chromosomes were present in a single population of only three of these species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Therefore, sex chromosome origin preceded B chromosome origin, for which reason we can infer that the B chromosomes sharing DNA sequences with sex chromosomes in C. gomesi and C. pterostictum probably derived from sex chromosomes in each species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>A possible caveat to this conclusion could be due to the fact that the DNA probes obtained by the GenomePlex method appear to contain a predominance of A+T rich DNA [56], and most painting signals observed by us were located on DAPI+ (i.e. A+T rich) regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>In fact, the probe obtained from the W chromosome (which contains rDNA, a kind of G+C rich DNA sequences) in C. gomesi (CgW) showed no hybridisation signals on the distal region of the autosome pair no. 17 (also carrying rDNA) of C. gomesi from the Pardo River population (fig. 3), suggesting that the probe did not contain rDNA sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>But, in spite of this bias, it is clear that the repetitive DNAs included in the probes suggested a high resemblance in DNA content between B and sex chromosomes in C. gomesi and C. pterostictum, and thus these Bs could have conceivably arisen from sex chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Similar derivation from sex chromosomes has been shown in the frog Leiopelma hochstetteri [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Similarity of DNA sequences between B and A chromosomes, thus suggesting the intraspecific origin of B chromosomes, has also been reported in the fish species Astyanax scabripinnis [25], [26], Prochilodus lineatus [23] and Lithocromis rubripinnis [10], the grasshoppers Eyprepocnemis plorans [57], [58], [59] Podisma sapporensis [60] and Locusta migratoria [12] and, the mouse Apodemus peninsulae [61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, B chromosomes in these species could have derived from autosomes and later acquired the repetitive elements they share with sex chromosomes, but this event should have occurred in the two species separately, given their phylogenetic distance (see Fig. 4) and is thus unlikely. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In C. pterostictum, the CpB, CgB and CgW probes showed also hybridization on the heterochromatic blocks of the autosomal acrocentric pair no. 25. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in this species, B chromosomes could have also derived from this A chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the similarity of DNA sequences between the acrocentric pair and sex chromosomes in populations lacking B chromosomes, such as Miracatu, Morretes, Paranaguá and Jaraguá do Sul (results not shown) indicates that these shared sequences had settled in the acrocentric pair prior to B origin in the Betari River population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Therefore, given the highly dynamic nature of repetitive DNA sequences and their ability to spread across chromosomes within a same genome, the former conclusions should be taken with caution since chromosome painting results, based only in sequence similarity, could in fact be supporting a false idea of common descent between sex and B chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Comparison of nucleotide sequence will provide more precise conclusions at this respect. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Our molecular phylogenetic analysis suggests that the B chromosomes in C. gomesi and C. pterostictum most likely had independent origins, as these two species belong to very different clades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The fact that B chromosomes in both species are found in only one population could point to a recent origin which has not yet been followed by spread to other populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>An estimation of gene flow among populations in these two species would throw much light on this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, the B chromosomes in these two species could have derived from a B chromosome already present in a common ancestor species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>But this would require the loss of the ancestor B chromosome in some species and populations, which is hardly parsimonious. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the B probes obtained in the two other species, that obtained in C. oiticicai failed to hybridize with any chromosome other than the B chromosome itself, The lack of hybridization with any A chromosome has already been observed in chromosome painting experiments for a human supernumerary microchromosome, indicating the absence of detectable homologous sequences in the normal chromosomes, thus being the only supernumerary marker chromosome whose ancestry could not be determined [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>These authors suggested possible mechanisms to explain the origin of this extra chromosome, including neocentromeric activity and either a complex amplicon of different genomic regions or the amplification of a very small region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Of course, these kinds of events cannot be ruled out to explain the origin of the B chromosome in C. oiticicai but, in fish, an alternative possibility is the interspecific origin through hybrydization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>This has been suggested in several cases, such as the fish Poecilia formosa [63] or the wasp Nasonia vitripennis [64], and experimentally shown by Perfectti and Werren [65] inthe wasp Nasonia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The B chromosomes found in C. oiticicai showed some cytological similarities with those found in C. pterostictum, such as very similar size and heterochromatin content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>But our chromosome painting and molecular phylogenetic results show that they can be B chromosomes independently originated in each species through different evolutionary pathways: intraspecific origin in C. pterostictum but interspecific origin in C. oiticicai. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>In other organisms, e.g. wasps, functionally equivalent B chromosomes showed independent origins, as shown for the paternal sex ratio (PSR) chromosomes in Nasonia vitripennis and Trichogramma kaykai [64], [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Ascertaining the precise introgressive hybridisation event that gave rise to the B chromosome in C. oiticicai is not an easy task, but a comparative analysis of DNA sequences contained in this B with those contained in the A chromosomes of this and other relative species, could be helpful [12], [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Two of the most interesting species for this research are C. zebra (which lives in sympatry with C. oiticicai) and C. lauroi, which is its closest relative species (see fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, we cannot rule out that the amplification method used here may have privileged specific repetitive DNA sequences of B chromosomes being absent in the autosomes, and thus other DNA sequences presumably shared between As and Bs would have gone unnoticed with the employed methods. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Our present results indicate that whereas sex chromosomes in the genus Characidium appear to have had a common and unique origin, B chromosomes in C. gomesi, C. pterostictum and C. oiticicai may have had an independent origin in every species, in the two former most likely derived intraspecifically from sex chromosomes, whereas in C. oiticicai they most likely arose through interspecific hybridization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0107169.s001"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide substitution models for each partition used in the phylogenetic analyses of each program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>(XLSX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0107169.s001.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>We thank Renato Devidé for support during sample collection and the anonymous reviewers for their substantial contributions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0107169-Green1"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>1 GreenDM, ZeylCW, SharbelTF (1993) The evolution of hypervariable sex and supernumerary (B) chromosomes in the relict New Zealand frog, Leiopelma hochstetteri . J Evol Biol 6: 417–441. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Bougourd1"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>2 BougourdSM, JonesRNB (1997) Chromosomes: A Physiological Enigma. New Phytologist 137: 43–54. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Camacho1"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>3Camacho JPM (2005) B chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In: Gregory TR editor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The evolution of the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Elsevier, San Diego pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>223–286. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Graphodatsky1"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>4 GraphodatskyAS, KukekovaAV, YudkinDV, TrifonovVA, VorobievaNV, et al (2005) The proto-oncogene C-KIT maps to canid B chromosomes. Chromosome Res 13: 113–122.15861301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Yudkin1"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>5 YudkinDV, TrifonovVA, KukekovaAV, VorobievaNV, RubtsovaNV, et al (2007) Mapping of KIT adjacent sequence on canid autosomes and B chromosomes. Cytogenet Genome Res 116: 100–103.17268185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-BanaeiMoghaddam1"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>6 Banaei-MoghaddamAM, MeierK, Karimi-AshtiyaniR, HoubenA (2013) Formation and expression of pseudogenes on the B chromosome of rye. Plant Cell 25(7): 2536–2544.23839789 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Trifonov1"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>7 TrifonovVA, DementyeaPV, LarkinDM, O'BrienPCM, PerelmaPL, et al (2013) Transcription of a protein-coding gene on B chromosomes of the Siberian roe deer (Capreolus pygargus). BMC Biology 11: 90.23915065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-RuzEstvez1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>8 Ruíz-EstévezM, López-LéonMD, CabreroJ, CamachoJPM (2012) B-Chromosome Ribosomal DNA is functional in the grasshopper Eyprepocnemis plorans . PLoS ONE 7(5): e36600.22570730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-RuzEstvez2"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>9 Ruíz-EstévezM, López-LéonMD, CabreroJ, CamachoJPM (2013) Ribosomal DNA is active in different B chromosome variants of the ghrasshopper Eyprepocnemis plorans . Genetica 141: 337–345.24008810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Yoshida1"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>10 YoshidaK, TeraiY, MizoiriS, AibaraM, NishiharaH, et al (2011) B Chromosomes have a functional effect on female sex determination in Lake Victoria cichlid fishes. PLoS Gen 7: e1002203. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Camacho2"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>11 CamachoJPM, SharbelTF, BeukboomLW (2000) B-chromosome evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Phil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Soc. Lond 355: 163–178. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Teruel1"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>12 TeruelM, CabreroJ, PerfecttiF, CamachoJPM (2010) B chromosome ancestry revealed by histone genes in the migratory locust. Chromosoma 119: 217–225.20016909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Sharbel1"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>13 SharbelTF, GreenDM, HoubenA (1998) B-chromosome origin in the endemic New Zealand frog Leiopelma hochstetteri through sex chromosome devolution. Genome 41: 14–22.9549055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Zhou1"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>14 ZhouQ, ZhuHM, HuangQF, ZhaoL, ZhangGJ, et al (2012) Deciphering neo-sex and B chromosome evolution by the draft genome of Drosophila albomicans. BMC Genomics 13: 109.22439699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Ziegler1"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>15 ZieglerCG, LamatschDK, SteinleinC, EngelW, SchartlM, et al (2003) The giant B chromosome of the cyprinid fish Alburnus alburnus harbours a retrotransposon-derived repetitive DNA sequence. Chromosome Res 11: 23–35.12675303 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Oliveira1"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>16Oliveira C, Foresti F, Almeida-Toledo LF (2007) Karyotypic evolution in Neotropical fishes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>In: Pisano E, Ozouf-Costaz C, Foresti F, Kapoor BG, editors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Fish Cytogenetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Enfield NH, Science Publisher, pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>111–164. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Poletto1"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>17 PolettoAB, FerreiraIA, MartinsC (2010) The B chromosome of the African ciclid fish Haplochromis obliquidens harbor 18S rRNA gene copies. BMC Gen 11: 1–8. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Fantinatti1"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>18 FantinattiBEA, MazzuchelliJ, ValenteGT, Cabral-de-MelloDC, MartinsC (2012) Genomic content and new insights on the origin of the B chromosome of the cichlid fish Astatotilapia latifasciata . Genetica 139: 1273. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Foresti1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>19 ForestiF, Almeida-ToledoLF, ToledoAS (1989) Supranumerary chromosome system, C-banding pattern characterization and multiple organizer regions in Moenkhausia sanctaefilomenae (Pisces, Characidae). Genetica 79: 107–114. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Pauls1"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>20 PaulsE, BertolloLAC (1981) Evidence for a system of supernumerary chromosomes in Prochilodus scrofa Steindachner (Pisces, Prochilodontidae). Caryologia 36: 307–314. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Maistro1"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>21 MaistroEL, ForestiF, OliveiraC, Almeida-ToledoLF (1992) Occurrence of macro B chromosomes in Astyanax scabripinnis paranae (Pisces, Characiformes, Characidae). Genetica 87: 101–106. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Salvador1"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>22 SalvadorLB, Moreira-FilhoO (1992) B chromosome in Astyanax scabripinnis (Pisces, Characidae). Heredity 69: 50–56. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Jesus1"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>23 JesusCM, Galetti JrPM, ValentiniSR, Moreira-FilhoO (2003) Molecular characterization and chromosomal localization of two families of satellite DNA in Prochilodus lineatus (Pisces, Prochilodontidae), A species with B chromosomes. Genetica 118: 25–3.12737143 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Artoni1"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>24 ArtoniRF, VicariMR, EndlerAL, CavallaroZI, JesusCM, et al (2006) Banding pattern of A and B chromosomes of Prochilodus lineatus (Characiformes, Prochilodontidae), with comments on B chromosomes evolution. Genetica 127: 277–284.16850231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Mestriner1"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>25 MestrinerCA, Galetti JrPM, ValentiniSR, RuizIRG, AbelLDS, et al (2000) Structural and functional evidence that a B chromosome in the characid fish Astyanax scabripinnis is an isochromosome. Heredity 85: 1–9.10971685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Vicari1"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>26 VicariMR, PistuneHFM, CastroJP, AlmeidaMC, BertolloLAC, et al (2011) New insights on the origin of B chromosomes in Astyanax scabripinnis obtained by chromosome painting and FISH. Genetica 139: 1073–1081.21948070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Vicari2"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>27 VicariMR, ArtoniRF, Moreira-FilhoO, BertolloLAC (2008) Diversification of a ZZ/ZW sex chromosome system in Characidium fish (Crenuchidae, Characiformes). Genetica 134: 311–317.18175199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Miyazawa1"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>28 MiyazawaCS, Galetti JrPM (1994) First cytogenetical studies in Characidium species (Pisces: Characiformes, Characidiinae). Cytologia 59: 73–79. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-PansonatoAlves1"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>29 Pansonato-AlvesJC, PaivaLRS, OliveiraC, ForestiF (2010) Interspecific chromosomal divergences in the genus Characidium (Teleostei: Characiformes: Crenuchidae). Neotrop Ichthyol 8: 77–86. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-PansonatoAlves2"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>30 Pansonato-AlvesJC, VicariMR, OliveiraC, ForestiF (2011a) Chromosomal diversification in populations of Characidium cf. gomesi (Teleostei, Crenuchidae). J Fish Biol 78: 183–194.21235554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Machado1"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>31 MachadoTC, Pansonato-AlvesJC, PucciMB, NogarotoV, AlmeidaMC, et al (2011) Chromosomal painting and ZW sex chromosomes differentiation in Characidium (Characiformes, Crenuchidae). BMC Genet 12: 65.21787398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Pucci1"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>32Pucci MB, Barbosa P, Nogaroto V, Almeida MC, Artoni RF, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>(2014) Population differentiation and speciation in the genus Characidium (Characiformes: Crenuchidae): effects of reproductive and chromosomal barriers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Biol J Linn Soc (in press). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>DOI: 10.1111/bij.12218. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Centofante1"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>33 CentofanteL, BertolloLAC, Moreira-FilhoO (2001) Comparative cytogenetics among sympatric species of Characidium (Pisces, Characiformes): Diversity analysis with the description of a ZW sex chromosome system and natural triploidy. Caryologia 5: 253–260. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-PansonatoAlves3"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>34 Pansonato-AlvesJC, OliveiraC, ForestiF (2011b) Karyotypic conservatism in samples of Characidium cf. zebra (Teleostei, Characiformes, Crenuchidae): Physical mapping of ribosomal genes and natural triploidy. Genet Mol Biol 34: 208–213.21734818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Maistro2"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>35 MaistroEL, JesusCM, OliveiraC, Moreira-FilhoO, ForestiF (2004) Cytogenetic analysis of A-, B- chromosomes and ZZ/ZW sex chromosomes of Characidium gomesi (Teleostei, Characiformes, Crenuchidae). Cytologia 69: 181–186. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Foresti2"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>36 ForestiF, Almeida-ToledoLF, Toledo-FilhoSA (1981) Polymorphic nature of nucleolus organizer regions in fishes. Cytogenet Cell Gen 31: 37–144. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Sumner1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>37 SumnerAT (1972) A simple technique for demonstrating centromeric heterochromatin. Exp Cell Res75: 304–306. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Gribble1"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>38 GribbleS, NgBL, PrigmoreE, BurfordDC, CarterNP (2004) Chromosome paints from single copies of chromosomes. Chromosome Res 12: 143–151.15053484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Pinkel1"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>39 PinkelD, StraumeT, GrayJW (1986) Cytogenetic analysis using quantitative, high-sensitivity, fluorescence hybridization. Proc Natl Acad Sci 83: 2934–2938.3458254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Ward1"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>40 WardRD, ZemlakTS, InnesBH, LastPR, HebertPDN (2005) DNA barcoding Australia's fish species. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci 360: 1847–1857.16214743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Kocher1"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>41 KocherTD, ThomasWK, MeyerA, EdwardsSV, PaaboS, et al (1989) Dynamics of mitochondrial DNA evolution in animals: Amplification and sequencing with conserved primers. Proc Nat Acad Sci 86: 6196–6200.2762322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Edgar1"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>42 EdgarRC (2004) MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput. Nucleic Acids Res 32: 1792–1797.15034147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Xia1"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>43 XiaX, XieZ, SalemiM, ChenL, WangY (2003) An index of substitution saturation and its application. Mol Phylogenet Evol 26: 1–7.12470932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Stamatakis1"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>44 StamatakisA, HooverP, RougemontJ (2008) A Rapid Bootstrap Algorithm for the RAxML Web Servers. Syst Biol 57: 758–771.18853362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Felsenstein1"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>45 FelsensteinJ (1985) ‘Confidence limits on phylogenies: An approach using the bootstrap’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Evolution Vol. 39: 783–791. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Posada1"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>46 PosadaD, CrandallKA (1998) MODELTEST: testing the model of DNA substitution. Bioinformatics 14: 817–818.9918953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Posada2"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>47 PosadaD, BuckleyTR (2004) Model selection and model averaging in phylogenetics: Advantages of Akaike Information Criterion and Bayesian approaches over likelihood ratio tests. Syst Biol 53: 793–808.15545256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Rambaut1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>48Rambaut A, Drummond AJ (2004) Tracer v1 4 [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link>]. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Swofford1"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>49Swofford DL (2003) PAUP*: Phylogenetic analysis using parsimony (*and other methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Version 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Massachusetts: Sinauer Associates. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Xia2"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>50Xia X, Lemey P (2009) Assessing substitution saturation with DAMBE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>In The Phylogenetic Handbook: A Practical Approach to DNA and Protein Phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>2nd edition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Edited by Lemey P, Salemi M, Vandamme A-M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Cambridge: University Press: 615–630. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Noleto1"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>51 NoletoRB, Amorin, AP VicariMR, ArtoniRF, CestariMM (2009) An unusual ZZ/ZW sex chromosome system in Characidium fishes (Crenuchidae, Characiformes) with the presence of rDNA sites. J Fish Biol 75: 448–453.20738550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Artoni2"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>52 ArtoniRF, BertolloLAC (2002) Evolutionary aspects of the ZZ/ZW sex chromosome system in the Characidae fish, genus Triportheus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>A monophyletic state and NOR. Heredity 89: 15–19.12080365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Henning1"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>53 HenningF, MoysesCB, CalcagnottoD, MeyerD, Almeida-ToledoLF (2011) Independent fusions and recent origins of sex chromosomes in the evolution and diversification of glass knife fishes (Eigenmannia). Heredity 106: 391–400.20571513 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Centofante2"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>54 CentofanteL, BertolloLAC, BuckupPA, Moreira-FilhoO (2003) Chromosomal divergence and maintenance of sympatric Characidium fish species (Crenuchidae, Characidiinae). Hereditas 138: 213–218.14641486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Silva1"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>55 SilvaAR, MaistroEL (2006) Cytogenetic divergence between two sympatric species of Characidium (Teleostei, Characiformes, Crenuchidae) from the Machado river, Minas Gerais, Brazil. Genet Mol Biol 29: 459–463. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Teruel2"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>56 TeruelM, CabreroJ, MontielEE, AcostaMJ, SánchezA, et al (2009) Microdissection and chromosome painting of X and B chromosomes in Locusta migratoria . Chromosome Res 17: 11–18.19105034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-LpezLen1"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>57 López-LeónMD, NevesN, SchwarzacherT, Heslop-HarrisonTS, HewittGM, et al (1994) Possible origin of a B chromosome deduced from its DNA composition using double FISH technique. Chromosome Res 2: 87–92.8032677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Teruel3"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>58 TeruelM, CabreroJ, PerfecttiF, AcostaMJ, SánchezA, et al (2009) Microdissection and Chromosome Painting of X and B Chromosomes in the Grasshopper Eyprepocnemis plorans . Cytogenet Genome Res 125: 286–291.19864892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Teruel4"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>59 TeruelM, Ruiz-RuanoFJ, MarchalJA, SanchezA, CabreroJ, et al (2014) Disparate molecular evolution of two types of repetitive DNAs in the genome of the grasshopper Eyprepocnemis plorans . Heredity 112: 531–542.24346496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Bugrov1"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>60 BugrovAG, KaramyshevaTV, PyatkovaMS, RubtsovDN, AndreenkovaOV, et al (2003) B chromosomes of the Podisma sapporensis Shir (Orthoptera, Acrididae) analyzed by chromosome microdissection and FISH. Folia Biol Krakow 51: 1–11.14686642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Matsubara1"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>61 MatsubaraK, YamadaK, UmemotoS, TsuchiyaK, IkedaN, et al (2008) Molecular cloning and characterization of the repetitive DNA sequences that comprise the constitutive heterochromatin of the A and B chromosomes of the Korean field mouse (Apodemus peninsulae, Muridae, Rodentia). Chromosome Res 16: 1013–1026.18949567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-MackieOgilvie1"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>62 Mackie OgilvieC, HarrisonRH, HorsleySW, HodgsonSV, KearneyL (2001) A mitotically stable marker chromosome negative for whole chromosome libraries, centromere probes and chromosome specific telomere regions: a novel class of supernumerary marker chromosome? Cytogenet Cell Genet 92: 69–73.11306799 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Schartl1"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>63 SchartlM, NandaI, SchluppI, WildeB, EpplenJT, et al (1995) Incorporation of subgenomic amounts of DNA as compensation for mutational load in a gynogenetic fish. Nature 373: 68–71. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-McAllister1"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>64 McAllisterBF, WerrenJH (1997) Hybrid origin of a B chromosome (PSR) in the parasitic wasp Nasonia vitripennis . Chromosoma 106: 243–253.9254726 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Perfectti1"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>65 PerfecttiF, WerrenJH (2001) The interspecific origin of B-chromosomes: experimental evidence. Evolution 55: 1069–1073.11430644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-VanVugt1"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>66 Van VugtJFA, JongJH, StouthamerR (2009) The origin of a selfish B chromosome triggering paternal sex ratio in the parasitoid wasp Trichogramma kaykai . Proc R Soc B 276: 4149–4154. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0107169-Silva2"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>67 SilvaDMZA, Pansonato-AlvesJC, UtsunomiaR, Arraya-JaimeC, Ruiz-RuanoFJ, et al (2014) Delimiting the origin of a B chromosome by FISH mapping, chromosome painting and DNA sequence analysis in Astyanax paranae (Teleostei, Characiformes). PLoS ONE 9(4): e94896.24736529 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
