
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Oncol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2234-943X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4109518</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2014.00184</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Trial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Long-Term Disease Control with Triapine-Based Radiochemotherapy for Patients with Stage IB2–IIIB Cervical Cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kunos</surname><given-names>Charles A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/43026"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sherertz</surname><given-names>Tracy M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://frontiersin.org/people/u/173781"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Summa Cancer Institute, Summa Health System</institution>, <addr-line>Akron, OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, CASE Comprehensive Cancer Center, University Hospitals Case Medical Center, Case Western Reserve University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Cleveland, OH</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Adam Paul Dicker, Thomas Jefferson University, USA </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Loren K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Mell, University of California San Diego, USA; Aradhana Kaushal, National Cancer Institute, USA </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp content-type="corresp" id="cor1">*Correspondence: Charles A. Kunos, Department of Radiation Oncology, Summa Cancer Institute, G-90 161 North Forge Street, Akron, OH 44304, USA e-mail: <email>kunosc@summahealth.org</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to Radiation Oncology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Oncology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>184</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 Kunos and Sherertz.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Background: National Cancer Institute phase I #7336 and phase II #8327 clinical trials explored the safety and efficacy of triapine (NSC #663249) added to cisplatin radiochemotherapy in untreated patients with advanced-stage cervical cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Triapine inhibits ribonucleotide reductase, the rate-limiting enzyme responsible for DNA-building deoxyribonucleotides, and thereby, enhances radiochemosensitivity by prolonging DNA repair time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Here, we report 3-year efficacy endpoints of pelvic locoregional relapse rate, disease-free, and overall survivals. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Methods: Eligible patients with bulky IB–IIIB cervical cancer underwent three-times weekly triapine (25 or 50 mg/m2), once-weekly cisplatin (40 mg/m2), and conventional daily pelvic radiation followed by brachytherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>A cumulative incidence method estimated pelvic locoregional relapse rates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Disease-free survival was measured from radiochemotherapy start date to the date of first relapse or cancer-related death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Overall survival was measured from radiochemotherapy start date to the date of any-cause death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The Kaplan–Meier method estimated survivals. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Findings: Between 2006 and 2011, 24 untreated patients with cervical cancer met criteria for reporting in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>A median 3.4 years of follow-up time (range, 0.3–7.6 years) has been observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>All had squamous cancers and the majority had either node-positive stage IB–IIA (33%) or stage IIIB (42%) disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The 3-year pelvic locoregional relapse rate, disease-free survival, and overall survival were 4% [95% confidence interval (CI), 0–20%], 80% (95% CI: 71–89%), and 82% (95% CI: 74–90%), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Interpretation: Triapine radiochemotherapy was safe, active, and effective in patients with untreated advanced-stage cervical cancer, worthy of randomized clinical trial study. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>triapine</kwd><kwd>cervical cancer</kwd><kwd>ribonucleotide reductase</kwd><kwd>radiation</kwd><kwd>cisplatin</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><fig-count count="2"/><table-count count="2"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="18"/><page-count count="5"/><word-count count="3576"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Incomplete radiochemotherapeutic treatment responses and poorer cancer-related survivals occur if human papilloma virus (HPV) and abnormal p53 signaling overactivates ribonucleotide reductase in cancers of the uterine cervix (1–8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Human cervical cancer cells overproduce de novo deoxyribonucleotides (the building blocks of DNA), overhaul radiochemotherapy-induced DNA damage more easily than other cancer cells, and outlive cytotoxic radiochemotherapy exposures (5–8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Pharmacological blockade of ribonucleotide reductase lowers enzyme catalytic activity, lengthens repair time of radiochemotherapy-induced DNA damage, and elicits cancer cell death (5–8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Enhanced cell lethality after ribonucleotide reductase inhibition may take advantage of a time-critical unmet high de novo deoxyribonucleotide demand during low de novo deoxyribonucleotide supply (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In previously conducted clinical trials in untreated patients with advanced-stage cervical cancer, inhibitors of ribonucleotide reductase (e.g., hydroxyurea, 5-fluorouracil, and gemcitabine) have improved radiochemotherapy efficacy (10–12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Another ribonucleotide reductase inhibitor, triapine (3-aminopyridine-2-carboxaldehyde thiosemicarbazone, NSC #663249), has further boosted radiochemotherapeutic activity and efficacy in untreated patients with advanced-stage cervical cancer (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Overall, two important anticancer strategies have demonstrated positive clinical outcomes in cervical cancer management: (a) ribonucleotide reductase inhibition (1, 2), and (b) angiogenesis inhibition (13, 14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>This study of triapine radiochemotherapy protocols #7336 and #8327 was undertaken to report long-term clinical outcomes and toxicity in selected previously untreated stage IB2–IIIB cervical cancer patients nearly matching the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group protocol #0417 cohort (13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods" id="S2"><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Patient eligibility </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>For the triapine dose-finding phase I protocol #7336, eligible patients had any histologically confirmed primary or recurrent pelvic gynecologic malignancy not amenable to curative surgery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>For the triapine efficacy phase II protocol #8327, eligible patients had squamous carcinoma, adenocarcinoma, or adenosquamous carcinoma staged IB2–IVB of the uterine cervix or staged II–IV of the vagina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Prior reports list detailed eligibility criteria (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Herein, we exclusively report on those enrolled patients with International Federation of Gynecologists and Obstetricians (FIGO) stage II or IIIB disease, or node-positive FIGO stage IB2 whose tumor size exceeded 5 cm (Figure 1; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>All patients provided written informed consent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>University Hospitals of Cleveland and Case Western Reserve University (Cleveland, OH, USA) institutional review board approvals were granted for these clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>The Case Comprehensive Cancer Center of University Hospitals of Cleveland and Case Western Reserve University provided oversight for the data and safety monitoring plans. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>STROBE diagram for progress through stages of analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>STROBE, strengthening the reporting of observational studies in epidemiology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fonc-04-00184-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Pretherapy patient and tumor characteristics (n = 24). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>FIGO, international federation of gynecology and obstetrics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="S2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Radiation, cisplatin chemotherapy, and triapine treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The details of dose-escalation and protocol therapy have been outlined previously (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Briefly, patients underwent three-times weekly triapine [25 or 50 mg/m2 (1 h after radiation on days 1, 3, and 5)] and once-weekly cisplatin [40 mg/m2 (prior to radiation on day 2)] chemotherapy during daily four-field pelvic radiation therapy (days 1 through 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This schedule was repeated for five consecutive weeks (median 45 Gy). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>An anteroposterior parametrial boost with central pelvic shielding (median 9 Gy) was given during week six, with any missed triapine doses allowed to be made up during this boost. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Intracavitary low-dose-rate brachytherapy (median 40 Gy) brought the median point A dose to 85 Gy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>No adjuvant therapy was administered in these trials. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-3"><title><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Patient assessments and follow-up </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Patients had physical examinations and hematologic, hepatic, and renal function blood testing and baseline computed tomography (CT) or 2-[18F]fluoro-2-deoxy-d-glucose positron emission tomography scans (FDG PET/CT) within 28 days before the start of radiochemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Physical examinations, adverse event assessments (National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.0), and blood work were repeated weekly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Posttherapy physical examinations and adverse event assessments were required at 1 month and at 3 months after completing all radiation therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Patients were followed generally every 3 months thereafter by one of the treating physicians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Three-month FDG PET/CT scans were mandatory on the phase II protocol #8327 and optional on the phase I protocol #7336. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S2-4"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Statistical methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>For this study, a pelvic locoregional relapse was defined as any disease occurring within the pelvic radiation treatment field. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Extrapelvic distant disease relapse was defined as any new disease occurring outside of the radiation treatment field, inclusive of para-aortic lymph node relapses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Pathologic confirmation of relapse was not required. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The rates of pelvic locoregional relapse were calculated as a proportion and with the 95% confidence interval (CI) determined with no continuity correction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Disease-free survival events were defined as cancer-related death, locoregional relapse, and extrapelvic relapse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Disease-free survival was measured from the start date of radiochemotherapy through the date of first relapse or cancer-related death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Overall survival events were deaths from any cause. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Overall survival was measured from radiochemotherapy start date through the date of death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Disease-free and overall survival were calculated by the method of Kaplan and Meier (15). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Toxicity endpoints were protocol-defined and scored according to National Cancer Institute Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events, version 3.0 (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Table 2 identifies protocol-defined adverse events happening during therapy or within the first 30 days posttherapy, and late adverse events occurring greater than 30 days posttherapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Protocol-defined triapine-attributed treatment adverse events occurring at any time (n = 24). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1"><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>aOccurring on-treatment or within 30 days of any protocol treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tfn2"><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>bOccurring &gt;30 days after any protocol treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="S3"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S3-5"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Phase I accrual to protocol #7336 occurred between May, 2006 and August, 2008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Phase II accrual to protocol #8327 transpired between August, 2009, and November, 2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Thirty-seven patients were recruited to these two protocols from a single institution; 33 patients had squamous, adenocarcinoma, or adenosquamous cancers of the uterine cervix of which 24 comprise this analysis (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Of the 13 patients excluded from this analysis, 1 patient had stage IV uterine stromal sarcoma; 3 patients had vaginal cancer; 1 patient did not receive any protocol therapy; 1 patient had a pretherapy Zubrod performance status of 2; 1 patient had clinical stage IIIB but radiographic stage IVB disease and died from an iatrogenic Mallory–Weiss tear prior to brachytherapy; 2 patients had stage IB2 node negative cervical cancer; 1 patient had stage IVA cervical cancer; and 3 patients had clinical stage IVB cervical cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Pretherapy demographic and tumor characteristics for the remaining 24 patients are listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Median follow-up time was 3.4 years (range, 0.3–7.6 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Median follow-up among survivors was 3.8 years (range, 2.2–7.6 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>For the 24 patients reported herein, the median age was 57 years (range, 33–68 years). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The majority of the 24 patients had a pretherapy Zubrod performance status of 0 (96%) and either node-positive stage IB–IIA (n = 8, 33%) or stage IIIB (n = 10, 42%) disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Although these protocols included non-squamous cervical cancers, all 24 patients under study here had squamous cell cancers of the uterine cervix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Fifteen (63%) had HPV subtype-16 and two (8%) had HPV subtype-18. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Seven tumors lacked (n = 5) or had unknown (n = 2) HPV status by polymerase chain reaction–restriction fragment length polymorphism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3-6"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Adverse events </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Adverse events attributable to triapine administration or biologic effect were low in these 24 patients (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Symptomatic methemoglobinemia [i.e., methemoglobin concentration &gt;20% associated with dyspnea (1, 2)] did not occur in patients in either protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Attributable grade 3 or 4 toxicity occurred on-treatment or within 30 days of any protocol therapy in six patients (25%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Attributable late &gt;30-day posttherapy toxicity included two (8%) incidences of grade 3 vaginitis and one (4%) incidence of enterovaginal fistula. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>No triapine radiochemotherapy treatment administration-related deaths took place. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3-7"><title><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Treatment compliance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Compliance with clinical trial protocol-specified radiation and chemotherapy administration was considered satisfactory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Three National Cancer Institute-monitored audits confirmed data timeliness and quality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>A total of 342 (95%) of an expected 360 triapine infusions occurred in the 24 patients studied here; there were no triapine infusion-related adverse events. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S3-8"><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Efficacy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The 3-year pelvic locoregional relapse rate, disease-free survival, and overall survival were 4% (95% CI: 0–20%), 80% (95% CI: 71–89%), and 82% (95% CI: 74–90%), respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 plots disease-free survival and overall survival curves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Nineteen (79%) patients were without treatment failure at the time of last follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Among women in this particular cohort, a single right pelvic sidewall relapse was detected at 8 months after the start of triapine radiochemotherapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>In this patient, a 3-month FDG PET/CT suggested an incomplete pelvic lymph node metabolic response (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>At surgery conducted to palliate non-treatment-related pain, a site of viable extranodal disease was removed surgically from the right pelvic sidewall. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Four extrapelvic relapses (i.e., outside the radiation portal) have been recorded: two (8%) para-aortic lymph node relapses; one (4%) abdominal wall relapse; and one (4%) left supraclavicular lymph node relapse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Five (20%) deaths have occurred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Two (8%) of the deaths were attributed to cancer-related factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier survival curves for disease-free survival (A) and overall survival (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fonc-04-00184-g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S4"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Triapine added to cisplatin radiochemotherapy resulted in a low treatment-related adverse event rate and produced a 3-year disease-free survival rate of 80% (95% CI: 71–89%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>These two important clinical trials demonstrate how the supply and demand economics of deoxyribonucleotides affect the degree to which cervical cancers respond to conventional treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The majority of cervical cancers have (1) HPVs that hijack ribonucleotide reductase to mint deoxyribonucleotides for replication of viral DNA, or (2) mutations in p53 that abrogate cell cycle restriction checkpoints, free-up ribonucleotide reductase to increase deoxyribonucleotide payout, and replicate DNA unchecked (9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>As a consequence of either biologic phenomenon, ribonucleotide reductase subunits M2 and M2b are abundant in cervical cancer cells (3, 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In this biologic state, ribonucleotide reductase M2 and M2b subunits saturate its catalytic M1 subunit (3, 4), which leads to overproduction of deoxyribonucleotides (5, 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Because cervical cancers are rich in active ribonucleotide reductase, which can facilitate DNA damage repair (3, 4), patients with (over)active ribonucleotide reductase might have a less than ideal radiochemotherapy treatment response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>And yet when ribonucleotide reductase activity is blocked, radiochemotherapy-induced DNA damage persists, cancer cell death occurs, and cervical cancer disease becomes better controlled. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Perhaps these concepts are best demonstrated by the 4% rate of pelvic locoregional treatment failure among previously untreated patients enrolled on these two radiochemotherapy trials using triapine to inhibit cervical cancer cell ribonucleotide reductase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Because of these intriguing findings, a National Cancer Institute Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program randomized phase II trial currently tests triapine radiochemotherapy versus cisplatin radiochemotherapy in untreated patients with locally advanced-stage cervical cancer (NCT01835171). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The antitumor consequence of ribonucleotide reductase inhibition has not been the only advancement in cervical cancer treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Angiogenesis inhibition has emerged as an effective alternative anticancer treatment strategy for patients with cancers of the uterine cervix and may serve to frame the triapine radiochemotherapy results reported herein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Inactivation of angiogenesis effectors reduces small blood vessel growth, blocks new blood vessel formation, and restores tumor blood nutrient and oxygen supply so that treatments such as chemotherapy and radiation are more deadly to cancer cells (16, 17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Gynecologic Oncology Group protocol #227C studied single-agent bevacizumab (15 mg/kg every 21 days) as an angiogenesis inhibitor in women with recurrent or metastatic cervical cancer and found a 24% rate of disease-free survival at 6 months (18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Phase III testing involved adding bevacizumab (15 mg/kg every 21 days) to cisplatin–paclitaxel or cisplatin–topotecan chemotherapy in patients with metastatic, persistent, or recurrent cervical cancer on Gynecologic Oncology Group protocol #240 (14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Bevacizumab was administered until disease progression or manifestation of unacceptable toxicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>On this trial, a noteworthy 3.7-month improvement in median overall survival (17 vs. 13.3 months) was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Also, the Radiation Therapy Oncology Group embarked upon protocol #0417 to evaluate the addition of three bevacizumab doses (10 mg/kg) to weekly cisplatin radiochemotherapy in 49 patients with bulky stage IB2–IIIB cervical cancer (13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>No maintenance bevacizumab was administered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The trial showed a 3-year overall survival of 81% (95% CI: 67–90%), disease-free survival of 69% (95% CI: 54–80%), and cumulative incidence of locoregional relapse of 23% (95% CI: 11–35%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The bevacizumab and cisplatin radiochemotherapy grade 3 and grade 4 worst overall toxicity rates were 27 and 10%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Because of the exciting clinical outcomes for these two ribonucleotide reductase inhibition clinical trials, a randomized phase II trial of cisplatin radiochemotherapy alone or with co-administered triapine has been put forward for consideration in the National Cancer Institute National Clinical Trials Network program. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="S4-9"><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Research in context </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="S4-9-1"><title><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Systematic review </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Our manuscript reports new 3-year safety and efficacy data from clinical trials conducted with triapine radiochemotherapy in untreated patients with advanced-stage IB2–IIIB cancers of the uterine cervix. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>We searched PubMed with the terms “triapine,” “radiation,” “cervical cancer,” and “clinical trial” for publications between January 1, 1999, and May 1, 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Only the original single institution phase I (1) and phase II (2) trials were found – with neither study providing more than 18-month clinical outcome data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>We broadened our publication search to include “bevacizumab,” given a publication discussing improved survival with bevacizumab in patients with advanced cervical cancer (14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>These three bevacizumab clinical trials were selected to frame the context of our new long-term triapine radiochemotherapy clinical trial data (13, 14, 18). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="S4-9-2"><title><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Interpretation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Three-year clinical trial outcomes after three-times weekly triapine added to cisplatin radiochemotherapy in patients with untreated locally advanced-stage cervical cancer demonstrate efficacy results that warrant further clinical trial evaluation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A randomized phase II clinical trial currently recruits untreated patients with stage IB–IVA cancers of the uterine cervix to cisplatin radiochemotherapy with or without triapine (NCT01835171). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec id="S5"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Charles A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Kunos and Tracy M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Sherertz contributed to the data collection and drafting of this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This manuscript has been seen, read, and agreed upon in its content by both designated authors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="S6"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>This work was supported originally by National Institutes of Health grants (U01 CA62502 and P30 CA43703-17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Clinical trial registry: NCT00335998 and NCT00941070 (clinicaltrials.gov). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>1KunosCWaggonerSVon GruenigenVEldermireEPinkJDowlatiAPhase I trial of intravenous 3-aminopyridine-2-carboxaldehyde thiosemicarbazone (3-AP, NSC #663249) in combination with pelvic radiation therapy and weekly cisplatin chemotherapy for locally advanced cervical cancer. Clin Cancer Res (2010) 16(4):1298–30610.1016/j.ygyno.2013.04.019<?supplied-pmid 23603372?>20145183 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>2KunosCRadivoyevitchTWaggonerSDeBernardoRZanottiKResnickK Radiochemotherapy plus 3-aminopyridine-2-carboxaldehyde thiosemicarbazone (3-AP, NSC #663249) in advanced-stage cervical and vaginal cancers. Gynecol Oncol (2013) 130(1):75–8010.1016/j.ygyno.2013.04.019<?supplied-pmid 23603372?>23603372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>3KunosCWinterKDickerASmallWJAbdul-KarimFWDawsonD Ribonucleotide reductase expression in cervical cancer: a radiation therapy oncology group translational science analysis. Int J Gynecol Cancer (2013) 23(4):615–2110.1097/IGC.0b013e31828b4eb5<?supplied-pmid 23552804?>23552804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>4KunosCRadivoyevitchTKresakADawsonDJacobbergerJYangB Elevated ribonucleotide reductase levels associate with suppressed radiochemotherapy response in human cervical cancers. Int J Gynecol Cancer (2012) 22(9):1463–910.097/IGC.0b013e318270577f<?supplied-pmid 23051959?>23051959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>5KunosCChiuSPinkJKinsellaT Modulating radiation resistance by inhibiting ribonucleotide reductase in cancers with virally or mutationally silenced p53 protein. Radiat Res (2009) 172(6):666–7610.1667/RR1858.1<?supplied-pmid 19929413?>19929413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>6KunosCRadivoyevitchTPinkJChiuSStefanTJacobbergerJ Ribonucleotide reductase inhibition enhances chemoradiosensitivity of human cervical cancers. Radiat Res (2010) 174(5):574–8110.1667/RR2273.1<?supplied-pmid 20954859?>20954859 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>7KunosCColussiVPinkJRadivoyevitchTOleinickN Radiosensitization of human cervical cancer cells by inhibiting ribonucleotide reductase: enhanced radiation response at low dose rates. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys (2011) 80(4):1198–20410.1016/j.ijrobp.2011.01.034<?supplied-pmid 21470790?>21470790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>8KunosCFerrisGPyatkaNPinkJRadivoyevitchT Deoxynucleoside salvage facilitates DNA repair during ribonucleotide reductase blockade in human cervical cancers. Radiat Res (2011) 176(4):425–3310.1667/RR2556.1<?supplied-pmid 21756082?>21756082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>9KunosCRadivoyevitchT Molecular strategies of deoxynucleotide triphosphate supply inhibition used in the treatment of gynecologic malignancies. Gynecol Obstetric (2011) S4:00110.4172/2161-0932.S4-001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>10RosePGBundyBNWatkinsEBThigpenJTDeppeGMaimanMA Concurrent cisplatin-based radiotherapy and chemotherapy for locally advanced cervical cancer. N Engl J Med (1999) 340(15):1144–5310.1056/NEJM19990415340150210202165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>11WhitneyCWSauseWBundyBNMalfetanoJHHanniganEVFowlerWCJr Randomized comparison of fluorouracil plus cisplatin versus hydroxyurea as an adjunct to radiation therapy in stage IIB-IVA carcinoma of the cervix with negative para-aortic lymph nodes: a Gynecologic Oncology Group and Southwest Oncology Group study. J Clin Oncol (1999) 17(5):1339–48<?supplied-pmid 10334517?>10334517 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>12Duenas-GonzalezAZarbaJPatelFAlcedoJBeslijaFCasanovaL A phase III, open-label, randomized study comparing concurrent gemcitabine plus cisplatin and radiation followed by adjuvant gemcitabine and cisplatin versus concurrent cisplatin and radiation in patients with stage IIB to IVA carcinoma of the cervix. J Clin Oncol (2011) 29(13):1678–8510.1200/JCO.2009.25.9663<?supplied-pmid 21444871?>21444871 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>13SchefterTWinterKKwonJStuhrKBalarajKYaremkoB RTOG 0417: efficacy of bevacizumab in combination with definitive radiation therapy and cisplatin chemotherapy in untreated patients with locally advanced cervical carcinoma. Int J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys (2014) 88(1):101–510.1016/j.ijrobp.2013.10.022<?supplied-pmid 24331655?>24331655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>14TewariKSSillMWLongHJIIIPensonRTHuangHRamondettaLM Improved survival with bevacizumab in advanced cervical cancer. N Engl J Med (2014) 370(8):734–4310.1056/NEJMoa130974824552320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>15KaplanEMeierP Nonparametric estimation from incomplete observations. J Am Stat Assoc (1958) 53:457–8110.1080/01621459.1958.10501452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>16ShordSBresslerLTierneyLCuellarSGeorgeA Understanding and managing the possible adverse effects associated with bevacizumab. Am J Health Syst Pharm (2009) 66(11):999–101310.2146/ajhp080455<?supplied-pmid 19451611?>19451611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>17GoelSDudaDXuLMunnLBoucherYFukumuraD Normalization of the vasculature for treatment of cancer and other diseases. Physiol Rev (2011) 91:1071–12110.1152/physrev.00038.2010<?supplied-pmid 21742796?>21742796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>18MonkBSillMBurgerRGrayHBuekersTRotmanL Phase II trial of bevacizumab in the treatment of persistent or recurrent squamous cell carcinoma of the cervix: a gynecologic oncology group study. J Clin Oncol (2009) 27(7):1069–7410.1200/JCO.2008.18.9043<?supplied-pmid 19139430?>19139430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
