<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4772096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep22284</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep22284</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Evolving <italic>Methanococcoides burtonii</italic> archaeal Rubisco for improved photosynthesis and plant growth</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Robert H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>Hernan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>Spencer M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Research School of Biology, The Australian National University, Acton, Australian Capital Territory</institution> 2601, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>spencer.whitney@anu.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>22284</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>01</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>02</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2016, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>In photosynthesis Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco) catalyses the often rate limiting CO<sub>2</sub>-fixation step in the Calvin cycle. This makes Rubisco both the gatekeeper for carbon entry into the biosphere and a target for functional improvement to enhance photosynthesis and plant growth. Encumbering the catalytic performance of Rubisco is its highly conserved, complex catalytic chemistry. Accordingly, traditional efforts to enhance Rubisco catalysis using protracted &#8220;trial and error&#8221; protein engineering approaches have met with limited success. Here we demonstrate the versatility of high throughput directed (laboratory) protein evolution for improving the carboxylation properties of a non-photosynthetic Rubisco from the archaea <italic>Methanococcoides burtonii</italic>. Using chloroplast transformation in the model plant <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> (tobacco) we confirm the improved forms of <italic>M. burtonii</italic> Rubisco increased photosynthesis and growth relative to tobacco controls producing wild-type <italic>M. burtonii</italic> Rubisco. Our findings indicate continued directed evolution of archaeal Rubisco offers new potential for enhancing leaf photosynthesis and plant growth.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>Improving the performance of the CO<sub>2</sub>-fixing enzyme Rubisco has the potential to significantly enhance photosynthetic efficiency and yield<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>. Strategies to achieve this goal involve either modifying the biochemistry and ultrastructure of leaf chloroplasts to concentrate CO<sub>2</sub> around Rubisco, or directly improving Rubisco catalysis itself by genetic crossing or transgenic modification<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. While both approaches face significant technical challenges, suggestions that Rubisco in plants is already operating at or near physiological optimum poses uncertainty as to the level of improvement possible<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. Somewhat overlooked in these small data set analyses is that plant Rubisco is not the pinnacle of evolution - as the superior Rubisco from some red algae have the potential to benefit C<sub>3</sub>-plant productivity by as much as 30%<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>. Unfortunately, replacing plant Rubisco with red algal Rubisco appears untenable due to chaperone incompatibilities that preclude assembly of algal Rubisco large (L-) and small (S-) subunits into functional L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> hexadecamer complexes in leaf chloroplasts<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. In recent years there have been significant advances in understanding the complex and specialised ancillary chaperones for the biogenesis of cyanobacteria and plant L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, however homologs for many of these chaperones in red algae are not readily identifiable.</p><p>Despite five decades of research, a dramatic amplification in computational power and more than 25 X-ray structures for different Rubisco isoforms<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref> we remain unable to improve Rubisco catalysis by rational design<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. This limitation has led to the development of directed (<italic>in vitro</italic> or laboratory) protein evolution approaches tailored to select for Rubisco mutants with improved function<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>. In general, directed protein evolution involves the identification of proteins with desired properties from a mutant library comprising sufficient genetic diversity<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. Advances in directed protein evolution technologies have spurred its success in identifying mutations that improve, or alter, the catalysis and/or solubility of a diverse array of enzymes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. A key benefit of directed evolution is it can reveal novel fitness solutions that would likely otherwise go unexplored during natural evolution<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>.</p><p>Directed evolution of Rubisco has primarily used low throughput photosynthetic selection systems (e.g. <italic>Rhodobacter capsulatus</italic>) or high throughput Rubisco dependent <italic>E. coli</italic> (RDE) selection systems that vary dramatically in efficiency<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. Common to RDE selection systems is the ectopic expression of phosphoribulokinase (PRK) whose product, the 5-carbon substrate of Rubisco ribulose-1,5-bisphospahte (RuBP), is fortuitously toxic to bacteria. A refined MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE selection has been genetically tailored to use a &#8216;PRK-Rubisco shunt&#8217; to bridge a <italic>gap</italic>A<sup>&#8722;</sup> introduced break in glycolysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1a</xref>&#8201;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>). The low frequency of false positives obtained using the MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE system contrasts with the striking inefficiency of other RDE systems<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>. As a result, the MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE system has identified mutations that negatively influence the CO<sub>2</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> specificity (S<sub>C/O</sub>) of bacterial L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco from <italic>Rhodospirillum rubrum</italic> as well as mutations that significantly enhance the assembly (solubility) of cyanobacteria L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco and, in one instance, marginally improved all catalytic parameters<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>. More recently, the MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE identified a <italic>Synechocystis</italic> PCC6803 L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco mutant with 3-fold improvements in carboxylation efficiency that improved photosynthesis rates by &gt;50% when re-integrated into the high CO<sub>2</sub> carboxysome compartment within the cyanobacterium<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. In contrast, it is unlikely that these improvements would be of benefit in plant leaves as the high CO<sub>2</sub> levels needed to account for the low CO<sub>2</sub> affinity and poor S<sub>C/O</sub> of cyanobacteria Rubisco are not met by chloroplasts<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>.</p><p>The non-photosynthetic role of the ancient L<sub>2</sub>/L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco isoforms in archaea implies they have likely undergone alternative selection pressures to photosynthetic Rubisco during evolution. For example, Rubisco from archaea have a high affinity for RuBP and high thermostability but low carboxylation rates (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>) and S<sub>C/O</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>. This catalytic distinctiveness arises from the alternative biological role of archaeal Rubisco in the pentose bisphosphate pathway where it functions to metabolize the RuBP produced during nucleoside metabolism<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. Despite its non-photosynthetic function, archaeal Rubisco can still support plant photosynthesis and growth. For example, the <italic>Methanococcoides burtonii</italic> L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco (MbR) is highly expressed in leaf chloroplasts and shown to support the growth to fertile maturity of tobacco under the high CO<sub>2</sub> levels needed to accommodate the low <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> and S<sub>C/O</sub> of MbR<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>.</p><p>The significantly poorer carboxylase properties and alternative function of Rubisco in archaea suggest this form of the enzyme has adapted to alternative evolutionary pressures compared with Rubisco in photosynthetic organisms. This questions whether the carboxylation properties of the archaeal L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco might be more amenable for improvement towards those required for enhanced photosynthetic potential. To address this question we used the MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE system (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1a</xref>) to select evolved MbR mutants with improvements in catalytic properties that are required to enhance C<sub>3</sub>-plant photosynthesis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. These properties include increasing <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>, carboxylation efficiency (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> divided by <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub><sup><italic>21%O2</italic></sup>; the <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> for CO<sub>2</sub> under ambient O<sub>2</sub>) and S<sub>C/O</sub>. Using chloroplast genome (plastome) transformation we introduce <italic>mbR</italic> genes into tobacco to demonstrate successful translation of improved MbR properties selected in <italic>E. coli</italic> into leaf chloroplasts. The enhanced photosynthesis and growth of the transformed plants producing improved MbR mutants relative to control lines producing non-mutated MbR provides novel proof of concept on the utility of improving Rubisco catalysis by directed evolution in <italic>E. coli</italic> to improve the CO<sub>2</sub>-assimilation rate in leaves.</p><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Directed evolution of <italic>M. burtonii</italic> Rubisco (MbR) in <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>The native <italic>mbii</italic>L gene coding <italic>M. burtonii</italic> Rubisco is efficiently translated in <italic>E. coli</italic> and assembles into abundantly expressed (&gt;6% (w/w) of soluble cell protein) as functional L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco (MbR)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. In the presence of substrate RuBP (or structurally comparable sugar phosphate ligand) the L<sub>2</sub> units assemble into a stable L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR complex. Random mutations were introduced into <italic>mbii</italic>L using error prone PCR (averaging 2 mutations per kb) and the mutant genes ligated into a <italic>lac</italic> inducible vector pTrcHisB<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>.</p><p>Three <italic>mbii</italic>L libraries (each comprising ~180&#8201;k variants) were transformed into MM1-<italic>prk</italic> cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1a</xref>) and grown at 23&#8201;&#176;C as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. The initial selection was performed under high-Rubisco inducing (0.5&#8201;mM IPTG) and low-PRK inducing conditions (0.05% (w/v) arabinose) in air supplemented with 2.5% (v/v) CO<sub>2</sub>. After 9&#8211;16 days 80 colonies showing improved growth relative to MM1-<italic>prk</italic> producing wild-type MbR were identified (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). The Rubisco-containing plasmid from each colony was sequenced revealing substitutions in 78 of the 474 amino acids (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). Each <italic>mbii</italic>L mutant was cloned back into pTrcHisB and re-transformed into MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE cells and separately grown under higher Rubisco activity selection (<italic>i.e.</italic> on media containing 0.1% (w/v) arabinose to elevate PRK expression; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1b</xref>). Colony growth was scored relative to MM1-<italic>prk</italic> cells expressing wild-type MbR that could not grow on media containing 0.1% (w/v) arabinose (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1b</xref>). Seven <italic>mbii</italic>L mutant genes were found to convey a distinct selective advantage to MM1-<italic>prk E. coli</italic> growth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1c</xref>).</p><p>The seven mutant and wild-type pTrc-<italic>mbii</italic>L genes were expressed in XL1-Blue <italic>E. coli</italic> without co-expressing PRK. This resulted in only L<sub>2</sub>&#8201;MbR oligomers being formed as the cells made no RuBP that is required for the formation of L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR complexes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. The cellular content and catalytic properties of each L<sub>2</sub>&#8201;MbR enzyme was measured (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Maximal rates of CO<sub>2</sub>-fixation (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>) at 25&#8201;&#176;C were determined under ambient O<sub>2</sub> levels (~252&#8201;&#956;M O<sub>2</sub>) and at pH 7.2 due to the low pH favoured by MbR catalysis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Under these conditions MbR mutant isolates #1 (MbR-K332E), #10A (MbR-E138V) and #63 (MbR-T421A) showed significant 40% to 90% improvements in <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> and corresponding 10% to 25% increases in S<sub>C/O</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2a</xref>). Quantification of MbR expression in <italic>E. coli</italic> by <sup>14</sup>C-CABP binding and confirmation by SDS PAGE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>) showed that most mutations had little effect on the level of MbR expression. The MbR-T421A mutant (#63) showed a modest, but significant, increase in expression while the mutations in MbR mutants #14, #23 and #45 significantly impeded MbR production (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Expression of improved MbR in tobacco chloroplasts</title><p>The tobacco genotype <sup>cm</sup>trL has been genetically tailored for Rubisco engineering using chloroplast transformation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. In the plastome of <sup>cm</sup>trL chloroplasts the wild type <italic>rbc</italic>L gene has been replaced with a synthetic, codon modified version of the <italic>R. rubrum</italic> bacterial <italic>rbc</italic>M gene (<sup>cm</sup><italic>rbc</italic>M) that codes for Form II L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco in place of tobacco L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). The increased O<sub>2</sub> sensitivity of <italic>R. rubrum</italic> L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco reduces both S<sub>C/O</sub> and carboxylation efficiency under ambient O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>/<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub><sup><italic>21%O2</italic></sup>) by ~7-fold relative to tobacco L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). These poorer catalytic properties result in the <sup>cm</sup>trL genotype requiring high CO<sub>2</sub> for growth in soil<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. As shown by Alonso <italic>et al.</italic>, (2009) the catalytic properties of MbR (both in L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>10</sub> complexes) are even more impeded than <italic>R. rubrum</italic> L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco, especially with increasing alkaline pH. Despite this impairment, transplastomic replacement of the <sup>cm</sup><italic>rbc</italic>M gene in <sup>cm</sup>trL with the wild-type <italic>mbii</italic>L gene generated the L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR producing tobacco genotype tob<sup><italic>mbii</italic>L</sup> that could survive under elevated CO<sub>2</sub> (2.5% v/v) in soil<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. The tob<sup><italic>mbii</italic>L</sup> lines took more than 300 days to reach fertile maturity compared with ~30 days for wild type tobacco and ~32 days for <sup>cm</sup>trL under the same growth conditions.</p><p>To test whether the evolved MbR enzymes translated to improved tobacco photosynthesis and growth, synthetic <italic>mb</italic>R genes were made that incorporated the codon use of the tobacco <italic>rbc</italic>L gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). In addition, the native MbR N-terminal MSLIYEDLV sequence was replaced with the MSPQTETKASVGF sequence of the tobacco L-subunit that undergoes a range of post-translational modifications that tentatively provide protection from proteolysis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. Three <italic>mb</italic>R genes coding wild-type MbR, MbR-K332E and MbR-E138V were cloned into the pLEV4 plastome transforming plasmid and transformed into <sup>cm</sup>trL leaves<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. Transplastomic tobacco lines producing L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR were identified by native PAGE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). At least two independent lines for each of the tob<sup>MbR</sup>, tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> and tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> genotypes were continuously propagated on spectinomycin-containing media until homoplasmic (<italic>i.e.</italic> no longer producing L<sub>2</sub>
<italic>R. rubrum</italic> Rubisco) before growing the T<sub>0</sub> plants to maturity in soil in air supplemented with 2.5% [v/v] CO<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>Only L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR was detected in leaves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>) due to the continuous production of RuBP under illumination and the relative stability of the decameric complex<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. While the T<sub>0</sub> tob<sup>MbR-E138V</sup> and tob<sup>MbR-K332E</sup> plants grew substantially quicker than tob<sup>MbR</sup>, little difference was detected in the L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR content in comparable upper canopy leaves of the juvenile (~21&#8201;cm tall) T<sub>0</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>). When at ~60&#8201;cm in height, 3&#8211;6-fold higher levels of L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR were measured in the newly emerging upper canopy leaves with significantly higher amounts detected in the faster growing, healthier looking, tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> and tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> T<sub>0</sub> plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>). At both development stages, the leaf MbR levels were generally 3&#8211;4-fold lower than the L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco content in the <sup>cm</sup>trL and wild-type tobacco controls growing alongside.</p><p>Limitations in the steady state <italic>mb</italic>R mRNA levels in each genotype contributed to the deficiency in MbR (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). As indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>, both a monocistronic <italic>mb</italic>R and a (50&#8211;70% less abundant) discistronic <italic>mb</italic>R-<italic>aad</italic>A transcript were made in each T<sub>0</sub> tob<sup>MbR</sup> genotype. In the young upper leaves of T<sub>0</sub> plants at ~21 cm in height the total <italic>mb</italic>R mRNA abundance was 30&#8211;70% lower in abundance than the <italic>rbc</italic>L mRNA levels in wild-type (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). As seen previously in Rubisco-modified tobacco genotypes with reduced photosynthetic potential<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>, these reduced mRNA levels correlate with the impaired viability of the thinner, smaller sized, pale green leaves of each transplastomic genotype (see below).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>The evolved MbR have improved carboxylase activity</title><p>The catalytic properties of the wild type and mutant L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR isoforms produced in the T<sub>0</sub> progenies were measured at pH 8 (the approximate pH of the chloroplast stroma, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). While the S<sub>C/O</sub> values matched those measured for the L<sub>2</sub> enzymes produced in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2b</xref>), the <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> rates were lower than those measured at pH7.2 due to the increased activity of MbR at low pH<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Nevertheless, even at pH 8 both <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> and the carboxylation efficiencies (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>/<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub><sup><italic>21%O2</italic></sup>) of the MbR-E138V and MbR-K332E enzymes were between 2 and 3.4-fold higher than MbR, with an accompanying ~15% increase in S<sub>C/O</sub> for the MbR-E138V enzyme (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). Importantly, these improvements in CO<sub>2</sub> affinity, specificity and fixation speed came without expense to the natural high affinity of MbR for RuBP (<italic>i.e</italic>. a low <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub><sup><italic>RuBP</italic></sup>, <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Enhancing MbR catalysis improves tobacco photosynthesis and growth</title><p>The improved growth and healthier phenotype of the tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> and tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> genotypes relative to the tob<sup>MbR</sup> lines was evident in the T<sub>1</sub> progeny. In tissue culture germination trials all the T<sub>1</sub> progeny emerged as green cotyledons on spectinomycin media after 1 week confirming all were transplastomic (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>). After 5 weeks it was evident that addition of sucrose to the tissue culture media was required for the germinated tob<sup>MbR</sup> and tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> lines to survive under elevated (2.5% v/v) CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4</xref>). In contrast, the tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> plants survived under high CO<sub>2</sub> without sucrose supplementation and grew quicker under all tissue culture conditions tested.</p><p>As shown by Alonso <italic>et al.</italic>, (2009), air enriched with &gt;2% (v/v) CO<sub>2</sub> was needed for each MbR producing tobacco line generated to grow to fertile maturity in soil. Consistent with the improved catalysis of the transplanted MbR-E138V and MbR-K332E enzymes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>), the tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> and tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> genotypes supported faster leaf photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation rates relative to the tob<sup>MbR</sup> lines (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5a</xref>). To compensate for the lower leaf levels of MbR and the poorer catalytic properties of the L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR relative to tobacco L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>), measurements of photosynthetic CO<sub>2</sub>-assimilation rates in all the MbR transformed leaves were performed under 1% (v/v) O<sub>2</sub>. Even under these low O<sub>2</sub> pressures, photosynthesis remained limited by MbR-activity over the full range of intercellular leaf CO<sub>2</sub> pressures (C<sub>i</sub>) tested (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5a</xref>) with the highest assimilation rate of 2.4&#8201;&#956;mol CO<sub>2</sub> fixed.m<sup>2</sup>.s<sup>&#8722;1</sup> measured in tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> leaves under the highest leaf gas exchange C<sub>i</sub> of 2000&#8201;&#956;bar CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4b</xref>). As this rate is more than 10-fold slower than the 26&#8211;30&#8201;&#956;mol CO<sub>2</sub> fixed.m<sup>2</sup>.s<sup>&#8722;1</sup> rates measured in high CO<sub>2</sub> grown wild type leaves<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref> the tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> grew ~5-fold slower than wild-type under high CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5b,c</xref>).</p><p>The relative differences in the leaf CO<sub>2</sub>-assimilation rates of each transplastomic genotype (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5a</xref>) correlated with their growth rate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5b</xref>). The tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> plants grew faster and reached fertile maturity before the tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> lines while the growth of the tob<sup>MbR</sup> controls were substantially impaired (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5b</xref>). The faster growth by the tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> plants contrasts with the better carboxylation properties of MbR-E138&#8201;V relative to MbR-K332E (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). This discrepancy can be attributed to the ~50% lower levels of MbR-E138&#8201;V produced in tob<sup>MbRE138V</sup> leaves relative to MbR levels produced in comparable leaves from both the tob<sup>MbR</sup> and tob<sup>MbRK332E</sup> genotypes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5a</xref>). Identifying if the E138&#8201;V mutation impedes the translation, biogenesis or/and stability of MbR remains to be tested.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>The structural location of the E138&#8201;V and K332E mutations in MbR</title><p>Phylogenetic analysis of MbR reveals it shares closer sequence homology with <italic>R. rubrum</italic> Form II Rubisco than other archaeal Rubisco (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplemental Fig. 2</xref>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. These alignments showed that E138 and K332 in MbR align with A134 and E331 in <italic>R. rubrum</italic> Rubisco and R134 and E324 in the <italic>T. kodakorensis</italic> archaeal L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6a</xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6b</xref>, A134 in the <italic>R. rubrum</italic> L<sub>2</sub> crystal structure is solvent exposed and located distil to the active site. In contrast R134 in the <italic>T. kodakarensis</italic> L<sub>10</sub> structure is one of only ten amino acids that form a highly ionic network between adjoining dimers (<italic>i.e.</italic> at each L<sub>2</sub>-L<sub>2</sub> interface)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>.</p><p>In both <italic>R. rubrum</italic> and <italic>T. kodakorensis</italic> Rubisco, the corresponding E331 and E324 residues are located near the hinge of the conserved flexible loop 6 structure of the C-terminal &#945;/&#946;-barrel (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6b</xref>). A glutamate at this position in loop 6 is highly conserved among photosynthetic L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco isoforms (e.g. E336 in plants like tobacco, E339 in red algae such as <italic>Griffithsia monilis</italic>) and is in close vicinity to the strictly conserved K334 catalytic residue (tobacco Rubisco numbering) whose side-chain interactions with RuBP and gaseous substrate are critical determinants of catalytic efficiency (<italic>i.e. k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> and S<sub>C/O</sub>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. The increased catalytic turnover rate and carboxylation efficiency of MbR-K332E (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>) imply a glutamate at this position in loop 6 may benefit Rubisco catalysis in photosynthetic organisms but pose no benefit for the non-photosynthtic role of archaea Rubisco.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Discussion</title><p>He we uniquely demonstrate the potential of directed evolution using RDE selection to successfully deliver more efficient forms of the non-photosynthetic <italic>M. burtonii</italic> archaeal Rubisco (MbR). The derived improvements in CO<sub>2</sub>-fixation speed, CO<sub>2</sub>-affinity and specificity for CO<sub>2</sub> of the evolved MbR-E138&#8201;V and MbR-K332E mutant enzymes translated to supporting faster rates of CO<sub>2</sub> assimilation and growth in tobacco relative to the control tob<sup>MbR</sup> genotype producing wild-type MbR. This finding provides the first proof of concept that directed evolution of non-photosynthetic Rubisco in <italic>E. coli</italic> can deliver mutants with improvements in all the catalytic parameters needed to stimulate photosynthesis in leaf chloroplasts. This contrasts with prior success in evolving improved catalytic mutants of cyanobacterial Rubisco that either show only marginal (&lt;5%) overall improvements in catalysis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref> or a significant enhancement (&gt;50%) in carboxylation efficiency that came at the expense of an unwanted parallel increase in inhibitory oxygenation efficiency<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>. An additional challenge with cyanobacterial L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco is its limited biogenesis potential in tobacco chloroplasts (~10% of wild-type<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>) compared with MbR L<sub>10</sub> which is produced at ~25&#8211;50% of wild-type tobacco Rubisco (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3c</xref>). The high solubility and overall success with evolving MbR catalysis inspires continued effort to evolve properties along evolutionary trajectories that further enhance its photosynthetic potential.</p><p>Exploration of Rubisco sequence space towards mutations that improve its efficiency in crop plants is an ongoing challenge<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>. Our continued inability after 50 years to rationally predict what sequence changes can improve Rubisco function steered our attention towards the potential of directed evolution to explore Rubisco sequence space for improved catalysis. A common requirement of successful directed evolution studies is identifying a suitable starting point for mutagenesis and appropriate selection system<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>. The ease by which the carboxylase activities of MbR could be enhanced by single amino acid changes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>) likely stems from it having undergone specialisation to an alternative metabolic role during its non-photosynthetic evolution<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. This implies that archaeal Rubisco may occupy an alternative position to photosynthetic Rubisco within the evolutionary landscape of sequence space diversity in relation to catalysis. Consistent with this, archaeal Rubisco catalysis is typically distinct relative to contemporary (photosynthetic) Rubisco<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Archaeal Rubisco can sustain functionality at extreme temperatures, under which thermotolerant archaea grow, and exhibit the heightened affinity for RuBP required to metabolise the finite levels made during nucleotide metabolism<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. Offsetting these beneficial features, archaeal Rubisco show low <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> and S<sub>C/O</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Improving our fundamental understanding of the structural features that determine these unconventional kinetics requires a more comprehensive survey of archaeal Rubisco structure, catalytic, and sequence diversity.</p><p>The merits of directed protein evolution are illustrated by the many examples of successfully altering protein solubility, improving catalysis, even enabling promiscuous catalytic function<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. These outcomes typically require multiple, incremental rounds of mutagenesis. For MbR, an attempt was made to select second generation mutants with improved activity using a combined library of epPCR mutated <italic>mb</italic>R genes coding MbR, MbR-E138V and MbR-K332E. No MbR mutants were detected that enabled MM1-prk RDE survival under high PRK induction (<italic>i.e.</italic> 0.2% w/v arabinose). Future goals are to examine the feasibility of capturing the epistasis of the spectrum of first generation <italic>mbii</italic>L mutant genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>) using a shuffling approach to identify adaptive trajectories that further improve MbR catalysis. Success however depends on the positive epistatic potential for evolving the carboxylase activity of MbR and ability to avoid or circumvent beneficial mutations that might produce destabilizing effects on structure and function. Such uncertainties are common to directed protein evolution studies. Forecasting the extent to which mutations (via direct or long distance amino acid interactions) influence artificial evolutionary trajectories remains unpredictable<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>.</p><p>A significant hurdle is the relatively low selection fidelity and throughput of the MM1-<italic>prk</italic> selection system<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. The frequency of success in directed evolution applications depends on the library selection throughput and sensitivity of the selection system to detect a desired trait<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. The reliance and throughput of existing RDE strains suffer from high frequencies of false positives that typically arise through transposon associated PRK escape mutations<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>. While relatively immune to false positives, the MM1-<italic>prk</italic> RDE selection throughput is impeded by a low growth temperature requirement (25&#8201;&#176;C), poor transformation efficiency, and reduced cell viability as a result of the <italic>gap</italic>A<sup>&#8722;</sup> mutation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Improving the selection fidelity of RDE systems is therefore critical to further evolving MbR, and other Rubisco isoforms, with improved photosynthetic properties. One solution might be to tether PRK with an antibiotic resistance protein in an RDE strain thus avoiding selection of &#8220;PRK-silenced&#8221; false positives as such mutations would also relinquish antibiotic resistance.</p><p>Adaptive evolution of archaeal Rubisco <italic>in vitro</italic> towards one that is more efficient than crop plant L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> enzymes is undeniably a significant, long term challenge. Unlike L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco from plants and algae, the folding and assembly requirements of archaeal Rubisco, like MbR, are met in <italic>E. coli</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1c</xref>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. This property strengthens the suitability of archaeal Rubisco for identifying catalysis enhancing mutants using RDE strains as it curtails selection of mutations that enhance solubility, an outcome that has dominated directed evolution studies with cyanobacteria L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>. The amenability of archaeal Rubisco to mutational testing in <italic>E. coli</italic> has already proven useful to demonstrate how incorporating spinach Rubisco sequence into <italic>T. kodakarensis</italic> L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco can improve <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. Improving archaeal Rubisco catalysis by rational design or directed evolution or a combination of both therefore poses viable future pathways to pursue, particularly given our finding that these benefits can directly translate to improving leaf photosynthesis.</p><p>As indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Fig. 6</xref>, the primary sequences of archaeal Rubisco are highly diverse and their oligomer structures as L<sub>2</sub> or L<sub>10</sub> appears variable. While mass spectrometry analysis infers a mature L<sub>10</sub> quaternary structure for MbR<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref> it is uncertain if it forms a comparable toroidal structure to <italic>T. kodakarensis</italic> archaeal Rubisco (PDB: 1GEH), in particular since they only share 36% amino acid homology and MbR contains a novel 11 amino acid insertion in its C-domain<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>. Ongoing efforts are focused on solving the crystal structures for both L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR to better understand the structural diversity among archaeal Rubisco as well as help interpret how mutations, such as E138V and K332E, functionally impart changes to catalysis.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Evolution, expression and purification of MbR in <italic>E. coli</italic></title><p>The <italic>mbii</italic>L gene from pHUE-mbiiL<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref> was cloned into pTrcHisB using <italic>Nco</italic>I/<italic>Hind</italic>III and the resulting pTrcMbR plasmid used as template to randomly mutate the <italic>mbii</italic>L by error-prone PCR (epPCR) as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. The PCR products were cloned into pTrcHisB and the diversity of the <italic>mbii</italic>L mutant library calculated using PEDEL-AA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>. The library was transformed into the Rubisco Dependent <italic>E. coli</italic> (RDE) strain MM1-<italic>prk</italic> and grown under varying selective conditions according to<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. The mutant <italic>mbii</italic>L genes from faster growing colonies were cloned into the 6xhistidine-tagged ubiquitin expression plasmid pHUE and each MbR isoform affinity purified by immobilised metal affinity chromatography (IMAC) as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Tobacco plastome transformation and growth</title><p>A synthetic gene, <italic>mb</italic>R, coding for <italic>M. burtonii</italic> Rubisco both with and without mutations coding E138&#8201;V or K332E substitutions was synthesised by GenScript. The codon use of <italic>mb</italic>R matched the tobacco <italic>rbc</italic>L gene and replaced the native N-terminal coding sequence (MSLIYEDLV) with that for the native tobacco Rubisco large (L-) subunit (MSPQTETKASVGF). The 1,418-bp <italic>mb</italic>R gene fragments were cloned into <italic>Nhe</italic>I/<italic>Sal</italic>I cut pLEV4<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> to produce the plastome transforming plasmids pLEVmbR, pLEVmbR-K332E and pLEVmbR-E138&#8201;V and transformed into ten <sup>cm</sup>trL leaves by biolistic bombardment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. Independent positively transformed lines producing L<sub>10</sub>&#8201;MbR were identified by non-denaturing PAGE (native PAGE)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref> and two independent lines for each MbR genotype were grown to maturity in soil in a growth chamber with the air supplemented with 2.5% (v/v) CO<sub>2</sub><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. The flowers of the fertile T<sub>0</sub> plants were fertilised with wild type pollen and the seed germinated in tissue culture on RMOP media supplemented with 0% to 3% (w/v) sucrose<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. The germinated T<sub>1</sub> progeny were carefully transferred to soil and the leaf gas exchange and cell biochemistry of near fully expanded leaves at comparable positions in the upper canopy analysed when the plants were 20&#8211;25&#8201;cm in height.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>DNA, protein and PAGE analyses</title><p>Total leaf genomic DNA was isolated using the DNeasy<sup>&#174;</sup> Plant Mini Kit and primers LSH and LSE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>) used to PCR amplify and sequence the plastome region transformed in each tobacco genotype as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref>. The preparation, quantification (against BSA) of soluble leaf protein and analysis by SDS-PAGE, native PAGE and immunoblot analysis was performed as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Rubisco content and catalysis</title><p>Rates of Rubisco <sup>14</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> fixation were made using soluble protein extracts isolated from bacteria or leaf protein in 50&#8201;mM HEPES-NaOH (pH 7.2 or 8.0) containing extraction buffer as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. Protein extract (20&#8201;&#956;L) was used to initiate activity in 0.5&#8201;mL assays performed in 7&#8201;mL septum-capped scintillation vials<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>. Each sample was measured in duplicate under varying concentrations of NaH<sup>14</sup>CO<sub>3</sub> (0&#8211;67&#8201;&#956;M) and O<sub>2</sub> (0, 2, and 5% (v/v)) to calculate the maximal rate of carboxylation (<italic>V</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub>) and the Michaelis constants (<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>) for CO<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub>) and O<sub>2</sub> (<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>O</italic></sub>)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>. The carboxylation turnover rate (<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>) was calculated by dividing <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub> by the Rubisco active sites content quantified by [<sup>14</sup>C]-2-CABP binding<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>. Rubisco CO<sub>2</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> specificity (S<sub>C/O</sub>) and the <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> for RuBP were quantified as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref> using MbR purified from <italic>E. coli</italic> by immobilised metal affinity chromatography<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref> or from tobacco leaves by ion exchange<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Growth and photosynthesis analysis</title><p>All plants were grown at 25&#8201;&#176;C in a growth chamber as described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref> under 200&#8201;&#177;&#8201;50&#8201;&#956;mol quanta.m<sup>2</sup>.s<sup>&#8722;1</sup> in air containing 2.5% (v/v) CO<sub>2</sub>. Once approximately 21&#8201;cm in height the leaf photosynthesis rates (<italic>A</italic>) in the 5<sup>th</sup> upper canopy leaf were measured using a LI-6400 XT gas exchange system (LI-COR) at varying atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> partial pressures (C<sub>a</sub>; 50&#8211;2000&#8201;ppm) at a constant leaf temperate of 25&#8201;&#176;C and 1000&#8201;&#956;mol quanta.m<sup>2</sup>.s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. The &#8220;A-C<sub>i</sub>&#8221; measurements (C<sub>i</sub>; leaf intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> levels) were performed at low O<sub>2</sub> partial pressures (1% (v/v) O<sub>2</sub> in N<sub>2</sub>) to obtain suitable measures of <italic>A</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Additional Information</title><p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Wilson, R. H. <italic>et al.</italic> Evolving <italic>Methanococcoides burtonii</italic> archaeal Rubisco for improved photosynthesis and plant growth. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>
<bold>6</bold>, 22284; doi: 10.1038/srep22284 (2016).</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d33e25" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Information</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was supported by Australian Research Council grants FT0991407and CE140100015 awarded to SW.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Improving photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>162</volume>, <fpage>1780</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1793</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23812345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>Stephen P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marshall-Colon</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>X.-G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Meeting the global food demand of the future by engineering crop photosynthesis and yield potential</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<volume>161</volume>, <fpage>56</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25815985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Savir</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tlusty</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cross-species analysis traces adaptation of Rubisco toward optimality in a low-dimensional landscape</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci</source>
<volume>107</volume>, <fpage>3475</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3480</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20142476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tcherkez</surname><given-names>G. G. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farquhar</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Despite slow catalysis and confused substrate specificity, all ribulose bisphosphate carboxylases may be nearly perfectly optimized</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci.</source>
<volume>103</volume>, <fpage>7246</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7251</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16641091</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Form I Rubiscos from non-green algae are expressed abundantly but not assembled in tobacco chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>547</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11439139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Structure and mechanism of the Rubisco assembly chaperone Raf1</article-title>. <source>Nat Struct Mol Biol</source> In press (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Popilka</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hartl</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hayer-Hartl</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Role of auxiliary proteins in Rubisco biogenesis and function</article-title>. <source>Nature Plants</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>15065</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Birch</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelso</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kapralov</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Improving recombinant Rubisco biogenesis, plant photosynthesis and growth by coexpressing its ancillary RAF1 chaperone</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>3564</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3569</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Photosynthesis: Getting it together for CO2 fixation</article-title>. <source>Nature Plants</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>15130</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Backlund</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structure and function of Rubisco</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18294858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dur&#227;o</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Opposing effects of folding and assembly chaperones on evolvability of Rubisco</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>155</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25558973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mueller-Cajar</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Directing the evolution of Rubisco and Rubisco activase: first impressions of a new tool for photosynthesis research</article-title>. <source>Photosynth Res</source>
<volume>98</volume>, <fpage>667</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>75</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18626786</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>M. A. J.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Rubisco activity and regulation as targets for crop improvement</article-title>. <source>J Exp Botany</source>
<volume>64</volume>, <fpage>717</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>730</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23162118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Methods for the directed evolution of proteins</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>379</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>394</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26055155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dalby</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Strategy and success for the directed evolution of enzymes</article-title>. <source>Cur Opin Struct Biol</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>473</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>480</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J. W.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Systems metabolic engineering of microorganisms for natural and non-natural chemicals</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>536</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>546</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22596205</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>F. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Exploring protein fitness landscapes by directed evolution</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>866</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>876</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19935669</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Satagopan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tabita</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Structure-function studies with the unique hexameric form II Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (Rubisco) from <italic>Rhodopseudomonas palustris</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Biol Chem</source>
<volume>289</volume>, <fpage>21433</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21450</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24942737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tabita</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Positive and negative selection of mutant forms of prokaryotic (cyanobacterial) Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>
<volume>331</volume>, <fpage>557</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>569</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12899828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mueller-Cajar</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morell</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Directed evolution of Rubisco in <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> reveals a specificity-determining hydrogen bond in the form II enzyme</article-title>. <source>Biochem.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>14067</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>74</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18004873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mueller-Cajar</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name> &amp; Whitney, <article-title>Spencer M. Evolving improved Synechococcus Rubisco functional expression in Escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>Biochemical Journal</source>
<volume>414</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>214</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18484948</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Development of an activity-directed selection system enabled significant improvement of the carboxylation efficiency of Rubisco</article-title>. <source>Protein &amp; Cell</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>552</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>562</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24870149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parikh</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woods</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Directed evolution of Rubisco hypermorphs through genetic selection in engineered <italic>E. coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Protein Engineering, Design and Selection</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>119</lpage> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Matsumura</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Artificially evolved Synechococcus PCC6301 Rubisco variants exhibit improvements in folding and catalytic efficiency</article-title>. <source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>404</volume>, <fpage>517</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>24</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17391103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>G. D.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Howitt</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Towards turbocharged photosynthesis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>513</volume>, <fpage>497</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>498</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25231859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blayney</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Substrate-induced assembly of <italic>Methanococcoides burtonii</italic> D-ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase dimers into decamers</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>284</volume>, <fpage>33876</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>82</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19837658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nishitani</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Structure-based catalytic optimization of a type III Rubisco from a hyperthermophile</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>285</volume>, <fpage>39339</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39347</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20926376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tabita</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Satagopan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>T. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kreel</surname><given-names>N. E.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Distinct form I, II, III, and IV Rubisco proteins from the three kingdoms of life provide clues about Rubisco evolution and structure/function relationships</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>1515</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1524</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18281717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aono</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Imanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Atomi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A pentose bisphosphate pathway for nucleoside degradation in Archaea</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>360</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25822915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sharwood</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Caemmerer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maliga</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The catalytic properties of hybrid Rubisco comprising tobacco small and sunflower large subunits mirror the kinetically equivalent source Rubiscos and can support tobacco growth</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>146</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>96</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17993544</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Sharwood</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Construction of a tobacco master line to improve Rubisco engineering in chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>1909</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18250079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<article-title>Isoleucine 309 acts as a C<sub>4</sub> catalytic switch that increases ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (rubisco) carboxylation rate in <italic>Flaveria</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>14688</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21849620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>von Caemmerer</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tazoe</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Exploiting transplastomically modified Rubisco to rapidly measure natural diversity in its carbon isotope discrimination using tuneable diode laser spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>J Exp Bot</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>3759</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24687980</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Occhialini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>M. T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andralojc</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>M. A. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Transgenic tobacco plants with improved cyanobacterial Rubisco expression but no extra assembly factors grow at near wild-type rates if provided with elevated CO2</article-title>. <source>The Plant Journal</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>148</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>160</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26662726</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Directed enzyme evolution: beyond the low-hanging fruit</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>406</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>412</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22579412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miton</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Tokuriki</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>How mutational epistasis impairs predictability in protein evolution and design</article-title>. <source>Protein Science</source>, n/a-n/a (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Firth</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Patrick</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>GLUE-IT and PEDEL-AA: new programmes for analyzing protein diversity in randomized libraries</article-title>. <source>Nuc Acids Res</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>285</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Sharwood</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Linked Rubisco subunits can assemble into functional oligomers without impeding catalytic performance</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>282</volume>, <fpage>3809</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3818</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17150955</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> R.H.W. and S.M.W. designed the experiments. R.H.W. and H.A. undertook the directed evolution studies with R.H.W. producing and analysing the transformed tobacco lines. R.H.W., H.A. and S.M.W. performed the biochemical analyses and wrote the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Selecting for improvements in MbR catalysis using Rubisco Dependent <italic>E. coli</italic> (RDE).</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Simplified schematic of the RDE selection system that uses a glycolysis/gluconeogenesis interrupted glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase deletion (<italic>gap</italic>A<sup>&#8722;</sup>) strain of <italic>E. coli</italic> (MM1). Ectopic expression of phosphoribulokinase (PRK) and Rubisco in MM1 acts as a bypass shunt for glycolysis to enable carbon flow from hexose carbon to the TCA cycle for energy and growth. PRK catalyses the conversion of ribulose-5-phosphate (rib-5-P) produced by the pentose phosphate pathway (PPP) to RuBP, which is toxic to cell growth. RuBP toxicity can be alleviated by Rubisco catalysed carboxylation followed by utilisation of the 3PGA product in glycolysis. Expression of PRK and Rubisco is carefully regulated by varying the inducing agents arabinose and IPTG respectively<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. Early cell division is facilitated by addition of trace levels of glycerol (0.4% v/v; upstream C-source), 30&#8201;mM malate and 0.5% w/v cas amino-acids (downstream C- and N- sources). (<bold>b</bold>) Comparative growth of MM1-<italic>prk</italic> cells expressing &#8220;improved&#8221; mutant and wild type MbR under increasing levels of arabinose induced PRK expression. (&#8722;) no growth; (+ to ++++) relative increase in colony size. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref> for comprehensive RDE growth screen and sequence of all primary MbR mutants selected. (<bold>c</bold>) A summary of colony growth scores for the seven best performing MbR mutants under increasing arabinose induced PRK expression.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Analysis of MbR mutants with improved catalysis.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Catalytic properties (maximum RuBP-carboxylation rate, <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup>; specificity for CO<sub>2</sub> over O<sub>2</sub>, S<sub>C/O</sub>) of wild type and mutant MbR at 25<sup>o</sup>C, pH 7.2 and their relative expression level in crude <italic>E. coli</italic> soluble lysate. Values shown are the average (&#177;S.E) of assays made on three cell preparations or, for S<sub>C/O</sub>, four technical replicates from duplicate purified enzyme preparations. nm, not measured. Significance variation relative to wild type MbR (*p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01, **p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) determined by T-test. (<bold>b</bold>) SDS PAGE analysis and immuno-blot detection of MbR content in the <italic>E. coli</italic> soluble protein (7&#8201;&#956;g/lane) used to measure <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup> and MbR content. pTrcHisB, vector-only control, *an abundant ~50kDa protein made in <italic>E. coli</italic> that is of similar size to the Rubisco L-subunit<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Transformation and expression of the mutated MbR enzymes in tobacco leaves.</title><p>The varying <sup>cm</sup><italic>mb</italic>R genes coding wild type and mutant MbR were integrated into the <italic>rbc</italic>L region of the tobacco plastome by chloroplast transformation. (<bold>a</bold>) Comparison of the plastome sequence and types of Rubisco made in the varying tobacco genotypes examined. The <sup>cm</sup><italic>mb</italic>R and selectable marker <italic>aad</italic>A gene in the pLEVMbR, pLEVMbR-E138V and pLEVMbR-K332E transforming plasmids were transformed into the plastome of the <sup>cm</sup>trL tobacco genotype to replace the <sup>cm</sup><italic>rbc</italic>M (that codes <italic>R. rubrum</italic> L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>) by homologous recombination of the flanking plastome sequence (located between the dashed lines, numbering relevant to Genbank sequence Z00044). P, 292-bp <italic>rbc</italic>L promoter/5&#8242;UTR; T, 288-bp<italic>rbc</italic>L 3&#8242;UTR; <italic>T</italic>, 112-bp of <italic>psb</italic>A 3&#8242;UTR; t, 147-bp <italic>rps</italic>16 3&#8242;UTR. Alignment position for primers LsD and LsE<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> and the 221-bp 5UTR probe<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref> are shown. (<bold>b</bold>) native PAGE analysis of the L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub>, L<sub>2</sub> and L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco isoforms produced, respectively, in leaves from tobacco, <sup>cm</sup>trL and the three tob<sup>MbR</sup> genotypes. *non-Rubisco protein. (<bold>c</bold>) <sup>14</sup>C-CABP quantification of Rubisco active site content in comparable young upper canopy leaves of each genotype during early (~20&#8201;cm in height, colored bars) and late (~60&#8201;cm in height, black bars) exponential growth.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The T<sub>1</sub> tob<sup>MbR-E138V</sup> and tob<sup>MbR-K332E</sup> progeny showed improved growth in tissue culture.</title><p>Comparison of the growth of each tob<sup>MbR</sup> genotype after 1 and 5 weeks growth on RMOP media containing 0.2&#8201;mg.mL<sup>&#8722;1</sup> spectinomycin and varying levels of sucrose. The plants were grown in air +2% (v/v) CO<sub>2</sub> and 25&#8211;100&#8201;&#956;mol photons.m<sup>&#8722;2</sup>.s<sup>&#8722;1</sup> illumination.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>The mutated MbR improve tobacco leaf photosynthesis and plant growth relative to tobacco producing wild-type MbR.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Comparison of photosynthesis rates in plants growing in soil quantified by leaf gas exchange measures of CO<sub>2</sub>-assimilation rates at 25&#8201;&#176;C at varying intercellular CO<sub>2</sub> pressures (C<sub>i</sub>). Shown are the average of 3 measurements (&#177;S.D) made at 1000&#8201;&#956;mol quanta m<sup>&#8722;2</sup>&#8201;s<sup>&#8722;1</sup> illumination on comparable upper canopy leaves of T<sub>1</sub> plants 21&#8201;&#177;&#8201;2&#8201;cm in height. The L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco content in the analysed leaves were quantified by <sup>14</sup>C-CABP binding (the average &#956;mol catalytic sites.m<sup>2</sup> shown in square brackets) and confirmed by coomassie staining following native PAGE. (<bold>b</bold>) A growth comparison of the transplastomic tobacco genotypes after 180 days at high CO<sub>2</sub> highlighting the faster growth of the tob<sup>MbR-E138V</sup> and tob<sup>MbR-K332E</sup> plants relative to the tob<sup>MbR</sup> controls, albeit slower than (<bold>c</bold>) the 40 day old wild type tobacco. pce, post-cotyledon emergence.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-f5"/></fig><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Structural analysis of the catalysis enhancing mutations in MbR.</title><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Alignment of MbR, <italic>R. rubrum</italic> (<italic>Rr</italic>) and <italic>T. kodakorensis</italic> (<italic>Tk</italic>) Rubisco large subunit sequences adjoining the E138 and K332 mutation sites in MbR. Only amino acids differing from MbR are shown. Secondary structure information is relative to that in <italic>Tk</italic> L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref>. (<bold>b</bold>) Location of the mutated residues in <italic>R. rubrum</italic> L<sub>2</sub> Rubisco (A134 and E321: PDB 9RUB) and <italic>Tk</italic> L<sub>10</sub> Rubisco (R134 and E324: PDB 3A12) are highlighted in cyan. <italic>Rr</italic> L-subunits are shaded red and green, active site bound RuBP or CABP in yellow. In the <italic>Tk</italic> structure R134 is located at the L<sub>2</sub>-L<sub>2</sub> interface (differentially coloured red and blue). E321 and E324 are located within the flexible loop 6 region in both <italic>Rr</italic> and <italic>Tk</italic> Rubisco respectively. Diagrams constructed using PyMOL.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep22284-f6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Rubisco catalysis measurements.</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>L<sub>10</sub> MbR catalytic properties at pH 8.0, 25&#8201;&#176;C relative to <italic>R. rubrum</italic> L<sub>2</sub> and tobacco L<sub>8</sub>S<sub>8</sub> Rubisco. <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>O</italic></sup>, maximal oxygenation rate calculated from S<sub><italic>C/O</italic></sub>&#8201;=&#8201;(<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>C</italic></sup><italic>/K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub>)/(<italic>k</italic><sub><italic>cat</italic></sub><sup><italic>O</italic></sup><italic>/K</italic><sub><italic>O</italic></sub>). <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub><sup><italic>21%O2</italic></sup>, <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub> under ambient atmospheric O<sub>2</sub> levels (<italic>O</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;252 &#956;M O<sub>2</sub> in air saturated H<sub>2</sub>O) calculated as <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>C</italic></sub>(1&#8201;+&#8201;<italic>O</italic>/<italic>K</italic><sub><italic>O</italic></sub>). Values in parenthesis are those measured previously by [1]<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref> and [2]<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. Significance variation relative to wild type MbR at pH 8.0 (*p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001) determined by T-test.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>