
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4333152</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1245</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-015-1245-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide comparative analysis reveals human-mouse regulatory landscape and evolution </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Denas</surname><given-names>Olgert</given-names></name><address><email>denas@adobe.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sandstrom</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><address><email>sull@uw.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Yong</given-names></name><address><email>yongc@stanford.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>Kathryn</given-names></name><address><email>kathryn.beal@eaglegenomics.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name><address><email>javier.herrero@ucl.ac.uk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hardison</surname><given-names>Ross C</given-names></name><address><email>rch8@psu.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>James</given-names></name><address><email>james@taylorlab.org</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Mathematics and Computer Science, Emory University, Atlanta, GA 30322 USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Biology, Johns Hopkins University, 3400 N Charles St, Mudd Hall 144, Baltimore, MD 21218 USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Genetics, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94305 USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Genome Sciences, University of Washington, Seattle, WA 98195 USA </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>The Genome Analysis Centre, Norwich Research Park, Norwich, UK </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Penn State University, University Park, Norwich, PA 16802 USA </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label/>European Bioinformatics Institute (EMBL-EBI), Norwich, UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>87</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Denas et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Because species-specific gene expression is driven by species-specific regulation, understanding the relationship between sequence and function of the regulatory regions in different species will help elucidate how differences among species arise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Despite active experimental and computational research, relationships among sequence, conservation, and function are still poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We compared transcription factor occupied segments (TFos) for 116 human and 35 mouse TFs in 546 human and 125 mouse cell types and tissues from the Human and the Mouse ENCODE projects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>We based the map between human and mouse TFos on a one-to-one nucleotide cross-species mapper, bnMapper, that utilizes whole genome alignments (WGA). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Our analysis shows that TFos are under evolutionary constraint, but a substantial portion (25.1% of mouse and 25.85% of human on average) of the TFos does not have a homologous sequence on the other species; this portion varies among cell types and TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, 47.67% and 57.01% of the homologous TFos sequence shows binding activity on the other species for human and mouse respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>However, 79.87% and 69.22% is repurposed such that it binds the same TF in different cells or different TFs in the same cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, within the set of repurposed TFos, the corresponding genome regions in the other species are preferred locations of novel TFos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>These events suggest exaptation of some functional regulatory sequences into new function. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Despite TFos repurposing, we did not find substantial changes in their predicted target genes, suggesting that CRMs buffer evolutionary events allowing little or no change in the TFos – target gene associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Thus, the small portion of TFos with strictly conserved occupancy underestimates the degree of conservation of regulatory interactions. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>We mapped regulatory sequences from an extensive number of TFs and cell types between human and mouse using WGA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A comparative analysis of this correspondence unveiled the extent of the shared regulatory sequence across TFs and cell types under study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Importantly, a large part of the shared regulatory sequence is repurposed on the other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>This sequence, fueled by turnover events, provides a strong case for exaptation in regulatory elements. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-015-1245-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Mouse ENCODE</kwd><kwd>Regulatory sequences</kwd><kwd>Comparative genomics</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Most eukaryotic gene regulation occurs at the level of transcription [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This form of regulation involves the interaction of transcription factors (TFs) with element and function specific DNA sequences, referred to as cis-regulatory modules (CRMs; reviewed by [3]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Their modular organization allows for elaborate regulatory mechanisms and fine control of gene expression [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Evolutionary changes in CRMs have a profound effect on species divergence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Many studies suggest that species specific CRMs are the defining factor for species identity [5-7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Differences in human and chimpanzee, for example, are almost completely due to changes in functional noncoding sequence [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Efforts to locate the “human gene” have only revealed differences in a small number of genes [9-11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Moreover, comparisons of organisms at the extremes of eukaryotes show that the genes encoding TFs and signaling components (e.g. for temporal/spatial gene expression patterns) are largely conserved [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Taken together, this evidence suggests a hierarchical organization of regulatory networks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Modules at the top, performing essential upstream functions, span large evolutionary distances virtually unchanged, while lower level modules, involved in peripheral sub-networks, show a higher level of adaptation [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Under this model, part of the regulatory material must be under purifying selection and thus conserved between any two species of sufficiently small evolutionary divergence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Evidence of conservation of regulatory sequence among species has inspired a series of computational methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Some of these methods use machine learning and phylogenetic profiling to discover CRMs (reviewed by [13]), others use comparative analysis to identify genomic material under purifying evolutionary constraint as a representative of the functional genome (reviewed by [14]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>At the same time, a number of experimental studies suggest that while sequence might encode enough information to drive TF binding [15], the way this information is encoded is not trivial – similar sequence does not necessarily translate in similar function and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>For example, regulatory elements have been found to tolerate sequence rearrangements [16] or even be under positive selection while maintaining the downstream regulatory machinery unchanged [17,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Recently, it was found that GATA1 changes its motif preferences during cell differentiation [19], serving as an example of TFs having multiple preferred motif sequences [20] while maintaining a regulatory function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Both computational and experimental approaches have provided valuable insight into the regulatory portion of the genome, but they have limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Computational methods are biased toward well-annotated and evolutionarily conserved genomic regions, indeed comparative analyses based on evolutionary conservation alone ignore species-specific functional elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Experimental approaches based on direct genome wide measurements of TFos are a powerful resource for the identification and analysis of TF binding sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>However, the number of cell types and TFs assessed so far has often been limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>With some studies pointing at conservation, others at divergence, and others yet at turnover of motifs and the importance of occupancy, the level of constraint on the CRMs is still an open question. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This apparently contradicting evidence can be reconciled by considering conservation as specific to the TF or the cell type. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>In this study, we combined several types of function-associated datasets from a large number of TFs from a wide variety of tissues and cell lines in both mouse and human. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Our main data source is ChIP-Seq experiments performed by the mouse and human ENCODE projects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>These data give evidence on the locations where TF have come close enough to the DNA to cross-link in cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The question remains whether these locations, termed TFos [13], could represent direct binding to a specific motif in the DNA or co-association with another TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>However, there is evidence that the TFos are active in assays for regulatory function at a far higher rate than non-occupied DNA segments, or DNA segments predicted as regulatory based on sequence motifs or conservation making them likely to have regulatory function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We also used DNase I Hypersensitive Sites (DHS) generated by the Human [21] and the Mouse ENCODE [22] projects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>DHS regions are markers of regulatory DNA and have underpinned the discovery of all classes of cis-regulatory elements including enhancers, promoters, insulators, silencers and locus control regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>We conduced a comparative analysis, by integrating TFos with human-mouse WGA, gene annotations, and TF-gene associations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>We have also compiled the data and annotations derived from this study into a database to serve as a resource in exploring the relationship between sequence evolution and function of regulatory elements (Additional file 1: Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>An alignment based map for human-mouse TFos </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Differences between present day genomes are the result of a series of evolutionary events originating on their most recent common ancestor [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Many of these events can be explained under probability models and represented in the form of WGA (See [24] for a review). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Sequence that has undergone a moderate number of evolutionary events will appear aligned, while highly divergent regions will usually be left un-aligned. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>We used WGA to obtain a consistent map for TFos across human and mouse (Figure 1(A)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>These alignments provide long, inferred homologous regions in the form of chains of gapless blocks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>They can account for inversions, translocations, duplications, large-scale deletions, and overlapping independent deletions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We considered chained blastz [25] alignments available from the UCSC browser [26] and the 12-way mammalian WGA from the EPO pipeline [27] available from Ensembl version 65 [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>To choose the most appropriate alignment for our mappings we used several criteria: symmetry, coverage, feature enrichment, and other method specific properties.Figure 1We built a one to one map between the human and mouse genomes from their WGA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>(A) The track diagram shows TFos (unfilled features on outer tracks) and how they map to the other species (middle track). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The thick part of the middle track is the mappable DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The features on the middle track can be mapped on the other species and are: SeqCons if not overlapping features from the other species (respective color), or FuncCons or FunctActive otherwise (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The Venn diagrams use the same color code to show the amount (rounded to the closest Mb) of mappable material from one species to the other for DNA sequence, TFos, and DHS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>For example, human TFos cover 121 Mb of the human genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>When mapped to mouse, these TFos cover 83 Mb of the mouse genome and 12 Mb of the sequence covered also by mouse TFos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The diagram for DHS is labeled in a similar fashion. (B) The distribution of mappable TFos nucleotides across cell types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The box-plot for each cell type summarizes the distribution of values for the fraction of nucleotides covered by TFos that can be mapped on the other species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Symmetry is important for unambiguously mapping features from one genome to the other and back. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The EPO based map is inherently symmetric; we only need to extract human-mouse alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>We remove segmental duplications based on criteria such as the score or the length of the alignment to obtain an unambiguous map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>UCSC alignments, on the other hand, are based on blastz pairwise alignments, which are not symmetric – a human-mouse alignment is different from a mouse-human alignment in general. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>However, it is possible to circumvent the problem by using a netting procedure and chaining again only the first layer in the resulting net. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>This corresponds to heuristically cleaning overlapping chains based on their score. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The resulting reciprocal map is identical to the one derived from the mouse-human alignments at the cost of losing around 10% sequence coverage on both species [29]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>UCSC alignments align a slightly larger fraction of the mouse genome (31% vs. 28% for UCSC and EPO respectively) to human. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>However, EPO alignments can assign a substantially higher amount of inserted mouse sequence (28% vs. 1.9%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In total 65.7% of the mouse genome remains unmapped by UCSC alignments and 42.5% by EPO alignments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Next, we computed the number of features that each alignment could map on the other species for all available cell types in human and mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>We found that UCSC alignments mapped more features on the other species (Additional file 1: Figure S2 and Tables S4-S6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Based on the above considerations, we adopted the reciprocal UCSC alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The alignments and the comparative pipeline described here were adopted by the Mouse Encode Consortium for the cross-species mapping of TFos. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Function and sequence conservation of TFos </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>We processed TFos generated by ChIP-Seq for 206 human and 55 mouse cell lines and tissues [22], with a variable number of factors for each cell or tissue (from 1 to 109 for human and from 1 to 38 for mouse). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The data were generated by the Human and the Mouse ENCODE projects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The ChIP-Seq experiments on mouse were conducted following the human ENCODE guidelines [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Data processing, including Irreproducible Discovery Rate (IDR) analysis, was done using a uniform data processing pipeline for both datasets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Elements recovered by the ChIP-Seq experiments and the subsequent peak-calling pipeline were subjected to thresholds for False Discovery Rate at 1% and IDR at 2%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>We then filtered these sets to retain only those TFos showing DHS enrichment, thereby increasing our confidence in the functional role of the filtered elements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Roughly 41.63% of ChIP-Seq peaks were filtered out from each species by DHS filtering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The resulting data contained 5330864 and 727680 elements covering 121.08 Mb and 31.6 Mb of the genome for human and mouse respectively (Additional file 1: Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The higher human coverage is due to the larger number of assays available in human. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>We asked whether the selected putative regulatory material is significantly conserved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>At the sequence level, we find that the fraction of TFos intersecting homologous regions is higher than one would expect by chance (Binomial test 0.99% CI: (0.7218, 0.7228) and 0.99% CI: (0.6908, 0.6936) with expected values of 0.3129 and 0.3648 for human and mouse respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>At the TF-binding activity level (i.e., having TF occupancy by any TF), mapped human and mouse TFos overlapped TFos on the other species more often than expected by chance (Binomial test 0.99% CI: (0.5358, 0.5371) and 0.99% CI: (0.7883, 0.7913) with expected values 0.0231 and 0.0857 for human and mouse respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Significant conservation at the TF-binding activity level continues to hold largely for individual TFs-cell pairs (Additional file 1: Figures S3-S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>These results indicate that most of these human and mouse regulatory regions have been under selective pressure both at the sequence and functional level. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Despite the selective pressure on the TFos, the data suggest extensive evolution of the regulatory material between human and mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>On average 74.2% and 74.9% of TFos can be mapped on the other species resulting in a 36.1% and 31.4% of regulatory sequence coverage that is lineage-specific for human and mouse respectively (Figure 1(B) and Additional file 1: S5-S12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Importantly, we found that the extent to which the remaining regulatory material is conserved varies substantially between species and among cell types and TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The variability fits with previous studies on smaller numbers of TFs and cell types, which have emphasized both, conservation of TFos [31] and extensive regulatory sequence evolution [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Binding signal differences between functionally and sequence conserved TFos </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>We focus our TFos comparative analysis on two Tier 1 ENCODE cell lines and their mouse analogs as chosen by the Mouse ENCODE consortium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The data consist of 17 TFs from human chronic myelogenous leukemia cell line (K562, [33]) and mouse erythroleukemia cell line (MEL, [34]); and 15 TFs from lymphoblast cell lines (GM12878 vs. CH12) (Additional file 1: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In total we have thus selected 442527 and 215251 TFos covering 33.61 Mb and 18.77 Mb on human and mouse respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>We mapped TFos of a species to homologous locations in the other and asked what function do those sites show. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The homologous site of a TFos can be: (i) not occupied by TFs, in which case we call the TFos SeqCons; (ii) repurposed, thus active in another cell or bound by another factor in the same cell type, in which case we call the TFos FunctActive; or (iii) bound by the same factor on the same cell type, in which case the TFos is called FunctCons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>SeqCons and FunctActive elements represent differences in human and mouse TF binding patterns due to TFos loss, gain, or both. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Turnover occurs in the case of loss and gain of the same TFos at different, but nearby, positions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>However, more complex differences can arise when the loss of one TFos is followed by compensatory gains of TFos of other TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>For the pairs of analogous cell types in human and mouse, the largest proportion of TFos (considered together) are FunctActive, while the relative proportions of FunctCons and SeqCons vary between cell types and species (Figure 2(A)).Figure 2 Conservation and re-use of TFos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>(A) The distribution of SeqCons, FunctActive, and FunctCons regulatory elements summarized for all human mouse analogous cell lines (Additional file 1: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>In both cell lines, a small fraction of mappable regulatory elements is FunctCons (33% and 15% cell average for human and mouse respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>A larger fraction (46% and 50% cell average for human and mouse respectively) is FunctActive (plots for each cell are in Additional file 1: Figures S15, S16). (B) Loss and gain of TF binding sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>We used TFos in our data to discover TF binding sites (TFBS) on both species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We mapped human (respectively mouse) TFBS to mouse (respectively human) and computed their distance to the closest mouse (respectively human) TFBS of the same TF on an analogous cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Among these TFBS those with a positive distance but less than 150 bp contribute to the corresponding bar in the human (respectively mouse) subplot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In other words, each bar is the count of TFBS that were lost and gained within a 150 bp window of the original site. (C) Reuse of FunctActive TFos between different cells and factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>A point on the scatterplot indicates the number of TFos of the corresponding assay in the reference species that can be classified as FunctCons or FunctActive when considering a fixed size set of randomly chosen assays in the comparison species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>We performed multiple computations for each chosen size of such sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Lines indicate the accumulated number of FunctCons, FunctActive, and Seqcons TFos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In this figure, about 93% of the (Mel, Max) assay is covered by TFos from just 35% of the query assays (plots for other cells/TFs in Additional file 1: Figures S17, S18). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Conservation of occupancy in the other species was associated with peak signal strength for several cell type-TF pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>For example, binding signal on FunctCons or FunctActive elements was higher than that on SeqCons elements for 59% and 50% of cell type-TF combinations for human and mouse respectively (with a Bonferroni-corrected error rate of 1%; Additional file 1: Figures S13, S14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Overall, FunctCons peak signal is on average 1.3 and 1.9 times larger than SeqCons peak signal on human and mouse respectively (Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>TF binding site turnover and TFos repurposing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>If SeqCons and FunctActive elements are the result of turnover of TF binding sites (TFBS) in human and mouse, then we should observe TFBS close to regions orthologous to TFBS on the other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>We discovered TFBS using motif discovery and motif matching on TFos for both species and analyzed their alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>We found that for several TFs, SeqCons TFBS map within 150 bp of a TFBS on the other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>On average, 51% and 48% of SeqCons TFBS have been subject to turnover in a 150 bp neighborhood for human and mouse respectively (Figure 2(B)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The large number of FunctActive elements (Figures 2(A) and Additional file 1: S15, S16) suggests recycling of TFos among cells and TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>We examined this more carefully with a novel approach, based on the intuition that extensive recycling would allow any set of TFos in a comparison species to identify the occurrence of specific TFos in the reference species (after cross-species mapping). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>To conduct this analysis, we sampled (multiple times) mapped TFos from k assays from the comparison species, took the union of these TFos, and computed the number of TFos a given assay (in the reference species) shares with this union. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The results strongly support extensive recycling of TFos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Specifically, we find that about 93% of the (Mel, Max) assay is covered by TFos from just 35% of the query assays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>As k increases, coverage saturates (Figures 2(C) and Additional file 1: S17, S18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>This ability of different assays in the comparison species to capture TFos in the reference species is substantially different than what is obtained by simulating non-associated assays (Additional file 1: Figure S19). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We tested the hypothesis that new TFos tend to arise over existing TFos – active in other cells or occupied by other factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Under the null hypothesis, the fraction of FunctActive elements with respect to the non-FunctCons elements should not be significantly higher than the fraction of the genome that can turn into a FunctActive TFos, should a new TFos occur (See Methods for details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>We found that fraction to be higher than expected (One sided Binomial test 99% CI: (0.377, 1.000) and (0.477, 1.000) with expected values 0.010 and 0.028 for human and mouse respectively), suggesting that existing CRMs are sites where new TFBS are likely to arise. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Turnover events or the appearance of novel TFBS lead to compositional changes in CRMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>However, these changes do not always reflect downstream in, for example, the set of target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Following [35] we extracted a set of TSS-enhancer connections based on synchronized DHS activity during the transcription of a gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Restricting on 15,736 human-mouse orthologous genes [22], we were thus able to define putative target genes for 1928211 and 204758 TFos for human and mouse respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>We observe that, similarly to FunctCons TFos, about 39% and 43% of FunctActive TFos retained at least one putative target gene for human and mouse respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the amount at which the set of target genes is conserved across species is not significantly different between the two classes of TFos (Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>p-values: &lt; 2.2e-16 and &lt; 2.2e-16 for human and mouse respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The example of the candidate enhancer linked to the ACAP3 gene in human illustrates this situation (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The DNA segment in mouse that is orthologous to the human enhancer has been repurposed such that it binds different TFs, but the mouse Acap3 gene is still the presumptive target.Figure 3 Conservation of presumptive gene targets for a repurposed TFos. We combined cross-species gene-gene and TFos-TFos associations and gene-TFos associations to determine whether the sets of target genes of FunctCons and FunctActive TFos differ significantly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Gene-gene association data are based on a set of orthologous genes between human and mouse produced by the mouse ENCODE consortium, gene-TFos data are based on synchronized DHS activity during gene transcription [35], and TFos-TFos associations are based on our cross-species map. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>In the figure, we show a human TFos of Mxi on K562 (empty oval) associated with PUSL1 and ACAP3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>This TFos is FunctActive, since its analogous location (broken oval linked by the dashed line with spaces between ovals indicating insertions in mouse) in mouse is bound by other TFs on other cell types (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>However, its analogous site in mouse is linked to gene Acap3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Incidentally, ACAP3 and Acap3 are orthologous and in our gene-gene association set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>The human TFos and its analogous site in mouse bind different TFs and are active in different cell types, but they share a target gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>We reported on the construction and use of a map of functional elements between human and mouse based on WGA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>This map is consistent and symmetrical in that it provides a one to one correspondence between genome elements in both directions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, it constitutes an improvement over aligning TFos directly on the other species guided by gene orthology; this approach is likely to deteriorate with the distance of an element from the nearest gene with an ortholog on the other species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Using this mapping approach, we were able to recover, on average, 75% and 73% of TFos in the other species, of which 63% and 78% are bound by any TFs and 13% and 25% by the same TF for human and mouse respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The rest of the regulatory material is species-specific either at the sequence or functional level and is likely to account for the phenotypic differences between human and mouse [8,12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>However, some of the species-specific material retains target genes suggesting that CRMs buffer changes toward downstream regulation [36]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>One potential difficulty, which affects this analysis, is the variation that can be introduced by technical factors such as signal thresholding or by differences in the environment of the cells being compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>By using data processed for reproducibility under the stringent standards developed by the Human and Mouse ENCODE projects, restricting to regions overlapping DHS for greater confidence, considering the TF activity on analogous cell types, and employing statistical controls we hope to have ameliorated these issues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have mapped the binding patterns of TFs between species, including mouse and human, by focusing on a single cell type and a few TFs (e.g., [32]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>While these important studies have revealed substantial divergence in the binding patterns of TFs between species, they do not explore FunctActive elements or related dynamics such as repurposing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>One important conclusion in our study is that the evolution of regulatory sequences varies considerably among TFs and cell types, and furthermore we document which TFos fall into the various evolutionary categories. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The traffic between noncoding functional and nonfunctional DNA in a genome is two-way. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>On the one hand, loss of a TFos can increase fitness, as dramatically illustrated by changes in the regulation of pitx1 in three-spined stickleback that lead to advantageous anatomical changes in a new environment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, new functional noncoding sequence can arise from nonfunctional sequence through turnover [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The differences between the sizes of FunctActive and FunctCons pools suggests another source of functional noncoding material traffic, characterized by the exaptation of TFos into functional noncoding material with novel TF or cell type activity [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>With a partial catalog of regulatory elements it is hard to distinguish the newly created functional material from the exapted one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>However with ever-increasing numbers of experimental assays the picture should become more clear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Despite previous elegant studies, the level of constraint on CRMs remains controversial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>We provide further evidence that TFos are more conserved than random sequence and that conservation is cell and TF specific. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we study the type of conservation of TFos and observe that 47.67% and 57.01% of TFos conserved at the sequence level for human and mouse respectively have been repurposed and are active in cell types or bind different TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>We show how this sequence makes a case for TFos exaptation into new function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Finally, we find that repurposing does not necessarily lead to changes in the TFos – target gene association. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Comparative studies of CRMs involve a mapping strategy of regulatory elements, often by aligning elements or reads on both genomes, possibly guiding mapping with gene homologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>We implemented a multiple WGA based process for TFos mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Using multiple WGA we should have a more sensitive and consistent mapping process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the mapper can provide one-to-one mappings between species, which is very useful during analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Data processing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>ChIP-Seq data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>We download all of the ChIP-Seq data generated by the Human and the Mouse ENCODE from the ENCODE DCC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The pipeline that filters the original ENCODE peaks is available in the supplementary material. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Distal DHS-to-promoter connections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>As described in [35] many cell-selective enhancers become DHSs synchronously with the appearance of hypersensitivity at the promoter of their target gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>This has been used to infer a genome-wide DHS/enhancer-promoter connection set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Using a conservative list of orthologous genes [22] we inferred a list of correspondences between TFos regulating human-mouse orthologous genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>EPO and UCSC based maps </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>We considered the EPO 12-way mammalian whole genome alignments from Ensembl project version 65 [28] and the UCSC human mouse chain and net alignments from the UCSC [26] genome browser to generate the reciprocal maps. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Details and programs for processing of the alignments are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/bxlab/mapper_comparisons">https://bitbucket.org/bxlab/mapper_comparisons</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Mapping strategy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>We built and used a one-to-one nucleotide mapper (bnMapper) to map elements between human and mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The mapping is bijective, so reverse application of the mapping to a mapped nucleotide, returns the original nucleotide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Elements that span matching blocks of different chains and elements that map to multiple chromosomes are filtered out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The mapper and a detailed analysis of performance between EPO and UCSC alignments are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/bxlab/mapper_comparisons">https://bitbucket.org/bxlab/mapper_comparisons</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Details on the mapping strategy are on Section 1.1 of the Additional file 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Significance tests </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>For a given genomic region of coverage C, the number of n randomly positioned features over the genome (length L) would follow a Binomial (n, C/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>For significance of TF conservation at the sequence level we set L, C, and n, to be the length of the genome, total TF coverage, and total number of peaks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>A success event is an overlap of 1 bp with the one to one mappable sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Similarly, for functional conservation, L, C, and n, are set to total one to one mappable sequence, coverage of mapped peaks, and number of mapped peaks overlapping with peaks on the target genome, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>For the paired Wilcoxon tests we consider all TFs within a cell line that appear on both species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Ranks are computed from FunctCons to SeqCons ratios of corresponding TFs on each species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>To test that a new TFos is more likely to occur in an existing TFos, possibly occupied by another TFs or active in another cell, consider the following quantities with respect to a fixed genome:The number of non-FunctCons TFos in this genome not less than the number of new TFos in this genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The inequality accounts for TFos deletions on the other genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>We write nFCo &gt; = nFCt.Coverage of SeqCons of the other genome after being mapped in this genome and FA elements in this genome not less than regions in this genome that would become FA should a new TFos occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The inequality accounts for those regions that would become FunctCons should a new TFos appear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We write Mo &gt; = Mt.Length of this genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>We write L.The number of FunctActive Tfos in this genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>We write FA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Here we are making the assumption that FunctCons elements have existed before human-mouse split and FunctActive are a result of a deletion or creation (or both) after the human-mouse split. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Thus, the fraction FA/nFCt is that of new elements that occurred in existing TFos involving other TFs or cell types, whether the fraction Mt/L indicates the chance of a new TFos to become FunctActive should it occur randomly in the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Under the alternative hypothesis, FA/nFCt &gt; Mt/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>However, because Mt/L &lt; = Mo/L and FA/nFCo &lt; = FA/nFCt, it suffices to show that FA/nFCo &gt; = Mo/L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Notice that we observe all the quantities in the last expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Data access </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>UCSC alignments can be downloaded from the UCSC website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/goldenPath/hg19/vsMm9/">http://hgdownload.soe.ucsc.edu/goldenPath/hg19/vsMm9/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>UCSC bijective (netted) alignments, the list of one-to-one orthologous genes, the list of DHS-gene associations, and the list of Mouse ChIP-Seq TFos and DHSs can be downloaded from the Mouse ENCODE web portal <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mouse.encodedcc.org/data">http://mouse.encodedcc.org/data</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mouseencode.org/">http://www.mouseencode.org/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>The mapping software can be freely downloaded as part of the bx-python software library from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://bitbucket.org/james_taylor/bx-python/wiki/Home">https://bitbucket.org/james_taylor/bx-python/wiki/Home</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Ensembl EPO 12-way alignments version 65 can be downloaded from the Ensembl (December 2011) at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.ensembl.org/pub/release-65/emf/ensembl-compara/epo_12_eutherian/">ftp://ftp.ensembl.org/pub/release-65/emf/ensembl-compara/epo_12_eutherian/</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/~kbeal/species_mapper/epo_547_hs_mm_12way_mammals_65.out.gz">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/~kbeal/species_mapper/epo_547_hs_mm_12way_mammals_65.out.gz</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>The human ChIP-Seq TFos and DHSs can be downloaded from the Human ENCODE website at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/ENCODE/">http://genome.ucsc.edu/ENCODE/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec17"><title>Additional file</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12864_2015_1245_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Supplemental Figures and Tables. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>OD wrote the main text, performed the comparative and statistical analysis, and wrote the mapper tool. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>RS helped designing the mapper, carried out statistical analysis for choosing the best whole genome alignments, prepared the DHS data, and the gene – TFos link data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>YC helped on the design of the mapper and performed analyses on the whole genome alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>KB worked on the design of the mapper and the preparation of the whole genome alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>JH worked on the design of the mapper and the preparation of the whole genome alignments, helped design the study and write the main text. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>RC wrote the main text and designed the study – JT wrote the main text, carried out statistical analyses, and designed the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Thanks to members of the Taylor and Hardison labs and the Mouse ENCODE consortium for their input and discussion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>This project was supported by grants from the National Institutes of Health to RCH and JT, specifically American Recovery and Reinvestment Act (ARRA) funds through grant number RC2 HG005573 from the National Human Genome Research Institute, and grants with numbers R01 DK065806 and R56 DK065806 from the National Institute for Diabetes, Digestive, and Kidney Diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>This work was also supported by the Wellcome Trust (grant number 095908) and the European Molecular Biology Laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The funding body had no role in the design of the experiment, in the collection, analysis, and interpretation of data, in the writing of the manuscript, or in the decision to submit the manuscript for publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>1.DermanEKrauterKWallingLWeinbergerCRayMDarnellJEJrTranscriptional control in the production of liver-specific mRNAsCell1981233731910.1016/0092-8674(81)90436-0<?supplied-pmid 7226226?>7226226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>2.RoopDRNordstromJLTsaiSYTsaiMJO’MalleyBWTranscription of structural and intervening sequences in the ovalbumin gene and identification of potential ovalbumin mRNA precursorsCell19781526718510.1016/0092-8674(78)90035-1<?supplied-pmid 719758?>719758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>3.MastonGAEvansSKGreenMRTranscriptional regulatory elements in the human genomeAnnu Rev Genomics Hum Genet20067295910.1146/annurev.genom.7.080505.115623<?supplied-pmid 16719718?>16719718 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>4.DavidsonEHThe regulatory genome: gene regulatory networks in development and evolution2006Burlington (MA)Academic Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>5.MeaderSPontingCPLunterGMassive turnover of functional sequence in human and other mammalian genomesGenome Res2010201013354310.1101/gr.108795.110<?supplied-pmid 20693480?>20693480 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>6.TaftRJPheasantMMattickJSThe relationship between non-protein-coding DNA and eukaryotic complexityBioessays20072932889910.1002/bies.20544<?supplied-pmid 17295292?>17295292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>7.BrittenRJDavidsonEHGene regulation for higher cells: a theoryScience196916538913495710.1126/science.165.3891.349<?supplied-pmid 5789433?>5789433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>8.KingMCWilsonACEvolution at two levels in humans and chimpanzeesScience197518841841071610.1126/science.1090005<?supplied-pmid 1090005?>1090005 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>9.HughesALYeagerMNatural selection at major histocompatibility complex loci of vertebratesAnnu Rev Genet1998324153510.1146/annurev.genet.32.1.415<?supplied-pmid 9928486?>9928486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>10.SwansonWJYangZWolfnerMFAquadroCFPositive Darwinian selection drives the evolution of several female reproductive proteins in mammalsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200198525091410.1073/pnas.051605998<?supplied-pmid 11226269?>11226269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>11.EnardWPrzeworskiMFisherSELaiCSWiebeVKitanoTMolecular evolution of FOXP2, a gene involved in speech and languageNature200241869008697210.1038/nature01025<?supplied-pmid 12192408?>12192408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>12.DavidsonEHErwinDHGene regulatory networks and the evolution of animal body plansScience2006311576279680010.1126/science.1113832<?supplied-pmid 16469913?>16469913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>13.HardisonRCTaylorJGenomic approaches towards finding cis-regulatory modules in animalsNat Rev Genet20121374698310.1038/nrg3242<?supplied-pmid 22705667?>22705667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>14.PontingCPHardisonRCWhat fraction of the human genome is functional?Genome Res2011211117697610.1101/gr.116814.110<?supplied-pmid 21875934?>21875934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>15.WilsonMDBarbosa-MoraisNLSchmidtDConboyCMVanesLTybulewiczVLSpecies-specific transcription in mice carrying human chromosome 21Science20083225900434810.1126/science.1160930<?supplied-pmid 18787134?>18787134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>16.HareEEPetersonBKIyerVNMeierREisenMBSepsid even-skipped enhancers are functionally conserved in Drosophila despite lack of sequence conservationPLoS Genet200846e100010610.1371/journal.pgen.1000106<?supplied-pmid 18584029?>18584029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>17.PheasantMMattickJSRaising the estimate of functional human sequencesGenome Res200717912455310.1101/gr.6406307<?supplied-pmid 17690206?>17690206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>18.BustamanteCDFledel-AlonAWilliamsonSNielsenRHubiszMTGlanowskiSNatural selection on protein-coding genes in the human genomeNature200543770621153710.1038/nature04240<?supplied-pmid 16237444?>16237444 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>19.MayGSonejiSTippingAJTelesJMcGowanSJWuMDynamic analysis of gene expression and genome-wide transcription factor binding during lineage specification of multipotent progenitorsCell Stem Cell20131367546810.1016/j.stem.2013.09.003<?supplied-pmid 24120743?>24120743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>20.JohnsonDSMortazaviAMyersRMWoldBGenome-wide mapping of in vivo protein-DNA interactionsScience20073165830149750210.1126/science.1141319<?supplied-pmid 17540862?>17540862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>21.The ENCODE Project ConsortiumBernsteinBEBirneyEDunhamIGreenEDGunterCAn integrated encyclopedia of DNA elements in the human genomeNature2012489(7414577422955616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>22.The Mouse ENCODE Consortium,YueFChengYBreschiAVierstraJWuWA comparative encyclopedia of DNA elements in the mouse genomeNature201451575273556410.1038/nature1399225409824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>23.KimuraMEvolutionary rate at the molecular levelNature19682175129624610.1038/217624a0<?supplied-pmid 5637732?>5637732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>24.Ureta-VidalAEttwillerLBirneyEComparative genomics: genome-wide analysis in metazoan eukaryotesNat Rev Genet2003442516210.1038/nrg1043<?supplied-pmid 12671656?>12671656 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>25.SchwartzSKentWJSmitAZhangZBaertschRHardisonRCHuman-mouse alignments with BLASTZGenome Res2003131103710.1101/gr.809403<?supplied-pmid 12529312?>12529312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>26.DreszerTRKarolchikDZweigASHinrichsASRaneyBJKuhnRMThe UCSC genome browser database: extensions and updates 2011Nucleic Acids Res201240Database issueD9182310.1093/nar/gkr1055<?supplied-pmid 22086951?>22086951 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>27.PatenBHerreroJBealKFitzgeraldSBirneyEEnredo and Pecan: genome-wide mammalian consistency-based multiple alignment with paralogsGenome Res2008181118142810.1101/gr.076554.108<?supplied-pmid 18849524?>18849524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>28.FlicekPAhmedIAmodeMRBarrellDBealKBrentSEnsembl 2013Nucleic Acids Res201341Database issueD485510.1093/nar/gks1236<?supplied-pmid 23203987?>23203987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>29.KentWJBaertschRHinrichsAMillerWHausslerDEvolution’s cauldron: duplication, deletion, and rearrangement in the mouse and human genomesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20031002011484910.1073/pnas.1932072100<?supplied-pmid 14500911?>14500911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>30.LandtSGMarinovGKKundajeAKheradpourPPauliFBatzoglouSChIP-seq guidelines and practices of the ENCODE and modENCODE consortiaGenome Res201222918133110.1101/gr.136184.111<?supplied-pmid 22955991?>22955991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>31.KimTHAbdullaevZKSmithADChingKALoukinovDIGreenRDAnalysis of the vertebrate insulator protein CTCF-binding sites in the human genomeCell2007128612314510.1016/j.cell.2006.12.048<?supplied-pmid 17382889?>17382889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>32.OdomDTDowellRDJacobsenESGordonWDanfordTWMacIsaacKDTissue-specific transcriptional regulation has diverged significantly between human and mouseNat Genet2007396730210.1038/ng2047<?supplied-pmid 17529977?>17529977 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>33.LozzioCBLozzioBBHuman chronic myelogenous leukemia cell-line with positive Philadelphia chromosomeBlood197545332134<?supplied-pmid 163658?>163658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>34.The Mouse ENCODE ConsortiumStamatoyannopoulosJASnyderMHardisonRRenBGingerasTAn encyclopedia of mouse DNA elements (Mouse ENCODE)Genome Biol201213841810.1186/gb-2012-13-8-41822889292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>35.ThurmanRERynesEHumbertRVierstraJMauranoMTHaugenEThe accessible chromatin landscape of the human genomeNature20124897414758210.1038/nature11232<?supplied-pmid 22955617?>22955617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>36.WeirauchMTHughesTRConserved expression without conserved regulatory sequence: the more things change, the more they stay the sameTrends Genet2010262667410.1016/j.tig.2009.12.002<?supplied-pmid 20083321?>20083321 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>37.WilsonMDOdomDTEvolution of transcriptional control in mammalsCurr Opin Genet Dev20091965798510.1016/j.gde.2009.10.003<?supplied-pmid 19913406?>19913406 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>38.GouldSJVrbaESExaptation - a missing term in the science of formPaleobiology198281415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
