
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Microbes Environ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Microbes Environ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Microbes and Environments</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1342-6311</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1347-4405</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Japanese Society of Microbial Ecology/The Japanese Society of Soil Microbiology</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4103557</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23047145</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1264/jsme2.ME11316</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">27_477</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Stimulatory Effects of Arsenic-Tolerant Soil Fungi on Plant Growth Promotion and Soil Properties </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>Pankaj Kumar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-27_477">1</xref><xref rid="c1-27_477" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>Belle Damodara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-27_477">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>Manjul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-27_477">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vaish</surname><given-names>Aradhana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-27_477">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mannan</surname><given-names>Shivee</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-27_477">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Nandita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-27_477">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tewari</surname><given-names>Shri Krishna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-27_477">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>Rudra Deo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-27_477">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-27_477"><label>1</label>National Botanical Research Institute (CSIR-NBRI), Rana Pratap Marg, Lucknow, 226001 <country>India</country></aff><aff id="af2-27_477"><label>2</label>Microbial Type Culture Collection and Gene Bank, Institute of Microbial Technology (CSIR-IMTECH), Sector 39A, Chandigarh, 160036 
<country>India</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-27_477"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. E-mail: <email>drpankajk@gmail.com</email>; Tel: +91–522–2297939; Fax: +91–522–2205836.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>27</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>482</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>04</day><month>10</month><year>2011</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2012 by the Japanese Society of Microbial Ecology / the Japanese Society of Soil Microbiology</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Fifteen fungi were obtained from arsenic-contaminated agricultural fields in West Bengal, India and examined for their arsenic tolerance and removal ability in our previous study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Of these, the four best arsenic-remediating isolates were tested for plant growth promotion effects on rice and pea in the present study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>A greenhouse-based pot experiment was conducted using soil inocula of individual fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The results indicated a significant (P&lt;0.05) increase in plant growth and improvement of soil properties in inoculated soils compared to the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>A significant increase in plant growth was recorded in treated soils and varied from 16–293%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Soil chemical and enzymatic properties varied from 20–222% and 34–760%, respectively, in inoculated soil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Plants inoculated with inocula of Westerdykella and Trichoderma showed better stimulatory effects on plant growth and soil nutrient availability than Rhizopus and Lasiodiplodia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>These fungi improved soil nutrient content and enhanced plant growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>These fungi may be used as bioinoculants for plant growth promotion and improved soil properties in arsenic-contaminated agricultural soils. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>pea</kwd><kwd>plant growth-promoting fungi</kwd><kwd>rice</kwd><kwd>soil enzymes</kwd><kwd>arsenic-contaminated soils</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Chemical fertilizers, agrochemicals and pesticides have been intensively applied to soils to increase crop production to meet food demands all over the world; however, these are disruptive to soil biological processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Exploring novel microorganisms is important in agriculture to promote soil nutrient cycling and to reduce dependence on inorganic fertilizers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Plant growth-promoting microbes have the ability to convert nutritionally important elements from their unavailable to available form (28) and so their bioavailability increases uptake and furthers plant growth promotion (13). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Rhizosphere-competent fungi that exert beneficial effects on plant growth and development are referred to as plant growth-promoting fungi (PGPF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In recent years, the use of PGPF to promote plant growth has increased (4, 18); however, the selection of effective PGPF is critical for maximizing the benefits of using this technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Several microbes have been isolated from soil, inoculated into rhizospheric soil and tested for their plant growth-promoting ability (24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Better understanding of the interactions between rhizospheric fungi and plants is necessary for the sustainable management of soil fertility vis-a-vis increasing crop production (12). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Certain fungal species of the genera Fusarium, Penicillium, Phoma, Trichoderma as well as other non-sporulating fungi isolated from the plant rhizosphere have been shown to promote the growth of several plants and suppress diseases (10, 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The mechanisms of plant growth stimulation by associative soil microbes are mainly through the mineralization of nutrients (14), stimulation of root growth by the production of phytohormones (4, 18), etc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Phosphorus uptake by plants can be increased by inoculation with soil mineral-phosphate-solubilizing fungi (23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Inoculation with Penicillium and Trichoderma spp. has increased the growth and yield of wheat and other crop species (36). Fusarium equiseti was tested for the control of crown and root rot of tomato in soil during long-term cultivation (10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Medina et al. (19) revealed that plant growth, nutrient uptake and soil enzymatic activities were increased in soil inoculated with native mycorrhizal fungi and plant growth-promoting yeast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the effect of phosphate-solubilizing fungi (Aspergillus awamori and Penicillium citrinum), isolated from crop rhizosphere, was observed on the growth and seed production of chickpea plants in pot experiments conducted by Mittal et al. (20). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Little is known about the efficiency of metal (loid)-tolerantcum- remediating microbes on plant growth promotion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Recently, some metal (loid)-tolerant microbial strains were isolated from metal (loid)-contaminated soils and evaluated for their role in promoting plant growth (5, 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In Southeast Asia, elevated arsenic levels in soils are of considerable concern due to the possibility of its uptake by plants and subsequent entry into the food chain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The authors of the study isolated natural fungal populations from arsenic-contaminated agricultural soils in the state of West Bengal, India and tested their arsenic removal efficiency (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the plant growth-promoting effects of the four best arsenic-remediating fungal isolates (27) were evaluated on rice and pea plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Changes occurring in rhizospheric soil treated with inocula of these fungi were also studied simultaneously in the same greenhouse-based pot experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In our previous study, fifteen fungal strains were isolated from paddy rhizospheres of arsenic-contaminated (range 9.45–15.63 mg kg−1) agricultural fields in the state of West Bengal, India (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Of these fifteen fungal strains, four isolates, frequently found in soil samples in the fields, were found to be tolerant to high levels of arsenic, such as 10,000 mg L−1, and were best for arsenic removal under laboratory conditions (27). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Identification of the fungal isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The fungal isolates were grown on potato dextrose agar (PDA) medium for 7 days at 27±2°C and their morphological and microscopic features were recorded using a Trinocular Upright Microscope (Olympus, Tokyo, Japan) (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Fungal isolates: FNBR-3, FNBR-6 and FNBR-19, were found to produce conidial structures on PDA medium, while fungal isolate FNBR-13 failed to sporulate on PDA medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This was followed by the isolation of total genomic DNA using the ZR Fungal/Bacterial DNA Kit (Zymo Research, Irvine, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>DNA quality was checked on 1% (w/v) agarose electrophoresis gel stained with ethidium bromide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The ITS4-ITS5 primer-pair (33, 35) was used to amplify the 5.8S rRNA gene and flanking internal transcribed spacers (ITS) 1 and 2 regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Amplification reactions were performed in a 50 μl reaction volume as outlined in Shenoy et al. (25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The PCR thermal cycle was programmed as follows: 95°C for 3 min, followed by 34 cycles of denaturation at 95°C for 1 min, annealing at 52°C for 30 s and elongation at 72°C for 1 min, with a final extension step of 72°C for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The PCR products spanning approximately 600 bp were checked on 1% (w/v) agarose electrophoresis gel stained with ethidium bromide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>PCR products were then checked using a quick spin column and buffers according to the manufacturer’s protocol (QIA quick gel extraction kit, Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>DNA sequencing was performed using the above mentioned primers in an Applied Biosystem 3130xl analyzer at the Central DNA sequencing facility of the Institute of Microbial Technology (Chandigarh, India). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Sequences obtained from the respective primers were aligned using Sequencher version 4.9 (Gene Codes, Ann Arbor, MI, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>A dataset based on the ITS/5.8S rRNA gene-sequence data was prepared for each fungal strain using reference sequences from NCBI-GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were conducted based on the maximum likelihood method using MEGA version 5.02 (29). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Preparation of inoculum </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Individual fungal isolates were pure-cultured on rose bengal chloramphenicol agar media (26) and pure mass-cultured in Mycological Broth (Hi-media, Mumbai, India). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Individual fungal inoculum was prepared from freshly grown 7-d-old respective pure culture plates by suspending the biomass in sterile distilled water and further mixed by vortex shaking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Inoculum density was adjusted to 106 spores mL−1 or mycelial fragments mL−1 using a hemocytometer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>In the study, soil was collected from the field of the National Botanical Research Institute, Lucknow, India (at 80°45′ to 80°53′E longitude and 26°40′ to 26°45′N latitude, at an elevation of 129 m above mean sea level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>This soil was sandy clay loam with pH 7.81 and contained 182 mg g−1 total organic carbon, 360 mg g−1 total nitrogen, 82 mg g−1 total phosphorus and 1.48 cmol kg−1 cation exchange capacity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Greenhouse Experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Two plants, rice (Oryza sativa L. var. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>IR-36) and pea (Pisum sativum L. var. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>PG-3) were used to assess the plant growth-promoting activity of these fungal isolates in a pot experiment under greenhouse conditions; 500 g soil was used per pot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Pots (size: 20 cm diameter and 25 cm height) were arranged in a completely randomized design with six replicates for each treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The seeds were surface sterilized with 1% (w/v) sodium hypochlorite solution followed by thorough washing using sterile distilled water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The roots of rice seedlings and seeds of pea were soaked for 30 min in fungal suspension before sowing in pots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Each pot was planted separately with five one-week-old seedlings in the case of rice and with five seeds in the case of pea and then placed in the greenhouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>After one week, seedlings were thinned to three per pot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Plants were grown under a natural photoperiod under greenhouse conditions with average temperatures of 8°C (night) to 22°C (day), 65–70% relative humidity during the winter season. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Plants were harvested after eight weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>A control set without fungal inocula for both crops was maintained under identical conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Manual weeding and watering were performed regularly throughout the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Sterilized water was used for watering the set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>No extra fertilizer or manure was added to experimental pots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Assessment of plant growth promotion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Plants were harvested eight weeks after planting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Plant root-shoot length and dry biomass were measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>To measure plant biomass, they were dried at 105°C for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The numbers of tillers/leaves, pods, and stipules produced were recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The total chlorophyll, carotenoid (17) and protein contents (16) of the plant leaves were also measured. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Soil chemical and enzyme assays </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Soil samples were taken at the time of plant harvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Rhizospheric soil samples were kept air-dried and sieved (2 mm) for further analysis in triplicate for each sample. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Among various parameters, total organic carbon (TOC) (11) and microbial biomass carbon (MBC) using the chloroform-fumigation-extraction method (32) were assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Soil samples had been previously extracted in 2% (w/v) Na-bicarbonate solution to determine the available phosphorus (P) (21). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Available potassium (K) was determined using a flame photometer (Systronix-128, Systronix, Salt Lake City, Utah, USA) after extracting samples in 2% (w/v) ammonium acetate solution (11). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Selected soil enzymatic activities were determined in each freshly grounded and sieved (&lt;2 mm) rhizosphere soil sample using four replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Dehydrogenase activity (DHA) was assayed following the method of Pepper et al. (22) by the reduction of 2,3,5-triphenyl tetrazolium chloride (TTC) and expressed in μg triphenyl formazan (g soil)−1h−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Alkaline phosphatase activity (7) and β-glucosidase activity (8) were measured using the substrate analogue paranitrophenyl- β-D-glucopyranoside (pNPG) based on determining the quantity of released p-nitrophenol after incubation of each gram of soil with pNPG solution for 1 h at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Re-isolation of fungal isolates </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Re-isolation of inoculated fungi was carried out to check the plant pathogenicity of tested isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>For epiphytic isolation, the root segments were washed using sterile water, cut into 1 cm long segments aseptically, and then incubated on PDA supplemented with a sterile commercial solution (100×) containing penicillin and streptomycin in 0.9% NaCl (Hi-media, Mumbai, India). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The colonies emerging from root segments were identified morphologically and microscopically by comparing their characteristics with those of tested original fungal colonies on PDA (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In addition, re-isolation was carried out under sterilized conditions to check the endophytic nature of the fungal isolates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For endophytic isolation, the harvested roots were cut into 5 cm long segments, washed in sterile water and then disinfected with 0.1% HgCl2 solution for 30 s followed by five washings with sterilized water to remove traces of HgCl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The segments were air dried under aseptic conditions, after which some segments were placed on PDA, pressed gently and removed after 30 s. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Re-occurrence of the tested isolates was checked to confirm the pathogenic nature of tested fungi. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>The experimental data were subjected to analysis of variance (ANOVA) with the Duncan Multiple Range Test (DMRT) using significance at P&lt;0.05 with the SPSS statistical package for Windows version 10.0 (SPSS, Chicago, IL, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide sequence accession numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The ITS/5.8S rRNA gene sequence data have been deposited in NCBI-GenBank with accession numbers JN102303 and JN118571– JN118573. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The accession URL for their phylogenies is <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S12359">http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S12359</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The results of the present study indicate the plant growth-promoting ability of tested fungal isolates under greenhouse conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Based on morphology, microscopic features (data not shown) and phylogenetic analysis of the ITS region, these fungal isolates have been identified as Westerdykella aurantiaca FNBR-3, Trichoderma longibrachiatum FNBR- 6, Lasiodiplodia sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>FNBR-13 and Rhizopus delemar FNBR-19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Taxonomically, Westerdykella aurantiaca FNBR-3 belongs to family—Sporormiaceae, order—Pleosporales of Ascomycota; Trichoderma longibrachiatum FNBR-6 to family— Hypocreaceae, order—Hypocreales of Ascomycota; Lasiodiplodia sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>FNBR-13 to family Botryosphaeriaceae, order—Botryosphaeriales of Ascomycota; and Rhizopus delemar FNBR-19 to family—Mucoraceae, order—Mucorales of Zygomycota. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Maximum likelihood trees generated in this study were registered in “Treebase” and the fungal isolates have been deposited in the Microbial Type Culture Collection and Gene Bank, Chandigarh, India (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mtcc.imtech.res.in">http://mtcc.imtech.res.in</ext-link>) with accession numbers MTCC 10845- 10848. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The re-isolated fungal colonies emerging from sterilized root segments were morphologically and microscopically different from the inoculated segments (data not shown), ruling out the possibility of the tested isolates being endophytic and pathogenic in nature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Identification of the reisolates other than the tested inoculants was not attempted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Changes in chemical and biochemical properties of plant rhizospheric soil most probably provoked by the fungal inoculum are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>These strains stimulated TOC and MBC contents of soil significantly (P&lt;0.05) with an increase in the range of 34–222% and 53–460%, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The inoculated fungi also increased the available K content of soil in the significant range of 20–119% and available P content as 18–110% compared to the control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Soil enzyme activities were also higher in the rhizosphere of inoculated plants than in un-inoculated controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Inoculation of these fungal strains had a significant stimulating effect on the soil enzyme activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The increase in DHA was 34–154% and 132–422% for alkaline phosphatase, and 262–760% for β-glucosidase activity in all four inoculated fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Fungal strains FNBR-3 and FNBR-6 performed better than the other two strains (FNBR-13 and FNBR-19) in provoking soil chemical properties as well as the enzymatic activities of inoculated soil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The results are presented in Table 2, showing the plant growth-promoting effects of the fungal inoculum on the growth of rice and pea plants grown for eight weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Inoculation of plant rhizospheres with these fungal strains significantly (P&lt;0.05) increased root length (25–85%), shoot length (20–82%), number of tillers (31–100%), and plant dry weight (47–250%) in the case of rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>A significant increase in root length (20–81%), shoot length (16–100%), number of stipules (22–84%), number of leaves (28–113%), number of pods (83–293%), and plant dry biomass (50–152%) was also observed in pea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>An increase in total plant dry matter of tested plants (in the case of rice as 104 and 250%; and in pea as 103 and 152% with FNBR-3 and FNBR-6, respectively) showed the efficiency of these two isolates over FNBR-13 and FNBR-19. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>FNBR-13 and FNBR-19 strains also stimulated plant growth, but without any comparable significant difference between their effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Quantitative assessment of the biochemical properties of plant leaves also showed that all the fungal isolates inoculated plants significantly (P&lt;0.05), increasing the total chlorophyll, carotenoids and protein contents (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Strains FNBR-13 and FNBR- 19 increased these biochemical parameters of plant leaves without any comparable significant difference between their effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Fungal strains FNBR-3 and FNBR-6 produced almost identical effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Presumably, the plant growth increase and soil improvement could be observed due to the activities of PGPF through the production and release of secondary metabolites (plant growth regulators, phytohormones and biologically active substances), preventing the effects of phyto-pathogenic organisms in the rhizosphere and/or facilitating the availability and uptake of soil nutrients from the root environment (4, 18, 30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>These mycelial exudates seem to play an important role in plant growth promotion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>According to Viterbo et al. (34), Trichoderma can produce 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylate (ACC) deaminase, which can contribute to plant growth promotion, such as an increase in root elongation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>These isolates did not have a negative impact on plants or soil, and no disease symptoms appeared on the tested plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Soil fungi have been shown to exhibit plant growth-promoting activity on numerous cultivated plants (4, 18). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Previously, Saldajeno et al. (23) discussed the significant plant growth-promoting effects and yield induced by inoculated PGPF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The maximum stimulatory effect on chickpea plant growth was observed by inoculation of Aspergillus and Penicillium strains and resulted in an incremental increase in shoot height, a nearly three-fold increase in seed number and two-fold increase in seed weight as compared to the control (un-inoculated) plants (20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Shoot and root plant biomass, values of thymidine and leucine incorporation as well as ergosterol and chitin in rhizosphere soil increased due to fungal metabolic activity and fungal biomass (19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Such microbial inoculation could compensate for nutrient deficiency and improve plant development through the production of plant growth regulators by microbes at the root interface (30). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon could stimulate the root development of plants and result in better absorption of water and nutrients from the soil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>The beneficial effects on plant growth observed as a result of the inoculation of PGPF may not be related only to the stimulation of colonization by these fungal isolates in plant rhizospheres, but an increase in the development of the extra-radical mycelium could also be involved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Improved soil structure might be achieved through the secretion of mucilage/polysaccharides by inoculated fungi, which could further improve soil aggregation (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>This might be the reason for the higher concentrations of TOC in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Effectiveness of these treatments on plant growth could also be due to the indirect effect through changes in microbial composition in the rhizosphere (19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Qualitative and quantitative changes in soil rhizospheric microbial populations due to bioinoculants have also been estimated through the measurement of soil enzyme activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The increased enzyme activities found in the rhizosphere of fungus-inoculated plants might be an indication of the increase in carbon and nutrient mineralization in the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The measurement of hydrolases provides an indication of changes in soil fertility, since they are related to the mineralization of important nutrient elements required for both plant and microbial growth (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Application of biofertilizer increased β-glucosidase, phosphatase activities, soil aggregate stability, water-soluble carbohydrates and plant phosphorus acquisition in inoculated soils (19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Many soil fungi have been shown to possess the ability to solubilize sparingly soluble phosphates in vitro by secreting inorganic or organic acids (36). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>George et al. (9) also indicated that the fungal phytases increased hydrolysis of inositol phosphates in soil environments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Likewise, Kim et al. (14) suggested that the secretion of phosphatases by phosphate-solubilizing fungi frequently facilitates the conversion of insoluble forms of phosphate to plant-available forms and enhances plant phosphorus uptake and further growth of the treated plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Microbe-inoculated plants showed an increased root system that, in turn, increased carbon and nutrient inputs to the rhizosphere zone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In the study, activities of glucosidase and phosphatase improved significantly in the rhizosphere of inoculated plants with more growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Caravaca et al. (3) also studied that the soil had higher levels of available phosphorus, aggregate stability, total carbohydrates, biomass carbon and water-soluble carbon and enzyme activities (dehydrogenase, phosphatase and β-glucosidase) in the rhizosphere of PGPF-inoculated plants than in control plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In the same study, shoot biomass of PGPF-inoculated Dorycnium pentaphyllum L. plants was about 219% greater with respect to control plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The solubilization of soil nutrients and their increased uptake have also been demonstrated by de Silva et al. (6) for soil-inhabiting fungal biocontrol agents such as Gliocladium virens and Trichoderma harzianum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Turpeinen et al. (31) suggested that metal-tolerant microbes can maintain their metabolic activities in contaminated soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>These fungi are able to tolerate, biosorb and detoxify arsenic by several mechanisms, including valence transformation, extra- and intracellular precipitation, active uptake and methylation (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>These results encourage mesocosmic research experiments that may help to study the growth promotion of crops inoculated with these arsenic-tolerant fungal strains in arsenic-contaminated soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Using these fungal strains could be a realistic and desirable strategy for maintaining crop production in arsenic-contaminated soils as well as mitigating arsenic contamination of crops. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, it is evident that additional research will be necessary to identify the application range of these arsenic-tolerant and plant growth-promoting fungal strains in terms of soil types, competitiveness and ecology for their ‘in-situ application’. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The use of plant growth-promoting rhizofungus (PGPF) as a bioinoculant is a recent area of interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Metal (loid)- tolerant and metal (loid)-remediating PGPF inoculants can play an important role in maintaining sustainable agricultural production in metal (loid)-contaminated soils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The results of the study reveal the plant growth-promoting efficiency of four arsenic-tolerant and -remediating fungi along with their positive effects on soil nutritive properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The stimulatory efficiency of tested fungal strains on plant growth and soil properties showed their potential to be utilized as bio-culture for better crop cultivation in arsenic-contaminated agricultural soils. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>This study was financially supported by a research grant to the corresponding authors from the Department of Biotechnology, New Delhi, Government of India and this is gratefully acknowledged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The authors are grateful to the Council of Scientific &amp; Industrial Research (CSIR), India and Director, National Botanical Research Institute (CSIR–NBRI), Lucknow, India for the institutional support. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-27_477"><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>1AlguacilMMCaravacaFRoldanA2005Changes in rhizosphere microbial activity mediated by native or allochthonous AM fungi in the re-afforestation of a Mediterranean degraded siteBiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Fert Soils415968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2-27_477"><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>2Caesar-TonthatTC2002Soil binding properties of mucilage produced by a basidiomycete fungus in a model systemMycol Res106930937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3-27_477"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>3CaravacaFAlguacilMMAzconRDiazGRoldanA2004Comparing the effectiveness of mycorrhizal inoculation and amendment with sugar beet, rock phosphate and Aspergillus niger to enhance field performance of the leguminous shrub Dorycnium pentaphyllum LAppl Soil Ecol25169180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4-27_477"><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>4ChandanieWAKubotaMHyakumachiM2009Interactions between the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus Glomus mosseae and plant growth-promoting fungi and their significance for enhancing plant growth and suppressing damping-off of cucumber (Cucumis sativus L.)Appl Soil Ecol41336341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5-27_477"><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>5CozzolinoVPignaMMeoVDCaporaleAGViolanteA2010Effects of arbuscular mycorrhizal inoculation and phosphorus supply on the growth of Lactuca sativa L. and arsenic and phosphorus availability in an arsenic polluted soil under non-sterile conditionsAppl Soil Ecol45262268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6-27_477"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>6de SilvaAPattersonKRothrockCMooreJ2000Growth promotion of High-bush Blueberry by fungal and bacterial inoculantsHort Science3512281230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7-27_477"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>7EivaziFTabatabaiMA1977Phosphatases in soilsSoil Biol Biochem9167172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8-27_477"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>8EivaziFTabatabaiMA1988Glucosidases and galactosidases in soilsSoil Biol Biochem20601606 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9-27_477"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>9GeorgeTSSimpsonRJGregoryPJRichardsonAE2007Differential interaction of Aspergillus niger and Peniophora lycii phytases with soil particles affects the hydrolysis of inositol phosphatesSoil Biol Biochem39793803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10-27_477"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>10HorinouchiHKatsuyamaNTaguchiYHyakumachiM2008Control of Fusarium crown and root rot of tomato in a soil system by combination of a plant growth-promoting fungus, Fusarium equiseti, and biodegradable potsCrop Prot27859864 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11-27_477"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>11JacksonML1962Soil Chemical Analysis, Prentice Hall Inc Eng Cliffs, USA. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12-27_477"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>12JohanssonJFPaulLRFinlayRD2004Microbial interactions in the mycorrhizosphere and their significance for sustainable agricultureFEMS Microbiol Ecol4811319712426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13-27_477"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>13KhanMSAlmasZWaniPA2007Role of phosphates-olubilizing microorganisms in sustainable agriculture—A reviewAgron Sust Devel272943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14-27_477"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>14KimKYJordanDMcDonaldGA1998Effect of phosphate-solubilizing bacteria and vesicular-arbuscular mycorrhizae on tomato growth and soil microbial activityBiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Fert Soils2679 87 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15-27_477"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>15KristinAVangronsveldJColpaertJV2006Zinc-tolerant Suillus bovinus improves growth of Zn-exposed Pinus sylvestris seedlingsMycorrhiza1655355817033817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16-27_477"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>16LowryOHRoserbroughNJFarrALRandallRJ1951Protein measurement with folin phenol reagentJ Biol Chem19326527514907713 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17-27_477"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>17MaclachlanSZalikS1963Plastid structure, chlorophyll concentration and free amino acid composition of chlorophyll mutant of barleyCan J Bot411053 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18-27_477"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>18MasunakaAHyakumachiMTakenakaS2011Plant growth-promoting fungus, Trichoderma koningi suppresses isoflavonoid phytoalexin vestitol production for colonization on/in the roots of Lotus japonicasMicrobes Environ2612813421502738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19-27_477"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>19MedinaAVassilevNAlguacilMMRoldanAAzconR2004Increased plant growth, nutrient uptake, and soil enzymatic activities in a desertified mediterranean soil amended with treated residues and inoculated with native mycorrhizal fungi and a plant growth-promoting yeastSoil Sci169260270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20-27_477"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>20MittalVSinghONayyarHKaurJTewariR2008Stimulatory effect of phosphate-solubilizing fungal strains (Aspergillus awamori and Penicillium citrinum) on the yield of chickpea (Cicer arietinum L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>GPF2)Soil Biol Biochem40718727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21-27_477"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>21OlsenSWatanabeFSBowmanRA1983Evaluation of fertilizer phosphate residues by plant uptake and extractable phosphorusSoil Sci Soc Am J47952958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22-27_477"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>22PepperILGerbaCPBrendeckeJW1995Environmental Microbiology: A Laboratory ManualAcademic PressNew York </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23-27_477"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>23ReddyMSKumarSKhoslaB2002Biosolubilization of poorly soluble rock phosphates by Aspergillus tubingensis and Aspergillus nigerBioresource Technol84187189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24-27_477"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>24SaldajenoMGBHyakumachiM2011The plant growth-promoting fungus Fusarium equiseti and the arbuscular mycorrhizal fungus Glomus mosseae stimulate plant growth and reduce severity of anthracnose and damping-off diseases in cucumber (Cucumis sativus) seedlingsAnn Appl Biol1592840 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25-27_477"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>25ShenoyBDJeewonRWuWPBhatDJHydeKD2006Ribosomal and RPB2 DNA sequence analyses suggest that Sporidesmium and morphologically similar genera are polyphyleticMycol Res11091692816908125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26-27_477"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>26SmithNRDawsonVT1944The bacteriostatic action of rose bengal in media used for the plate counts of soil fungiSoil Sci58467471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27-27_477"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>27SrivastavaPKVaishADwivediSChakrabartyDSinghNTripathiRD2011Biological removal of arsenic pollution by soil fungiSci Total Environ4092430244221459413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28-27_477"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>28StrombergerME2005Fungal communities of agroecosystem813832DightonJThe Fungal CommunityCRC PressBoca Raton, FL </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29-27_477"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>29TamuraKPetersonDPetersonNStecherGNeiMKumarS2011MEGA5: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis using Maximum Likelihood, Evolutionary Distance, and Maximum Parsimony MethodsMol Biol Evol282731273921546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30-27_477"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>30TikhonovichIAProvorovNA2007Beneficial plant-microbe interactions365420DyakovYTDzhavakhiyaVKorpelaTComprehensive and Molecular PhytopathologyElsevierAmsterdam </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31-27_477"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>31TurpeinenRKairesaloTHaggblomMM2004Microbial community structure and activity in arsenic-, chromium- and copper-contaminated soilsFEMS Microbiol Ecol47395019712345 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32-27_477"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>32VanceEDBrookesPCJenkinsonDS1987An extraction method for measuring soil microbial biomass CSoil Biol Biochem19703707 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33-27_477"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>33ViaudMPasquierABrygooY2000Diversity of soil fungi studied by PCR-RFLP of ITSMycol Res10410271032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34-27_477"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>34ViterboALandauUKimSCherninLChetI2010Characterization of ACC deaminase from the biocontrol and plant growth-promoting agent Trichoderma asperellum T203FEMS Microbiol Lett305424820148973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35-27_477"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>35WhiteTJBrunsTDLeeSTaylorJW1990Amplification and direct sequencing of fungal ribosomal RNA genes for phylogenetics315322InnisMAGelfandDHSninskyJWhiteTJPCR Protocols: A Guide to Methods and ApplicationsAcademic PressSan Diego </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36-27_477"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>36WhitelawMA1999Growth promotion of plants inoculated with phosphate-solubilizing fungiAdv Agron6999151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1-27_477" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Effects of rhizofungal inoculum on total chlorophyll, carotenoid and protein contents (mg g−1 fresh weight) of plant leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Values (mean ± SD) of a line followed by the same letter are not significantly different according to the Duncan Multiple Range Test (P&lt;0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="27_477f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t1-27_477" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Effects of rhizofungal inoculum on chemical and biochemical properties of rhizospheric soil of rice and pea plants grown for eight weeks </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-27_477"><p>Values (mean ± SD) within a row for each plant followed by the same letter are not significantly different according to the Duncan Multiple Range Test (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t2-27_477" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Effects of rhizofungal inoculum on the growth of rice and pea plants grown for eight weeks </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn2-27_477"><p>Values (mean ± SD) within a row followed by the same letter are not significantly different according to the Duncan Multiple Range Test (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.05)</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
