
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4094779</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24996224</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-558</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analysis gene expression in the liver of Coilia nasus during the stress response </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>Fukuan</given-names></name><address><email>adublg@126.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Gangchun</given-names></name><address><email>xugc@ffrc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nie</surname><given-names>Zhijuan</given-names></name><address><email>niezj@ffrc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Pao</given-names></name><address><email>xup@ffrc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Ruobo</given-names></name><address><email>gurb@ffrc.cn</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><aff id="Aff18">Key Laboratory of Freshwater Fisheries and Germplasm Resources Utilization, Ministry of Agriculture, Freshwater Fisheries Research Center, Chinese Academy of Fishery Sciences, No. 9 Shanshui East Road, Wuxi, Jiangsu Province China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>558</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Du et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The estuarine tapertail anchovy (Coilia nasus) is widely distributed in the Yangtze River, the coastal waters of China, Korea, and the Ariake Sound of Japan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>It is a commercially important species owing to its nutritional value and delicate flavor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, Coilia nasus is strongly responsive to stress, this often results in death, which causes huge losses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used next-generation sequencing technologies to study changes in gene expression in response to loading stress and the mechanism of death caused by loading stress in Coilia nasus. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Using next-generation RNA-seq technologies on an Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform, we assembled a de novo transcriptome and tested for differential expression in response to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A total of 65,129 unigenes were generated, the mean unigene size and N50 were 607 bp and 813 bp, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Of the assembled unigenes, we identified 2,990 genes that were significantly up-regulated, while 3,416 genes were significantly down-regulated in response to loading stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Pathway enrichment analysis based on loading stress-responsive unigenes identified significantly stress related pathways. “Metabolism” and “immunity” were the two most frequently represented categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In the “metabolism” category, “glucose metabolism” and “lipid metabolism” were major subclasses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The transcriptional expression of rate-limiting enzymes in “glucose metabolism” and “lipid metabolism” was detected by RT-qPCR, all were significantly increased after stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis associated proteins tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNF-α), caspase 9, cytochrome c and caspase 3 in the stress group were significantly elevated, moreover, liver injury indicators (Alanine aminotransferase, ALT, and aspartate transaminase, AST) were also significantly elevated, which indicates that loading stress induced liver injury. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>This study provided abundant unigenes that could contribute greatly to the discovery of novel genes in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The alterations in predicted gene expression patterns reflected possible responses to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Loading stress may induce liver injury through the mitochondrial apoptosis pathway, which was activated by TNF-α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our data not only provide information that will aid the identification of novel genes from fish, but also shed new light on the understanding of mechanisms by which physical stressors cause death in fish. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/1471-2164-15-558) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Gene expression</kwd><kwd><italic>Coilia nasus</italic></kwd><kwd>Stress</kwd><kwd>Liver injury</kwd><kwd>Apoptosis</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Stress exists in all aspects of aquaculture, daily management such as netting, loading and transporting can lead to a stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Stress may result in inhibition of growth, reproductive failure, and reduced resistance to pathogens [1–5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The estuarine tapertail anchovy (Coilia nasus, junior synonym C. ectenes) is widely distributed in the Yangtze River, the coastal waters of China, Korea, and the Ariake Sound of Japan [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>It is a commercially important species owing to its nutritional value and delicate flavor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, Coilia nasus is strongly responsive to stress, this often results in death, which causes huge losses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Currently, little is known of the mechanism by which loading stress causes death in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used next-generation sequencing technologies to study gene expression changes in response to loading stress and the mechanism of death caused by loading stress in Coilia nasus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Recently, several species-specific cDNA microarrays have been developed for teleosts, and they are being used increasingly to reveal global gene expression patterns in response to stressor exposure and/or hormone treatment [7–10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>These studies in fish have revealed that the majority of changes, inspite of the use of different arrays and different types of acute stressor, can be broadly categorized functionally into genes encoding proteins involved in metabolism, immune function and reproduction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Although these studies have identified several genes that were previously not known to be stress responsive, the significance of these observed transcript changes to overall stress adaptation is far from clear. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>While the previous studies that used various microarray platforms in fish were limited by large representation of expressed sequence tags (EST), which made gene-specific interpretation of the data difficult, the advent of next-generation sequencing methods, including pyrosequencing, has effectively overcome this limitation [11, 12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Rapid progress in next-generation sequencing technologies has allowed large-scale efficient and economical production of ESTs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome sequencing facilitates functional genomic studies, including global gene expression, novel gene discovery, and assembly of full-length genes [13–16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>To date, available molecular information on Coilia nasus remains sparse, which limits research on the mechanism by which loading stress causes death. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The powerful new technologies provide a new opportunity for studies of species without genome reference databases, and non-model organisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Experimental animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Coilia nasus (average weight, 9.6 g) were adapted to the conditions in a 7.0 × 5.0 × 1.0 m3 aquarium with a water temperature of 24.5 ± 1.0°C, pH 7.2, and dissolved oxygen concentration of 9.2 ± 0.5 mg O2/L dechlorinated and aerated water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The fish were fed twice daily, at 7:00 AM and 5:00 PM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>At the onset of the experiments, all fish appeared healthy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Stressing experiment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>In March 2012, three 7.0 × 5.0 × 1.0 m3 ponds were stocked with 120 juvenile Coilia nasus each. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The fish were acclimated to the ponds for approximately 14 months before the experiment, at which time the fish were 15 months old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Excess fish were stocked in the ponds in order to ensure subsequent access to the intended numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In detail, Coilia nasus prefer to swim towards lighted areas in dark situations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>To take advantage of this phototaxis, a sifter was put into the water and lit, following which the fish moved into the sifter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The fish were euthanized immediately with 70 mg/L buffered tricaine methanesulfonate (MS-222). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Using this method, five fish were removed from each pond, these 15 fish were the non-stressed controls and were processed immediately (see tissue sampling below). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, another five fish were netted from each pond and loaded into 75 × 55 × 33 cm3 tanks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>After 0.5 h, the fish were euthanized as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Compared with the stressed fish, they did not experience the netting and handling used for the control fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The mean length was 136.98 mm ± 9.26 SEM and mass was 8.86 g ± 1.76 SEM for all fish (n = 30) sampled in this experiment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Tissue sampling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>During the experiments, euthanized fish were submerged immediately in crushed ice to retard degradation of RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Blood was collected into ammonium-heparinized capillary tubes after severance of the caudal fin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>All fish appeared healthy during dissection and their livers were removed and placed in liquid nitrogen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Plasma was separated by centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Plasma and liver samples were stored at -80°C until later analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Animal welfare and experimental procedures were carried out in accordance with the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals (Ministry of Science and Technology of China, 2006), and were approved by the animal ethics committee of the Chinese Academy of Fishery Sciences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Cortisol and glucose </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Blood glucose measurement was performed by glucose-oxidase-superoxide enzyme endpoint colorimetry, the test kit was obtained from Shanghai Biological Product Research Institute, Ministry of Public Health, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Cortisol was measured by radioimmunoassay in accordance with the method described by Pickering and Pottinger [17], the test kit was purchased from Beijing Beifang Biotech Research Institute, China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Plasma samples were measured using a Beckman Cx-4 spectrophotometer (Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Student’s t test was used to analyze differences among all treatments (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>RNA sequencing, assembly and annotation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome sequencing was carried out on an Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform that generated approximately 100-bp paired-end (PE) raw reads (BGI, Shenzhen, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>After removing adaptor sequences, ambiguous ‘N’ nucleotides (with the ratio of ‘N’ greater than 5%) and low quality sequences (with quality score less than 10), the remaining clean reads were assembled using trinity software [18] as described for de novo transcriptome assembly without a reference genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>For homology annotation, non-redundant sequences were subjected to public databases, including NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>) non-redundant protein (Nr) and non-redundant nucleotide (Nt), Swiss-Prot (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/uniprot/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/uniprot/</ext-link>), Gene Ontology (GO, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/">http://www.geneontology.org/</ext-link>), Clusters of Orthologous Groups (COG, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/COG/</ext-link>) and the Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genome.jp/kegg/">http://www.genome.jp/kegg/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>If the results from different databases conflicted, a priority order of alignments from Nr, Nt, KEGG, Swiss-Prot, GO and COG databases was followed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Comparison with the Nr, Nt and Swiss-Prot databases was carried out using the BlastX algorithm with an E-value cut-off of 0.00001; GO terms at the 2nd level were used to perform GO annotation; COG and KEGG classification were performed using BlastX with an E-value cut-off of 0.00001. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Analysis of differentially expressed genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>To analyze stress-responsive, differentially expressed genes in Coilia nasus, the number of reads for each of the contigs from the two samples was converted to reads per kilo base per million (RPKM) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Following this, the MA-plot-based method with Random Sampling model (MARS) in the DEGseq package was used to calculate the expression abundance of each contig among the analyzed samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>We used an FDR (false discovery rate) to determine the P-value threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>An FDR &lt; 0.001 was considered to indicate significant expression abundance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Pathway enrichment analysis identifies significantly enriched metabolic pathways or signal transduction pathways in differentially expressed genes by comparing them with the whole genome background. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Bonferroni adjustments [20] were used to estimate levels of significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>After correction for multiple testing, we chose pathways with a Q-value ≤ 0.05 to represent those significantly enriched in differentially expressed genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The Q-value is defined to be the FDR analog of the P-value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The Q-value of an individual hypothesis test is the minimum FDR at which the test maybe reported as significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Gene expression validation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Genes identified in this transcriptome sequencing analysis were validated and quantified by real-time PCR (RT-qPCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The primers (Additional file 1: Table S1) were designed according to Illumina sequencing data with Primer Premier 5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The prepared total RNA used in RT-PCR analysis was isolated from the same sample as that used for Illumina sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The RT-qPCR was performed on the ABI 7500 real-time PCR system (ABI, USA) using 2× SYBR green real-time PCR mix (Takara, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The PCR amplification was performed in triplicate, using the following cycling parameters: 94°C for 2 min, followed by 40 cycles of 15 s at 94°C, 15 s at 60°C, and 34 s at 72°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>All samples were analyzed in triplicate and the expression of target genes was calculated as relative fold values using the 2-△△CT method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Analysis of liver lipid peroxides, tumor necrosis factor alpha and apoptosis-associated proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Hepatocyte damage following stress was assessed by measuring alanine aminotransferase (ALT) and aspartate transaminase (AST) activities in plasma, using corresponding detection kits (Jusbio, Shanghai, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>TNF-α, cytochrome c, caspase-9, and caspase-3 in hepatic tissue were analyzed using an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay kit (Zhaorui, Shanghai, China), as described by the manufacturer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Lipid peroxides (LPO) were detected by colorimetric methods, using a kit (Jiancheng, Nanjing, China) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Student’s t test or ANOVA, where appropriate, were used to identify significant differences among the treatments at p = 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>All data in this study were expressed as mean ± standard (S.D.). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Plasma cortisol and glucose </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Plasma cortisol was significantly elevated (P &lt; 0.01) in the stressed fish (407.72 ng/mL ± 9.50 SEM, n = 15) compared with the control fish (187.76 ng/mL ± 9.07, n = 15) (Figure  1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>There were no significant differences between control replicates (P &gt; 0.05).Figure 1 Plasma cortisol and glucose concentrations in control and loading stress groups. Bars represent the mean for replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Values with different letters are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Plasma cortisol concentrations for control and stressed groups (n = 15). (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Plasma glucose levels for the two groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Plasma glucose concentrations (Figure  1B) in the stressed group (6.31 mmol/L ± 0.20, n = 15) were statistically higher than in the controls (4.03 mmol/L ± 0.66, P &lt; 0.05, n = 15). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Generation and de novo assembly of Coilia nasus transcriptome data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In this study, we performed transcriptome sequencing of two libraries from liver samples in Coilia nasus via an Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform sequencer: 64.8 and 67.8 million reads were obtained from the two libraries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>After removing low-quality reads, short reads and reads belonging to mitochondria, a total of 111,053,176 clean reads corresponding to mRNAs were obtained, these reads covered a total of 9,994,785,840 bases (Table  1).Table 1 Summary of sequence data generated for the Coilia nasus transcriptome, and quality filtering  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Using the Trinity assembly program, we generated a total of 65,129 unigenes (Table  2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The length distribution of unigenes larger than 200 bp is shown in Figure  2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The mean unigene size and N50 were 607 bp and 813 bp, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>About half of the unigenes (30,582; 47.0%) were ≥ 500 bp and 648 unigenes were &gt; 3,000 bp in length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The largest unigene was 10,911 bp in length (Table  2).Table 2 Assembly statistics of reads Figure 2 Length distribution of unigenes.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Functional annotation and pathway assignment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>According to Gene Ontology (GO), an internationally standardized gene functional classification system, 21,688 non-redundant unigenes were classified into three major functional categories (biological process, cellular component and molecular function) and 49 subcategories (Table  3, Figure  3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In the category of cellular components, “cell part” (15,015, 69.2%) were the most commonly represented, followed by “organelle” (11,679, 53.9%) and “organelle part” (7,270, 33.5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Among the molecular function terms, a significant proportion of clusters were assigned to “binding” (14,201, 65.5%) and “catalytic activity” (9,099, 50.0%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Of sequences categorized as biological processes, dominant subcategories were “cellular process” (15,851,73.1%) and “metabolic process” (13,020, 60.0%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>However, within each of the three categories, few genes were assigned to the subcategories of “growth”, “cell junction” and “receptor regulator activity”.Table 3 Blast analysis of non-redundant unigenes against public databases Figure 3 GO categorization of non-redundant unigenes.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>To classify orthologous gene products, 10,631 (16.3%) non-redundant unigenes (Table  3) were subdivided into 25 COG classifications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Among them, the cluster of “general function prediction only” (3,830, 36.0%) represented the largest group, followed by “translation, ribosomal structure and biogenesis” (2,260, 21.3%), “transcription” (1,893, 17.8%), “replication, recombination and repair” (1,858, 17.5%), “cell cycle control, cell division, chromosome partitioning” (1,608, 15.1%), “post-translational modification, protein turnover, chaperon” (1,522, 14.3%) and “function unknown” (1,506, 14.2%), “nuclear structure” (4, 0.03%) was the smallest group (Figure  4).Figure 4 COG annotation of putative proteins.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) pathway analysis revealed that diverse pathways were represented in our transcriptome dataset: 25,188 unigenes (Additional file 2: Table S2) were assigned to 259 specific pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Among them, “metabolism pathways”, “regulation of actin cytoskeleton”, “pathways in cancer”, “focal adhesion”, and “endocytosis” were the five most frequently represented pathways (Additional file 2: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Some important pathways involved in signal transduction were also identified, including “MAPK signaling pathway”, “calcium signaling pathway” and “Jak-STAT signal pathway” (Additional file 2: Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Loading stress-responsive unigenes in Coilia nasus </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Unigene expression was estimated by the FPKM method, and differentially expressed genes were identified by referenceto Audic [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>We found that 2,990 genes were significantly up-regulated, while 3,416 genes were significantly down-regulated in response to loading stress (Figure  5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The up-regulated and down-regulated genes are listed in Additional file 3: Table S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The indicated genes included metabolic genes, enzymes, and other immune-related genes, such as the GTPase gene, threonine-protein kinase and MHC class I heavy chain gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>These genes showed different expression patterns after stress, which implies that they may play an important role in physiological processes associated with stress.Figure 5 Genes differentially expressed following stress.  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Pathway enrichment analysis based on loading stress-responsive unigenes identified significantly stress-related pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Among these pathways, “metabolism” and “immunity” were the two most commonly represented categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>In the “metabolism” category, “glucose metabolism” and “lipid metabolism” were major subclasses, and included “glycolysis/gluconeogenesis”, “starch and sucrose metabolism”, “glycerophospholipid metabolism” and “fat digestion and absorption” pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>In the “immunity” category, “phagosome”, “HTLV-I infection” and “amoebiasis” were the most frequently represented pathways (Table  4).Table 4 KEGG pathways of differentially expressed genes  </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Loading stress-induced liver injury </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Glucose-6-phosphataseand glucokinase are rate-limiting enzymes in gluconeogenesis and glycolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Liver glucose-6-phosphatase and glucokinase revealed 13.2- and 1.4-fold increased expression after stressing, respectively (Figure  6; P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Hormone-sensitive lipase and carnitine actyltransferase I are rate-limiting enzymes for adipokinetic action and fatty acid beta-oxidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The RT-qPCR results also revealed 11.3- and 6.0-fold increased expression for liver hormone-sensitive lipase and carnitine actyltransferase I in stressed Coilia nasus (Figure  6; P &lt; 0.05).Figure 6 Glucose-6-phosphatase, glucokinase, hormone-sensitive lipase and carnitine actyltransferase I mRNA expression levels in liver in response to stress. The vertical axis shows the relative gene expression levels (means ± SD), bars represent the mean for each replicate ± SD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Replicates or treatments with different letters are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Lipid peroxides (LPO) are produced in the fatty acid beta-oxidation process, and are cytotoxic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The LPO content in the stressed group was significantly higher than that in the control group (P &lt; 0.05; Table  5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>We measured hepatic TNF-α levels in both control and stressed groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>As shown in Table  5, stress markedly increased hepatic TNF-α levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis-associated proteins caspase 9, cytochrome c and caspase 3 were significantly elevated in the stressed group (38.45 ± 1.39, 232.50 ± 3.54, 81.45 ± 3.23) compared with those in control group (34.34 ± 0.43, 187.22 ± 5.36, 68.28 ± 4.06; P &lt; 0.05).Table 5 Levels of lipid peroxides and apoptosis-associated proteins  athe value in the stressed group is significantly different from that in the control group, P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Plasma aminotransferases were assayed to evaluate hepatotoxicity in Coilia nasusu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The ALT and AST concentrations in the control group were 4.10 ± 0.85 and 41.45 ± 7.79 IU/L, while in the stressed group the concentrations were 8.76 ± 1.08 and 202.12 ± 10.01 IU/L, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The results indicate that significantly increasing plasma levels of ALT and AST developed following stress (Figure  7).Figure 7 Liver injury induced by stress in Coilia nasus ( n  = 15). Plasma samples were collected 0.5 h after challenge, and plasma transaminase (ALT and AST) concentrations were determined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Bars represent the mean for each replicate or treatment ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Replicates or treatments with different letters are significantly different at P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The physiological and biochemical response to exposure to stressors has been studied widely in teleosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>One of the evolutionarily conserved stress responses is the rapid elevation in plasma cortisol and plasma glucose levels in response to stressor challenges [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In teleosts, the production of cortisol is under the control of the hypothalamus–pituitary–adrenal (HPA) axis [23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Cortisol is released from the adrenal tissue, resulting in up-regulation of the plasma glucose level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Therefore, plasma cortisol and plasma glucose can be used as indicators of the stress response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In our experiment, these parameters were significantly elevated in the stressed fish when compared with the control fish (Figure  1), this suggested that our sample could be used for transcriptome sequencing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We found that 2,990 genes were significantly up-regulated, while 3,416 genes were significantly down-regulated in response to loading stress (Figure  5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>On pathway enrichment analysis, “metabolism” and “immunity” were the two most frequently represented categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>In the “metabolism” category, “carbohydrate metabolism” and “lipid metabolism” were major subclasses, and included the “glycolysis/gluconeogenesis”, “starch and sucrose metabolism”, “glycerophospholipid metabolism” and “fat digestion and absorption” pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>These carbohydrate metabolic pathways are mainly involved in blood glucose elevation (gluconeogenesis) and glucose utilization (glycolysis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The transcriptional expression of the rate-limiting enzymes (glucose-6-phosphatase and glucokinase) in this process was detected by RT-qPCR, both enzymes were significantly increased following stress (Figure  6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>In addition, plasma glucose levels were significantly elevated after stress (Figure  1B), which provided further confirmation of the findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with studies that have reported higher activities of glycolytic enzymes after exposure to an acute stressor in fish, this may be necessary to cope with the increased energy demand of the liver, including enhanced gluconeogenesis, that is required to re-establish homeostasis [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Those two lipid metabolism pathways are involved mainly in fat digestion, absorption and oxidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Transcript levels for the rate-limiting enzymes (hormone-sensitive lipase and carnitine actyltransferase I) in adipokinetic activity and the fatty acid beta-oxidation process were also significantly increased after stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results suggest that molecular regulation of enzymes critical for energy substrate mobilization and utilization is a key mechanism involved in acute stress adaptation in fish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>However, problems may be associated with these processes, for example, the fatty acid beta-oxidation process may produce lipid peroxides (LPO) [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>High levels of LPO or plasma glucose may induce an increase in TNF-α [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>It is now well accepted that trimerization of the respective receptor by TNF leads to the assembly of the death-initiating signaling complex (disc) [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The disc consists of the death domain of the receptor, one or several associated proteins, and procaspase-8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Upon assembly of the disc, procaspase-8 is autocatalytically cleaved and activated [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The active caspase-8 can either process downstream effector caspases such as caspase-3, -6, and -7 directly [28, 29] or activate mitochondria as an amplification mechanism [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>If mitochondria are involved, caspase-8 cleaves bid, a protein of the Bcl-2 family [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The C-terminal portion of the bid molecule inserts into the outer mitochondrial membrane and induces the release of cytochrome c into the cytosol [31, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Cytochrome c, together with dATP, apoptosis activating factor-1 (Apaf-1) and procaspase-9, forms the apoptosome, which leads to the activation of caspase-9 and subsequently caspase-3 [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Caspase-3 and other effector caspases cleave death substrates, leading to apoptosis [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>In our study, the levels of TNF-α, caspase 9, cytochrome c and caspase 3 in the liver were significantly elevated in the stressed fish compared with the control fish (Table  5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>ALT and AST are important indicators of liver injury, and were also significantly elevated (Figure  7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>These lines of evidence suggested that loading stress induces liver cell apoptosis mediated by TNF-α, which causes liver injury. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>In the present study, using Illumina sequencing and bioinformatics analysis we analyzed the liver transcriptome of Coilia nasus that were stressed by loading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The main objective of this study was to annotate genes from this transcriptome analysis and identify potential stress gene and signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>On the basis of the transcriptome date, we explored the mechanism by which loading stress causes death in Coilia nasus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>A total of 65,129 unigenes were generated, the mean unigene size and N50 were 607 bp and 813 bp, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Of the assembled unigenes, we identified 2,990 genes that were significantly up-regulated, while 3,416 genes were significantly down-regulated in response to loading stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Pathway enrichment analysis based on loading stress-responsive unigenes identified significantly stress-related pathways. “Metabolism” and “immunity” were the two most frequently represented categories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>In the “metabolism” category, “glucose metabolism” and “lipid metabolism” were the major subclasses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The transcriptional expression of rate-limiting enzymes in “glucose metabolism” and “lipid metabolism” was investigated by RT-qPCR, all were significantly increased following stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Apoptosis-associated proteins TNF-α, caspase 9, cytochrome c and caspase 3 were significantly elevated in the stressed group, indicators of liver injury (ALT and AST) were also significantly elevated, which indicates that loading stress induces liver injury in this fish. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Availability of supporting data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Raw sequencing data is available through the NCBI Sequence Read Archive under Project Accession SRP034828 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>All samples were sequenced as 90 bp paired-end reads on an Illumina HiSeq 2000 sequencer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec21"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2013_6232_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1: Table S1: Genes and specific primers used for real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>(DOCX 12 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2013_6232_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Additional file 2: Table S2: KEGG pathway analysis for all unigenes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 21 MB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12864_2013_6232_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Additional file 3: Table S3: List of the genes up-regulated or down-regulated in response to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>(XLSX 2 MB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>RNA-Seq</term><def><p>RNA sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p>Gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RPKM</term><def><p>Reads/Kb/Million</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ALT</term><def><p>Alanine aminotransferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AST</term><def><p>Aspartate transaminase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TNF-α</term><def><p>Tumor necrosis factor alpha</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Cyt c</term><def><p>Cytochrome c.</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>FKD performed the bioinformatics analysis, qRT-PCR validation and drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>GCX and ZJN participated in RNA extraction, primer design, and bioinformatics analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>RBG and PX contributed to the experimental design and manuscript editing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by a grant from the National Key Technology R&amp;D Program (2012BAD26B05), the Three New Projects of Agricultural Aquaculture Program of Jiangsu Province (DZ2012-1, Y2013-33), and the National Special Research Fund for Non-Profit Sector (201203065). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>1.BartonBAIwamaGKPhysiological changes in fish from stress in aquaculture with emphasis on the response and effects of corticosteroidsAnn Rev Fish Dis1991132610.1016/0959-8030(91)90019-G </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>2.GoedeRWBartonBAOrganismic indices and an autopsy-based assessment as indicators of health and condition of fish1990BethesdaAmerican Fisheries Society </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>3.CampbellPMPottingerTGSumpterJPPreliminary evidence that chronic confinement stress reduces the quality of gametes produced by brown and rainbow troutAquaculture19941201–215116910.1016/0044-8486(94)90230-5 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>4.SchreckCBContreras-SanchezWFitzpatrickMSEffects of stress on fish reproduction, gamete quality, and progenyAquaculture20011971–432410.1016/S0044-8486(01)00580-4 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>5.AlfordPBTomassoJRBodineABKendallCApoptotic death of Peripheral Leukocytes in Channel Catfish: effect of confinement-induced stressJ Aquat Anim Health199461646910.1577/1548-8667(1994)006&lt;0064:ADOPLI&gt;2.3.CO;2 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>6.JiangTYangJLiuHShenX-qLife history of Coilia nasus from the Yellow Sea inferred from otolith Sr:Ca ratiosEnviron Biol Fishes201295450350810.1007/s10641-012-0066-6 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>7.WisemanSOsachoffHBassettEMalhotraJBrunoJVanaggelenGMommsenTPVijayanMMGene expression pattern in the liver during recovery from an acute stressor in rainbow troutComp Biochem Physiol Part D Genomics Proteomics20072323424410.1016/j.cbd.2007.04.005<?supplied-pmid 20483297?>20483297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>8.AluruNVijayanMMHepatic transcriptome response to glucocorticoid receptor activation in rainbow troutPhysiol Genomics200731348349110.1152/physiolgenomics.00118.2007<?supplied-pmid 17848605?>17848605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>9.MoranPWAluruNBlackRWVijayanMMTissue contaminants and associated transcriptional response in trout liver from high elevation lakes of WashingtonEnviron Sci Technol200741186591659710.1021/es070550y<?supplied-pmid 17948813?>17948813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>10.VilleneuveDLKnoeblILarkinPMiracleALCarterBJDenslowNDAnkleyGTAltered gene expression in the brain and liver of female fathead minnows Pimephales promelas Rafinesque exposed to fadrozoleJ Fish Biol20087292281234010.1111/j.1095-8649.2008.01897.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>11.Garcia-ReyeroNGriffittRJLiuLKrollKJFarmerieWGBarberDSDenslowNDConstruction of a robust microarray from a non-model species largemouth bass, Micropterus salmoides (Lacèpede), using pyrosequencing technologyJ Fish Biol20087292354237610.1111/j.1095-8649.2008.01904.x<?supplied-pmid 19936325?>19936325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>12.QuinnNLLevenkovaNChowWBouffardPBoroevichKAKnightJRJarvieTPLubienieckiKPDesanyBAKoopBFHarkinsTTDavidsonWSAssessing the feasibility of GS FLX Pyrosequencing for sequencing the Atlantic salmon genomeBMC Genomics2008940410.1186/1471-2164-9-404<?supplied-pmid 18755037?>18755037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>13.HuangYHuangXYanYCaiJOuyangZCuiHWangPQinQTranscriptome analysis of orange-spotted grouper (Epinephelus coioides) spleen in response to Singapore grouper iridovirusBMC Genomics20111255610.1186/1471-2164-12-556<?supplied-pmid 22078027?>22078027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>14.VeraJCWheatCWFescemyerHWFrilanderMJCrawfordDLHanskiIMardenJHRapid transcriptome characterization for a nonmodel organism using 454 pyrosequencingMol Ecol20081771636164710.1111/j.1365-294X.2008.03666.x<?supplied-pmid 18266620?>18266620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>15.AlagnaFD’AgostinoNTorchiaLServiliMRaoRPietrellaMGiulianoGChiusanoMLBaldoniLPerrottaGComparative 454 pyrosequencing of transcripts from two olive genotypes during fruit developmentBMC Genomics20091039910.1186/1471-2164-10-399<?supplied-pmid 19709400?>19709400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>16.SalemMRexroadCE3rdWangJThorgaardGHYaoJCharacterization of the rainbow trout transcriptome using Sanger and 454-pyrosequencing approachesBMC Genomics20101156410.1186/1471-2164-11-564<?supplied-pmid 20942956?>20942956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>17.PickeringADPottingerTGSumpterJPOn the use of dexamethasone to block the pituitary-interrenal axis in the brown trout, Salmo trutta LGen Comp Endocrinol198765334635310.1016/0016-6480(87)90119-5<?supplied-pmid 3030876?>3030876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>18.GrabherrMGHaasBJYassourMLevinJZThompsonDAAmitIAdiconisXFanLRaychowdhuryRZengQChenZMauceliEHacohenNPalmaFBirrenBWNusbaumCLindbladTFriedmanNRegevAFull-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genomeNat Biotechnol201129764465210.1038/nbt.1883<?supplied-pmid 21572440?>21572440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>19.MortazaviAWilliamsBAMcCueKSchaefferLWoldBMapping and quantifying mammalian transcriptomes by RNA-SeqNat Meth20085762162810.1038/nmeth.1226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>20.CabralHJMultiple comparisons proceduresCirculation2008117569870110.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.107.700971<?supplied-pmid 18250280?>18250280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>21.AudicSClaverieJMThe significance of digital gene expression profilesGenome Res1997710986995<?supplied-pmid 9331369?>9331369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>22.BartonBAMorganJDVijayanMMAdamsSMPhysiological and condition-related indicators of environmental stress in fish2002BethesdaAmerican Fisheries Society </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>23.Wendelaar BongaSEThe stress response in fishPhysiol Rev1997773591625<?supplied-pmid 9234959?>9234959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>24.MommsenTVijayanMMoonTCortisol in teleosts: dynamics, mechanisms of action, and metabolic regulationRev Fish Biol Fisheries19999321126810.1023/A:1008924418720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>25.YagiKLipid peroxides in biology and medicine1982TokyoAcademic Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>26.DayCPJamesOFWSteatohepatitis: a tale of two “hits”?Gastroenterology1998114484284510.1016/S0016-5085(98)70599-2<?supplied-pmid 9547102?>9547102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>27.PeterMEKrammerPHMechanisms of CD95 (APO-1/Fas)-mediated apoptosisCurr Opin Immunol199810554555110.1016/S0952-7915(98)80222-7<?supplied-pmid 9794832?>9794832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>28.Fernandes-AlnemriTArmstrongRCKrebsJSrinivasulaSMWangLBullrichFFritzLCTrapaniJATomaselliKJLitwackGAlnemriESIn vitro activation of CPP32 and Mch3 by Mch4, a novel human apoptotic cysteine protease containing two FADD-like domainsProc Natl Acad Sci U S A199693157464746910.1073/pnas.93.15.7464<?supplied-pmid 8755496?>8755496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>29.EnariMTalanianRVWongWWNagataSSequential activation of ICE-like and CPP32-like proteases during Fas-mediated apoptosisNature1996380657672372610.1038/380723a0<?supplied-pmid 8614469?>8614469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>30.KuwanaTSmithJJMuzioMDixitVNewmeyerDDKornbluthSApoptosis induction by caspase-8 is amplified through the mitochondrial release of cytochrome cJ Biol Chem199827326165891659410.1074/jbc.273.26.16589<?supplied-pmid 9632731?>9632731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>31.GrossAYinXMWangKWeiMCJockelJMillimanCErdjument-BromageHTempstPKorsmeyerSJCaspase cleaved BID targets mitochondria and is required for cytochrome c release, while BCL-XL prevents this release but not tumor necrosis factor-R1/Fas deathJ Biol Chem199927421156116310.1074/jbc.274.2.1156<?supplied-pmid 9873064?>9873064 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>32.Bossy-WetzelEGreenDRCaspases induce cytochrome c release from mitochondria by activating cytosolic factorsJ Biol Chem199927425174841749010.1074/jbc.274.25.17484<?supplied-pmid 10364179?>10364179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>33.JiangXWangXCytochrome c promotes Caspase-9 activation by inducing Nucleotide binding to Apaf-1J Biol Chem200027540311993120310.1074/jbc.C000405200<?supplied-pmid 10940292?>10940292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>34.CohenGMCaspases: the executioners of apoptosisBiochem J1997326Pt 1116<?supplied-pmid 9337844?>9337844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
