<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article"><?npg-journal-abbreviation?><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPGSJ//DTD full length article DTD version 7.0 XML//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName ajarticle_v7_x.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 7.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName naturesa2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncogenesis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncogenesis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncogenesis</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2157-9024</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4670961</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">oncsis201535</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/oncsis.2015.35</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26619402</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Targeting self-renewal pathways in cancer stem cells: clinical implications for cancer therapy</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running">Targeting self-renewal pathways in CSCs</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Borah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Raveendran</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rochani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maekawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>D S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="caf1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Bio Nano Electronics Research Center, Graduate School of Interdisciplinary New Science, Toyo University</institution>, Kawagoe, Saitama, <country>Japan</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="caf1"><label>*</label><institution>Bio Nano Electronics Research Center, Graduate School of Interdisciplinary New Science, Toyo University</institution>, Saitama 350 - 8585, Kawagoe, <country>Japan</country>. E-mail: <email>sakthi@toyo.jp</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e177</fpage><lpage/><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>07</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>09</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>09</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2015 Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p><italic>Oncogenesis</italic> is an open-access journal published by <italic>Nature Publishing Group</italic>. This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Extensive cancer research in the past few decades has identified the existence of a rare subpopulation of stem cells in the grove of cancer cells. These cells are known as the cancer stem cells marked by the presence of surface biomarkers, multi-drug resistance pumps and deregulated self-renewal pathways (SRPs). They have a crucial role in provoking cancer cells leading to tumorigenesis and its progressive metastasis. Cancer stem cells (CSCs) are much alike to normal stem cells in their self-renewal mechanisms. However, deregulations in the SRPs are seen in CSCs, making them resistant to conventional chemotherapeutic agents resulting in the tumor recurrence. Current treatment strategies in cancer fail to detect and differentiate the CSCs from their non-tumorigenic progenies owing to absence of specific biomarkers. Now, it has become imperative to understand complex functional biology of CSCs, especially the signaling pathways to design improved treatment strategies to target them. It is hopeful that the SRPs in CSCs offer a promising target to alter their survival strategies and impede their tumorigenic potential. However, there are many perils associated with the direct targeting method by conventional therapeutic agents such as off targets, poor bioavailability and poor cellular distribution. Recent evidences have shown an increased use of small molecule antagonists directly to target these SRPs may lead to severe side-effects. An alternative to solve these issues could be an appropriate nanoformulation. Nanoformulations of these molecules could provide an added advantage for the selective targeting of the pathways especially Hedgehog, Wnt, Notch and B-cell-specific moloney murine leukemia virus integration site 1 in the CSCs while sparing the normal stem cells. Hence, to achieve this goal a complete understanding of the molecular pathways corroborate with the use of holistic nanosystem (nanomaterial inhibition molecule) could possibly be an encouraging direction for future cancer therapy.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Cancer remains one of the deadliest diseases affecting large number of people worldwide every year. Even after profound cancer treatments, cancer relapse and drug resistance are reported. In the past decade, underlying cause discovered to be associated with tumor recurrence, metastasis and chemoresistance are a relatively small population of stem cells inhabiting each adult tissue called as the cancer stem cells (CSCs). These stem cells in the long run have the opportunity to accumulate the mutations required for malignant transformation owing to their unlimited division potential. These cells were first identified by Bonnet and Dick (1997)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> in acute myeloid leukemia and following their findings many other groups have identified these cells in various solid tumors of brain,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref></sup> breast,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> pancreas,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">4</xref></sup> prostate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">6</xref></sup> to name a few. CSCs display certain properties such as high expression of drug efflux transporters, abnormal cellular metabolism, deregulated SRPs, acquisition of epithelial-mesenchymal transition and extensive DNA-repair mechanisms.</p><p>Self-renewal is one of the important properties employed by the CSCs to maintain the proliferating capacities. As genetic and epigenetic changes might have a role in the unrestrained growth, invasion and acquired resistance in cancer cells, it is implicated that epigenesis may accord deregulation of self-renewal pathways (SRPs) in CSCs. There are number of signaling pathways functioning in the normal stem cells, which have assigned roles in the early embryogenesis-like cell proliferation, cell differentiation, cell fate, cell polarity and so on and are under strict regulation. In CSCs, these SRPs when deregulated lead to extensive cell proliferation and may be considered an early event in the process of carcinogenesis. Extensive experimental evidences have revealed Hedgehog (Hh), Wnt, Notch and B-cell-specific moloney murine leukemia virus integration site 1 (BMI1) pathways to be the key players in maintaining the proliferating capacity of CSCs and activated in most of the solid tumors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">7</xref></sup> Among other signaling proteins such as phosphatase and tensin homolog,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">8</xref></sup> bone morphogenetic protein and transforming growth factor beta are also of specific interest as they too control self-renewal and cell differentiation in various tissues and are additionally implicated in tumorigenesis. Recent investigations of targeting the signaling pathways in CSCs have found to be of prime interest. This review focuses on several aspects of major SRPs, which are found to be upregulated in CSCs and certain novel strategies to target these pathways by nanodrug-delivery platforms for the prevention of tumor relapse and chemoresistance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Self-renewal pathways in CSCs</title><p>CSCs make up a minor fraction of the tumor tissues. It acquires a heterogeneous phenotype and can maintain tumor formation at a high degree. Apparently, it is seen that the CSCs share common attributes with the normal stem cells, for instance, self-renewal and differentiation capacity. However, there exist fine-drawn differences between CSCs and normal stem cells for using the same pathways. The molecular mechanisms underlying these phenomena of CSCs hijacking the SRPs of normal stem cells for its own maintenance though remains vague. In the following sections, we are going to review the potential pathways, which are implicated in the CSCs self-renewal activity and tumor initiation through immense experimental findings.</p></sec><sec><title>Hh pathway</title><p>It is known that the Hh pathway helps in controlling cell growth, tissue patterning, morphogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">9</xref></sup> in animal development. The Hh family of proteins has at least three Drosophila Hh gene homologs in vertebrates: Sonic Hh (SHh), Desert Hh and Indian Hh, among which SHh is the most widely used one. The Hh is a 400&#8211;460 amino-acid long precursor protein. The (HhN) amino-terminal domain works as a signaling molecule, whereas the carboxy-terminal domain (HhC) has an auto-catalyzing Hint module. The signaling cell releases the Hh protein through a committed transmembrane receptor called the Dispatched. This happens only after the amino terminal of the Hh protein is being palmitoylated by Rasp/Skinny located in endoplasmic reticulum.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">10</xref></sup> The modified Hh protein binds to its 12 transmembrane receptor known as the Patched (Ptc) and initiates the signaling process. In Hh pathway, a seven-pass transmembrane receptor named Smoothened (Smo) activation is necessary for further signaling process. In the absence of Hh, the Ptc prevents Smo from being located to the primary cilium and its catalytic activity. However, when Ptc is bound by Hh ligand, the inhibitory effect of Ptc on Smo is rendered inactive. Smo now activates the Gli family of transcription factors to carry out the downstream signaling process. Without Smo activation, Gli is maintained in a complex with Suppressor of Fused, which is a negative regulator of Hh signaling. Upon Smo activation, Gli is dissociated from Suppressor of Fused-Gli complex for nuclear translocation to promote the transcription of Hh targeted genes namely patched, cyclin (D/E). In mammals, there are three types of Gli transcription factors Gli1, Gli2 and Gli3 of which Gli1 and Gli2 are activators and Gli3 acts as a repressor. The loss of Suppressor of Fused results in the activation of Hh signaling, which indicates its central role in the repression of the pathway.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">11</xref></sup></p><p>The Hh signal transduction pathway components tightly control embryonic development, and also expressed in postnatal and adult tissues, where these components have assigned roles in the maintenance of stem cells, tissue repair and regeneration. Hence, defects in Hh signaling may affect at the embryonic and later stages of life in humans.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">12</xref></sup> Many human congenital diseases have been associated with Hh signaling defects such as holoprosencephaly in which there is loss of one copy of SHh.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">13</xref></sup> Mutations in Ptc1 result in a rare autosomal genetic form of basal cell carcinoma also known as the Gorlin syndrome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">15</xref></sup> Increasing evidence have widely supported the fact that dysregulated Hh signaling is present in majority of the human cancers today, which includes brain tumors, melanomas, leukemia's, gastro-intestinal, malignancies of the breast, ovary, prostate and pancreas.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">16</xref></sup> However, in most of these cancers mutation of Hh pathway components is not the only basis for its aberrant activation, but rather has been caused by high expression of Hh ligands.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">18</xref></sup> Experimental evidences in the past have confirmed the presence of CSCs in most of the human tumors and the self-renewal property of these cells has been attributed to Hh signaling.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> Hh signaling maintains the self-renewal capacity of the malignant clone, which was demonstrated in mouse models of chronic myeloid leukemia.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">23</xref></sup> Hh signaling is also under epigenetic regulation in CSCs mainly the Gli transcription factors. As Gli1 and Gli2 are acetylated, their deacetylation mediated by Histone deacetylase (HDAC) complex promotes Hh pathway activation. Downregulation of Gli1 is mediated by miR-324-5p, and subsequent loss of miR-324-5p have led to neoplastic transformation into medulloblastoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">24</xref></sup> Ptc and Gli1 proteins were seen to be highly expressed in ovarian cancer patients as reported by Liao <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">25</xref></sup> The authors in this study also observed that there was a significant overexpression of SHh mRNA in the patient's tumor tissues. It is also affirmed that Hh signaling has an active role in the progression of prostate cancer; however, there is paucity of the precise mechanism involved in its abnormal signaling. Sheng <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26">26</xref></sup> have reported a loss-of-function mutations in Suppressor of Fused, in most of the prostatic tumor tissues. Other independent studies carried out by groups have presented with data that there is a ligand-dependent paracrine or autocrine Hh signaling in prostate tumors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28">28</xref></sup> Hh signaling is also found to regulate self-renewal in normal and mammary CSCs acting in concert with BMI pathway as investigated by Liu <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib29">29</xref></sup> in their <italic>in vitro</italic> and <italic>in vivo</italic> studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Notch pathway</title><p>Notch signaling is a developmental pathway in multicellular organisms involved in cell fate decisions and pattern formation during embryogenesis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30">30</xref></sup> Post-translational modifications result in the formation of a heterodimeric NECD (notch receptor comprising of an extracellular domain) and TM-NICD (transmembrane-intracellular domain) inserted in the plasma membrane of a signal-receiving cell. Once a ligand for example, Delta (DLL1, DLL3, DLL4) and Jagged (jag1, jag2) binds to the notch receptor, the TNF-alpha ADAM metalloprotease-converting enzyme mediates the cleavage of NECD from TM-NICD. The NECD-ligand complex is endocytosed/recycled in the signal-sending cell by Mind Bomb ubiquitination, whereas in the signal-receiving cell the &#947;-secretase enzyme cleaves TM-NICD complex, releasing NICD. It further proceeds into the nucleus and associate with the CSL (centromere-binding factor 1/Suppressor of hairless/Lag1) transcription complex. This CSL-NICD complex now subsequently activates the notch target genes: Hairy and enhancer of split family, p21 and Myc.</p><p>Apart from regulating cellular communication in embryogenesis, it also helps in stem cell growth and differentiation. Studies have elucidated the pathological role of notch pathway in human malignancies going from T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (T-ALL)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31">31</xref></sup> to breast cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib33">33</xref></sup> and others where inappropriate activation of the pathway that led to uncontrolled proliferation, restricted differentiation and prevents apoptosis in the cancer cells. Of late, a mere reason of focusing on notch pathway in recent years is due to the identification of a distinct cellular hierarchy in human acute myeloid leukemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">1</xref></sup> and other solid tumors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">3</xref></sup> This cellular hierarchy is the CSCs, which maintains the tumor and recapitulates the features of normal stem cells. Notch pathway is one of the developmental pathways active in this subset of CSCs, which maintains the self-replication and differentiation decisions. A significant evidence of the Notch pathway, that it is related for the survival of CSCs, came from the independent studies conducted by Farnie and Clarke;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34">34</xref></sup> Sansone <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> Farnie and Clarke reported the role of aberrant notch signaling as one of the factors involved in early breast cancer. Studies by Gustafasson <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36">36</xref></sup> have indicated that the notch and hypoxia response factor HIF&#945; interacts with each other to assist the outset of a stem cell phenotype and its survival in hypoxic environment. Based on these findings, Sansone <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35">35</xref></sup> carried out various studies to report that the expression of notch-3 is being controlled by the 66k-Da isoform of the Src homology 2 domain-containing gene (p66Shc), which gets induced in a breast cancer cell line when exposed to a hypoxic environment also leading to the survival of mammary gland progenitor cells. Notch signaling also has an oncogenic role in T-ALL where Notch 1 was identified to be involved in t (7; 9)(q34;q34.3) chromosomal translocation to bring out the disease outcome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37">37</xref></sup> Subsequent studies have brought newer insights to the role of Notch in human T-ALLs, with discovery of two types activating mutations within Notch 1.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup> One mutation was in the extracellular hetero-dimerization domain, a change in the amino-acid sequence leading to ligand-independent metalloproteinase cleavage site S2, whereas the second involved Notch 1 proline, glutamic acid, serine, threonine sequence domain. These mutations were reported to be present in 50% of human T-ALLs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib38">38</xref></sup> Notch 1 is also shown to have an elevated expression in pancreatic CSCs compared with non-pancreatic CSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39">39</xref></sup> In pancreatic cancer, notch pathway maintains the epithelial cells in a progenitor state, acquiring epithelial-mesenchymal transition phenotype leading to tumor growth, invasiveness and metastasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref></sup> Emerging evidences show that the resistance of pancreatic cancers toward several chemotherapeutic measures is due to activated Notch signaling, although underlying mechanism still remains elusive.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42">42</xref></sup> These studies provides the rationale to develop targeted therapies, which will interfere with notch signaling in human malignancies.</p></sec><sec><title>WNT pathway</title><p>The Wnt signaling pathway is an ancient and evolutionary conserved developmental pathway, which controls stem cells and determines cellular fate during development. The Wnt family is a group of 19 glycoproteins in humans involving a complex mechanism of signaling phenomena, with salient functional and biological outcome.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43">43</xref></sup> It may lead to much serious pleiotropic pathology when these tightly controlled mechanisms go awry. The Wnt ligand binds to a transmembrane receptor Frizzled and displaces the GSK-3&#946; (glycogen synthase kinase 3 beta) from the adenomatous polyposis coli (APC)/Axin/GSK-3&#946; regulatory complex. However, the absence of Wnt ligand marks the degradation of &#946;-catenin a cell adhesion protein and transcription regulator in APC/Axin/GSK-3&#946; and casein kinase1 destruction complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45">45</xref></sup> through the beta transducing repeat containing E3 ubiquitin protein ligase pathway. Once Wnt ligand binds to its receptor the pathway is turned on and brings the co receptor low-density lipoprotein receptor related protein 5/6 to the vicinity of the Wnt bound Frizzled complex. This activates downstream component Disheveled by sequential phosphorylation, polyubiquitination, polymerization and finally stabilizing &#946;-catenin.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46">46</xref></sup> &#946;-catenin now translocate to the nucleus where it associates with T-cell factor/lymphoid-enhanced factor family of transcription factors, and recruits other co-activators such as cAMP response element-binding protein, p300,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib48">48</xref></sup> Bcl9<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib49">49</xref></sup> and Pygopus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50">50</xref></sup> This ultimately leads to transcription of target Wnt genes: survivin, cyclin D and c-myc.</p><p>The relevance of Wnt signaling in human cancers was perhaps best well known for its role in colon cancer where the healthy colonic epithelia accumulates mutation in specific genes such as APC, &#946;-catenin, K-ras and p53.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51">51</xref></sup> Morin PJ <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52">52</xref></sup> had carried out genetic studies in four different kinds of APC mutants and analyzed that the presence of APC mutations in colorectal cancer also leads to defective downregulation of &#946;-catenin and Tcf-4 transcriptional activity. There are numerous mechanisms that can drive the aberrant Wnt/&#946;-catenin signaling, leading to cancer formation in a mutually exclusive manner. In certain colorectal cancers, there is a probability of finding an exclusive catenin (cadherin-associated protein) beta 1 mutation when APC mutations are lacking.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53">53</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib54">54</xref></sup> This was also supported by the conclusive evidence, which came from the studies of Mirabelli-Primadehl <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55">55</xref></sup> regarding the role of &#946;-catenin mutations in colorectal cancers. Hepatocellular carcinoma<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56">56</xref></sup> and endometrial ovarian tumors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib57">57</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58">58</xref></sup> were also found to possess catenin (cadherin-associated protein) beta 1 mutations, which led to aberrant nuclear accumulation of &#946;-catenin. A vast majority of the colorectal tumors harbor APC mutations, which may lead to the constitutive activation of &#946;-catenin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib61">61</xref></sup> Like Hh and Notch, Wnt/&#946;-catenin signaling too has an important role in embryogenesis and regulates cell proliferation and lineage differentiation in many tissues.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib62">62</xref></sup> In adults, Wnt signals are basically involved in stem cell renewal especially in intestinal crypts,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib63">63</xref></sup> hair follicles<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib64">64</xref></sup> and bone growth plate.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib65">65</xref></sup> As Wnt signaling has a notable role to play in stem cell proliferation and differentiation, its disruptions will certainly affect stem cell function with serious implications for malignancy. Consistent findings have shed light to the fact that &#946;-catenin is present in a variety of CSCs settings<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib66">66</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib67">67</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib68">68</xref></sup> including colon,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">69</xref></sup> cutaneous CSC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib70">70</xref></sup> and also HSC.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib71">71</xref></sup> Among all these CSCs, colon CSCs were found to have a very high concentration of &#946;-catenin, which contributes to its stemness, in part orchestrated by the microenvironment finally giving rise to drug resistance and also metastasis.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib69">69</xref></sup> Wnt signaling has been also shown to be responsible for epithelial-mesenchymal transition<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib72">72</xref></sup> in tumors as a result of high concentration of &#946;-catenin in the nucleus.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib73">73</xref></sup> This leads to the arrest of tumor cell division and acquiring mesenchymal markers like fibronectin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib74">74</xref></sup> while retaining the self-renewal capacity, a characteristic feature employed by the CSCs.</p></sec><sec><title>BMI1 pathway</title><p>The BMI1 pathway is one of the proto-oncogenic signaling pathways like Hh, Notch and Wnt involved in the differentiation and self-renewal mechanisms of stem cells persistently.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib75">75</xref></sup> The BMI1 belongs to the Polycomb group of gene family, well-known epigenetic gene silencers, targeting the p16 and p19Arf locus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib76">76</xref></sup> both of which suppresses cell proliferation. Human BMI1 gene comprises of 10 exons and is localized on chromosome 10.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib77">77</xref></sup> BMI1 gene encodes a 324 amino-acid long protein with a predominant nuclear localization comprising of a <italic>N</italic>-terminal RING finger domain and a central helix turn helix motif.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib78">78</xref></sup> BMI1 affects morphogenesis during embryonic development and in hematopoiesis as reported by van Der Lugt <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib79">79</xref></sup> in 1994 with a pervasive expression in almost all tissues. Extensive studies have also reported the association of BMI1 in the initiation of various cancers where BMI1 can cooperate with c-myc and initiate the disease.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib80">80</xref></sup> Its expression was found to be highly upregulated in acute myeloid leukemia,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib81">81</xref></sup> cancers of the lung,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib82">82</xref></sup> ovaries,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib83">83</xref></sup> breast<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib84">84</xref></sup> and neuroblastoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">85</xref></sup> It is noted that CSCs are highly enriched with BMI1, and seen to be co-expressive with stem cell markers, CD133 and CD44, in most of the tumor CSC population.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib86">86</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib87">87</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib88">88</xref></sup> Zhang <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib89">89</xref></sup> in their study asserted that epithelial ovarian cancers arise from a population of tumor-initiating cells with the CD44- and CD117-positive marker phenotype along with the expression of BMI1 and others such as Notch 1, ATP-binding cassette sub-family G member 2, Nanog, Nestin and Oct-4. The expression of these markers led to chemoresistance and exacerbated the disease condition. Cui H <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib85">85</xref></sup> reported BMI1 to be overexpressed in human neuroblastoma primary tumors and cell lines, cooperating with MYCN gene in transforming the benign S-type neuroblastoma cells. Prostate cancer cells too have a heightened expression of BMI1 in tumors with Gleason scores of 8 or higher.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib90">90</xref></sup> Glinsky and colleagues<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib91">91</xref></sup> carried out a microarray analysis in 11 different types of cancer specimens and indicated that the conserved BMI1 driven pathway is engaged in a metastatic behavior of human malignancies along with a stem cell-like expression profile ultimately leading to disease recurrence after therapy. These studies indicate that the overexpression of BMI1 is critical for the maintenance of CSCs in most of the human tumors.</p></sec><sec><title>Targeting strategies to inhibit self-renewal pathways in CSCs</title><p>Conventional cancer treatment of chemotherapy and radiotherapy can target only the bulk of sensitive tumor cells, which are in rapidly dividing phase. This therapeutic intervention induces many tumor cells to undergo apoptosis and die, whereas the CSCs survive this process by remaining in G<sup>0</sup> phase and give rise to 'second-line tumors' with acquired resistance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib92">92</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib93">93</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib94">94</xref></sup> Henceforth, current cancer research is focused toward targeting these CSCs and it has become essential to develop novel therapeutic approaches to prevent cancer recurrence and emergence of drug resistance. Even though tremendous research has been carried out to eliminate the CSCs, but efficient modalities to target the SRPs in CSCs have been gaining prime focus in recent years. During and after the treatment period CSCs maintain their self-renewal and differentiation capacities by activating the embryonic signaling pathways. The Hh, Notch, Wnt and BMI1 maintains the proper functionality in normal stem cells but a deregulated behavior in these pathways, owing to some alterations in the genes encoding the signaling molecules is observed in CSCs and also have been found in human tumor samples clearly stating their role in tumor development and maintenance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib95">95</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib96">96</xref></sup> As normal stem cells and CSCs share similarities in the signaling pathways, it would be extremely important while designing drugs to understand the complex biology of these pathways to destroy the CSCs and selectively sparing the normal stem cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Drugs targeting self-renewal pathways</title><p>Cyclopamine, a plant derived teratogen binds and deactivate Smo which is otherwise being suppressed by Ptc. Targeting the Hh pathway using cyclopamine was shown by Taipale <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib97">97</xref></sup> where they suggested that Hh pathway related tumors associated with Ptc mutations might respond well to treatment with cyclopamine. As cyclopamine is a steroidal compound, it affects the activity of Ptc by blocking its sterol-sensing domain.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib98">98</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib99">99</xref></sup> Bar EE <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib100">100</xref></sup> conducted a study on cyclopamine-mediated inhibition of Hh pathway in glioblastoma CSCs, and observed a significant 40&#8211;60% decrease in growth of adherent glioma cell lines with high Gli1 expression and no new neurospheres formed. Apart from cyclopamine, another synthetic small molecule inhibitors of Smo, GDC-0449 identified by Genentech was shown to inhibit the Hh pathway activity in metastatic basal cell carcinoma (ClinicalTrials.govnumber, NCT00607724).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib101">101</xref></sup> Oral administration of GDC-0449 was given to 33 patients with advanced basal cell carcinoma for a median duration of 9.8 months and reported two complete responses and 16 partial responses.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib101">101</xref></sup> GDC-0449 was also shown to have its inhibitory effect in medulloblastoma, pancreatic cancer but its effect is more prominent in advanced basal cell carcinoma. Several other small molecule Smo antagonists, which are investigated clinically include IPI-926,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib102">102</xref></sup> BMS-833923 (Clinical trials.govnumber, NCT00884546), PF-04449913 (Clinical trials.govnumber, NCT00953758), LDE-225.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib104">104</xref></sup> However, there may be resistance to these molecules over a period of time due to point mutations in Smo. Hence, targeting the SHh ligand and the downstream components such as Gli transcription factors by small molecules namely Robotnikinin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib105">105</xref></sup> and HPIs 1-4,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib106">106</xref></sup> GANT58,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib107">107</xref></sup> GANT61,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib107">107</xref></sup> respectively, is a promising approach to prevent tumor relapse and metastasis. In addition to chemical compounds used for the treatment of human cancer, researchers have also considered the use of dietary chemopreventive agents known as nutraceuticals for targeting the Hh signaling such as Resveratrol,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib108">108</xref></sup> Curcumin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib109">109</xref></sup> and epigallocatechin-3-gallate,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib110">110</xref></sup> which have been experimentally shown to inhibit Hh signaling in prostate cancer, medulloblastoma and chondrosarcoma, respectively.</p><p>Most of the agents that have been developed to inhibit notch signaling are designed to target notch ligands, notch receptors, ligand receptor binding, &#947;-secretase-mediated cleavage and transcriptional nuclear complex. &#947;-secretase inhibitors are small molecule agents, which are widely studied, as notch activation largely depends on &#947;-secretase activity and is a promising target. A number of clinical trials on &#947;-secretase inhibitors is well indicated to inhibit notch signaling in many cancers, for example, T-ALL, central nervous system malignancies,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib111">111</xref></sup> breast cancer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib112">112</xref></sup> MK0752, one of the potent &#947;-secretase inhibitors in clinical development was shown to inhibit notch signaling in majority of human T-ALL.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib113">113</xref></sup> Another &#947;-secretase inhibitor PF-03084014 was shown to inhibit Notch activity in T-ALL cell lines by Wei P <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib114">114</xref></sup> Apart from targeting the &#947;-secretase activity, notch ligand-inhibiting agents specially DLL4 monoclonal antibodies, for example, OMP-21M18 are in clinical development, designed for patients diagnosed with colon cancer, pancreatic cancer and small cell lung cancer.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib115">115</xref></sup> DLL4, specific notch ligand for embryonic vascular development and arteriogenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib116">116</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib117">117</xref></sup> when blocked by a selective antibody-impeded tumor growth in several solid tumor models.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib118">118</xref></sup> Other agents that inhibit notch signaling in cancer include mastermind-like peptide inhibitors, which interferes with the notch nuclear co-activator mastermind-like protein, a part of the Notch transcriptional complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib119">119</xref></sup> and notch soluble receptor decoys.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib120">120</xref></sup> Also, the use of natural compounds such as genistein,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib121">121</xref></sup> sulforaphane,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib122">122</xref></sup> quercetin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib123">123</xref></sup> owing to their relative low toxicity was seen to inhibit notch activity in tumor cells or in CSCs.</p><p>Agents that can inhibit Wnt signaling, currently under investigations, employ strategies to target receptor/ligand interactions, cytosolic and nuclear signaling components. One of the approaches to inhibit receptor ligand interactions is to target the Frizzled family of receptors by using antibodies. Studies have been carried out using a humanized antibody against Frizzled 10 for patients with synovial sarcoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib124">124</xref></sup>
<italic>In vitro</italic> studies revealed that synovial sarcoma cells were suppressed by the polyclonal antibody in mediating antibody dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity against the Frizzled 10 receptor overexpressed cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib124">124</xref></sup> Monoclonal antibodies targeting the Wnt (1&#8211;2) ligands have also disclosed the inhibition of Wnt signaling in colon cancer<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib125">125</xref></sup> and human melanoma.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib126">126</xref></sup> Disheveled protein is one of the key cytosolic signaling components in the Wnt pathway that associates extracellular signals to its downstream components. Disheveled could be a therapeutic intervention in inhibiting the Wnt pathway for cancer therapy. Compounds that have been preclinically tested in this direction include FJ9<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib127">127</xref></sup> and NSC668036.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib128">128</xref></sup> One of the critical steps in the activation of Wnt signaling is the interaction of &#946;-catenin with the T-cell factor/lymphoid-enhanced factor transcription factors, and recruits a myriad of co-activators such as cAMP response element-binding protein, p300 to name a few.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib47">47</xref></sup> These co-activators represent potential targets to interfere with the &#946;-catenin/transcription factor stabilization complex. ICG-001 a small molecule inhibitor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib129">129</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib130">130</xref></sup> (Institute for chemical genomics) was developed in this direction to target these co-activators.</p><p>BMI1 has no enzymatic function hence traditional drug discovery approaches to target this protein remains a challenge. However, the use of HDAC inhibitors to suppress the expression of BMI1 and its downstream components was recently shown by Bommi <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib131">131</xref></sup> in human breast cancer. The HDAC inhibitors such as sodium butyrate and valproic acid were investigated in the study where the compounds seem to inhibit BMI1 activity through a transcriptional mechanism repressing the polycomb complexes. Another drug artemisinin and its derivatives having antimalarial activity were shown to have inhibition on cancer cell growth and angiogenesis. This drug was investigated to check its inhibitory role in regulating BMI1 expression both in protein and transcript levels in nasopharyngeal carcinoma cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib132">132</xref></sup> To date, no small molecules have been reported to inhibit BMI1 with competent specificities, although experimental evidences cited above using HDAC inhibitors and artemisinin bring a rationale to develop more agents for therapeutic targeting of BMI 1.</p></sec><sec><title>Prospects of nanodrug targeting</title><p>In current cancer treatment strategies, targeted drug delivery is one of the safest ways to target the tumor. To address this issue, nanoparticles have had an important role in delivery of drugs specifically at the designated site at the required concentration, evading immune response without having any off targets within the safety margins. Nanoparticles in the past have received quite unprecedented success as drug-delivery vectors in cancer therapy and diagnosis because of their biophysiological properties and the ability to interact with cells due to the similarity of their size with cellular components.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib133">133</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib134">134</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib135">135</xref></sup> They can carry multiple payloads owing to their large surface area, multi-functionalized with targeting moieties and controlled drug release.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib136">136</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib137">137</xref></sup> Taking into account about the multiple advantages of nanoparticles, they can be harnessed to the best of their ability to target the drug-resistant CSCs. Independent studies conducted by researchers have applied nanoparticles to target CSCs in diverse overlapping areas. Lee <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib138">138</xref></sup> and Swaminathan <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib139">139</xref></sup> in their distinctive studies have made use of nanoparticles as 'beacons' to label CSCs as a diagnostic measure. Nanoparticles were also successfully used to deliver non-druggable anticancer agents to kill the drug-resistant CSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib140">140</xref></sup> Moreover, nanoparticles in the form of stealthy liposomes were used as therapeutic intervention by Liu <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib141">141</xref></sup> to wipe out CSCs and non CSCs selectively. Many groups have recently targeted the CSCs effectively through the use of combination therapy of antibodies and conventional chemotherapeutic drugs against the CSC surface markers CD133<sup>+</sup><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib142">142</xref></sup> and drug efflux transporters.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib143">143</xref></sup> Yu <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib144">144</xref></sup> in their study eliminated CD133<sup>+</sup> osteosarcoma CSCs through salinomycin delivery via CD133 aptamer-conjugated PEGylated PLGA nanoparticles. These approaches though have received encouraging results, but still leave plenty of room for improvement. Another approach to target the CSCs, which is the main focus of this review, and have received a lot of attention over the years is the targeting of the SRPs, which are implicated to maintain the self-renewal capacity of the CSCs and involved in tumorigenesis. Till date, SRPs as discussed in the above sections are being targeted directly by the use of small molecule inhibitors, monoclonal antibodies and natural compounds. Although these agents have shown promising results in inhibiting the deregulated pathways in CSCs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib145">145</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib146">146</xref></sup> there have been certain drawbacks associated such as toxicity, poor water solubility and poor specificity. Hence, nanoformulation of these compounds along with the combination of conventional chemotherapeutic drugs is a holistic approach to inhibit the SRPs in CSCSs.</p><p>Chenna <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib147">147</xref></sup> recently have engineered a polymeric nanoparticle encapsulating a small molecule inhibitor, HPI-1 (Hh pathway inhibitor), which was shown to bypass the secondary mutational resistance toward Smoothened antagonists. Hh signaling is seen to be aberrantly active in most of the human cancers, and Smo secondary mutation abrogates the binding of most of the Hh inhibitors. The group addressed this issue by nanoformulating HPI-1 (NanoHHI) that is a potent antagonist of Gli1 and reported that NanoHHI markedly inhibits the growth of mouse medulloblastoma allografts, which harbor a Smo<sup>D477G</sup>-binding site mutation, accompanied by significant downregulation of Gli1 mRNA. Nanoformulation of HPI-1 improved its aqueous solubility and also systemic bioavailability.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib147">147</xref></sup> The same group further confirmed their studies by using NanoHHI to check the inhibition of Hh signaling in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) in an orthotopic model. NanoHHI markedly reduced systemic metastases in HCC cell lines both in vitro and <italic>in vivo</italic> settings. Moreover, it also decreased the population of CD133<sup>+</sup>-expressing HCC cells, considered to be the tumor-initiating cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib148">148</xref></sup> Lim K <italic>et al.</italic> revealed that polymeric nanoparticle formulation of curcumin suppressed the growth of multiple brain tumor cell lines. The authors observed that NanoCurc when administered to brain tumor cell lines in a dose-dependent manner, it led to programmed cell death in addition to depleting CSCs. In their study, microarray analyses disclosed that when medulloblastoma DAOY cells treated with 20&#8201;&#956;<sc>M</sc> curcumin showed 2.4-fold downregulation of Gli1 expression, which is a key effector in Hh signaling. However, notch activity was not seen to be much affected by curcumin treatment in DAOY cells.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib149">149</xref></sup> A liquid&#8211;lipid nanoparticle delivery system has been harnessed in a recent study by You <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib150">150</xref></sup> to deliver the Smo antagonist CPA-LLP (cyclopamine) in 4T1 murine breast cancer and Miapaca-2 human pancreatic carcinoma models (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2a and b</xref>). The group used a combination strategy of CPA-LLP and core-cross-linked polymeric micelles bound lutetium-177 in the carcinoma models and reported slow tumor growth. Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma is characterized with desmoplasia, aberrant Hh signaling and downregulation of tumor suppressor miR-let7b. Desmoplastic environment provides the niche for CSCs. Mahato <italic>et al.</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib151">151</xref></sup> carried out synergistic treatment of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma through co-delivery of Hh inhibitor GDC-0449 and miRNA (miR-let7b) into micelles using methoxy poly (ethylene glycol)-<italic>block</italic>-poly (2-methyl- 2-carboxyl-propylenecarbonate-graft-dodecanol-graft-tetraethylene-pentamine) (mPEG-b-PCC-g-DC-g-TEPA). It was observed that the combination therapy of GDC-0449 and miR-let7b micelles led to reduced cell viability in the different pancreatic cell lines (HPAF-II, Capan-I, T3M4, MIA-PaCa-I) even at low dose concentration of the formulation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Figures 2c&#8211;f</xref>).</p><p>Notch signaling is mostly targeted by the use of gamma-secretase inhibitors but its clinical use is hindered by acute after-effects and hence the need for an alternative strategy. A novel approach of delivering the gamma-secretase inhibitors to block Notch signaling was presented by Mamaeva and colleagues using imagable mesoporous silica nanoparticles, which were found to be biocompatible, biodegradable and delivered gamma-secretase inhibitors without any toxic side-effects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig3">Figures 3a&#8211;c</xref>). The group designed a drug-loaded mesoporous silica nanoparticles of average size centered ~200&#8211;350 nm and surface modified with folate (FA) to the outer polyethylenimine layer of the particles. <italic>In vitro</italic> analyses were screened using different breast cancer cell lines (MCF7 (FR-positive), MDA-MB-231, T47D, SK-BR-3, MDA-MB-468). The study revealed the mesoporous silica nanoparticles-mediated delivery of gamma-secretase inhibitors was specific toward the cells and also inhibited Notch signaling. MCF7 cells were reported to have the highest FA-mediated endocytosis due to its surface functionalization. Moreover, <italic>in vivo</italic> studies also supported that targeted gamma-secretase inhibitors delivery-enhanced tumor penetration and retainment at the tumor site as compared with free drug.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib152">152</xref></sup> Recently Lo <italic>et al.</italic> have designed a small interfering RNA-delivery approach against the enhancer of zeste homolog 2 and Oct-4 genes upregulated in head and neck squamous cell carcinoma using polyurethane-short branch polyethylenimine. The small interfering RNA polyethylenimine constructs used was able to repress epithelial-mesenchymal transition and radioresistance in aldehyde dehydrogenase 1+/CD44+ CSC-like cells, in addition to inhibiting Wnt signaling, which may be involved in the CSCs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib153">153</xref></sup></p><p>Although these experimental findings are encouraging to target the SRPs through nanoparticle-mediated delivery. However, it is imperative to extend more research in combining the SRPs-targeting therapeutics with nanotechnology-based platforms for a robust cancer treatment strategy for clinical applications.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion and future direction</title><p>In this review, we have tried to render a picture of the heterogeneous CSCs being implicated to be a cause of cancer relapse, chemo and radioresistance in recent times. Understanding the complex biology behind the survival mechanism of CSCs in solid tumors, deregulation in the SRPs is seen to be one of the prominent reasons for their inevitable existence even after treatment. Despite the availability of small molecule inhibitors used to target the SRPs, a small fraction of them only has been put to clinical application owing to their non-specific toxicity and solubility issues. This could be solved by nanoformulating these compounds, which will overcome their barriers and specifically deliver these molecules to the designated sites. Nanoparticles as mentioned above have been used in recent times to target the CSCs in solid tumors; hence, nanotechnology could also be extended to target the SRPs active in CSCs. As there occurs crosstalks between the different signaling pathways in cancer development and progression, inhibition of one could lead to the downregulation of the others. Nanoparticles could provide a platform to carry multiple pathway inhibitors along with a conventional chemotherapeutic to target the pathways. Although there have been very few reports cited in literature in this direction, comprehending the biology of the pathways combined with the use of wide range of nanoparticles in dispose is a challenging area of research and leaves a futuristic hope for cancer treatment in killing the CSCs.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Ankita Borah and Ankit Rochani would like to acknowledge their sincere gratitude to the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT), Japan for the financial support under the Monbukagakusho fellowship during the research. Also, part of this study has been supported by a grant for the program of the strategic research foundation at private universities S1101017, organized by the MEXT, Japan since April 2012.</p></ack><notes><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">1Bonnet D, Dick JE. <article-title>Human acute myeloid leukemia is organized as a hierarchy that originates from a primitive hematopoietic cell</article-title>. <source>Nat Med</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>730</fpage>&#8211;737.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9212098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">2Singh SK, Clarke ID, Terasaki M, Bonn VE, Hawkins C, Squire J et al. <article-title>Identification of a cancer stem cell in human brain tumors</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>5821</fpage>&#8211;5828.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14522905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">3Al-Hajj M, Wicha MS, Benito-Hernandez A, Morrison SJ, Clarke MF. <article-title>Prospective identification of tumorigenic breast cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>100</volume>: <fpage>3983</fpage>&#8211;3988.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12629218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">4Li C, Heidt DG, Dalerba P, Burant CF, Zhang L, Adsay V et al. <article-title>Identification of pancreatic cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>1030</fpage>&#8211;1037.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17283135</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">5Maitland NJ, Collins AT. <article-title>Prostate cancer stem cells: a new target for therapy</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>2862</fpage>&#8211;2870.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18539965</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">6Lang SH, Frame FM, Collins AT. <article-title>Prostate cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>J Pathol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>217</volume>: <fpage>299</fpage>&#8211;306.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19040209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">7Jamieson CHM, Ailles LE, Dylla SJ, Muijtjens M, Jones C, Zehnder JL et al. <article-title>Granulocyte-macrophage progenitors as candidate leukemic stem cells in blast-crisis CML</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>351</volume>: <fpage>657</fpage>&#8211;667.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">8Korkaya H, Paulson A, Charafe-Jauffret E, Ginestier C, Brown M, Dutcher J et al. <article-title>Regulation of mammary stem/progenitor cells by PTEN/Akt/&#946;-catenin signaling</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1000121</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19492080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">9Ingham PW, McMahon AP. <article-title>Hedgehog signaling in animal development: paradigms and principles</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>3059</fpage>&#8211;3087.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">10Micchelli CA, The I, Selva E, Mogila V, Perrimon N. <article-title>Rasp, a putative transmembrane acyltransferase, is required for Hedgehog signaling</article-title>. <source>Development</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>&#8211;851.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11861468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">11Sv&#228;rd J, Henricson KH, Persson-Lek M, Rozell B, Lauth M, Bergstr&#246;m &#197; et al. <article-title>Genetic elimination of suppressor of fused reveals an essential repressor function in the mammalian hedgehog signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#8211;197.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16459298</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">12Ruiz iAltaba A, S&#225;nchez P, Dahmane N. <article-title>Gli and hedgehog in cancer: tumours, embryos and stem cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>361</fpage>&#8211;372.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12044012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">13Roessler E, Belloni E, Gaudenz K, Jay P, Berta P, Scherer SW et al. <article-title>Mutations in the human Sonic Hedgehog gene cause holoprosencephaly</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>357</fpage>&#8211;360.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8896572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">14Hahn H, Wicking C, Zaphiropoulous PG, Gailani MR, Shanley S, Chidambaram A et al. <article-title>Mutations of the human homolog of Drosophila patched in the nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>85</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>&#8211;851.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8681379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">15Johnson RL, Rothman AL, Xie J, Goodrich L V, Bare JW, Bonifas JM et al. <article-title>Human homolog of patched, a candidate gene for the basal cell nevus syndrome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1996</year>; <volume>272</volume>: <fpage>1668</fpage>&#8211;1671.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8658145</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">16Kiesslich T, Berr F, Alinger B, Kemmerling R, Pichler M, Ocker M et al. <article-title>Current status of therapeutic targeting of developmental signalling pathways in oncology</article-title>. <source>Curr Pharm Biotechnol</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>2184</fpage>&#8211;2220.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21605074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">17Berman DM, Karhadkar SS, Maitra A, Montes De Oca R, Gerstenblith MR, Briggs K et al. <article-title>Widespread requirement for Hedgehog ligand stimulation in growth of digestive tract tumours</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>425</volume>: <fpage>846</fpage>&#8211;851.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14520411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">18Watkins DN, Berman DM, Burkholder SG, Wang B, Beachy PA, Baylin SB. <article-title>Hedgehog signalling within airway epithelial progenitors and in small-cell lung cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>422</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#8211;317.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12629553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">19Clement V, Sanchez P, de Tribolet N, Radovanovic I, Ruiz i, Altaba A. <article-title>HEDGEHOG-GLI1 signaling regulates human glioma growth, cancer stem cell self-renewal, and tumorigenicity</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;172.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17196391</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">20Dierks C, Beigi R, Guo GR, Zirlik K, Stegert MR, Manley P et al. <article-title>Expansion of Bcr-Abl-positive leukemic stem cells is dependent on Hedgehog pathway activation</article-title>. <source>Cancer Cell</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>238</fpage>&#8211;249.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18772113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">21Feldmann G, Dhara S, Fendrich V, Bedja D, Beaty R, Mullendore M et al. <article-title>Blockade of hedgehog signaling inhibits pancreatic cancer invasion and metastases: a new paradigm for combination therapy in solid cancers</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>2187</fpage>&#8211;2196.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17332349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">22Peacock CD, Wang Q, Gesell GS, Corcoran-Schwartz IM, Jones E, Kim J et al. <article-title>Hedgehog signaling maintains a tumor stem cell compartment in multiple myeloma</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>4048</fpage>&#8211;4053.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">23Zhao C, Chen A, Jamieson CH, Fereshteh M, Abrahamsson A, Blum J et al. <article-title>Hedgehog signalling is essential for maintenance of cancer stem cells in myeloid leukaemia</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>458</volume>: <fpage>776</fpage>&#8211;779.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19169242</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">24Ferretti E, De Smaele E, Miele E, Laneve P, Po A, Pelloni M et al. <article-title>Concerted microRNA control of Hedgehog signalling in cerebellar neuronal progenitor and tumour cells</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>2616</fpage>&#8211;2627.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18756266</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">25Liao X, Siu MKY, Au CWH, Wong ESY, Chan HY, Ip PPC et al. <article-title>Aberrant activation of hedgehog signaling pathway in ovarian cancers: effect on prognosis, cell invasion and differentiation</article-title>. <source>Carcinogenesis</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;140.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19028702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">26Sheng T, Li C, Zhang X, Chi S, He N, Chen K et al. <article-title>Activation of the hedgehog pathway in advanced prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>29</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15482598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">27Fan L, Pepicelli C V, Dibble CC, Catbagan W, Zarycki JL, Laciak R et al. <article-title>Hedgehog signaling promotes prostate xenograft tumor growth</article-title>. <source>Endocrinology</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>145</volume>: <fpage>3961</fpage>&#8211;3970.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15132968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">28Sanchez P, Hern&#225;ndez AM, Stecca B, Kahler AJ, DeGueme AM, Barrett A et al. <article-title>Inhibition of prostate cancer proliferation by interference with SONIC HEDGEHOG-GLI1 signaling</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>12561</fpage>&#8211;12566.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314219</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">29Liu S, Dontu G, Mantle ID, Patel S, Ahn NS, Jackson KW et al. <article-title>Hedgehog signaling and Bmi-1 regulate self-renewal of normal and malignant human mammary stem cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>6063</fpage>&#8211;6071.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">30Artavanis-Tsakonas S. <article-title>Notch signaling: cell fate control and signal integration in development</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>284</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&#8211;776.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10221902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">31Roy M, Pear WS, Aster JC. <article-title>The multifaceted role of Notch in cancer</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>52</fpage>&#8211;59.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17178457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">32Reedijk M, Odorcic S, Chang L, Zhang H, Miller N, McCready DR et al. <article-title>High-level coexpression of JAG1 and NOTCH1 is observed in human breast cancer and is associated with poor overall survival</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>8530</fpage>&#8211;8537.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16166334</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">33Dickson BC, Mulligan AM, Zhang H, Lockwood G, O'Malley FP, Egan SE et al. <article-title>High-level JAG1 mRNA and protein predict poor outcome in breast cancer</article-title>. <source>Mod Pathol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>685</fpage>&#8211;693.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17507991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">34Farnie G, Clarke RB. <article-title>Mammary stem cells and breast cancer&#8211;role of Notch signalling</article-title>. <source>Stem Cell Rev</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>&#8211;175.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17873349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">35Sansone P, Storci G, Giovannini C, Pandolfi S, Pianetti S, Taffurelli M et al. <article-title>p66Shc/Notch-3 interplay controls self-renewal and hypoxia survival in human stem/progenitor cells of the mammary gland expanded <italic>in vitro</italic> as mammospheres</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>807</fpage>&#8211;815.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158237</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">36Gustafsson M V, Zheng X, Pereira T, Gradin K, Jin S, Lundkvist J et al. <article-title>Hypoxia requires Notch signaling to maintain the undifferentiated cell state</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&#8211;628.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16256737</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">37Ellisen LW, Bird J, West DC, Soreng AL, Reynolds TC, Smith SD et al. <article-title>TAN-1, the human homolog of the Drosophila notch gene, is broken by chromosomal translocations in T lymphoblastic neoplasms</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>1991</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>649</fpage>&#8211;661.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1831692</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">38Weng AP, Ferrando AA, Lee W, Morris JP, Silverman LB, Sanchez-Irizarry C et al. <article-title>Activating mutations of NOTCH1 in human T cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>306</volume>: <fpage>269</fpage>&#8211;271.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15472075</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">39Wang YH, Li F, Luo B, Wang XH, Sun HC, Liu S et al. <article-title>A side population of cells from a human pancreatic carcinoma cell line harbors cancer stem cell characteristics</article-title>. <source>Neoplasma</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>56</volume>: <fpage>371</fpage>&#8211;378.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19580337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">40Castellanos JA, Merchant NB, Nagathihalli NS. <article-title>Emerging targets in pancreatic cancer: and cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Onco Targets Ther</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>1261</fpage>&#8211;1267.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24049451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">41Wang Z, Li Y, Kong D, Banerjee S, Ahmad A, Azmi AS et al. <article-title>Acquisition of epithelial-mesenchymal transition phenotype of gemcitabine-resistant pancreatic cancer cells is linked with activation of the notch signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>69</volume>: <fpage>2400</fpage>&#8211;2407.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19276344</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">42Long J, Zhang Y, Yu X, Yang J, LeBrun DG, Chen C et al. <article-title>Overcoming drug resistance in pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>Expert Opin Ther Targets</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>817</fpage>&#8211;828.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21391891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">43Komiya Y, Habas R. <article-title>Wnt signal transduction pathways</article-title>. <source>Organogenesis</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>&#8211;75.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19279717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">44MacDonald BT, Tamai K, He X. <article-title>Wnt/??-catenin signaling: components, mechanisms, and diseases</article-title>. <source>Dev Cell</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>9</fpage>&#8211;26.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19619488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">45Gordon MD, Nusse R. <article-title>Wnt signaling: multiple pathways, multiple receptors, and multiple transcription factors</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>22429</fpage>&#8211;22433.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16793760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">46Bilic J, Huang Y-L, Davidson G, Zimmermann T, Cruciat C-M, Bienz M et al. <article-title>Wnt induces LRP6 signalosomes and promotes dishevelled-dependent LRP6 phosphorylation</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>316</volume>: <fpage>1619</fpage>&#8211;1622.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17569865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">47Mosimann C, Hausmann G, Basler K. <article-title>Beta-catenin hits chromatin: regulation of Wnt target gene activation</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>&#8211;286.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19305417</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">48Willert K, Jones KA. <article-title>Wnt signaling: is the party in the nucleus</article-title>? <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>1394</fpage>&#8211;1404.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16751178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">49Kramps T, Peter O, Brunner E, Nellen D, Froesch B, Chatterjee S et al. <article-title>Wnt/Wingless signaling requires BCL9/legless-mediated recruitment of pygopus to the nuclear &#946;-catenin-TCF complex</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>109</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#8211;60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11955446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">50Jessen S, Gu B, Dai X. <article-title>Pygopus and the Wnt signaling pathway: a diverse set of connections</article-title>. <source>Bioessays</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>448</fpage>&#8211;456.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18404694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">51Fearon ER, Vogelstein B. <article-title>A genetic model for colorectal tumorigenesis</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>1990</year>; <volume>61</volume>: <fpage>759</fpage>&#8211;767.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2188735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">52Morin PJ, Sparks AB, Korinek V, Barker N, Clevers H, Vogelstein B et al. <article-title>Activation of beta-catenin-Tcf signaling in colon cancer by mutations in beta-catenin or APC</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>1787</fpage>&#8211;1790.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9065402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">53Iwao K, Nakamori S, Kameyama M, Imaoka S, Kinoshita M, Fukui T et al. <article-title>Activation of the ??-catenin gene by interstitial deletions involving exon 3 in primary colorectal carcinomas without adenomatous polyposis coli mutations</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1021</fpage>&#8211;1026.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9500465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">54Sparks AB, Morin PJ, Vogelstein B, Kinzler KW. <article-title>Mutational analysis of the APC/beta-catenin/Tcf pathway in colorectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1130</fpage>&#8211;1134.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9515795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">55Mirabelli-Primdahl L, Gryfe R, Kim H, Millar A, Luceri C, Dale D et al. <article-title>??-Catenin mutations are specific for colorectal carcinomas with microsatellite instability but occur in endometrial carcinomas irrespective of mutator pathway</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>59</volume>: <fpage>3346</fpage>&#8211;3351.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10416591</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">56Nhieu JT, Renard CA, Wei Y, Cherqui D, Zafrani ES, Buendia MA. <article-title>Nuclear accumulation of mutated beta-catenin in hepatocellular carcinoma is associated with increased cell proliferation</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>703</fpage>&#8211;710.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10487827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">57Palacios J, Gamallo C. <article-title>Mutations in the &#946;-catenin gene (CTNNB1) in endometrioid ovarian carcinomas</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>1344</fpage>&#8211;1347.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9537226</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">58Gamallo C, Palacios J, Moreno G, Calvo de Mora J, Su&#225;rez A, Armas A. <article-title>beta-catenin expression pattern in stage I and II ovarian carcinomas : relationship with beta-catenin gene mutations, clinicopathological features, and clinical outcome</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>155</volume>: <fpage>527</fpage>&#8211;536.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">59Groden J, Thliveris A, Samowitz W, Carlson M, Gelbert L, Albertsen H et al. <article-title>Identification and characterization of the familial adenomatous polyposis coli gene</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>1991</year>; <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>589</fpage>&#8211;600.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1651174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">60Kinzler KW, Nilbert MC, Su LK, Vogelstein B, Bryan TM, Levy DB et al. <article-title>Identification of FAP locus genes from chromosome 5q21</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1991</year>; <volume>253</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>&#8211;665.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1651562</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">61Korinek V, Barker N, Morin PJ, van Wichen D, de Weger R, Kinzler KW et al. <article-title>Constitutive transcriptional activation by a beta-catenin-Tcf complex in APC-/- colon carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>275</volume>: <fpage>1784</fpage>&#8211;1787.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9065401</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">62Clevers H. <article-title>Wnt/beta-catenin signaling in development and disease</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>469</fpage>&#8211;480.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17081971</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">63Pinto D, Gregorieff A, Begthel H, Clevers H. <article-title>Canonical Wnt signals are essential for homeostasis of the intestinal epithelium</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1709</fpage>&#8211;1713.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12865297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">64Van Genderen C, Okamura RM, Farinas I, Quo RG, Parslow TG, Bruhn L et al. <article-title>Development of several organs that require inductive epithelial- mesenchymal interactions is impaired in LEF-1-deficient mice</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>2691</fpage>&#8211;2703.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7958926</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">65Andrade AC, Nilsson O, Barnes KM, Baron J. <article-title>Wnt gene expression in the post-natal growth plate: regulation with chondrocyte differentiation</article-title>. <source>Bone</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1361</fpage>&#8211;1369.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17337262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">66Eaves CJ, Humphries RK. <article-title>Acute myeloid leukemia and the Wnt pathway</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>362</volume>: <fpage>2326</fpage>&#8211;2327.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20554989</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">67Nusse R, Fuerer C, Ching W, Harnish K, Logan C, Zeng A et al. <article-title>Wnt signaling and stem cell control</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>73</volume>: <fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;66.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19028988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">68Reya T, Clevers H. <article-title>Wnt signalling in stem cells and cancer</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>434</volume>: <fpage>843</fpage>&#8211;850.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15829953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">69Vermeulen L, De Sousa E, Melo F, van der Heijden M, Cameron K, de Jong JH, Borovski T et al. <article-title>Wnt activity defines colon cancer stem cells and is regulated by the microenvironment</article-title>. <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>468</fpage>&#8211;476.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20418870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">70Malanchi I, Peinado H, Kassen D, Hussenet T, Metzger D, Chambon P et al. <article-title>Cutaneous cancer stem cell maintenance is dependent on beta-catenin signalling</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>452</volume>: <fpage>650</fpage>&#8211;653.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18385740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">71Reya T, Duncan AW, Ailles L, Domen J, Scherer DC, Willert K et al. <article-title>A role for Wnt signalling in self-renewal of haematopoietic stem cells</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>423</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>&#8211;414.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12717450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">72Brabletz T, Jung A, Reu S, Porzner M, Hlubek F, Kunz-Schughart LA et al. <article-title>Variable beta-catenin expression in colorectal cancers indicates tumor progression driven by the tumor environment</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>98</volume>: <fpage>10356</fpage>&#8211;10361.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11526241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">73Jung A, Schrauder M, Oswald U, Knoll C, Sellberg P, Palmqvist R et al. <article-title>The invasion front of human colorectal adenocarcinomas shows co-localization of nuclear beta-catenin, cyclin D1, and p16INK4A and is a region of low proliferation</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>159</volume>: <fpage>1613</fpage>&#8211;1617.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11696421</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">74Kirchner T, Brabletz T. <article-title>Patterning and nuclear beta-catenin expression in the colonic adenoma-carcinoma sequence. Analogies with embryonic gastrulation</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>157</volume>: <fpage>1113</fpage>&#8211;1121.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11021815</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">75Gil J, Bernard D, Peters G. <article-title>Role of polycomb group proteins in stem cell self-renewal and cancer</article-title>. <source>DNA Cell Biol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>&#8211;125.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15699631</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">76Jacobs JJ, Kieboom K, Marino S, DePinho RA, van Lohuizen M. <article-title>The oncogene and Polycomb-group gene bmi-1 regulates cell proliferation and senescence through the ink4a locus</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>1999</year>; <volume>397</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>&#8211;168.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9923679</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">77Alkema MJ, Wiegant J, Raap AK, Berns A, van Lohuizen M. <article-title>Characterization and chromosomal localization of the human proto-oncogene BMI-1</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
<year>1993</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1597</fpage>&#8211;1603.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8268912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">78Itahana K, Zou Y, Itahana Y, Martinez J-L, Beausejour C, Jacobs JJL et al. <article-title>Control of the replicative life span of human fibroblasts by p16 and the polycomb protein Bmi-1</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell Biol</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>&#8211;401.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12482990</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">79Van Der Lugt NMT, Domen J, Linders K, Van Roon M, Robanus-Maandag E, Te Riele H et al. <article-title>Posterior transformation, neurological abnormalities, and severe hematopoietic defects in mice with a targeted deletion of the bmi-1 proto-oncogene</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>757</fpage>&#8211;769.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7926765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">80Haupt Y, Alexander WS, Barri G, Klinken SP, Adams JM. <article-title>Novel zinc finger gene implicated as myc collaborator by retrovirally accelerated lymphomagenesis in E mu-myc transgenic mice</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>
<year>1991</year>; <volume>65</volume>: <fpage>753</fpage>&#8211;763.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1904009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">81Sawa M, Yamamoto K, Yokozawa T, Kiyoi H, Hishida A, Kajiguchi T et al. <article-title>BMI-1 is highly expressed in M0-subtype acute myeloid leukemia</article-title>. <source>Int J Hematol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>42</fpage>&#8211;47.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16105758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">82Vonlanthen S, Heighway J, Altermatt HJ, Gugger M, Kappeler A, Borner MM et al. <article-title>The bmi-1 oncoprotein is differentially expressed in non-small cell lung cancer and correlates with INK4A-ARF locus expression</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>84</volume>: <fpage>1372</fpage>&#8211;1376.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11355949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">83Zhang F, Sui L, Xin T. <article-title>Correlations of Bmi-1 expression and telomerase activity in ovarian cancer tissues</article-title>. <source>Exp Oncol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>&#8211;74.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18438345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">84Dimri GP, Martinez JL, Jacobs JJL, Keblusek P, Itahana K, Van Lohuizen M et al. <article-title>The Bmi-1 oncogene induces telomerase activity and immortalizes human mammary epithelial cells</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>4736</fpage>&#8211;4745.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12183433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">85Cui H, Hu B, Li T, Ma J, Alam G, Gunning WT et al. <article-title>Bmi-1 is essential for the tumorigenicity of neuroblastoma cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Pathol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>170</volume>: <fpage>1370</fpage>&#8211;1378.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17392175</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">86Bertolini G, Roz L, Perego P, Tortoreto M, Fontanella E, Gatti L et al. <article-title>Highly tumorigenic lung cancer CD133+ cells display stem-like features and are spared by cisplatin treatment</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>16281</fpage>&#8211;16286.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19805294</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">87Yin T, Wei H, Gou S, Shi P, Yang Z, Zhao G et al. <article-title>Cancer stem-like cells enriched in Panc-1 spheres possess increased migration ability and resistance to gemcitabine</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1595</fpage>&#8211;1604.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21673909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">88Raaphorst FM. <article-title>Deregulated expression of Polycomb-group oncogenes in human malignant lymphomas and epithelial tumors</article-title>. <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>R93</fpage>&#8211;R100.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15809278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">89Zhang S, Balch C, Chan MW, Lai H-C, Matei D, Schilder JM et al. <article-title>Identification and characterization of ovarian cancer-initiating cells from primary human tumors</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>4311</fpage>&#8211;4320.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18519691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">90Van Leenders GJLH, Dukers D, Hessels D, van den Kieboom SWM, Hulsbergen CA, Witjes JA et al. <article-title>Polycombgroup oncogenes EZH2, BMI1, and RING1 are overexpressed in prostate cancer with adverse pathologic and clinical features</article-title>. <source>Eur Urol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>52</volume>: <fpage>455</fpage>&#8211;463.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17134822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">91Glinsky G V, Berezovska O, Glinskii AB. <article-title>Microarray analysis identifies a death-from-cancer signature predicting therapy failure in patients with multiple types of cancer</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>115</volume>: <fpage>1503</fpage>&#8211;1521.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15931389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">92Neuzil J, Stantic M, Zobalova R, Chladova J, Wang X, Prochazka L et al. <article-title>Tumour-initiating cells vs. cancer &#8216;stem' cells and CD133: what's in the name</article-title>? <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>355</volume>: <fpage>855</fpage>&#8211;859.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17307142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">93Visvader JE, Lindeman GJ. <article-title>Cancer stem cells in solid tumours: accumulating evidence and unresolved questions</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>755</fpage>&#8211;768.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784658</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">94McDermott SP, Wicha MS. <article-title>Targeting breast cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Oncol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>4</volume>: <fpage>404</fpage>&#8211;419.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20599450</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">95Lobo NA, Shimono Y, Qian D, Clarke MF. <article-title>The biology of cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>675</fpage>&#8211;699.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17645413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">96S&#225;nchez-Garc&#237;a I, Vicente-Due&#241;as C, Cobaleda C. <article-title>The theoretical basis of cancer-stem-cell-based therapeutics of cancer: can it be put into practice</article-title>? <source>Bioessays</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1269</fpage>&#8211;1280.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18022789</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">97Taipale J, Chen JK, Cooper MK, Wang B, Mann RK, Milenkovic L et al. <article-title>Effects of oncogenic mutations in Smoothened and Patched can be reversed by cyclopamine</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2000</year>; <volume>406</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>&#8211;1009.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10984056</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">98Goodrich L V, Scott MP. <article-title>Hedgehog and patched in neural development and disease</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<year>1998</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1243</fpage>&#8211;1257.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9883719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">99Beachy PA, Cooper MK, Young KE, Von Kessler DP, Park WJ, Hall TMT et al. <article-title>Multiple roles of cholesterol in hedgehog protein biogenesis and signaling</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Symp Quant Biol</source>
<year>1997</year>; <volume>62</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;204.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9598352</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">100Bar EE, Chaudhry A, Lin A, Fan X, Schreck K, Matsui W et al. <article-title>Cyclopamine-mediated hedgehog pathway inhibition depletes stem-like cancer cells in glioblastoma</article-title>. <source>Stem Cells</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>2524</fpage>&#8211;2533.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17628016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">101Von Hoff DD, LoRusso PM, Rudin CM, Reddy JC, Yauch RL, Tibes R et al. <article-title>Inhibition of the hedgehog pathway in advanced basal-cell carcinoma</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>361</volume>: <fpage>1164</fpage>&#8211;1172.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19726763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">102Olive KP, Jacobetz MA, Davidson CJ, Gopinathan A, McIntyre D, Honess D et al. <article-title>Inhibition of Hedgehog signaling enhances delivery of chemotherapy in a mouse model of pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>324</volume>: <fpage>1457</fpage>&#8211;1461.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19460966</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib103"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">103Skvara H, Kalthoff F, Meingassner JG, Wolff-Winiski B, Aschauer H, Kelleher JF et al. <article-title>Topical treatment of Basal cell carcinomas in nevoid Basal cell carcinoma syndrome with a smoothened inhibitor</article-title>. <source>J Invest Dermatol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>1735</fpage>&#8211;1744.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21430703</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">104Stuetz A, de Rie MA, Skvara H, Mickel L, Schuster C, Stary G et al. <article-title>FC24 LDE225, a specific smoothened inhibitor, for the topical treatment of nevoid basal cell carcinoma syndrome (Gorlin's syndrome)</article-title>. <source>Melanoma Res</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>20</volume>: <fpage>e40</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">105Stanton BZ, Peng LF, Maloof N, Nakai K, Wang X, Duffner JL et al. <article-title>A small molecule that binds Hedgehog and blocks its signaling in human cells</article-title>. <source>Nat Chem Biol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>154</fpage>&#8211;156.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19151731</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">106Hyman JM, Firestone AJ, Heine VM, Zhao Y, Ocasio CA, Han K et al. <article-title>Small-molecule inhibitors reveal multiple strategies for Hedgehog pathway blockade</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>106</volume>: <fpage>14132</fpage>&#8211;14137.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19666565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">107Lauth M, Bergstr&#246;m A, Shimokawa T, Toftg&#229;rd R. <article-title>Inhibition of GLI-mediated transcription and tumor cell growth by small-molecule antagonists</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>104</volume>: <fpage>8455</fpage>&#8211;8460.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17494766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">108&#346;lusarz A, Shenouda NS, Sakla MS, Drenkhahn SK, Narula AS, MacDonald RS et al. <article-title>Common botanical compounds inhibit the hedgehog signaling pathway in prostate cancer</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>3382</fpage>&#8211;3390.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20395211</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">109Elamin MH, Shinwari Z, Hendrayani SF, Al-Hindi H, Al-Shail E, Khafaga Y et al. <article-title>Curcumin inhibits the Sonic Hedgehog signaling pathway and triggers apoptosis in medulloblastoma cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Carcinog</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>302</fpage>&#8211;314.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib110"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">110Tang GQ, Yan TQ, Guo W, Ren TT, Peng CL, Zhao H et al. <article-title>(-)-Epigallocatechin-3-gallate induces apoptosis and suppresses proliferation by inhibiting the human Indian Hedgehog pathway in human chondrosarcoma cells</article-title>. <source>J Cancer Res Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>136</volume>: <fpage>1179</fpage>&#8211;1185.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20127255</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib111"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">111Fouladi M, Stewart CF, Olson J, Wagner LM, Onar-Thomas A, Kocak M et al. <article-title>Phase I trial of MK-0752 in children with refractory CNS malignancies: a pediatric brain tumor consortium study</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>3529</fpage>&#8211;3534.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21825264</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib112"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">112Pandya K, Meeke K, Clementz AG, Rogowski A, Roberts J, Miele L et al. <article-title>Targeting both Notch and ErbB-2 signalling pathways is required for prevention of ErbB-2-positive breast tumour recurrence</article-title>. <source>Br J Cancer</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>105</volume>: <fpage>796</fpage>&#8211;806.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21847123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib113"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">113Deangelo DJ, Stone RM, Silverman LB, Stock W, Attar EC, Fearen I et al. <article-title>A phase I clinical trial of the notch inhibitor MK-0752 in patients with T-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia/lymphoma (T-ALL) and other leukemias</article-title>. <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>6585</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib114"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">114Wei P, Walls M, Qiu M, Ding R, Denlinger RH, Wong A et al. <article-title>Evaluation of selective gamma-secretase inhibitor PF-03084014 for its antitumor efficacy and gastrointestinal safety to guide optimal clinical trial design</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1618</fpage>&#8211;1628.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20530712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib115"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">115Oncomed Pharmaceuticals. <article-title>A Phase 1 Dose Escalation Study of OMP-21M18 in Subjects With Solid Tumors</article-title>. ClinicalTrials.gov <year>2012</year>, available at https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00744562.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib116"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">116Gale NW, Dominguez MG, Noguera I, Pan L, Hughes V, Valenzuela DM et al. <article-title>Haploinsufficiency of delta-like 4 ligand results in embryonic lethality due to major defects in arterial and vascular development</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>15949</fpage>&#8211;15954.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib117"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">117Duarte A, Hirashima M, Benedito R, Trindade A, Diniz P, Bekman E et al. <article-title>Dosage-sensitive requirement for mouse Dll4 in artery development</article-title>. <source>Genes Dev</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>2474</fpage>&#8211;2478.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15466159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib118"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">118Ridgway J, Zhang G, Wu Y, Stawicki S, Liang W-C, Chanthery Y et al. <article-title>Inhibition of Dll4 signalling inhibits tumour growth by deregulating angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>444</volume>: <fpage>1083</fpage>&#8211;1087.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17183323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib119"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">119Moellering RE, Cornejo M, Davis TN, Del Bianco C, Aster JC, Blacklow SC et al. <article-title>Direct inhibition of the NOTCH transcription factor complex</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>462</volume>: <fpage>182</fpage>&#8211;188.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19907488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib120"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">120Funahashi Y, Hernandez SL, Das I, Ahn A, Huang J, Vorontchikhina M et al. <article-title>A notch1 ectodomain construct inhibits endothelial notch signaling, tumor growth, and angiogenesis</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>4727</fpage>&#8211;4735.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18559519</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib121"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">121Wang Z, Zhang Y, Li Y, Banerjee S, Liao J, Sarkar FH. <article-title>Down-regulation of Notch-1 contributes to cell growth inhibition and apoptosis in pancreatic cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source>
<year>2006</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>483</fpage>&#8211;493.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16546962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib122"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">122Kallifatidis G, Labsch S, Rausch V, Mattern J, Gladkich J, Moldenhauer G et al. <article-title>Sulforaphane increases drug-mediated cytotoxicity toward cancer stem-like cells of pancreas and prostate</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>188</fpage>&#8211;195.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20940707</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib123"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">123Kawahara T, Kawaguchi-Ihara N, Okuhashi Y, Itoh M, Nara N, Tohda S. <article-title>Cyclopamine and quercetin suppress the growth of leukemia and lymphoma cells</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>4629</fpage>&#8211;4632.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20032413</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib124"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">124Nagayama S, Fukukawa C, Katagiri T, Okamoto T, Aoyama T, Oyaizu N et al. <article-title>Therapeutic potential of antibodies against FZD 10, a cell-surface protein, for synovial sarcomas</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>6201</fpage>&#8211;6212.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16007199</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib125"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">125He B, Reguart N, You L, Mazieres J, Xu Z, Lee AY et al. <article-title>Blockade of Wnt-1 signaling induces apoptosis in human colorectal cancer cells containing downstream mutations</article-title>. <source>Oncogene</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>3054</fpage>&#8211;3058.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15735684</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib126"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">126You L, He B, Xu Z, Uematsu K, Mazieres J, Fujii N et al. <article-title>An anti-Wnt-2 monoclonal antibody induces apoptosis in malignant melanoma cells and inhibits tumor growth</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>64</volume>: <fpage>5385</fpage>&#8211;5389.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15289346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib127"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">127Fujii N, You L, Xu Z, Uematsu K, Shan J, He B et al. <article-title>An antagonist of dishevelled protein-protein interaction suppresses beta-catenin-dependent tumor cell growth</article-title>. <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>67</volume>: <fpage>573</fpage>&#8211;579.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17234765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib128"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">128Shan J, Shi D-L, Wang J, Zheng J. <article-title>Identification of a specific inhibitor of the dishevelled PDZ domain</article-title>. <source>Biochemistry</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>15495</fpage>&#8211;15503.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16300398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib129"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">129Takahashi-Yanaga F, Kahn M. <article-title>Targeting Wnt signaling: can we safely eradicate cancer stem cells</article-title>? <source>Cancer Res</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>3153</fpage>&#8211;3162.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib130"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">130Emami KH, Nguyen C, Ma H, Kim DH, Jeong KW, Eguchi M et al. <article-title>A small molecule inhibitor of beta-catenin/CREB-binding protein transcription [corrected]</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>101</volume>: <fpage>12682</fpage>&#8211;12687.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15314234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib131"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">131Bommi P V, Dimri M, Sahasrabuddhe AA, Khandekar JD, Dimri GP. <article-title>The polycomb group protein BMI1 is a transcriptional target of HDAC inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>2663</fpage>&#8211;2673.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20543557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib132"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">132Wu J, Hu D, Yang G, Zhou J, Yang C, Gao Y et al. <article-title>Down-regulation of BMI-1 cooperates with artemisinin on growth inhibition of nasopharyngeal carcinoma cells</article-title>. <source>J Cell Biochem</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>112</volume>: <fpage>1938</fpage>&#8211;1948.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21445878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib133"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">133Veeranarayanan S, Poulose AC, Mohamed MS, Varghese SH, Nagaoka Y, Yoshida Y et al. <article-title>Synergistic targeting of cancer and associated angiogenesis using triple-targeted dual-drug silica nanoformulations for theragnostics</article-title>. <source>Small</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>3476</fpage>&#8211;3489.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22865683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib134"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">134Raveendran S, Poulose AC, Yoshida Y, Maekawa T, Kumar DS. <article-title>Bacterial exopolysaccharide based nanoparticles for sustained drug delivery, cancer chemotherapy and bioimaging</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr Polym</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>&#8211;32.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23044101</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib135"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">135Raveendran S, Chauhan N, Palaninathan V, Nagaoka Y, Yoshida Y, Maekawa T et al. <article-title>Extremophilic polysaccharide for biosynthesis and passivation of gold nanoparticles and photothermal ablation of cancer cells</article-title>. <source>Part Part Syst Charact</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>54</fpage>&#8211;64.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib136"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">136Sivakumar B, Aswathy RG, Nagaoka Y, Iwai S, Venugopal K, Kato K et al. <article-title>Aptamer conjugated theragnostic multifunctional magnetic nanoparticles as a nanoplatform for pancreatic cancer therapy</article-title>. <source>RSC Adv</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>20579</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib137"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">137Raveendran S, Palaninathan V, Nagaoka Y, Fukuda T, Iwai S, Higashi T et al. <article-title>Extremophilic polysaccharide nanoparticles for cancer nanotherapy and evaluation of antioxidant properties</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Macromol</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>76</volume>: <fpage>310</fpage>&#8211;319.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25749105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib138"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">138Lee K, Drachev VP, Irudayaraj J. <article-title>DNA-gold nanoparticle reversible networks grown on cell surface marker sites: application in diagnostics</article-title>. <source>ACS Nano</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>2109</fpage>&#8211;2117.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21314177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib139"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">139Swaminathan SK, Roger E, Toti U, Niu L, Ohlfest JR, Panyam J. <article-title>CD133-targeted paclitaxel delivery inhibits local tumor recurrence in a mouse model of breast cancer</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>171</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>&#8211;287.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23871962</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib140"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">140Wei X, Senanayake TH, Warren G, Vinogradov S V. <article-title>Hyaluronic acid-based nanogel-drug conjugates with enhanced anticancer activity designed for the targeting of cd44-positive and drug-resistant tumors</article-title>. <source>Bioconjug Chem</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>658</fpage>&#8211;668.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23547842</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib141"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">141Liu Y, Lu WL, Guo J, Du J, Li T, Wu JW et al. <article-title>A potential target associated with both cancer and cancer stem cells: a combination therapy for eradication of breast cancer using vinorelbine stealthy liposomes plus parthenolide stealthy liposomes</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>&#8211;25.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18466993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib142"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">142Bostad M, Berg K, H&#248;gset A, Skarpen E, Stenmark H, Selbo PK. <article-title>Photochemical internalization (PCI) of immunotoxins targeting CD133 is specific and highly potent at femtomolar levels in cells with cancer stem cell properties</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>168</volume>: <fpage>317</fpage>&#8211;326.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23567040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib143"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">143Yang C, Xiong F, Wang J, Dou J, Chen J, Chen D et al. <article-title>Anti-ABCG2 monoclonal antibody in combination with paclitaxel nanoparticles against cancer stem-like cell activity in multiple myeloma</article-title>. <source>Nanomedicine (Lond)</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>45</fpage>&#8211;60.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23534833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib144"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">144Yu Z, Ni M, Xiong M, Zhang X, Cai G, Chen H et al. <article-title>Poly(lactic-co-glycolic acid) nanoparticles conjugated with CD133 aptamers for targeted salinomycin delivery to CD133+ osteosarcoma cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Int J Nanomedicine</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>2537</fpage>&#8211;2554.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25848270</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib145"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">145Takebe N, Harris PJ, Warren RQ, Ivy SP. <article-title>Targeting cancer stem cells by inhibiting Wnt, Notch, and Hedgehog pathways</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>97</fpage>&#8211;106.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21151206</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib146"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">146Maugeri-Sacc&#224; M, Zeuner A, De Maria R. <article-title>Therapeutic targeting of cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Front Oncol</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>10</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22655230</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib147"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">147Chenna V, Hu C, Pramanik D, Aftab BT, Karikari C, Campbell NR et al. <article-title>A polymeric nanoparticle encapsulated small-molecule inhibitor of Hedgehog signaling (NanoHHI) bypasses secondary mutational resistance to smoothened antagonists</article-title>. <source>Mol Cancer Ther</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;173.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22027695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib148"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">148Xu Y, Chenna V, Hu C, Sun HX, Khan M, Bai H et al. <article-title>Polymeric nanoparticle-encapsulated hedgehog pathway inhibitor HPI-1 (NanoHHI) inhibits systemic metastases in an orthotopic model of human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1291</fpage>&#8211;1302.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21868763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib149"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">149Lim KJ, Bisht S, Bar EE, Maitra A, Eberhart CG. <article-title>A polymeric nanoparticle formulation of curcumin inhibits growth, clonogenicity and stem-like fraction in malignant brain tumors</article-title>. <source>Cancer Biol Ther</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>&#8211;473.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21193839</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib150"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">150You J, Zhao J, Wen X, Wu C, Huang Q, Guan F et al. <article-title>Chemoradiation therapy using cyclopamine-loaded liquid&#8211;lipid nanoparticles and lutetium-177-labeled core-crosslinked polymeric micelles</article-title>. <source>J Control Release</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>202</volume>: <fpage>40</fpage>&#8211;48.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25637565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib151"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">151Kumar V, Mondal G, Slavik P, Rachagani S, Batra SK, Mahato RI. <article-title>Codelivery of small molecule Hedgehog inhibitor and miRNA for treating pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Pharm</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1289</fpage>&#8211;1298.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25679326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib152"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">152Mamaeva V, Rosenholm JM, Bate-Eya LT, Bergman L, Peuhu E, Duchanoy A et al. <article-title>Mesoporous silica nanoparticles as drug delivery systems for targeted inhibition of Notch signaling in cancer</article-title>. <source>Mol Ther</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>1538</fpage>&#8211;1546.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21629222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib153"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">153Lo WL, Chien Y, Chiou GY, Tseng LM, Hsu HS, Chang YL et al. <article-title>Nuclear localization signal-enhanced RNA interference of EZH2 and Oct4 in the eradication of head and neck squamous cell carcinoma-derived cancer stem cells</article-title>. <source>Biomaterials</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>3693</fpage>&#8211;3709.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22361100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Targeting strategies in self-renewal pathways in CSCs including their pharmacological antagonists and different nanoparticles used for formulation. (1) Hh ligand Inhibitors (2) GLI Antagonists (3) SMO Inhibitors (4) Anti-DLL4 Antibodies (5) &#947; &#8211;Secretase Inhibitors (6) MAML Inhibitors (7) Anti-FZD Antibodies (8) Wnt Ligand inhibitors (9) Wnt Transcription Complex Inhibitors (10) HDAC Inhibitors.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oncsis201535f1"/></fig><fig id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>(<bold>a</bold>) Schematic illustration of study design. Radioactive polymeric micelles containing 177Lu were injected intratumorally, and CPA-loaded lipid nanoparticles were injected intravenously. (<bold>b</bold>) Transmission electron microscopy images of CPA- LLP (negative staining). (Reproduced with permission from You J <italic>et al.</italic> 2015). (<bold>c</bold>&#8211;<bold>f</bold>) Effect of GDC-0449 and miR-let7b on cell viability in human pancreatic cancer cell line by micelles. HPAF-II, Capan-1, T3M4 and MIAPaCa-2 cells (5000/well) were treated with micelles containing (blue bars) GDC-0449 (0, 1, 5 and 10&#8201;&#956;<sc>M</sc>), (green bars) GDC-0449 and scrambled miRNA, (red bars) GDC-0449 and miR-let7b (10 pmol), (peach bars) miR-let7b alone, and (purple bars) blank for 48&#8201;h. Cell viability was measured by MTT assay at the end of incubation period. (Reproduced with permission from Kumar V <italic>et al.</italic> 2015).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oncsis201535f2"/></fig><fig id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Mesoporous silica nanoparticles (MsnPs) accumulate in the tumors, are biocompatible biodegradable and eliminated through renal excretion. (<bold>a</bold>) <italic>In vivo</italic> imaging of mice injected peritumoral with PEI-MSNPs or folate (FA)-MSNPs. Images of the abdominal area demonstrate accumulation of fluorescence in the bladder, and imaging of the dorsal area show accumulation of fluorescence in the tumors. Time lapse imaging of the abdominal area shows elimination of fluorescence within 48&#8201;h after injections (number of animals per group, <italic>n</italic>=4, two tumors per animal). (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>Ex vivo</italic> analyses (left) and quantification of fluorescence intensity (right) in organs from mice injected intravenous (i.v.) with FA-MSNPs. Mice were killed 196&#8201;h after injection (<italic>n</italic>=4). Please note the occasional signal from brain tissue, which most likely represents background fluorescence, as it is present also in untreated control animals. (<bold>c</bold>) Histological analysis of the brain, kidney, spleen, liver and lungs of untreated mice and FA-MSNPs-treated mice showed no morphological changes. Mice were killed 192&#8201;h after i.v.injection. (Reproduced with permission from Mamaeva V <italic>et al.</italic> 2011.)</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="oncsis201535f3"/></fig></floats-group></article>