
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Trials</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Trials</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Trials</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1745-6215</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4318133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25622594</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">544</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13063-014-0544-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Progressive high-load strength training compared with general low-load exercises in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy: study protocol for a randomised controlled trial </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ingwersen</surname><given-names>Kim G</given-names></name><address><email>kingwersen@health.sdu.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>Robin</given-names></name><address><email>robin.christensen@regionh.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sørensen</surname><given-names>Lilli</given-names></name><address><email>lilli.Soerensen@rsyd.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jørgensen</surname><given-names>Hans RI</given-names></name><address><email>hans.Ri.Joergensen@rsyd.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>Steen Lund</given-names></name><address><email>steen.lund.jensen@rn.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>Sten</given-names></name><address><email>sten.rasmussen@rn.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Søgaard</surname><given-names>Karen</given-names></name><address><email>ksogaard@health.sdu.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Juul-Kristensen</surname><given-names>Birgit</given-names></name><address><email>bjuul-kristensen@health.sdu.dk</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Institute of Sports Science and Clinical Biomechanics, University of Southern Denmark, Campusvej 55, DK-5230 Odense, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Physiotherapy Department, Hospital Lillebaelt, Vejle Hospital, Kabbeltoft 25, DK-7100 Vejle, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Department of Rheumatology, Musculoskeletal Statistics Unit, The Parker Institute, Copenhagen University Hospital, Bispebjerg and Frederiksberg, Nordre Fasanvej 57, road 8, entrance 19, DK-2000 Frederiksberg, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Orthopaedic Department, Shoulder Unit, Hospital Lillebaelt, Vejle Hospital, Kabbeltoft 25, DK-7100 Vejle, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>Orthopaedic Department, Shoulder Unit, Odense University Hospital, Svendborg Hospital, Valdemarsgade 53, DK-5700 Svendborg, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Shoulder Unit, Aalborg University Hospital, Farsø Hospital, Højgårdsvej 11, DK-9640 Farsø, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label/>Orthopaedic Surgery Research Unit, Aalborg University Hospital, Sdr. Skovvej 15, DK-9000 Aalborg, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label/>Department of Clinical Medicine, Aalborg University, Sdr. Skovvej 15, DK-9000 Aalborg, Denmark </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label/>Department of Health Sciences, Institute of Occupational Therapy, Physiotherapy and Radiography, Bergen University College, Inndalsveien 28, NO-5063 Bergen, Norway </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><elocation-id>27</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Ingwersen et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Shoulder pain is the third most common musculoskeletal disorder, often affecting people’s daily living and work capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The most common shoulder disorder is the subacromial impingement syndrome (SIS) which, among other pathophysiological changes, is often characterised by rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Exercise is often considered the primary treatment option for rotator cuff tendinopathy, but there is no consensus on which exercise strategy is the most effective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>As eccentric and high-load strength training have been shown to have a positive effect on patella and Achilles tendinopathy, the aim of this trial is to compare the efficacy of progressive high-load exercises with traditional low-load exercises in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Methods/Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The current study is a randomised, participant- and assessor-blinded, controlled multicentre trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>A total of 260 patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy will be recruited from three outpatient shoulder departments in Denmark, and randomised to either 12 weeks of progressive high-load strength training or to general low-load exercises. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Patients will receive six individually guided exercise sessions with a physiotherapist and perform home-based exercises three times a week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The primary outcome measure will be change from baseline to 12 weeks in the patient-reported outcome Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) questionnaire. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Previous studies of exercise treatment for SIS have not differentiated between subgroups of SIS and have often had methodological flaws, making it difficult to specifically design target treatment for patients diagnosed with SIS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it was considered important to focus on a subgroup such as tendinopathy, with a specific tailored intervention strategy based on evidence from other regions of the body, and to clearly describe the intervention in a methodologically strong study. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Trial registration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The trial was registered with Clinicaltrials.gov (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/study/NCT01984203?term=RoCTEx&amp;rank=1">NCT01984203</ext-link>) on 31 October 2013. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Shoulder</kwd><kwd>Impingement</kwd><kwd>Tendinopathy</kwd><kwd>Exercise</kwd><kwd>Rotator cuff</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>People with pain in the neck and shoulder region are often disabled to the point where they cannot live a normal life. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>The pain may also influence the person’s work capacity and financial as well as social situation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Pain in the shoulder is the third most common musculoskeletal disorder, and the lifetime prevalence is estimated to be between seven and 10% [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The prevalence for daily non-specific shoulder pain in a normal working population in an industrialised country is estimated to be 12% [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, up to 23% of the workforce seeking care from the healthcare system with a shoulder problem have been sick-listed for more than one week [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Clinically, the most common shoulder-related cause of contact with the healthcare system is subacromial impingement syndrome (SIS), which accounts for 33% of all shoulder-related healthcare contact [4,5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>SIS is generally considered to be a cluster of symptoms, rather than a single pathology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The Complaints of the Arm, Neck and/or Shoulder (CANS) model defines SIS as ‘Disorders that include the rotator cuff syndrome, tendonitis of the m. infraspinatus, m. supraspinatus and m. subscapularis, and bursitis in the shoulder area’ [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The cause of SIS is considered to be multi-factorial and involves an altered muscle recruitment pattern in the rotator cuff and thoracoscapular muscles, potentially in combination with alterations to the anatomical structures in the subacromial space. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These alterations may result in varying degrees of micro-traumas and degenerative pathophysiological changes in the rotator cuff muscle and surrounding tissue, which eventually can result in rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Generally, the clinically relevant pathophysiological conditions associated with the diagnosis of SIS, such as rotator cuff tendinopathy, are often difficult to identify objectively [7,8], and consequently the diagnosis of rotator cuff tendinopathy is primarily based on a combination of the patient’s history, clinical tests and ultrasonographic visualisation of changes in the rotator cuff tendons. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The Danish national clinical guidelines for the treatment of SIS recommend active rehabilitation strategies, and in cases where three to six months of exercise has been ineffective, arthroscopic subacromial decompression surgery can be considered [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These recommendations are, amongst others, based on the evidence that exercise has shown results comparable to arthroscopic subacromial decompression when evaluated on pain and patient-reported function [10-14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>However, the recommended guidelines rarely describe specific exercise programmes, nor are they sufficient in detail to be targeted at subgroups of SIS, such as rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This means there is no consensus on specific rehabilitation exercise programmes for SIS patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Among patients with Achilles or patella tendinopathy, studies of eccentric or progressive high-load exercises have shown promising effects on pain and function [15], and such exercises for chronic tendinopathy are often considered to be the first line of treatment [16-18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Some of the mechanisms believed to be responsible for the positive outcomes of eccentric exercises are reduced structural abnormalities, such as hypoechoic areas, irregular structures, neovascularisation and tendon thickness [19,20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The reasons for these changes could possibly be increased collagen type I synthesis [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Considering that collagen synthesis peaks at between 24 and 72 hours post-exercise [22], programmes prescribing daily training, such as those recommended for standard eccentric exercise programs, might not be optimal [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In support of this, very high-load eccentric training with relatively few repetitions and low frequency (twice a week) has shown equally beneficial effects on patella tendinopathy [24,25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Also, concentric heavy slow resistance exercises, without emphasis on the eccentric component, three times a week [25] has shown positive effects on patella tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, heavy slow resistance exercises seem to reduce abnormal fibrillar morphology among patients with patella tendinopathy [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>However, rotator cuff tendinopathy is often treated as any other subgroup of SIS, with a combination of low-load exercises for internal and external rotation of the shoulder joint, with an attempt to target the rotator cuff muscles and optimise muscle coordination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Only a few studies have used progressive exercises or eccentric exercises in patients with SIS, and they have reported positive results on pain and function [27-32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>But all these studies have primarily targeted SIS and did not differentiate between the underlying pathologies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Inclusion of different subgroups of SIS in the same trial makes it difficult to customise an optimal exercise programme and, possibly, to detect a clinically relevant change between different exercise strategies [8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Based on the evidence reported from studies on knee, Achilles and elbow tendons, applying eccentric or high-load exercise programmes in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy could be beneficial for patients’ pain, function and quality of life [8], and for ultrasonographic visualised structural changes [33-35], when compared with traditional exercise strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>But the rationale for using progressive high-load exercises is the diagnosis of tendinopathy and therefore, unlike existing studies, a study of eccentric or progressive high-load exercises should include only patients with tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, no studies have investigated the effect on pain and function of progressive high-load exercises compared with traditional low-load exercises in the subgroup of SIS patients primarily showing signs of rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>A proportion of patients diagnosed with tendinopathy will also have a concomitant pathology in the surrounding tissue of the glenohumeral joint. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Often corticosteroid injection into the subacromial space is used as an adjunct treatment for exercise interventions, if regarded relevant by the orthopaedic specialist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>It is uncertain if this concomitant treatment has an additional effect on the exercise treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The aim of the study is to determine in a randomised, double-blind controlled trial if a progressive high-load exercise programme for the rotator cuff muscles is superior to a traditional low-load exercise programme in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy, based on the primary endpoint; change in score on the Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) questionnaire [36] after 12 weeks of exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The second aim is to evaluate the possible interaction of concomitant use of corticosteroids with the exercise intervention. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Methods/Design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Study design </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>This trial, called the Rotator Cuff Tendinopathy Exercise (RoCTEx) trial, is a multicentre (three sites), stratified (by corticosteroid injection (yes or no)), randomised, controlled, observer- and patient-blinded superiority trial, with a two-group parallel design, to be conducted in Denmark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The primary endpoint will be 12 weeks after baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Patients will be randomised to either progressive high-load exercises or low-load exercises (block randomisation with a 1:1 allocation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>As illustrated in Figure 1, patients will also be assessed at one year from the baseline, referred to as the follow-up assessment.Figure 1Expected flow of participants through the study. LLE: low-load exercises; PHLE: Progressive high-load exercises. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Settings and locations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Patients will be recruited from the shoulder units at the outpatient clinics of orthopaedic departments at the Hospital Lillebaelt - Vejle Hospital, Aalborg University Hospital - Farsø Hospital and Odense University Hospital - Svendborg Hospital. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The orthopaedic specialists will perform a standardized initial screening of all patients referred to the shoulder units. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>If patients fulfil the eligibility criteria they will be referred to the principal investigator, who will perform the final eligibility assessment and give detailed information about the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Patients will be invited to participate if they meet the following inclusion criteria: between 18 and 65 years of age, have a current shoulder complaint lasting at least three months prior to the time of enrolment, pain is located in the proximal lateral aspect of the upper arm (C5 dermatome) that is aggravated by abduction, a positive ‘Full Can Test’ and/or Jobe’s test and/or Resisted External Rotation Test, a positive Hawkins-Kennedy test and/or Neer’s test, ultrasonographic verification of either tendon swelling, and/or presence of hypoechoic areas, calcification, fibrillar disruption and/or neovascularisation in the m. supraspinatus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Patients will be excluded if they fulfil any of the following exclusion criteria: Resting pain more than 40 mm on a visual analogue pain scale (range: 0 to 100), bilateral shoulder pain, less than 90 degrees of active elevation of the arm, a full thickness rupture in the rotator cuff tendon verified by ultrasonography, presence of calcification larger than 5 mm (vertical distance) verified by x-ray, corticosteroid injection within the last six weeks, a radiologically verified fracture, glenohumeral osteoarthritis, prior surgery or dislocation of the affected shoulder, a clinically suspected labrum lesion, symptomatic arthritis in the acromioclavicular joint, a frozen shoulder or symptoms derived from the cervical spine, sensory or motor deficit in the neck or arm, suspected competing diagnoses (for example, rheumatoid arthritis, cancer, neurological disorders, fibromyalgia, psychiatric illness), pregnancy or inability to understand spoken and written Danish. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Interventions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Generally, both groups will receive the same exercises (although they differ on the amount of load), attention and basic information about ergonomic corrections related to the daily use of the upper extremity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The exercise program will consist of six exercises: two exercises for the scapula stabilising muscles (push-up plus exercise and low row exercise), two for the rotator cuff muscles (scaption and side-lying external rotation), and two stretching and mobility exercises (posterior capsule stretch and scapulae retraction). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Patients will be instructed in performing home-based training three times per week, and will be seen for initial instruction in week one (60 minutes), and follow-up exercise sessions (30 minutes) in weeks two, three, four, six and nine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>The general information about the project and exercise instructions will be given through a DVD to minimise the influence of the physiotherapist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>On the first visit to the physiotherapist, the patients will receive detailed instructions on how to perform the exercise programme based on the instructions on the DVD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>At the follow-up exercise sessions corrections will be made, and weights adjusted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>The patients will be given a copy of the DVD and an exercise brochure to enable them to follow the instructions and exercises at home. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>The difference between the intervention and control groups will be the external load targeting exercises for the rotator cuff. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The intervention group will perform 12 weeks of progressive high-load exercises, gradually increasing the load from 15 repetitions maximum (RM) in week one to six RM in weeks nine to 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The intervention group will only be allowed to do isometric exercises if the pain exceeds 50 mm on the visual analogue scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The control group will perform 12 weeks of low-load exercises, performed with 20 RM from weeks one to 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For both groups, scapulae exercises will be performed with 20 RM, and stretching and mobility exercises will be performed five times, for 20 seconds each, in weeks one to 12. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Concomitant use of corticosteroid injections will be based on the orthopaedic specialist’s evaluation, in accordance with the department’s standard procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Between 25 and 50% of patients are expected to receive injections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The corticosteroid injections will be given to patients at the shoulder unit of the orthopaedic departments, after baseline assessment but before randomisation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Randomisation will be performed in a stratified manner to ensure even distribution of patients receiving and not receiving corticosteroid injections in the two exercise groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Outcome measures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The primary outcome measure will be change from baseline to week 12 in the patient-reported outcome Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand (DASH) questionnaire (0 to 100 score, 100 = no problems) [36], and reported as the difference in mean change between the groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The secondary endpoint assessment on the primary outcome will be performed 12 months after baseline (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The secondary outcome, measured at baseline and after 12 weeks, will include: the Shoulder injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (SOOS; 0 to 100 score, 100 = no problems) [37], the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HAD Scale; 0 to 21 score, 0 = no problems) [38], EuroQol instrument (EQ-5D index; −0.59 to 1 score, −0.59 = lowest health-related quality of life), EuroQol Visual Analogue Scale (EQ-VAS; 0 to 100 score, 0 = lowest health-related quality of life) [39], perceived pain at rest, general activity and maximum pain experienced during the previous 24 hours (visual analogue scale, 0 to 100 score, 0 = no pain) [40], maximum isometric voluntary contraction (MVC) of external and/or internal rotation and scaption measured by dynamometers, active and passive range of movement in scaption (0 to 180 degrees), external (0 to 90 degrees) and internal rotation (0 to 90 degrees) measured by goniometer, clinical tests (Scapula Assistance Test [41], Scapula Retraction Test (positive or negative) [42] and ultrasonography measurements (aggregated sum of: supraspinatus tendon thickening (grade 0 to 3), fibrillar disruption (grade 0 to 3), calcification (grade 0 to 3) and neovascularisation (grade 0 to 4) [33]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The following secondary outcomes will only be measured at the 12-month follow-up assessment: number of patients referred for, or completed, arthroscopic subacromial decompression; patients given subacromial corticosteroid injections after the intervention period; the number of visits to a general practitioner or secondary healthcare setting due to the shoulder problem (registration in the Danish Central Office of Patient Registration); and economic variables (for example, patient-reported number of sick days from work and sport attributed to the shoulder and time spent on rehabilitation in the trial period and post-trial, (patient-reported and register-controlled). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Table 1 presents all outcome measures and at which time point they will be collected.Table 1 Summary of measures to be collected n/a: not assessed; SAT: Scapulae Assistance Test; SRT: Scapulae Retraction Test.Article 1: Progressive high-load exercise compared with general low-load exercise in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy: a randomised trial.Article 2: The effect of 12 weeks of progressive high-load exercise in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy on patient-reported and economic outcomes – 12 months follow-up.Article 3: The prognostic evaluation of clinical tests in patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Demographic data and other measurements will be recorded, covering socio-economic variables such as: employment, education, statement of income, history of injury (for example, accident, slow development and fluctuations), duration of current symptoms and physical demands in work and/or hobby activities (patient-reported). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The patients will be instructed to complete an exercise and pain diary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>In the exercise diary, the patients will be asked to report the number of sets and repetitions per set for every training session, as well as the load during the exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Self-reported pain will be registered immediately before and 30 minutes after each training session. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>All pain measurements will be reported on the Numeric Pain Rating Scale. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In addition to pain, patients will be asked to report use of analgesics (type and amount). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Good compliance will be defined by attendance at four out of the six visits to the physiotherapist, and an 80% complete exercise diary, where 100% will be defined by performance of 36 sessions of training (12 weeks at three training sessions per week). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Data collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Three outcome assessors will perform all enrolment, baseline and follow-up assessments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Before starting the data collection, the assessors will train together with the primary investigator and decide on a consensus standard of interpreting all outcome variables. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Sample size and power considerations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Studies on patients with SIS have shown mean baseline values for DASH scores between 18 and 65, and standard deviations (SD) between 12 and 20 [30,31,43-47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Often a 50% reduction in DASH score is seen after treatment [30,31,44,46,47], and it is suggested that a 40% change corresponds to a substantial improvement for the patient [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Based on these data, we expect a mean baseline of 40 points on the DASH questionnaire with an SD of 17. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>We expect a 50% change (change from 40 to 20 DASH points) in the progressive high-load exercise group, and 25% (change from 40 to 30 DASH points) in the low-load exercise group (Figure 2A).Figure 2 Anticipated outcome (primary and secondary objectives). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>A: (Primary objective) Illustration of expected DASH score at 12 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Black = intervention group, White = control group. B: (Secondary objective) Illustration of expected DASH score at 12 weeks stratified for concomitant corticosteroid injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Columns I + II = intervention group, Columns III + IV = control group, Black = concomitant corticosteroid injection, White = no concomitant corticosteroid injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>DASH, Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand Questionnaire. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>For a two-sample pooled t-test of a normal mean difference with a two-sided significance level of 0.05 (P ≤0.05), assuming a common SD of 17 DASH points, a sample size of 100 patients per group has a power of 0.985 (&gt;95% power for the primary outcome) to detect a between-group mean difference of 20 and 30 DASH points after 12 weeks in the progressive high-load exercise group and the low-load exercise group, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>As the second objective is to explore the interaction between corticosteroid use (yes or no) and exercise (progressive high-load exercise or low-load exercise), it is hypothesised that, in the high-load group receiving corticosteroids at baseline, the DASH score at endpoint (12 weeks) will be more favourable than those without corticosteroids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>With an SD of 17 DASH points, a sample size of 62 patients per stratum (having progressive high-load exercise) will be required to obtain a power of at least 0.9 (90%) to detect a mean difference of 10 DASH points between the two subgroups within the progressive high-load exercise group (Figure 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Consequently, it is decided to include 260 patients in the study, assuming a similar number of patients injected and not injected with corticosteroids (1:1; 2 × 130 patients randomly assigned to each exercise group (progressive high-load exercise versus low-load exercise)). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>A final deadline for patient recruitment is set at Marts 2015, meaning that patient recruitment stops when the total number of 260 patients has been recruited, or the deadline of Marts 2015 is reached. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In case the target number of 260 patients has not been met within the specified recruitment period, the power of the study will be less than expected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>With an SD of 17 DASH points, a sample size of 46 patients per group will be required to obtain a power of at least 0.8 (80%) to detect a mean difference of 10 DASH points between the two groups. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Randomisation and allocation concealment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Patients will be randomly assigned to either of the two exercise groups with a 1:1 allocation as per a computer-generated randomisation schedule, stratified by administration of concomitant corticosteroid injection using permuted blocks of random sizes (two to six). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The primary investigator, assessors and administrator of the randomisation procedure will not know block sizes in order to ensure allocation concealment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>In practice, after recruitment and baseline measurements, the secretary at the physiotherapy department will administer the allocation procedure by taking a sequentially numbered, opaque sealed envelope from one of two ring binders, determined by the potential referral to corticosteroids (yes or no) by the orthopaedic specialist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Blinding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Outcome assessors will perform both baseline and follow-up assessments, and will be kept blinded from treatment allocation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>At the follow-up assessments, patients will be strongly encouraged not to disclose the components of their exercise programme, in order to keep the outcome assessor blinded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Patients will be blinded regarding exercise allocation by informing them that the trial involves testing two exercise programmes consisting of the same exercises, and that they will be performed in two different ways, but not defining the specific difference between these, or which is hypothesised to be more effective. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis plan </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The primary efficacy analysis performed is assessment of the between-group difference in change in the DASH score after 12 weeks in the intent-to-treat (ITT) population (all randomised patients independent of compliance and withdrawals). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In the case of missing data due to drop-outs, a non-responder imputation will be applied; a baseline observation carried forward (BOCF) technique will be used for patients who do not complete the study (as will be illustrated in a corresponding trial flow diagram). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>For the primary analyses at week 12, we will use analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) to compare the progressive high-load exercise group with the low-load exercise group for mean changes from baseline in the DASH score, as well as the secondary continuous outcomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The primary model includes the change from baseline as the dependent variable, with treatment group (progressive high-load exercise or low-load exercise), corticosteroid status (yes or no), and the centre site (one, two or three) as main effects, with the baseline score as an additional covariate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The secondary analysis for the primary outcome will add the interaction term for group × corticosteroid in the primary model. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>To analyse the longitudinal element of time effects of DASH in the randomised trial (repeated measures design three, six, nine, and 12 weeks), a linear approach will be used, fitted in SAS software (version 9.3 Service Pack 4; SAS Institute Inc., Cary, North Carolina, United States) using the procedure ‘PROC MIXED’ based on restricted maximum likelihood (REML) estimates of the parameters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The variable ‘patient’ will be applied as a random effects factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Assessment of the treatment and time effects is of exploratory interest for the primary outcome in testing for a possible interaction, and both treatment and time will be used as systematic factors, using the baseline value as covariate to reduce random variation and increase power. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>For all of the above analyses, results will be expressed as the difference between the group means and 95% confidence intervals with associated P values, based on the mixed linear model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>All data analyses will be carried out according to the pre-established analysis plan, and will be performed applying SAS software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>All descriptive statistics and tests will be reported in accordance with the recommendations of the Enhancing the QUAlity and Transparency Of health Research (EQUATOR) network [48] and the Consolidating Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) statement [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the empirical distributions of the continuous outcomes, visual inspection (of the studentised residuals from the statistical model) will be used to suggest whether the assumption of normality and variance homogeneity is reasonable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis of the economic variables will be presented as descriptive statistics, and a cost-utility analysis of the economic burden of each specific exercise programme in relation to the EQ-5D will be performed, expressed in quality-adjusted life years (QALYs) gained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Interim analysis and early stopping rules </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>An early stopping rule will be applied when complete rotator cuff ruptures, verified by ultrasonography, occur due to the performance of the exercise programme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>If six or more cases of complete rupture occur in the progressive high-load exercise group, and the rate of rupture is 50% more compared with the low-load exercise group, the trial will be stopped. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Data monitoring </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Since adverse events are expected to be minimal and the intervention is not considered a high-risk intervention, no data monitoring committee will be established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The physiotherapists at each centre will be asked to report adverse events to the primary investigator, who will report these to the ethics committee and monitor if the number of adverse events has reached the threshold for the early stopping rule. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Ethics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>All patients will participate on a voluntary basis and will be informed that they can withdraw at any time without this influencing their subsequent treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Informed consent will be obtained from all patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>The Regional Scientific Ethics Committee of Southern Denmark approved the trial on the 27 June 2013 (project ID: S-20130071). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The trial was registered with the Danish Data Protection Agency and approved on the 30 May 2013 (registration number: 2008-58-0035). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>The trial is registered at Clinicaltrials.gov (identifier: NCT01984203). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The Danish Act concerning Processing of Personal Data (DAPPD) will be followed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The trial will follow the principles of the Declaration of Helsinki [50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The effect of exercise on the rehabilitation of SIS has been well studied, but the latest systematic reviews focusing on active exercise rehabilitation of SIS consistently report that most studies are of low to moderate quality [8,51-57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>This is primarily due to small sample sizes, inadequate blinding of patients and/or investigators and incomplete intervention descriptions, making it difficult to translate the results into clinical practice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, previous studies show a wide range in clinical outcome (from some effect to almost no effect), which is probably the result of mixed populations within the SIS ‘umbrella of pathologies’, and variation in the interventions used [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>However, collectively there is evidence that active exercise is effective in the rehabilitation of SIS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>When evaluating new treatment approaches that already have some evidence of efficacy, it is considered unethical to compare treatment with a placebo or similar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>New approaches should at least always be tested against current best practice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The RoCTEx trial will add new knowledge to the field as described in the following points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Firstly, the focus on patients with rotator cuff tendinopathy will result in a more homogeneous group, giving the possibility to transfer exercise principles (such as progressive high-load exercise) to the shoulder that previously have been shown to have positive results in other body regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The specific exercises for this trial have been selected on the basis of evidence from Electromyography (EMG) studies, resulting in targeting primarily the m. supraspinatus, which is most often considered the site of tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>In addition, the trial’s exercises will be focusing on stabilising muscles for the scapulae, thereby providing the foundation for optimal functioning of the glenohumeral joint [58-61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Secondly, efforts will be made to keep both primary assessors and patients blinded to the intervention group, which has been one of the most frequent criticisms of earlier studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Thirdly, we will include an active rehabilitation strategy for our control group in order to specify if the effect of the intervention is due specifically to the high-load exercise, or merely to the effect of improved muscle activation of the shoulder muscles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Fourthly, allowing for a subgroup of the included patients having a corticosteroid injection if deemed necessary by the orthopaedic specialist, and subsequently stratifying for this effect, increases the external validity of the results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Since no gold standard exists for diagnosing rotator cuff tendinopathy, the current inclusion criteria may be questioned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The inherent diagnostic difficulties could result in the inclusion of patients not having rotator cuff tendinopathy, thereby increasing participant variability and thereby make it more difficult to reach a significant result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>However, our sample size is calculated on the basis of studies with the same variation in populations, thereby presumably taking this variation into account. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, ultrasound has shown moderate sensitivity and excellent specificity in diagnosing rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The excellent specificity of 0.88 suggests an acceptable probability of not including patients who do not have rotator cuff tendinopathy [62]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The multifactorial pathophysiology of SIS (rotator cuff pathology and degeneration based on decreased vascularity, scapular dyskinesia, instability of the glenohumeral joint or glenohumeral internal rotation deficit) may result in patients not responding positively to a single modality exercise programme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, as we focus our inclusion on those patients who have signs of rotator cuff tendinopathy, and only distinguish the intervention and control groups by the external load applied, we expect that this will not excessively dilute the results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the trial’s exercise programme will consider the multifactorial origin by including exercises focused on the overall strength, stability and mobility of the scapula-humeral complex. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>The progressive high-load exercise programme is optimised in several ways that distinguish it from traditional eccentric exercise programmes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The concentric heavy slow resistance exercises are favourable because of their similarity to daily activities, thereby presumably increasing the likelihood of compliance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, eccentric exercises for the rotator cuff muscles may induce a more unsuitable initial position, reducing the subacromial space, with an anticipated increased risk of subacromial impingement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, using exercises starting with a concentric phase, and allowing the patients only to do isometric exercises when restricted by pain, will potentially minimise the risk of irritating the subacromial structures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>The objective of the RoCTEx trial is to show whether there is a significant advantage in progressive high-load exercise compared with the more traditional low-load exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>If this is the case, the description and availability of a standardised progressive high-load exercise programme will help practitioners to treat patients diagnosed with rotator cuff tendinopathy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>If no difference occurs between the two groups, practitioners will have the possibility of allowing their patients to choose the exercise modality that best optimises their compliance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Trial status </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>At the time of submission of this study protocol, the trial is ongoing and still recruiting patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Recruitment began November 2013, and is expected to end Marts 2015. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>ANCOVA</term><def><p>ANalysis of COVAriance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BOCF</term><def><p>Baseline Observation Carried Forward</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CANS</term><def><p>Complaints of the Arm, Neck and/or Shoulder</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CONSORT</term><def><p>CONsolidating Standards Of Reporting Trials</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAPPD</term><def><p>Danish Act concerning Processing of Personal Data</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DASH</term><def><p>Disabilities of the Arm, Shoulder and Hand questionnaire</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMG</term><def><p>ElectroMyoGraphy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EQUATOR</term><def><p>Enhancing the QUAlity and Transparency Of health Research</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HAD</term><def><p>Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ITT</term><def><p>Intention-To-Treat</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LLE</term><def><p>Low-Load Exercises</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MVC</term><def><p>Maximum isometric Voluntary Contraction</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PHLE</term><def><p>Progressive High-Load Exercises</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>QUALY</term><def><p>QUality-Adjusted Life Years</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RM</term><def><p>Repetitions Maximum</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RC</term><def><p>Rotator Cuff</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RoCTEx</term><def><p>Rotator Cuff Tendinopathy Exercise</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAT</term><def><p>Scapulae Assistance Test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SD</term><def><p>Standard Deviations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SIS</term><def><p>Subacromial Impingement Syndrome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SRT</term><def><p>Scapulae Retraction Test</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOOS</term><def><p>Shoulder injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VAS</term><def><p>Visual Analogue Scale</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>KGI will be the primary assessor in the trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>He initiated the project in collaboration with BJK and KS, and will lead the coordination of the trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>KGI, BJK, KS and RC assisted in trial design and wrote this manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>RC designed the statistical analysis plan and provided the randomisation schedule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>KGI, LS, SLJ, SR and HJ planned the coordination at the hospitals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>All authors were involved in drafting the manuscript and critically revising it for important intellectual content and, finally, read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>We thank all participating orthopaedic specialists and physiotherapists performing the initial screening of patients and instructing patients in the exercises. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The participating departments at Hospital Lillebaelt - Vejle Hospital, Aalborg University Hospital - Farsø Hospital and Odense University Hospital - Svendborg Hospital will contribute personnel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Region of Southern Denmark’s Research fund, The Danish Rheumatism Association and the Ryholts Foundation funds the trial. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Dr Christensen is employed in the Musculoskeletal Statistics Unit at The Parker Institute, which is supported by grants from the Oak Foundation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>We thank them for their support. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>1.LuimeJJKoesBWHendriksenIJBurdorfAVerhagenAPMiedemaHSPrevalence and incidence of shoulder pain in the general population: a systematic reviewScand J Rheumatol.200433738110.1080/03009740310004667<?supplied-pmid 15163107?>15163107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>2.MirandaHViikari-JunturaEHeistaroSHeliovaaraMRiihimakiHA population study on differences in the determinants of a specific shoulder disorder versus nonspecific shoulder pain without clinical findingsAm J Epidemiol.20051618475510.1093/aje/kwi112<?supplied-pmid 15840617?>15840617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>3.HuisstedeBMWijnhovenHABierma-ZeinstraSMKoesBWVerhaarJAPicavetSPrevalence and characteristics of complaints of the arm, neck, and/or shoulder (CANS) in the open populationClin J Pain.200824253910.1097/AJP.0b013e318160a8b4<?supplied-pmid 18287832?>18287832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>4.FeleusABierma-ZeinstraSMMiedemaHSVerhaarJAKoesBWManagement in non-traumatic arm, neck and shoulder complaints: differences between diagnostic groupsEur Spine J.20081712182910.1007/s00586-008-0710-1<?supplied-pmid 18607647?>18607647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>5.van der WindtDAKoesBWde JongBABouterLMShoulder disorders in general practice: incidence, patient characteristics, and managementAnn Rheum Dis.1995549596410.1136/ard.54.12.959<?supplied-pmid 8546527?>8546527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>6.HuisstedeBMMiedemaHSVerhagenAPKoesBWVerhaarJAMultidisciplinary consensus on the terminology and classification of complaints of the arm, neck and/or shoulderOccup Environ Med.200764313910.1136/oem.2005.023861<?supplied-pmid 17043078?>17043078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>7.LewisJSRotator cuff tendinopathy/subacromial impingement syndrome: is it time for a new method of assessment?Br J Sports Med.2009432596410.1136/bjsm.2008.052183<?supplied-pmid 18838403?>18838403 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>8.LittlewoodCAshtonJChance-LarsenKMaySSturrockBExercise for rotator cuff tendinopathy: a systematic reviewPhysiotherapy.201298101910.1016/j.physio.2011.08.002<?supplied-pmid 22507359?>22507359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>9.Authority DHaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>National clinical guidelines for diagnostic and treatment of patients with selected shoulder impairments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>In: National clinical guidelines - publications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>2013. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sundhedsstyrelsen.dk/publ/Publ2013/09sep/NKRUdvalgteSkulderlidelser.pdf">http://sundhedsstyrelsen.dk/publ/Publ2013/09sep/NKRUdvalgteSkulderlidelser.pdf</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Accessed 14 Jan 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Danish. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>10.BroxJIGjengedalEUppheimGBohmerASBrevikJILjunggrenAEArthroscopic surgery versus supervised exercises in patients with rotator cuff disease (stage II impingement syndrome): a prospective, randomized, controlled study in 125 patients with a 2 1/2-year follow-upJ Shoulder Elbow Surg.199981021110.1016/S1058-2746(99)90001-0<?supplied-pmid 10226960?>10226960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>11.BroxJIStaffPHLjunggrenAEBrevikJIArthroscopic surgery compared with supervised exercises in patients with rotator cuff disease (stage II impingement syndrome)BMJ.199330789990310.1136/bmj.307.6909.899<?supplied-pmid 8241852?>8241852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>12.HaahrJPAndersenJHExercises may be as efficient as subacromial decompression in patients with subacromial stage II impingement: 4-8-years’ follow-up in a prospective, randomized studyScand J Rheumatol.200635224810.1080/03009740600556167<?supplied-pmid 16766370?>16766370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>13.HaahrJPOstergaardSDalsgaardJNorupKFrostPLausenSExercises versus arthroscopic decompression in patients with subacromial impingement: a randomised, controlled study in 90 cases with a one year follow upAnn Rheum Dis.200564760410.1136/ard.2004.021188<?supplied-pmid 15834056?>15834056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>14.KetolaSLehtinenJArnalaINissinenMWesteniusHSintonenHDoes arthroscopic acromioplasty provide any additional value in the treatment of shoulder impingement syndrome?: a two-year randomised controlled trialJ Bone Joint Surg Br.20099113263410.1302/0301-620X.91B10.22094<?supplied-pmid 19794168?>19794168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>15.MalliarasPBartonCJReevesNDLangbergHAchilles and patellar tendinopathy loading programmes: a systematic review comparing clinical outcomes and identifying potential mechanisms for effectivenessSports Med.2013432678610.1007/s40279-013-0019-z<?supplied-pmid 23494258?>23494258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>16.AndresBMMurrellGATreatment of tendinopathy: what works, what does not, and what is on the horizonClin Orthop Relat Res.200846615395410.1007/s11999-008-0260-1<?supplied-pmid 18446422?>18446422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="?"><plain>17.CookJLPurdamCRIs tendon pathology a continuum? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>A pathology model to explain the clinical presentation of load-induced tendinopathyBr J Sports Med.2009434091610.1136/bjsm.2008.051193<?supplied-pmid 18812414?>18812414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>18.KingmaJJde KnikkerRWittinkHMTakkenTEccentric overload training in patients with chronic Achilles tendinopathy: a systematic reviewBr J Sports Med.200741e310.1136/bjsm.2006.030916<?supplied-pmid 17035479?>17035479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>19.OhbergLAlfredsonHEffects on neovascularisation behind the good results with eccentric training in chronic mid-portion Achilles tendinosis?Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc.2004124657010.1007/s00167-004-0494-8<?supplied-pmid 15060761?>15060761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>20.OhbergLLorentzonRAlfredsonHEccentric training in patients with chronic Achilles tendinosis: normalised tendon structure and decreased thickness at follow upBr J Sports Med.20043881110.1136/bjsm.2001.000284<?supplied-pmid 14751936?>14751936 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>21.LangbergHEllingsgaardHMadsenTJanssonJMagnussonSPAagaardPEccentric rehabilitation exercise increases peritendinous type I collagen synthesis in humans with Achilles tendinosisScand J Med Sci Sports.200717616<?supplied-pmid 16787448?>16787448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>22.MillerBFOlesenJLHansenMDossingSCrameriRMWellingRJCoordinated collagen and muscle protein synthesis in human patella tendon and quadriceps muscle after exerciseJ Physiol.200556710213310.1113/jphysiol.2005.093690<?supplied-pmid 16002437?>16002437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>23.LangbergHKongsgaardMEccentric training in tendinopathy–more questions than answersScand J Med Sci Sports.200818541210.1111/j.1600-0838.2008.00864.x<?supplied-pmid 19522891?>19522891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>24.FrohmASaartokTHalvorsenKRenstromPEccentric treatment for patellar tendinopathy: a prospective randomised short-term pilot study of two rehabilitation protocolsBr J Sports Med.200741e710.1136/bjsm.2006.032599<?supplied-pmid 17289855?>17289855 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>25.KongsgaardMKovanenVAagaardPDoessingSHansenPLaursenAHCorticosteroid injections, eccentric decline squat training and heavy slow resistance training in patellar tendinopathyScand J Med Sci Sports.20091979080210.1111/j.1600-0838.2009.00949.x<?supplied-pmid 19793213?>19793213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>26.KongsgaardMQvortrupKLarsenJAagaardPDoessingSHansenPFibril morphology and tendon mechanical properties in patellar tendinopathy: effects of heavy slow resistance trainingAm J Sports Med.2010387495610.1177/0363546509350915<?supplied-pmid 20154324?>20154324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="?"><plain>27.MaenhoutAGMahieuNNDe MuynckMDe WildeLFCoolsAMDoes adding heavy load eccentric training to rehabilitation of patients with unilateral subacromial impingement result in better outcome? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>A randomized, clinical trialKnee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc.20132111586710.1007/s00167-012-2012-8<?supplied-pmid 22581193?>22581193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>28.LombardiIJrMagriAGFleuryAMDa SilvaACNatourJProgressive resistance training in patients with shoulder impingement syndrome: a randomized controlled trialArthritis Rheum.2008596152210.1002/art.23576<?supplied-pmid 18438933?>18438933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>29.JonssonPWahlstromPOhbergLAlfredsonHEccentric training in chronic painful impingement syndrome of the shoulder: results of a pilot studyKnee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc.200614768110.1007/s00167-004-0611-8<?supplied-pmid 15877219?>15877219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>30.HolmgrenTBjornsson HallgrenHObergBAdolfssonLJohanssonKEffect of specific exercise strategy on need for surgery in patients with subacromial impingement syndrome: randomised controlled studyBMJ.2012344e78710.1136/bmj.e787<?supplied-pmid 22349588?>22349588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>31.CamargoPRAvilaMAAlburquerque-SendinFAssoNAHashimotoLHSalviniTFEccentric training for shoulder abductors improves pain, function and isokinetic performance in subjects with shoulder impingement syndrome: a case seriesRev Bras Fisioter.201216748310.1590/S1413-35552012000100013<?supplied-pmid 22441232?>22441232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>32.BernhardssonSKlintbergIHWendtGKEvaluation of an exercise concept focusing on eccentric strength training of the rotator cuff for patients with subacromial impingement syndromeClin Rehabil.201125697810.1177/0269215510376005<?supplied-pmid 20713438?>20713438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>33.PoltawskiLAliSJayaramVWatsonTReliability of sonographic assessment of tendinopathy in tennis elbowSkeletal Radiol.20124183910.1007/s00256-011-1132-4<?supplied-pmid 21384199?>21384199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>34.Kim SY, Ko JB, Farthing JP, Butcher SJ: Investigation of supraspinatus muscle architecture following concentric and eccentric training. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>J Sci Med Sport. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>2014. doi: 10.1016/j.jsams.2014.05.007. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>35.KimSBleakneyRBoyntonERavichandiranKRindlisbacherTMcKeeNInvestigation of the static and dynamic musculotendinous architecture of supraspinatusClin Anat.201023485510.1002/ca.21045<?supplied-pmid 19941361?>19941361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>36.HudakPLAmadioPCBombardierCDevelopment of an upper extremity outcome measure: the DASH (disabilities of the arm, shoulder and hand) [corrected]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The Upper Extremity Collaborative Group (UECG)Am J Ind Med199629602810.1002/(SICI)1097-0274(199606)29:6&lt;602::AID-AJIM4&gt;3.0.CO;2-L<?supplied-pmid 8773720?>8773720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>37.Ingwersen KGBJ-KShoulder Injury and Osteoarthritis Outcome Score (SOOS) - Reliability and Validity of a New Patient Reported Outcome MeasureSports Medicine Congress; 2012 Feb 2–4; Kolding, Denmark2012Kolding, DenmarkDansk Idrætsmedicinsk Selskab </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>38.ZigmondASSnaithRPThe hospital anxiety and depression scaleActa Psychiatr Scand.1983673617010.1111/j.1600-0447.1983.tb09716.x<?supplied-pmid 6880820?>6880820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>39.RabinRde CharroFEQ-5D: a measure of health status from the EuroQol GroupAnn Med.2001333374310.3109/07853890109002087<?supplied-pmid 11491192?>11491192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>40.CarlssonAMAssessment of chronic pain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Aspects of the reliability and validity of the visual analogue scalePain.1983168710110.1016/0304-3959(83)90088-X<?supplied-pmid 6602967?>6602967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>41.KiblerWBThe role of the scapula in athletic shoulder functionAm J Sports Med.19982632537<?supplied-pmid 9548131?>9548131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>42.KiblerWBMcMullenJScapular dyskinesis and its relation to shoulder painJ Am Acad Orthop Surg.20031114251<?supplied-pmid 12670140?>12670140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>43.de WittePBHenselerJFNagelsJVliet VlielandTPNelissenRGThe Western Ontario rotator cuff index in rotator cuff disease patients: a comprehensive reliability and responsiveness validation studyAm J Sports Med.2012401611910.1177/0363546512446591<?supplied-pmid 22582227?>22582227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>44.KarthikeyanSKwongHTUpadhyayPKParsonsNDrewSJGriffinDA double-blind randomised controlled study comparing subacromial injection of tenoxicam or methylprednisolone in patients with subacromial impingementJ Bone Joint Surg Br.201092778210.1302/0301-620X.92B1.22137<?supplied-pmid 20044683?>20044683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>45.LeeJHLeeSHSongSHClinical effectiveness of botulinum toxin type B in the treatment of subacromial bursitis or shoulder impingement syndromeClin J Pain.201127523810.1097/AJP.0b013e31820e1310<?supplied-pmid 21368663?>21368663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>46.MichenerLASnyder ValierARMcClurePWDefining substantial clinical benefit for patient-rated outcome tools for shoulder impingement syndromeArch Phys Med Rehabil2013947253010.1016/j.apmr.2012.11.011<?supplied-pmid 23164979?>23164979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>47.TateARMcClurePWYoungIASalvatoriRMichenerLAComprehensive impairment-based exercise and manual therapy intervention for patients with subacromial impingement syndrome: a case seriesJ Orthop Sports Phys Ther.2010404749310.2519/jospt.2010.3223<?supplied-pmid 20710088?>20710088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>48.ChristensenRBliddalHHenriksenMEnhancing the reporting and transparency of rheumatology research: a guide to reporting guidelinesArthritis Res Ther.20131510910.1186/ar4145<?supplied-pmid 23448311?>23448311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>49.MoherDHopewellSSchulzKFMontoriVGotzschePCDevereauxPJCONSORT 2010 explanation and elaboration: updated guidelines for reporting parallel group randomised trialsJ Clin Epidemiol.201063e13710.1016/j.jclinepi.2010.03.004<?supplied-pmid 20346624?>20346624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>50.VollmannJWinauRInformed consent in human experimentation before the Nuremberg codeBMJ.19963131445910.1136/bmj.313.7070.1445<?supplied-pmid 8973233?>8973233 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>51.FaberEKuiperJIBurdorfAMiedemaHSVerhaarJATreatment of impingement syndrome: a systematic review of the effects on functional limitations and return to workJ Occup Rehabil.20061672510.1007/s10926-005-9003-2<?supplied-pmid 16705497?>16705497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>52.KellySMWrightsonPAMeadsCAClinical outcomes of exercise in the management of subacromial impingement syndrome: a systematic reviewClin Rehabil.2010249910910.1177/0269215509342336<?supplied-pmid 20103573?>20103573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>53.KromerTOTautenhahnUGde BieRAStaalJBBastiaenenCHEffects of physiotherapy in patients with shoulder impingement syndrome: a systematic review of the literatureJ Rehabil Med.2009418708010.2340/16501977-0453<?supplied-pmid 19841837?>19841837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>54.KuhnJEExercise in the treatment of rotator cuff impingement: a systematic review and a synthesized evidence-based rehabilitation protocolJ Shoulder Elbow Surg.2009181386010.1016/j.jse.2008.06.004<?supplied-pmid 18835532?>18835532 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>55.MichenerLAWalsworthMKBurnetENEffectiveness of rehabilitation for patients with subacromial impingement syndrome: a systematic reviewJ Hand Ther.2004171526410.1197/j.jht.2004.02.004<?supplied-pmid 15162102?>15162102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>56.PapadonikolakisAMcKennaMWarmeWMartinBIMatsenFA3rdPublished evidence relevant to the diagnosis of impingement syndrome of the shoulderJ Bone Joint Surg Am.20119318273210.2106/JBJS.J.01748<?supplied-pmid 22005869?>22005869 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>57.von der HeydeRLOccupational therapy interventions for shoulder conditions: a systematic reviewAm J Occup Ther.201165162310.5014/ajot.2011.09184<?supplied-pmid 21309367?>21309367 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>58.AndersenCHZebisMKSaervollCSundstrupEJakobsenMDSjogaardGScapular muscle activity from selected strengthening exercises performed at low and high intensitiesJ Strength Cond Res.20122624081610.1519/JSC.0b013e31823f8d24<?supplied-pmid 22076101?>22076101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>59.CoolsAMDewitteVLanszweertFNotebaertDRoetsASoetensBRehabilitation of scapular muscle balance: which exercises to prescribe?Am J Sports Med.20073517445110.1177/0363546507303560<?supplied-pmid 17606671?>17606671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>60.EscamillaRFYamashiroKPaulosLAndrewsJRShoulder muscle activity and function in common shoulder rehabilitation exercisesSports Med.2009396638510.2165/00007256-200939080-00004<?supplied-pmid 19769415?>19769415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>61.KiblerWBSciasciaADUhlTLTambayNCunninghamTElectromyographic analysis of specific exercises for scapular control in early phases of shoulder rehabilitationAm J Sports Med.20083617899810.1177/0363546508316281<?supplied-pmid 18469224?>18469224 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>62.Martin-HervasCRomeroJNavas-AcienAReboirasJJMunueraLUltrasonographic and magnetic resonance images of rotator cuff lesions compared with arthroscopy or open surgery findingsJ Shoulder Elbow Surg.200110410510.1067/mse.2001.116515<?supplied-pmid 11641696?>11641696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
