
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Nanopart Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Nanopart Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Nanoparticle Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1388-0764</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1572-896X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4021069</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24839395</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2419</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11051-014-2419-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Dark field nanoparticle tracking analysis for size characterization of plasmonic and non-plasmonic particles </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>Thorsten</given-names></name><address><phone>+49-231-7556721</phone><email>wagner@biomedical-imaging.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lipinski</surname><given-names>Hans-Gerd</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wiemann</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><address><email>martin.wiemann@ibe-ms.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Biomedical Imaging Group, Dortmund University of Applied Sciences and Arts, Emil-Figge-Straße 42, 44227 Dortmund, Germany </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>IBE R&amp;D Institute for Lung Health gGmbH, Mendelstraße 11, 48149 Münster, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>2419</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and the source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Dark field microscopy is a widely unknown method to measure the particle size distribution of diffusing nanoparticles by particle tracking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Here we demonstrate that by using the surface plasmonic resonance of Au nanoparticles, size differences of ca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>20 nm can be identified within the particle size distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>For that purpose, we developed a software tool which helps to analyze color videos of diffusing nanoparticles retrieved from CCD or CMOS cameras. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Polystyrene beads with a diameter of 100 and 200 nm were used to compare the results to those obtained with a well-established laser-based particle tracking system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The methodology will be discussed in the light of recent developments in the emerging field of optical nanoparticle tracking. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><sec><title><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s11051-014-2419-x) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Nanoparticle tracking analysis</kwd><kwd>Dark field microscopy </kwd><kwd>Instrumentation development</kwd><kwd>Surface plasmon resonance</kwd><kwd>Particle characterization</kwd><kwd>ImageJ</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© Springer Science+Business Media Dordrecht 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The use of gold and silver nanoparticles (NPs) has received much attention in recent years because of their unique light scattering and absorption characteristics (Ringe et al. 2013; El-Brolossy et al. 2008; Kelly et al. 2003; Link and El-Sayed 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Due to their plasmonic resonance and the lack of photobleaching or blinking (Cai et al. 2008), these metal particles are used as bio-nano-sensors (Anker et al. 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>As early as 1902 Siedentopf and Zsigmondy (1902) showed that diffusing Au NPs are visible with dark field microscopy (DFM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>They also observed diffraction patterns of NP in multiple colors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon, based on the surface plasmonic resonance (SPR) of metal NPs, is influenced by the dielectric constant, the temperature of the surrounding medium, and mainly by particle size and shape (Link and El-Sayed 1999; Kelly et al. 2003; Buecker 2007; El-Brolossy et al. 2008; Bingham and Willets 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Thus, under ideal conditions, the color information offers the opportunity to characterize the size of NPs with refined methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Since a couple of years a size measurement technique called nanoparticle tracking analysis (NTA) is increasingly used to determine the size distribution of NPs in liquids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>This NTA technique makes use of intense laser light to illuminate freely diffusing particles, tracks their Brownian motion by analysis of monochrome images, and finally, estimates their size distribution using the Stokes–Einstein relation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>As the technique is applicable to biological fluids and to comparatively low particle concentrations, it has become major importance e.g., for measuring NPs in the field of nanotoxicology (Buzea et al. 2007; Yang et al. 2010; Stone et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Another widely used method for particle characterisation is dynamic light scattering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>This technique determines the size distribution of a nanoparticle collective (down to 1 nm) and is well suited for concentrated nanoparticle suspensions, whereas it is disturbed by larger, gravitationally settling particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The latter is not a problem if single particles are tracked by NTA (Filipe et al. 2010; Hole et al. 2013) or the tracking method used in this paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This method takes advantage from DFM, which has previously been applied to other scientific issues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Sönnichsen and Alivisatos (2005) used single particle tracking to estimate the plasmon-based orientation of Au nanorods; Bingham and Willets (2009) tracked single Ag NPs, analyzed their scattering spectra, and estimated their diffusion coefficient simultaneously; and Sagle et al. (2012) tracked single Au NPs for the study of bilayers with ganglioside lipids to distinguish between random and confined diffusion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>However, little attention has been paid to the capabilities of DFM to estimate size distribution of suspended NP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>This paper, therefore, focuses on the advantages and limitations of calculating size distributions of NP from DFM videos by means of nanoparticle tracking. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In particular, we will demonstrate that the color information of NP retrieved from CCD or CMOS cameras bears valuable information which may help identify subpopulations of metal NP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Therefore, an ImageJ-based software called NanoTrackJ (Wagner et al. 2014) was developed which is capable to analyze a wide range of particle videos including their color information. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Material &amp; methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Particles </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Gold NPs (BBI, Cardiff, UK), nominally sized 60 and 80 nm, were used due to their stability and pronounced SPR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>These particle qualities were diluted in essentially particle-free double distilled H\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}O and mixed to obtain suitable bimodal particle suspensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>For verification purposes, 100 nm (Kisker-Biotech, PPs-0.1) and 200 nm (Kisker-Biotech, PPs-0.2) polystyrene particles were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Trackable concentrations amounted to approximately \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$5\times 10^{8}/\text {ml}$$\end{document} and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$3\times 10^{9}/\text {ml}$$\end{document} for NTA and dark field measurements, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Imaging equipment and data acquisition </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Image data were collected with a NanoSightTM LM10 system equipped with a LM14 green (535 nm) laser module and a cooled Andor camera (Andor-DL-658-OEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>For DFM, an Olympus BX51 microscope was used which was illuminated with a CytoVivaTM dark field oil condenser. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Particle suspension was pipetted into a micro-chamber consisting of a cleaned slide and a cover slip which was supported by two cover slip fragments, thus defining the height of the chamber to ca. \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$160\,\upmu \text {m}$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>A 100-fold oil immersion objective with iris aperture (Olympus) was brought in place and the optimal dark field illumination was adjusted with a completely closed iris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Measurements were carried out at a defined temperature (\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$22- 24\, ^{\circ }\text {C}$$\end{document}). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Color image series were taken with a digital single-lens reflex camera (Canon EOS 5D Mark II) set to the highest sensitivity (ISO 3200) in the movie mode (25 fps, resolution 1920 \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\times$$\end{document} 1020 px) or with a PCO Pixelfly Edge camera (PCO AG, Kehlheim, Germany, black and white custom model). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The NTA measurements were analyzed by the NTA 2.3 software and by the newly developed NanoTrackJ software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Dark field measurements were analyzed by NanoTrackJ only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>All captured video files and settings to reproduce the measurements are listed in the supplementary information. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Nanoparticle tracking analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>NTA adapts some principles of single particle tracking to estimate size distributions of NPs in liquid suspensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>To estimate a size distribution, four steps are necessary: (i) Each particle in each frame has to be identified and its center needs to be calculated, (ii) each identified particle has to be tracked for an acceptable time period, (iii) the diffusion coefficients have to be estimated by means of the particle trajectories, and (iv) the size distribution is calculated considering temperature and viscosity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The following section describes how these issues are solved by NanoTrackJ, and gives advice as to which method provides most robust results. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>(i) Identifying each particle </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The objective of this step is to segment each diffraction pattern and estimate the center of it. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>NanoTrackJ offers three alternative ways to solve that problem: (i) utilize the “Find Maximum” method, (ii) combine the “Find Maximum” method and a Gaussian fit procedure, and (iii) let the user segment the video data on his own and use the binary video data. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Method (i) was used throughout all measurements conducted with NanoTrackJ and works as follows: The 8-neighborhood of each pixel is scanned for higher pixels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>If no higher pixel is found, the center pixel is marked as the maximum; all maximum values are sorted by intensity value in descending order, and commencing with the first local maximum (in sorted order) a flood filling algorithm is carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>This flood filling algorithm groups all pixels around the respective maximum value and uses a pre-set intensity tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>If another local maximum is located inside this grouped region, it will be discarded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The centers of gravity of the grouped regions are returned as maximum values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Method (ii) provides center estimations with “sub-pixel accuracy.” Starting from the position returned by method (i), it estimates the spread of the main maximum of the diffraction pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, it fits a 2D Gaussian distribution to the main maximum of the diffraction pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The center of this Gaussian fit, theoretically, provides subpixel accuracy (Cheezum et al. 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>However, the main maximum often suffers from saturation effects or lacks a Gaussian shape, such that a subpixel accuracy cannot be reached in these cases. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Method (iii) works with binary image sequences only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>It is useful for data that could not be analyzed by method (i) or (ii). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>The user has to segment the footage using ImageJ before the image sequence can be analyzed by NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Then, the center of gravity of each connected component is calculated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>(ii) Tracking each particle </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>After identifying each particle in every frame, the particle positions have to be connected to a trajectory (or “track”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, the software has to track the particle in the image sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>In NanoTrackJ, this is done as follows: Let an image sequence consist of N frames \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$F=\{F_{\triangle t},F_{2\triangle t},\ldots ,F_{N\triangle t}\}$$\end{document} captured at a constant time interval of \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\triangle t$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Let \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$K_{i\triangle t}$$\end{document} be the set of identified particles in frame \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$F_{i\triangle t}$$\end{document} and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$1\le i\le N$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Given a particle with a position \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$p_{j}$$\end{document} with \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$0&lt;j&lt;|K_{i\triangle t}|$$\end{document} in frame \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$F_{i\triangle t}$$\end{document} then \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$M_{j}$$\end{document} is the set of particles in the previous frame \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$F_{(i-1)\triangle t}$$\end{document} which are inside a circle with the radius r centered at the position \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$p_{j}$$\end{document}:1\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} M_{j}=\{q:q\in K_{(i-1)\triangle t},\Vert p_{j}-q\Vert &lt;r\} \end{aligned},$$\end{document}where \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$||\cdot ||$$\end{document} is the euclidean norm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>However, the tracking algorithm interconnects the particle positions only if the following conditions are fulfilled:2\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} |M_{j}|&amp;= 1\end{aligned}$$\end{document}3\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} M_{j}\cap M_{k}&amp;= \{\emptyset \}\quad {\rm for}\, j\ne k \end{aligned}$$\end{document}This means that the decision of connecting two particles has to be unique. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Eq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>(2) ensures that a particle is not connected to more than one particle in the previous frame and Eq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>(3) ensures that two particles are not connected to the same particle in the previous frame. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>If two particles in subsequent frames are connected successfully, it is assumed that these two centers represent the same particle which had changed its positions during \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\triangle t$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>This change in the particle position is referred to as a “step.” A trajectory of a particle is formed of L steps, where L is proportional to the diffusion time of the particle and is referred to as “tracklength.” In an ideal case, the tracklength covers the complete registration period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>However, this occurs rather infrequently because (i) the particle diffuses out of the field of view or (ii) an assignment does not satisfy Eq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>(2) or (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Whereas the first issue depends in part on the optical and instrumental settings (illumination intensity, numerical aperture of the objective, camera sensitivity), the second issue may be minimized not only by preparing samples with a reasonably adapted particle concentration (see "Particles" section ) but also by software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>For this purpose, NanoTrackJ is parametrized by a minimum expected particle diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Knowing the sample’s temperature and viscosity, the corresponding maximum-expected diffusion coefficient \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$D_{max}$$\end{document} can be calculated by the Stokes–Einstein relation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Using this maximum-expecting diffusion coefficient, the search radius r is calculated by4\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} r=3\sqrt{\pi D_{max}\triangle t} \end{aligned},$$\end{document}where \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\sqrt{\pi D_{max}\triangle t}$$\end{document} is the mean step length of a particle with the diffusion coefficient \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$D_{max}$$\end{document}(der Meeren et al. 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>This radius ensures that more than 99 % of the expected particle steps are shorter than this radius (Wieser and Schütz 2008), provided that there is no smaller particle as specified by the minimum expected particle diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>It is worthwhile to note that the search radius is of critical importance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A too large radius will result in shorter track lengths, because Eqs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>(2) and (3) will be satisfied less often. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>In case the radius r is too small, steps exceeding r will not become detected, which leads to a smaller mean step length and a bias towards a larger mean particle size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>(iii) Diffusion coefficient estimation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Given a particle trajectory, its diffusion coefficient could be calculated in several ways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Two methods are available in NanoTrackJ: The “regression method” and the “covariance method.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The regression method is the most often used method in the literature to estimate the diffusion coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>It evaluates the mean squared displacement \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\left\langle d^{2}\right\rangle$$\end{document} of particle diffusion in \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$n$$\end{document} dimensions for different time lags \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\tau _{k}=k\triangle t$$\end{document}:5\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\langle d^{2}\right\rangle _{k}=2nD\tau _{k} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}Evaluation of Eq. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>(5) for different \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\tau _{k}$$\end{document} leads to a bunch of data points \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$(\left\langle d^{2}\right\rangle _{k},k)$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The diffusion coefficient is then estimated by the slope of a regression line fitting a specific number of data points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The slope of this regression line is proportional by \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$2n\triangle t$$\end{document} to the diffusion coefficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>This method is very simple but unfortunately error prone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Up to now it’s not clear, how many data points lead to the best estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Wieser and Schütz (2008) states that only the first two time lags \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$(k=1,2)$$\end{document} should be used and Vestergaard (2012) concluded that the more data points are included in the fit the greater is the error in the estimate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>However, Ernst and Köhler (2013) recommend to use the data points with the time lag \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$k=2$$\end{document} to \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$k=5$$\end{document}, and Michalet and Berglund (2012) used an iterative approach to estimate the optimal number of data points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Due to these contradictory recommendations for the correct number of data points, NanoTrackJ allows the user to determine what minimum and maximum time lag should be used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>However, here we decided to use the covariance estimator throughout the paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Because it is unbiased and needs no parameters, it outperforms the regression method for most diffusion-to-noise ratios and it almost attains the minimum standard deviation for an unbiased estimator, the Cramer–Rao bound (see Appendix). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Given the measured position \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$x[n]$$\end{document} at discrete timepoints \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$t_n=n\triangle t$$\end{document} of a particle diffusing in one dimension, then the covariance estimator is defined in the following way:6\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \hat{D}=\frac{\overline{\triangle x_{n}\triangle x_{n}}}{2\triangle t}+\frac{\overline{\triangle x_{n}\triangle x_{n+1}}}{\triangle t} \end{aligned},$$\end{document}where the second term in the right-hand side is an estimator for the localization noise and7\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \triangle x_{n}=x[n]-x[n-1] \end{aligned}$$\end{document}Please refer to Appendix for a more comprehensive precision analysis of both estimators. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>(iv) Estimation of the size distribution </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Once the diffusion coefficients are estimated, the derivation of a size distribution is straight forward. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>NanoTrackJ provides two methods for this purpose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The first method simply transforms the diffusion coefficients to a hydrodynamic diameter using the Stokes-Einstein relation and weights each diameter by the track length from which it is derived. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>Then, a histogram is formed using the weighted diameter data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The weighting is important not only because longer tracks provide more precise estimate but also because smaller particles diffuse in and out the field of view more rapidly and, therefore, more often than larger particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Consequently, it makes sense to treat each particle step as a single event instead of the complete track (ASTM 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The second method also accounts for this fact by using a maximum likelihood method as suggested by Walker (2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>He defines the following iterative algorithm to estimate the particle size histogram with M radius bins and a bin size of \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\triangle r$$\end{document}8\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} P_{m}^{(j+1)}=P_{m}^{(j)}\frac{1}{N}\sum \limits _{n-1}^{N}\left\{ \frac{P_{d}(\triangle _{n};k_{n},m\cdot \triangle r)}{\sum \nolimits _{l=1}^{M}\frac{P_{d}(\triangle _{n};k_{n},l\cdot \triangle r)}{\sum \nolimits _{i=1}^{M}P_{i}^{(j)}}}\right\} \end{aligned},$$\end{document}where9\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} P_{d}(\triangle _{n};k_{n},r)=\frac{k_{n}(k_{n}\triangle _{n})^{k_{n}-1}\cdot exp(-k_{n}\triangle _{n}/\theta _{r})}{\theta _{r}^{k_{n}}\cdot \varGamma (k_{n})} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\theta _{r}=(2K_{b}T\triangle t)/(3\pi \eta r), \triangle _{n}$$\end{document} is the mean squared displacement of track \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$n$$\end{document} , and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$k_{n}$$\end{document} is the number of steps of track \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$n$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The algorithm starts from uniform distribution (\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$P_{m}^{0}$$\end{document}) and updates the bin probabilities for all bins \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$1\le m\le M$$\end{document} in one iteration. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The mean squared displacement is derived from the estimator chosen in step (iii) by using the relation \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\triangle _{n}=2D_{n}\triangle t$$\end{document}. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Here the covariance estimator was used, since it is an efficient estimator for both the diffusion coefficient and \documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\triangle _{n}$$\end{document} which linearly depends on the former. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>The algorithm stops, if the differences between the histogram of the displacement data and the maximum likelihood histogram for the displacement are no longer changing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>This method leads to very “clean” histograms within which the modal values are easily identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Throughout the paper, this method was used for all measurements with NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Results and discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In the first section, we will demonstrate the ability of NanoTrackJ to determine the correct particle size, using the proprietary NanoSightTM system as a NTA reference system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Then, the utilization of SPR of Au NP for an advanced size measurement will be demonstrated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Finally, advantages and disadvantages of either method will be discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Quality control of NanoTrackJ </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Videos of polystyrene beads diffusing in H\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$_{2}$$\end{document}O were captured using the NTA device and analyzed by both, the NanoSightTM NTA 2.3 software and NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Size distributions determined by NanoTrackJ (Fig. 1b, d) agreed well with distributions reported by NTA software (Fig. 1a, c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Data in Table 1 show that not only the modal values match fairly well but also the inter-quantile ranges are in good agreement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Using the same video material, the modal diameter reported for the 200 nm polystyrene video by NanoTrackJ came slightly close to the nominal particle diameter compared to NTA, an effect which may be caused e.g., by the different diffusion coefficient estimators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Although DFM is predestined for analyzing plasmonic NPs (see "Utilizing the surface plasmon resonance for dark field NTA" section), NPs made from polystyrene can be evaluated as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 shows the size distributions of 100 and 200 nm NP viewed with DFM and analyzed with NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Modal values are centered at the nominal size of the beads indicating the correctness of the method.Fig. 1Comparison of NanoTrackJ and NTA using a 100 nm and a 200 nm NP suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Video sequences were captured with a NanoSightTM LM10 microscope and analyzed by NTA 2.3 (a, c) and NanoTrackJ (b, d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Because NTA 2.3 reports continuous size distributions, we added a kernel density estimate to plot a and c Table 1Quantitative validation of NanoTrackJ (NTJ) using the polystyrene experiments shown in Fig. 1  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Fig. 2Size distribution of polystyrene NP (100 and 200 nm) viewed with DFM and analyzed with NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Both histograms were calculated by Walker’s method based on 937 tracks (a) / 438 tracks (b) with a mean track length of 35 (a) / 71 (b)Fig. 3Footage of the color video of a bimodal mixture of 60 and 80 nm Au NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>A diverging SPR can be seen with dominating colors green and orange. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>(Color figure online)Fig. 4Size distribution of the bimodal AuNP mixture from NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The 561 tracks of Au NPs shown in Fig. 3 are evaluated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The modal value is 60 nm </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Utilizing the surface plasmon resonance for dark field NTA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>In the next step, we investigated how colors of Au NP elicited by dark field illumination can add to or even improve the determination of their size distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We found that using the SPR of Au NPs it was possible to identify the particle subpopulations in the bimodal Au NP suspension. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows a multi-colored set of diffusing particles with green and orange being the dominating colors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>As outlined above, difference in plasmon resonance could reflect a different size, shape, or dielectric environment of the AuNP (Bingham and Willets 2009; Buecker 2007; El-Brolossy et al. 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>As there was no change in color of each single particle over time, a torsion of an irregularly shaped particle was unlikely to account for this disparity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, according to manufacturer’s specification, all visible Au NPs were designated as spherical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>As NP was in the same chemical surrounding, divergent colors were most likely provoked by the different sizes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Figure 4 shows the size distribution estimated by NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>The modal value was 60 nm but the size distribution also exhibited a “shoulder” pointing to a 80 nm subpopulation of particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>A histogram was generated using the color information around the center of each particle which was transformed to the HSB color space. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The hue was than mapped to its monochromatic wavelength. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>As the different colors of NP in Fig. 3 and also the histogram of particle colors (Fig. 4) suggested two different particle populations, we used the color thresholder inbuilt in NanoTrackJ and analyzed green-to-yellow particles (wavelength: 450–582 nm) and orange-to-red particles (wavelength: 583–620 nm) separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>This identified two different NP populations whose modal values exactly amounted to 60 and 80 nm, respectively (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>It is furthermore noteworthy that these two populations were hardly separable without their color information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Also the cluster analysis method, previously devised by us to identify subpopulations of NP (Wagner et al. 2013) during NTA, was unable to separate the subpopulations of the current study.Fig. 5Assignment of color information to the size of gold NP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>The size distribution from Au NPs shown in Fig. 3 was separated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Upper histogram: For the orange distribution, the wavelength range is 583–620 nm and the green size distribution includes particles with a range of 450–582 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The modal values are 60 and 80 nm, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>(Color figure online) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Detection limit of dark field nanoparticle tracking </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The detection limit for NP viewed with DFM is hard to define, as it depends on the type of light source and its intensity, the microscope objective, and the amount of light passing the (variable) aperture. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Also, the sensitivity of the camera is an important part of the experimental setup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>With respect to the particles, the refractive index and the particular properties leading to plasmonic resonance are important to obtain a color image to be evaluated with NanoTrackJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>As stated by Boyer et al. (2002), the minimal detectable plasmonic particle size should be around 40 nm because the Rayleigh scattering decreases as the sixth power of diameter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>In our experiments, 50 nm Au NP was visible by eye and could also be tracked with a color CCD or CMOS camera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In contrast, 50 nm polystyrene NP, which is easily tracked with the NanoSight System, could not be imaged with DFM as used here. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>In case that all optical elements were carefully adjusted images from diffusing 100 nm polystyrene beads became observable and could be tracked with sensitive cameras, suggesting a detection limit for non-plasmonic particles in the 100 nm range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Therefore, DFM will hardly lower the size limit of particles to be analyzed by tracking analysis, which is in the range of 10 nm for gold NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Instead, it is useful to analyze colored NP which, as shown here, can help to identify subpopulations of particles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>First results have also shown that plasmonic particles undergo a color change secondary to cellular uptake (Wang et al. 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This opens new possibilities for visualizing alterations of the chemical surrounding, compartmentalization and/or corona formation of NPs, while simultaneously studying their movement inside cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec14" sec-type="conclusions"><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>DFM is a valuable tool for characterizing nanoparticle suspensions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The technique is especially applicable for nanoparticle tracking from color videos of diffusing plasmonic NPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>The exploitation of the color information can improve the identification of particle subpopulations under defined conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>This means that not only size information may be retrieved, as shown here, but also changes of chemical surrounding and/or particle coating may become experimentally accessible, e.g., during the uptake of NP by cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the open source software NanoTrackJ was devised as a tool for the expanding scientific community of nano researchers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Supplementary material 1 (pdf 55 KB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec15"><title>Appendix</title><sec id="Sec16"><title>Precision analysis: covariance estimator, regression estimator and the Cramer–Rao Bound</title><p>In this section, we will provide a comparison of the precision of the regression and covariance estimator under localization noise. Both estimators are accurate, which means that they are unbiased. The precision of an estimator is quantified by its variance. We will compare the variance of the estimators with each other and, secondly, also with the minimal attainable variance of an unbiased estimator, called the Cramer–Rao bound. To derive this bound, we need a model of the diffusion process which includes localization noise: Let <inline-formula id="IEq50"><alternatives><tex-math id="M54">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x[n]$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq50.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> be the measured positions of a one dimensional diffusion of a particle with the diffusion coefficient <inline-formula id="IEq51"><alternatives><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$D$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq51.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> then<disp-formula id="Equ10"><label>10</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M56">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} x[n]&amp;= x_{true}[n]+\xi _{n} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ10.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ11"><label>11</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} x_{true}[n]&amp;= x_{true}[n-1]+\beta _{n} \end{aligned},$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ11.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <inline-formula id="IEq52"><alternatives><tex-math id="M58">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\beta$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq52.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is normal random variable <inline-formula id="IEq53"><alternatives><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$N(\mu _{\beta }=0,\sigma _{\beta }^{2}=2D\triangle t)$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq53.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> which represents the step length distribution, <inline-formula id="IEq54"><alternatives><tex-math id="M60">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\triangle t$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq54.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the time between two measurements, <inline-formula id="IEq55"><alternatives><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x_{true}[n]$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq55.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the true position of the particle, and <inline-formula id="IEq56"><alternatives><tex-math id="M62">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\xi$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq56.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> is the normal distributed localization noise with mean <inline-formula id="IEq57"><alternatives><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\mu _{\xi }=0$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq57.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> and standard deviation <inline-formula id="IEq58"><alternatives><tex-math id="M64">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\sigma _{\xi }$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq58.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>. For the expected value and the variance of the position differences apply<disp-formula id="Equ12"><label>12</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\langle x[n]-x[n-1]\right\rangle&amp;= \left\langle \beta _{n}\right\rangle +\left\langle \xi {}_{n}\right\rangle +\left\langle -\xi {}_{n-1}\right\rangle =0 \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ12.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ13"><label>13</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M66">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\langle (x[n]-x[n-1])^{2}\right\rangle&amp;= \left\langle \left( \beta _{n}+\xi _{n}-\xi _{n-1}\right) ^{2}\right\rangle \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ13.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ14"><label>14</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned}&amp;= 2D\triangle t+2\sigma _{\xi }^{2} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ14.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>Now we are able to define the likelihood function of the position differences. Let <inline-formula id="IEq59"><alternatives><tex-math id="M68">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$x=(x[0],...,x[N-1])$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq59.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> then the likelihood is<disp-formula id="Equ15"><label>15</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} p_{\chi }(x;D)&amp;= \prod \limits _{1}^{N-1}\frac{\exp \left( -\frac{(x[n]-x[n-1])^{2}}{4D\triangle t+4\sigma _{\xi }^{2}}\right) }{\sqrt{4\pi D\triangle t+4\pi \sigma _{\xi }^{2}}}\end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ15.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula><disp-formula id="Equ16"><label>16</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M70">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \,&amp;= \frac{\exp \left( -\frac{S}{4D\triangle t+4\sigma _{\xi }^{2}}\right) }{(4\pi D\triangle t+4\pi \sigma _{\xi }^{2})^{\frac{(N-1)}{2}}} \end{aligned},$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ16.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where<disp-formula id="Equ17"><label>17</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} S=\sum \limits _{n=1}^{n=N-1}(x[n]-x[n-1])^{2} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ17.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>The second derivative of the log-likelihood is<disp-formula id="Equ18"><label>18</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M72">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \frac{\partial ^{2}\, ln\, p(x;D)}{\partial ^{2}D}&amp;= \frac{(N-1)\triangle t{}^{2}}{2(D\triangle t+\sigma _{\xi }^{2})^{2}}-\frac{\triangle t{}^{2}S}{2(D\triangle t+\sigma _{\xi }^{2})^{3}} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ18.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>and taking the expectation results in<disp-formula id="Equ19"><label>19</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} \left\langle \frac{\partial ^{2}\, ln\, p(x;D)}{\partial ^{2}D}\right\rangle&amp;= -\frac{(N-1)\triangle t{}^{2}}{2(D\triangle t+\sigma _{\xi }^{2})^{2}} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ19.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>This leads to the Cramer–Rao inequality<disp-formula id="Equ20"><label>20</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M74">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} var(\hat{D)}\ge -\frac{1}{\left\langle \frac{\partial ^{2}\, ln\, p(x;D)}{\partial ^{2}D}\right\rangle }=\frac{2(D\triangle t+\sigma _{\xi }^{2})^{2}}{(\triangle t)^{2}(N-1)} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ20.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>To compare the precision of the estimators, we have carried out Monte Carlo simulations. Therefore, we define a signal to noise ratio as<disp-formula id="Equ21"><label>21</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M75">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\begin{aligned} SNR=\frac{\sqrt{2D\triangle t}}{\sigma _{\xi }} \end{aligned}$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_Equ21.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>For each signal to noise ratio, 3,000 trajectories with tracklength of 30 were generated and the variance was calculated. Figure <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows the precision comparison of the covariance estimator suggested by Vestergaard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2012</xref>) and the regression estimators based on the time lag <inline-formula id="IEq60"><alternatives><tex-math id="M76">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$2-5$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq60.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (<inline-formula id="IEq61"><alternatives><tex-math id="M77">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{2-5}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq61.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) and <inline-formula id="IEq62"><alternatives><tex-math id="M78">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$1-2$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq62.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> (<inline-formula id="IEq63"><alternatives><tex-math id="M79">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{1-2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq63.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) as suggested by Ernst and Köhler (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2013</xref>) and Wieser and Schütz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2008</xref>), respectively.<SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Variance for different diffusion coefficient estimators versus the signal to noise ratio for simulated trajectories </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Fig6_HTML" id="MO27"/></fig></SecTag></p><p>For signal to noise ratios below 1, the <inline-formula id="IEq64"><alternatives><tex-math id="M80">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{2-5}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq64.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> estimator has a higher precision than the <inline-formula id="IEq65"><alternatives><tex-math id="M81">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{1-2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq65.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> estimator. For more practically relevant signal to noise ratios (&gt;1), the <inline-formula id="IEq66"><alternatives><tex-math id="M82">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$R_{1-2}$$\end{document}</tex-math><inline-graphic xlink:href="11051_2014_2419_Article_IEq66.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula> estimator has a significant higher precision. The covariance estimator provides a higher precision as both regression estimators for all signal to noise ratios but does not attain the Cramer–Rao bound even for large SNRs. However, the Cramer–Rao bound does not provide any information if such an estimator even exists. We, therefore, recommend that the covariance estimator should be used instead of the regression estimator because of its higher precision and easy implementation which needs no numerical fitting.</p></sec></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>This paper was supported by Grants of the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF, NanoGEM Project, FKZ 03X0105G, and 03X0105H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>We thank Martin Ward from the University of Edinburgh for helpful discussions and software testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>AnkerJNHallWPLyandresOShahNCZhaoJVan DuyneRPBiosensing with plasmonic nanosensorsNat Mater2008764425310.1038/nmat216218497851 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>ASTM (2012) Standard guide for measurement of particle size distribution of nanomaterials in suspension by nanoparticle tracking analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>BinghamJWilletsKLocalized surface plasmon resonance imaging: simultaneous single nanoparticle spectroscopy and diffusional dynamicsJ Phys Chem C Nanomater Interfaces2009416,83916,84210.1021/jp907377h </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>BoyerDTamaratPMaaliALounisBOrritMPhotothermal imaging of nanometer-sized metal particles among scatterersScience200229755841160310.1126/science.107376512183624 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Buecker P (2007) Integration of receptors into inert matrices for the label-free and quantitative detection of biospecific interactions with LSPR-active nanoparticle-surfaces. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>PhD Thesis, University Heidelberg </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>BuzeaCPachecoIIRobbieKNanomaterials and nanoparticles: sources and toxicityBiointerphases200724MR17MR7110.1116/1.281569020419892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>CaiWGaoTHongHSunJApplications of gold nanoparticles in cancer nanotechnologyNanotechnol Sci Appl20081173224198458 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>CheezumMKWalkerWFGuilfordWHQuantitative comparison of algorithms for tracking single fluorescent particlesBiophys J200181423788810.1016/S0006-3495(01)75884-511566807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>der MeerenPVKasinosMSaveynHSolovievMRelevance of two-dimensional Brownian motion dynamics in applying nanoparticle tracking analysisNanoparticles in biology and medicine, methods in molecular biology2012TotowaHumana Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>El-BrolossyTAbdallahTMohamedMBAbdallahSEasawiKNegmSTalaatHShape and size dependence of the surface plasmon resonance of gold nanoparticles studied by Photoacoustic techniqueEur Phys J Spec Topics2008153136136410.1140/epjst/e2008-00462-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>ErnstDKö hlerJHow the number of fitting points for the slope of the mean-square displacement influences the experimentally determined particle size distribution from single-particle trackingPhys Chem Chem Phys201315103429343210.1039/c3cp44391d23381508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>FilipeVHaweAJiskootWCritical evaluation of nanoparticle tracking analysis (NTA) by NanoSight for the measurement of nanoparticles and protein aggregatesPharm Res201027579681010.1007/s11095-010-0073-220204471 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>HolePSillenceKHannellCMaguireCMRoessleinMSuarezGCapracottaSMagdolenovaZHorev-AzariaLDybowskaACookeLHaaseAContalSManøSVennemannASauvainJJStauntonKCAnguissolaSLuchADusinskaMKorensteinRGutlebACWiemannMPrina-MelloARiedikerMWickPInterlaboratory comparison of size measurements on nanoparticles using nanoparticle tracking analysis (NTA)J Nanoparticle Res2013152027210110.1007/s11051-013-2101-8 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>KellyKLCoronadoEZhaoLLSchatzGCThe optical properties of metal nanoparticles: the influence of size, shape, and dielectric environmentJ Phys Chem B2003107366867710.1021/jp026731y </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>LinkSEl-SayedMASize and temperature dependence of the plasmon absorption of colloidal gold nanoparticlesJ Phys Chem B1999103214212421710.1021/jp984796o </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>MichaletXBerglundAOptimal diffusion coefficient estimation in single-particle trackingPhys Rev E2012856061,91610.1103/PhysRevE.85.061916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>RingeESharmaBHenryAIMarksLDVan DuyneRPSingle nanoparticle plasmonicsPhys Chem Chem Phys2013151241102910.1039/c3cp44574g23420338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>SagleLBRuvunaLKBinghamJMLiuCCremerPSVan DuyneRPSingle plasmonic nanoparticle tracking studies of solid supported bilayers with ganglioside lipidsJ Am Chem Soc20121343815,83215,83910.1021/ja305409522136359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>SiedentopfHZsigmondyRUber Sichtbarmachung und Grö ß enbestimmung ultramikoskopischer Teilchen, mit besonderer Anwendung auf Goldrubinglä serAnn Phys1902315113910.1002/andp.19023150102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>SönnichsenCAlivisatosAPGold nanorods as novel nonbleaching plasmon-based orientation sensors for polarized single-particle microscopyNano lett20055230130410.1021/nl048089k15794615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>StoneVNowackBBaunAVan Den BrinkNKammerFVDDusinskaMHandyRHankinSHassellövMJonerEFernandesTFNanomaterials for environmental studies: classification, reference material issues, and strategies for physico-chemical characterisationSci Total Environ201040871745175410.1016/j.scitotenv.2009.10.03519903569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Vestergaard C (2012) Optimal estimation of diffusion coefficients from noisy time-lapse-recorded single-particle trajectories. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>PhD Thesis, Technical University of Denmark </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>WagnerTWiemannMSchmitzILipinskiHGA cluster-based method for improving analysis of polydisperse particle size distributions obtained by nanoparticle trackingJ Nanoparticle201320131910.1155/2013/936150 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Wagner T, Wiemann M, Lipinski HG (2014) NanoTrackJ: size characterization of freely diffusing nanoparticles by nanoparticle tracking. figshare. doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.805052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>WalkerJGImproved nano-particle tracking analysisMeas Sci Technol2012236065,60510.1088/0957-0233/23/6/065605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>WangSHLeeCWChiouAWeiPKSize-dependent endocytosis of gold nanoparticles studied by three-dimensional mapping of plasmonic scattering imagesJ Nanobiotechnol2010813310.1186/1477-3155-8-33 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>WieserSSchü tzGJTracking single molecules in the live cell plasma membrane-Do’s and Don’t’sMethods200846213114010.1016/j.ymeth.2008.06.01018634880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>YangZLiuZWAllakerRPReipPOxfordJAhmadZRenGA review of nanoparticle functionality and toxicity on the central nervous systemJ R Soc Interface20107Suppl\_441142210.1098/rsif.2010.0158.focus </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
