
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Case Rep Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Case Rep Genet</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">CRIG</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Case Reports in Genetics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-6544</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-6552</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4212645</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/517091</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Case Report</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Atypical Association of Angelman Syndrome and Klinefelter Syndrome in a Boy with 47,XXY Karyotype and Deletion 15q11.2-q13 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sánchez</surname><given-names>Javier</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peciña</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso-Luengo</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>González-Meneses</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vázquez</surname><given-names>Rocío</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Antiñolo</surname><given-names>Guillermo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2513-6161</contrib-id><name><surname>Borrego</surname><given-names>Salud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Department of Genetics, Reproduction and Fetal Medicine, Institute of Biomedicine of Seville (IBIS), University Hospital Virgen del Rocío/CSIC/University of Seville, 41013 Seville, Spain</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Centre of Biomedical Network Research on Rare Diseases (CIBERER), 41013 Seville, Spain</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Pediatrics, University Hospital Virgen del Rocío, Avenida Manuel Siurot s/n, 41013 Seville, Spain</aff><aff id="I4"><sup>4</sup>Department of Neurophysiology, University Hospital Virgen del Rocío, Avenida Manuel Siurot s/n, 41013 Seville, Spain</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Salud Borrego: <email>salud.borrego.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editor: Jose Luis Royo </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>2014</volume><elocation-id>517091</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>18</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2014 Javier Sánchez et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Angelman syndrome (AS, OMIM 105830) is a neurogenetic disorder with firm clinical diagnostic guidelines, characterized by severe developmental delay and speech impairment, balanced and behavioral disturbance as well as microcephaly, seizures, and a characteristic electroencephalogram (EEG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The majority of AS cases (70%) are caused by a 15q11.2-q13 deletion on the maternally derived chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>The frequency of AS has been estimated to be between 1/10000 and 1/20000. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Klinefelter syndrome (KS) occurs due to the presence of an extra X chromosome (karyotype 47,XXY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The main features in KS are small testes, hypergonadotropic hypogonadism, gynecomastia, learning difficulties, and infertility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We present what is, to our knowledge, the first case of a patient with both KS and AS due to a 15q11.2-q13 deletion on the maternally derived chromosome and an extra X chromosome of paternal origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>He showed dysmorphic features, axial hypotonia, and delayed acquisition of motor skills. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Early diagnosis is essential for optimal treatment of AS children; this is one of the earliest diagnosed cases of AS probably due to the presence of two syndromes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Clinical findings in this patient here described may be helpful to identify any other cases and to evaluate recurrence risks in these families. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Angelman syndrome (AS, OMIM 105830) is a neurogenetic disorder with firm clinical diagnostic guidelines, characterized by severe developmental delay and speech impairment as well as balanced and behavioral disturbance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Other frequent clinical features include microcephaly, seizures, and a characteristic electroencephalogram (EEG) [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The majority of AS cases (70%) are caused by a 15q11.2-q13 deletion on the maternally derived chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Other less frequent genetic mechanisms are paternal uniparental disomy of 15 chromosome (7%), imprinting defects (3%), or mutations in the maternal copy of the UBE3A gene (11%) [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The frequency of AS has been estimated to be between 1/10000 and 1/20000 [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Recurrence risk varies from &lt;1% for deletion cases where no chromosome rearrangements or germinal mosaicism is present [4–6] to 50% for maternally inherited imprinting center deletions or UBE3A mutations [7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Klinefelter syndrome (KS) also shows a clear clinical pattern, although no firm guidelines for diagnosis exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The main features in KS are small testes, hypergonadotropic hypogonadism, gynecomastia, learning difficulties, and infertility [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>KS occurs due to the presence of an extra X chromosome (karyotype 47,XXY) and the underlying putative genetic cause is that some genes escape inactivation of the extra X chromosome [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>KS affects one in 150 per 100,000 male newborns and is the most common sex chromosome disorder in males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Since KS patients show great phenotypic variability, the majority of patients are diagnosed during the second decade of life and it is difficult to diagnose KS without cytogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>In some instances chromosomal analysis is performed due to development delay, learning difficulties, or behavior problems [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Taking into account the incidence rates for both AS and KS, the anticipated incidence of both syndromes occurring together would be around 1 in 6–12 million by chance alone. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Here we present what is, to our knowledge, the first case of a patient with both KS and AS due to a 15q11.2-q13 deletion on the maternally derived chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>To date, few patients with KS and other microdeletion syndromes have been reported: six cases of KS and Prader-Willi syndrome (PWS) due to a 15q11.2-q13 deletion on the paternally derived chromosome have been published [11], a patient with KS and 22q11 microdeletion [12] and a combination of KS and 7q11.23 deletion (Williams syndrome) [13]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Patient Description </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The propositus was the second child born to a healthy 33-year-old mother with a previous healthy son, now three years old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>The parents were not consanguineous, and no remarkable family history was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>During pregnancy, she developed diabetes mellitus, which was well controlled by her diet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The mother reported the first fetal movements at 22-week gestation, with reduced fetal movements throughout the pregnancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>The propositus was delivered spontaneously at 37-week gestation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>His birth weight was 3,190 g and head circumference was 34 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Apgar scores were 9 (1 min), 9 (5 min), and 10 (10 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Severe hypotonia, feeding difficulties, and continuous crying were noted at birth. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>At 8 months his head circumference was 46 cm (p75), weight 9,555 g (p90), and height 70 cm (p75–p90). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>He showed delayed acquisition of motor skills, he could not remain seated or handle objects, and axial hypotonia was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>He showed dysmorphic features, occipital flattening, a thin upper lip, a wide mouth, tongue protrusion, a broad nasal root, and divergent strabismus (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>A brain MRI showed a structurally normal brain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The EEG at 8 months showed diffuse high-amplitude 4–6 Hz activity and posterior intermittent rhythmic delta waves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>No epileptiform discharges were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Three months later, the EEG showed no significant changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Chromosome analysis and PWS/AS were performed due to dysmorphic features and hypotonia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Informed consent was obtained from all participants for clinical and molecular genetic studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The study conformed to the tenets of the declaration of Helsinki as well as the requirements established by our institutional review board. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood cytogenetic analysis revealed 47 chromosomes, with an extra X chromosome, karyotype 47,XXY (KS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>FISH analysis with specific probes (D15Z1/SNRPN/PML) [Vysis, Downers Grove, IL] revealed a deletion of the SNRPN locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Karyotype: 47,XXY.ish del (15)(q11.2q11.2)(SNRPN-)[20] (Figures 2 and 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>No deletion or rearrangements were observed in the parents' karyotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Molecular analysis using Multiple Ligation Probe Amplification methodology (SALSA MLPA probemix kit P245-A2, MRC-Holland, Amsterdam, NL) confirmed the deletion of the PWS/AS critical region, while the dose of control probes located at 15q24.1 was normal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>In order to determine the origin of the chromosome with the 15q11.2-q13 deletion, we analyzed five microsatellite markers: D15S541, D15S11, and GABR3, located within the critical region of PWS/AS, and D15S131 and D15S984 located outside of the critical region, which were used as controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Analysis of D15S541, D15S11, and GABR3 markers confirmed the deletion of 15q11.2-q13 on the maternal chromosome (AS) (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Control markers showed paternal and maternal 15 chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The paternal origin of the extra X chromosome was determined by analysis of a set of microsatellites located on the X chromosome by multiplex PCR (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this is the first case of a patient with coexisting AS and KS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The combined effects of both syndromes are not clear, since the patient is currently only 11 months old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The main phenotypic effects in KS are manifested in the mid-30s and in AS do not appear until 2-3 years after birth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>This is one of the earliest diagnosed cases of AS, and it may be due to the presence of two syndromes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We can expect that the main phenotypic features that he will exhibit will be those of AS, since typical KS clinical features are much milder. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>We showed that the extra X chromosome was of paternal origin and the deletion in 15 chromosome was of maternal origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Paternal and maternal sex chromosome nondisjunction contribute equally as causes of KS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Both parents were young and had normal karyotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the abnormalities are most probably a coincidental event in our patient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>In light of this, we estimate that the recurrence risk in the next pregnancy for both syndromes is low. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Early diagnosis is essential for optimal treatment of AS children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Abnormal EEG is used as diagnostic criteria since it is present in almost all AS patients [1, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that EEG abnormalities are age-dependent: they usually appear early and decrease with age [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Seizures are a common feature observed in AS patients [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Seizures and EEG abnormalities were not detected in our patient, maybe because he is 11 months old and these do not usually occur until 22–24 months of age. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The most likely situation is that both conditions are coincidental. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Therefore, to calculate risk, both conditions must be considered separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Hence, KS patients with uncommon clinical features—such as the hypotonia, feeding difficulties, or frequent laughing observed in our patient—may be considered for assessment of another associated condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Since there are no prenatal findings of AS and/or KS, for this couple we recommend offering cytogenetic prenatal diagnosis and FISH or array-CGH for AS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to acknowledge the patient and his family for their kind cooperation and for providing the figure. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec sec-type="conflict"><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interests.</p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>1WilliamsC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>A.BeaudetA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>L.Clayton-SmithJ.KnollJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>H.KyllermanM.LaanL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A.MagenisR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>E.MonclaA.SchinzelA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>A.SummersJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>A.WagstaffJ.Angelman syndrome 2005: updated consensus for diagnostic criteriaAmerican Journal of Medical Genetics2006140541341810.1002/ajmg.a.310742-s2.0-3364486549116470747 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>2DagliA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>I.WilliamsC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A.PagonR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>A.AdamM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>P.BirdT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>D.Angelman SyndromeGeneReviews [Internet]2013Seattle, Wash, USAUniversity of Washington<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1144/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK1144/</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>3van BuggenhoutG.FrynsJ.-P.Angelman syndrome (AS, MIM 105830)European Journal of Human Genetics200917111367137310.1038/ejhg.2009.672-s2.0-7035035271819455185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>4StalkerH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>J.WilliamsC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>A.Genetic counseling in Angelman syndrome: the challenges of multiple causesAmerican Journal of Medical Genetics199877154599557895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>5CamprubíC.CollM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>D.GabauE.GuitartM.Prader-Willi and Angelman syndromes: genetic counselingEuropean Journal of Human Genetics201018215415510.1038/ejhg.2009.1702-s2.0-7444908954019809481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>6SánchezJ.FernándezR.MadrugaM.Bernabeu-WittelJ.AntiñoloG.BorregoS.Somatic and germ-line mosaicism of deletion 15q11.2-q13 in a mother of dyzigotic twins with Angelman syndromeAmerican Journal of Medical Genetics Part A2014164237037610.1002/ajmg.a.362812-s2.0-84892894469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>7WilliamsC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>A.DriscollD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>J.DagliA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>I.Clinical and genetic aspects of Angelman syndromeGenetics in Medicine201012738539510.1097/GIM.0b013e3181def1382-s2.0-7795517345420445456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>8SmythC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>M.BremnerW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>J.Klinefelter syndromeArchives of Internal Medicine1998158121309131410.1001/archinte.158.12.13092-s2.0-00318065719645824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>9GrothK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>A.SkakkebækA.HøstC.GravholtC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>H.BojesenA.Clinical review: Klinefelter syndrome—a clinical updateJournal of Clinical Endocrinology and Metabolism2013981203010.1210/jc.2012-23822-s2.0-8487208952823118429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>10AksglaedeL.LinkK.GiwercmanA.JørgensenN.SkakkebækN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>E.JuulA.47,XXY Klinefelter syndrome: Clinical characteristics and age-specific recommendations for medical managementAmerican Journal of Medical Genetics C: Seminars in Medical Genetics20131631556310.1002/ajmg.c.313492-s2.0-84873086506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>11VasudevanP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>C.QuarrellO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>J.Prader-willi and klinefelter syndrome: a coincidence or not?Clinical Dysmorphology200716212712910.1097/MCD.0b013e32801472cf2-s2.0-3394710156717351360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>12VelagaletiG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>N.KumarA.LockhartL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>H.MatalonR.Patent ductus arteriosus and microdeletion 22q11 in a patient with Klinefelter syndromeAnnales de Génétique20004321051072-s2.0-003379843010998453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>13LeY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>L.SweeC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Q.ChongS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>S.TanA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>C.LumJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>S.GohD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>M.Clinical report: a case of Williams syndrome and Klinefelter syndromeAnnals of the Academy of Medicine Singapore200635129019042-s2.0-33847715456 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>14ThibertR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>L.LarsonA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>M.HsiehD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>T.RabyA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>R.ThieleE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>A.Neurologic manifestations of Angelman syndromePediatric Neurology201348427127910.1016/j.pediatrneurol.2012.09.0152-s2.0-8487515362823498559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>15UemuraN.MatsumotoA.NakamuraM.WatanabeK.NegoroT.KumagaiT.MiuraK.OhkiT.MizunoS.OkumuraA.AsoK.HayakawaF.KondoY.Evolution of seizures and electroencephalographical findings in 23 cases of deletion type Angelman syndromeBrain and Development200527538338810.1016/j.braindev.2004.01.0092-s2.0-2224447545015963670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Facial appearance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Dysmorphic features, broad nasal root, and thin upper lip. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIG2014-517091.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Karyotype showing the presence of an extra X chromosome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIG2014-517091.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>FISH analysis in metaphase with specific probes for 15 chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Upper 15 chromosome with SNRPN deletion (del 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>D15Z1, SpectrumAqua; SNRPN, SpectrumOrange; PML, SpectrumGreen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIG2014-517091.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite analysis and pedigree of the family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite from X chromosome showed one of paternal origin and other of maternal origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Microsatellite from 15 chromosome showed a deletion of D15S541, D15S11, GARB3, and D15S113 of maternal origin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="CRIG2014-517091.004"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
