
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4308911</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25547313</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">383</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-014-0383-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>CenH3 evolution in diploids and polyploids of three angiosperm genera </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Masonbrink</surname><given-names>Rick E</given-names></name><address><email>remkv6@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>Joseph P</given-names></name><address><email>jpg@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jareczek</surname><given-names>Josef J</given-names></name><address><email>jareczek@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Renny-Byfield</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><address><email>simonrb@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grover</surname><given-names>Corrinne E</given-names></name><address><email>corrinne@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><address><email>gongl086@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wendel</surname><given-names>Jonathan F</given-names></name><address><email>jfw@iastate.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1">Department of Ecology, Evolution, and Organismal Biology, Iowa State University, Ames, IA 50011 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>383</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>12</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Masonbrink et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Centromeric DNA sequences alone are neither necessary nor sufficient for centromere specification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The centromere specific histone, CenH3, evolves rapidly in many species, perhaps as a coevolutionary response to rapidly evolving centromeric DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>To gain insight into CenH3 evolution, we characterized patterns of nucleotide and protein diversity among diploids and allopolyploids within three diverse angiosperm genera, Brassica, Oryza, and Gossypium (cotton), with a focus on evidence for diversifying selection in the various domains of the CenH3 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In addition, we compare expression profiles and alternative splicing patterns for CenH3 in representatives of each genus. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>All three genera retain both duplicated CenH3 copies, while Brassica and Gossypium exhibit pronounced homoeologous expression level bias. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Comparisons among genera reveal shared and unique aspects of CenH3 evolution, variable levels of diversifying selection in different CenH3 domains, and that alternative splicing contributes significantly to CenH3 diversity. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Since the N terminus is subject to diversifying selection but the DNA binding domains do not appear to be, rapidly evolving centromere sequences are unlikely to be the primary driver of CenH3 sequence diversification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>At present, the functional explanation for the diversity generated by both conventional protein evolution in the N terminal domain, as well as alternative splicing, remains unexplained. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12870-014-0383-3) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Diversifying selection</kwd><kwd><italic>CenH3</italic> evolution</kwd><kwd>Alternative splicing</kwd><kwd>Centromeres</kwd><kwd><italic>Gossypium</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Brassica</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Oryza</italic></kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The centromere is a specific region of the eukaryotic chromosome that is the assembly point of the kinetochore, a group of proteins that act as a tether for microtubules during cell division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Although eukaryotic centromeres have highly conserved machinery for chromosome segregation, centromere sequences and binding proteins specific to centromeric chromatin are highly variable, even among closely related taxa [1,2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Specific retroelements and highly homogenized tandem repeats are common in the DNA of eukaryotic centromeres [3,4], though these too apparently diverge rapidly among closely related species [2,5,6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Appropriate recruitment of these potentially co-evolving molecular components to the same site is enigmatic, as is their mechanism of spread and homogenization among chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Explanations for the apparent paradox between conservation of function but variability in sequence typically invoke an interplay between centromere function, centromere sequences, and epigenetic factors, such that DNA sequences per se become less functionally constrained [2,6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, it is generally accepted that centromeres are specified epigenetically [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>The evolution of CenH3 is of particular interest due to its centrality in centromere specification and function [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Unlike its highly conserved counterpart (histone H3), CenH3 has extensive sequence variability, particularly in two regions: (1) the non-canonical NH2 terminal tail, (2) the longer loop 1 region [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>DNA sequence diversity as well as alternative splicing can both play roles in generating diversity, which is thought to compensate for the fast-evolving centromeric DNA to ensure consistent centromeric function, although centromeric sequences are neither necessary nor sufficient for kinetochore assembly [2,11]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Given the twin observations of rapid sequence homogenization of centromeric repeats among chromosomes within species, yet rapid divergence among repeats between species, the question arises as to the fate of centromeric repeats, and CenH3 evolution, in allopolyploids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Polyploidy plays an integral role in the evolution of many organisms, particularly plants [12-14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The consequences of polyploidy are often extensive [15-23], and the resulting duplicated genes have myriad possible fates [18,24], including gene loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Patterns of gene retention and loss following genome duplication have been extensively studied with respect to their broad classifications [25-29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Because two presumably divergent suites of centromeric sequences become reunited into common nucleus at the time of allopolyploid formation, it is intriguing to investigate the subsequent evolutionary dynamics of the centromeric repeats as well as the now duplicated CenH3 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In most modern diploids, CenH3 appears to have returned to single copy status following paleopolyploidy events [30], with a few notable exceptions [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>In contrast, recent allopolyploids often have multiple CenH3 gene copies [30-32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Here we evaluate the fate of CenH3 in allopolyploids from three divergent genera (Brassica, Oryza, and Gossypium) to address the question of whether the evolution of CenH3 is similar across a broad range of angiosperm taxa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>The genera selected contain a diversity of allopolyploid species having either monophyletic or polyphyletic origins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The Brassica genus contains three diverse and widely cultivated diploid species (genomes designated A – C) and three allopolyploid species resulting from independent polyploidization events (BBCC, AACC, AABB) [33], while Oryza contains multiple diploid genome groups (designated A – G) and allopolyploids of diverse genomic origin (BBCC, CCDD, and HHJJ) [34]. Gossypium includes 45 diploid species divided into genome groups designated A – G and K [19], as well as a single, monophyletic [35] polyploid clade (AD genome) containing 6 species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Previous work on CenH3 in Brassica and Oryza allopolyploids has focused on selection in specific regions of the gene and the relative expression of the retained homoeologs [30,32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Less is known about CenH3 and centromeric evolution in allopolyploid Gossypium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>A prior study reported a centromeric gypsy-like retroelement (CRG) present in all centromeres of both the allotetraploid G. hirsutum (AD-genome) and the model progenitor D-genome diploid (G. raimondii), but absent from A-genome species [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Neither the sequence nor the expression of duplicated CenH3 have been evaluated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We characterize CenH3 sequence evolution on in three phylogenetically disparate angiosperm genera containing diploids and allopolyploids, and assess patterns of molecular evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>We address whether allopolyploids retain duplicated copies following allopolyploid formation; the dynamics of sequence evolution of the duplicated, newly co-resident sequences; and the relative expression levels of homoeologous copies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In addition to reporting on CenH3 sequence evolution within and between genera, we describe novel patterns of alternative splicing in CenH3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>We cloned and sequenced the CenH3 genes from 7 diploid and 5 allotetraploid Gossypium species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The length of genomic sequences varied from 2565 to 2673 bp in the diploids and 2654 to 2673 bp in the polyploids (Additional file 1), although protein-coding length was consistent for all species, 492 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>While length variation was not detected among cDNAs, we cannot account for length variation that occurs outside of our external primers in the first and last exons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The structure of CenH3, 7 exons and 6 introns, was conserved among all polyploid species, (diploid cDNA sequences were inferred from genomic sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>As expected, CenH3 was largely conserved across the genus, with the majority of polymorphisms occurring in introns. Gossypium exiguum exhibited the greatest difference observed among the diploids (93 bp deletion in intron 6); the remainder of the polymorphisms were small (&lt;10 bp), five of which were phylogenetically informative (Additional file 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Since CenH3 is thought to co-evolve with rapidly changing centromeric DNA, we mapped nonsynonymous substitutions to the secondary protein structure for three genera (Brassica, Oryza, and Gossypium) (Figure 1) in order to localize evolution along the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The N terminus was the only domain with high levels of nonsynonymous substitutions that was consistent between all three genera. Brassica had the highest numbers of nonsynonomous substitutions, which was followed by Oryza and then Gossypium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>This observation is in agreement with previous analyses which show that rates of molecular evolution are faster in herbaceous plants (Oryza and Brassica) than in trees and shrubs (Gossypium) [37].Figure 13D structures of CenH3 proteins from a single species in each genus. a. Brassica napus (AC8). b. Oryza australiensis isolate (EE). c. Gossypium raimondii (D5). The secondary protein structures are depicted below each 3D model containing nonsynonymous SNPs within each genus mapped to the secondary structure of the CenH3 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The different shades of blue signify the borders of each protein domain; α signifies an alpha helix and L signifies a loop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Black rectangles signify nonsynonymous SNPs, while yellow rectangles signify nonsynonymous SNPs under positive selection (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The N terminus was the primary site of length variation among the three genera and the long black rectangle in the N terminus of the Brassica CenH3 signifies gaps in the alignment among Brassica species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To determine the extent of CenH3 evolution, we compared Ka/Ks (nonsynonymous/synonymous substitutions) ratios for all CDSs of a species from each genus with respect to an outgroup. CenH3 is indeed a relatively fast evolving gene, with the Brassica, Oryza, and Gossypium genes falling in the 81st, 85th, and 97th percentile of all genes in these genomes, respectively (Figure 2).Figure 2 The Ka/Ks ratio for the CDS from a representative species of Brassica, Oryza, and Gossypium. Each representative species was used to compare the rate of CenH3 evolution to other genes in each genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The y-axis is the number of genes that correspond to the Ka/Ks bin values on the x-axis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The blue line is the whole genome Ka/Ks, and the orange line is CenH3 from each taxon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>To quantify CenH3 evolution in each genus we estimated the mean Ka/Ks of CenH3 using DNAsp (Table 1) [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The overall mean Ka/Ks ratios within each genus and between each genus and an outgroup all indicate that diversifying selection is absent from the CenH3 gene as a whole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To determine whether this finding is consistent at a finer scale, we used the mixed effects model of evolution software (MEME) [39] to evaluate selection at the codon level in each genus (Table 2, Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>In Brassica and Oryza, the only codons with evidence suggestive of diversifying selection were limited to the N terminus, while no evidence of diversifying selection was found for Gossypium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Inferred codons subject to selection in Oryza and Brassica were phylogenetically episodic and specific to only a few species for each codon (Figure 3).Table 1 Jukes Cantor corrected estimates of Ka/Ks within each genus, and between each genus and outgroup Table 2 Significant p-values associated with codons in Brassica and Oryza , as inferred from MEME analysis Figure 3 Episodic diversifying selection in Brassica and Oryza , as inferred using MEME. Each phylogeny represents a single codon exhibiting diversifying selection in the specified genus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The scale bar represents distance and EBF is the empirical Bayes factor, which signifies diversifying selection with warm colors and stabilizing selection with cool colors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Particular branches are labeled with numbers, which correspond to the Ka:Ks of a single codon on the right of each phylogeny. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>CenH3 evolution in allopolyploids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Given the single copy status observed in most diploid angiosperms sequenced to date, despite an evolutionary history, which encompasses multiple episodes of polyploidy, we wished to address whether or not CenH3 has been retained in duplicate following recent allopolyploidy events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In Gossypium, we found that each diploid representative had a single CenH3 gene and that all allopolyploid species had two, indicating retention of both parental copies, as reported for Brassica and Oryza [30,32,40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>To address whether or not duplicated CenH3 sequences evolve independently of one another following allopolyploid formation, or if instead they are subjected to some form of sequence interaction or homogenization, we manually analyzed CenH3 sequences from all three genera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>This lack of independence has been demonstrated for other homoeologous single copy genes in allopolyploids, most notably in Gossypium where the phenomenon was first described [41,42]. CenH3 gene conversion was absent in all three genera, which is consistent with previous reports in Brassica and Oryza [30,32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA sequences for CenH3 from Gossypium were used to construct a maximum likelihood tree, which concurs with the currently accepted phylogeny for the genus (Additional file 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>We resolved monophyletic clades for both the AT and DT homoeologs and their respective model diploid progenitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Gene conversion was not detected in the homoeologs, further confirming that independent evolution of CenH3 homeologs occurred in this 1–2 MYD polyploid clade. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>CenH3 gene expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>As mentioned above, there are various possible fates for genes duplicated via polyploidy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>While both parental copies of CenH3 were retained in all studied allopolyploid species of Oryza, Brassica, and Gossypium, the transcriptional usage of each parental copy can vary from equivalent to complete silencing of one parental copy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>To assess expression of CenH3 in Gossypium, we used three independent methods that allow us to assess the relative expression of homoeologs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The same tissue source was used for clone-counting and chromatogram measurements, while RNA-seq data from different sources was used to investigate other aspects of CenH3 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The RNA-seq data sources included (A2 vs D5) to determine the relative expression of CenH3 in the model diploid progenitors to the cotton polyploids, a synthetic hybrid between these two diploids (A2XD5F1), a synthetic polyploid (2_A2D1), and a domesticated and wild accession of AD1 (maxxa and yuc respectively). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The three methods to analyze expression resulted in differing degrees of homoeolog bias (where AT and DT are used to denote the two homoeologs), which was moderate in the RNA-seq data, and more extreme in the other methods (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>AT homoeolog, expression was favored in every species, tissue, and test (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>With RNA-seq data we compared the total expression levels of the model progenitor diploids (A2 vs D5), a synthetic polyploid (2(A2D1)), and wild and domesticated accessions of AD1 (yucatanense and Maxxa, respectively), all of which lacked a significant difference in expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The only sample with a significant expression bias was the F1(A2D5), biased at 87.5% (P ≤ 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The difference in homoeolog expression was not significantly different (T test) between leaf and bud tissue, except that AT homoeolog expression was significantly higher in leaves for G. barbadense (P = 1.1024 × 10−10).Figure 4 Homoeolog expression of CenH3 in Gossypium species. AD1-AD5 denote G. hirsutum, G. barbadense, G. tomentosum, G. mustelinum, and G. darwinii, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>The L and B suffixes denote leaf and bud tissue, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>A2 vs D5 is a comparison of the total level of expression in the model diploid progenitor species, G. arboreum (A) and G. raimondii (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>A2xD5F1 is an F1 hybrid between G. arboreum and G. raimondii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>2_A2D1 is a colchicine-doubled F1 hybrid between G. arboreum (A) and G. thurberi (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>AD1_maxxa and AD1_yuc are domesticated and wild accessions of G. hirsutum, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Only partial data were generated for AD1B and AD4B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Standard deviations are represented by the error bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>A single asterisk represents samples that were statistically significant below 0.05, while two asterisks represent significant below 0.01. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Due to the sequence similarity between homoeologs, specific primers could not be designed for quantitative PCR, and thus we measured homoeolog expression bias with three separate methods, accompanied by different caveats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Due to the low number of SNPs between the homoeologs, a large number of RNA-seq reads could not be allocated to a particular homoeolog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>We also cloned CenH3 cDNAs, which were counted to calculate relative expression of homoeologs, albeit with a smaller sample size (Additional file 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Alternative splicing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Alternative splicing of transcripts is one mechanism by which novel proteins are created, which conceivably may provide the diversity for interaction between rapidly evolving partners like CenH3 and centromeric DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>To address how alternative splicing affects CenH3, we assessed the level of alternative splicing for each homoeolog of CenH3 in allopolyploid Gossypium by cloning and sequencing the amplified CenH3 cDNAs from leaf and leaf bud tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The sum frequency of alternatively spliced transcripts for both tissues was 26.7% (55/206 transcripts) and consisted of 33 exon deletions and 22 intron retentions (relative to the major variant) for all allopolyploids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Three splicing variants were found in all species evaluated (Figure 5): (1) 45 bp intron retention at position 99 (8.3% of transcripts); (2) a 6 bp exon deletion from position 137–142 (9.2% of transcripts); and (3) a 39 bp exon deletion in AT homeologs from 137–175 (3.4% of all transcripts or 4.9% of AT transcripts; Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>One splicing variant, a 12 bp intron retention, was shared only between G. hirsutum (AD1) and G. tomentosum (AD3) (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The most common splicing variants resulted in either a slight deletion or extension of the N terminus, thus adding diversity to an already rapidly evolving domain of CenH3, while the least common splicing variants resulted in nonfunctional protein predictions.Figure 5 Frequency of splicing variants in all Gossypium allopolyploids. Splicing variants found from cloning PCR amplified cDNAs and displayed as a percent of the total number of clones obtained from each species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>For the “All” category the splicing variants are displayed as a percent of the total number of clones obtained for all species combined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Exon stands for exon deletion and Intron denotes an intron retention. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The asterisk on EXON 429–435 stands for unknown, since the PCR product ended at nucleotide position 435. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>AD1-AD5 denote different polyploid species in numerical order: G. hirsutum, G. barbadense, G. tomentosum, G. mustelinum, and G. darwinii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>CenH3 protein secondary structure is aligned to the nucleotide positions of the cDNA below. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>G. hirsutum (AD1) had the highest frequency of spliced transcripts at 44.4% (Additional file 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Each species had a different proportion of each splicing variant; for example, the exon 137–142 deletion was present in 25% of G. hirsutum (AD1) clones, while it was present at 2.9-7.8% of other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>17.6% of G. mustelinum (AD4) clones included the 45 bp intron insertion at position 99, which was only present 5.6-7.8% in the other species (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Despite its crucial role in centromere specification, many aspects of CenH3 evolution are poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Recent years have brought advances in our understanding of centromere epigenetics and evolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>For example, tandem repeats in many species have an evolutionary relationship with the CenH3 protein to reduce nucleosomal bending energy [43], multiple proteins interact with centromeric DNA to induce positive supercoiling of centromeric DNA [44], and CenPA (CenH3 in plants) provides the foundation for binding other kinetochore proteins [45]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>CenH3 sequence evolution in angiosperms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>The present study extends our knowledge of the pace and process of CenH3 evolution by evaluating genomic and expression changes in three diverse angiosperm genera. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Previous research in Brassica and Oryza showed that the CenH3 N terminus and CATD (loop 1 and α2 helix domains) sequences were under diversifying selection in lineage specific manners [30,32]. To assess the generality of these findings in angiosperms, we reanalyzed the Oryza and Brassica sequences at a finer scale to identify specific regions of CenH3 that have actively diversified, and performed the first CenH3 sequence analysis for Gossypium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Across all three genera, diversification generally occurs in the N terminus, a result consistent with previous reports of rapid evolution in this domain, but contrary to reports of diversification in the CenPA Targeting Domain [10,46-50]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Retention and expression of CenH3 alleles in allopolyploids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>In all three genera, both homoeologous copies are retained following genome doubling, demonstrating that restoration to single copy status, as widely observed among modern “diploid” plants, need not occur quickly following WGD events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, expression of homoeologous CenH3 copies in Gossypium exhibited directional bias in all samples, although differences were not always statistically significant (Figure 4); this result contrasts with reports from Brassica and Oryza allopolyploids [30,32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>In Brassica allotetraploids, a variety of CenH3 expression patterns were found for homoeologs, from a 2:1 ratio in an accession of B. juncea to complete B-genome CenH3 suppression in an accession of B. carinata [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In allotetraploid O. minuta and O. alta, CenH3 expression is unbiased [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The variation in expression profiles among allopolyploids in these three genera is notable and without an obvious explanation, although it seems likely that homoeolog expression levels reflect the unique genomic and evolutionary idiosyncrasies that characterize hybridization and genome doubling in each genus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Alternative splicing of CenH3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In addition to non-synonymous evolution, protein diversity may be generated by alternative splicing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Considering the three genera collectively, it appears that alternative splicing frequently modifies the N terminus of CenH3 in Brassica and Gossypium, and this is the only domain modified in Oryza [30,32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the N terminus often cannot be aligned among closely related genera, yet it is necessary for centromeric deposition of CenH3 during meiosis in A. thaliana [51,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The N terminus also interacts with kinetochore proteins in S. cerivisiae [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Perhaps alternative splicing represents another means to generate the diversity of sequences necessary for CenH3 to target centromeres in meiosis, or a rapid defense that introduces new CenH3 proteins in response to increased centromere size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>An alternative is that alternative splicing can also lead to a differing abundance of alternate transcripts between cells and tissues, which has implications in centromeric DNA if CenH3 and centromeric DNA are indeed coevolving. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>By comparing the CenH3 sequences from three disparate angiosperm genera, we have gained insight into the rates and regions of evolution in this important protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>The most commonly mutated domain is the N terminus, which is also subject to alternative splicing, and contributes significantly to diversity in the N terminus of Brassica and Gossypium CenH3s. Alternative splicing is largely absent from the histone fold domain, even though loop 1 and α2 helix domains bind centromeric DNA, which therefore likely are subject to length constraints. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>While CenH3 is considered a rapidly evolving protein, the N terminus is the only domain that is unalignable among closely related genera and is the most diverse domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Roles have been attributed to the N terminus of CenH3, such as ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis [53] and it is indispensable for meiotic localization of CenH3, yet the domain is expendable in mitosis [51,52]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In humans the N terminus is a hotspot for posttranslational modifications that interact with other centromeric proteins [54], and perhaps this is the case in plants as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>At present, the functional explanation for the diversity generated by both conventional protein evolution in the N terminal domain, as well as alternative splicing, remain unexplained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The basis for the interest in CenH3 is its ability to bind to rapidly evolving centromeric repeats and yet still interact with conserved elements in the kinetochore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The dynamics of this relationship at the polyploid scale are increasingly complex due to the duplication of CenH3 and exposure to a new regime centromere repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>The mono and polyphyletic origins of polyploids seem to influence the direction and level of expression bias between CenH3 homoeologs (Figure 4) and is most pronounced after hybridization, as is seen in the F1(A2D5) of Gossypium, but not following polyploidy 2(A2D1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Another compelling issue is obtaining diversity in these transcripts to respond to repeat evolution in the centromere, which is sparse in our tests for selection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Alternative splicing may be an another means to obtain this diversity, although neither selection nor alternative splicing modified the DNA binding domain of CenH3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Since the N terminus is the only domain modified by alternative splicing and subject to diversifying selection, but the DNA binding domains are not, rapidly evolving centromere sequences are unlikely to be the primary driver of CenH3 sequence diversification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Plant materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Leaves (2–4 cm) and leaf buds were collected from eight diploid cottons: G. arboreum cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>101 [A2] (ISC427583), G. anomalum [B1] (ISC447893), G. robinsonii [C2] ISC451818), G. raimondii [D5] (ISC429440), G. stocksii [E1] (ISC447876), G. longicalyx [F1] (ISC418550), G. bickii [G1] (ISC414834), G. exiguum [K] (ISC416400), and from five allopolyploid cottons (G. hirsutum cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>TM1 [AD1] (ISC451819), G. barbadense cv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Pima S6 [AD2] (ISC451820), G. tomentosum 95 [AD3] (ISC451821), G. mustelinum local lab accession [AD4] (ISC429442), and G. darwinii PW45 [AD5] (ISC429431). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>For purposes of phylogenetic reconstruction, we included the outgroup species Gossypioides kirkii (ISC 418555) [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>All lines were grown in the Pohl Conservatory at Iowa State University and were used for both DNA and RNA extractions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>DNA was extracted using the Qiagen DNeasy Plant Kit following the manufacturers recommended protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>RNA was extracted using the Sigma Spectrum RNA Extraction Kit following the manufacturers recommended protocol with the following modifications: protocol A was followed at step 4, one wash each was performed for wash solutions I and II, and on-column DNA digestion was performed with the Sigma On-Column DNase I Digest Set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>CenH3 sequencing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>CenH3 gene sequence data for G. raimondii was obtained from Phytozome [56,57], from which primers were designed (Additional file 6) for PCR amplification and sequencing from other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>PCR amplifications were performed using the manufacturers recommended reaction mixtures/cycling conditions and a melting temperature of 57°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>PCR amplicons from all diploid accessions (except G. exiguum) were cleaned via the Qiaquick PCR column cleanup (Qiagen) and sequenced with the amplification primers and a set of internal sequencing primers (Additional file 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>PCR products from G. exiguum and all polyploid species were visualized on an Invitrogen E-gel to isolate bands, and cloned with the P-GEM-T Easy Vector ligation kit (Promega) and Top10 Competent Cells (Invitrogen) according to the recommended protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Clones were sequenced at the Iowa State DNA Sequencing Facility using both M13 primers and internal primers (Additional file 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>CenH3 cDNA sequences for Oryza and Brassica were downloaded from GenBank [58] and Phytozome [57] (Additional file 7). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Jukes Cantor corrected estimates of Ka/Ks were measured using DNAsp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The MEME software package [39] accessed via the (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.datamonkey.org">http://www.datamonkey.org</ext-link>) server [59], was used to test for selection at the codon level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The automatic selection tool was used to determine the correct substitution models for Brassica (F81), Gossypium (F81), and Oryza (HKY85). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The significance level cutoff was set at P = &lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We used Arabidopsis thaliana (24 million years divergence (MYD); Lysak et al. [60]), Gossypioides kirki (13.6 MYD; Cronn et al. [61]), and Brachypodium distachyon (46 MYD; Sanderson [62]) as the outgroups for Brassica (7.9 MYD; Jacquemin et al. [63]), Gossypium (5–10 MYD; Senchina et al. [64]), and Oryza (15 MYD; Sanderson [62]), respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>We used the SynMap tool of CoGe (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genomeevolution.org/CoGe">http://genomeevolution.org/CoGe</ext-link>) [65,66] to identify blocks of syntenic orthologs to evaluate whole genome Ka/Ks for a representative species from each genus (Brassica rapa, Oryza sativa, Gossypium raimondi). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The following parameters were used: BlastN, relative gene order, −D 50, −A 10, quota align merge –Dm 80, quota align with a ratio of coverage depth at 3:1 for (B. rapa: A. thaliana), 1:1 for (O. sativa: B. distachyon), and 6:1 for (G. raimondii: Theobroma cacao), overlap distance 40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Each species was compared to their previously described outgroups, except T. cacao (60 MYD) [67] was the outgroup for G. raimondii, since Gossypioides kirki lacks a sequenced genome. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNA sequences were aligned using CLUSTALW [68] in BioEdit [69] and converted to NEXUS format using readal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://trimal.cgenomics.org">http://trimal.cgenomics.org</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The best fitting model of DNA sequence evolution was determined using the AIC and BIC, as calculated by jModelTest [70,71]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Since both the GTR + Γ model and the HKY + Γ model were favored by AIC and BIC respectively, MEGA6 was used to build bootstrapped maximum likelihood trees with 100 replicates under both models [72,73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The log likelihood of the GTR + Γ tree was slightly higher and is reported here; however, both trees exhibited a similar topology. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Protein structure prediction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Secondary and tertiary protein structures were modeled using RaptorX [74-77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>This software compares alignments of the sample protein to other proteins with known structural information to determine a probable structure using statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>A representative CenH3 sequence from each genus was modeled (G.raimondii (D5), Oryza australiensis (EE), and Brassica napus (AC8)) (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>cDNA generation and sequencing of CenH3 transcripts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Reverse transcription was performed using the Invitrogen SuperScript III First-Strand Synthesis System Kit using oligo dT primers, and CenH3 was amplified from the cDNA pool using primers that were designed from the 5’ and 3’ outermost exons (Additional file 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>PCR products were processed using the Qiaquick PCR Cleanup columns and sequenced with the amplification primers (Additional file 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Chromatogram-based expression estimates were calculated as described previously [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>At least three replicates were used for each tissue to permit standard error calculations and paired, two-tailed T tests were used to test for significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Expression levels for the polyploid accessions were secondarily estimated with RNA-seq data and by cloning cDNA amplicons (as described above). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The clones were randomly selected from each sample, sequenced, and then grouped by their subgenomic origin “AT” and “DT”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Since the samples should follow a binomial distribution, the null hypothesis for the rate of cloning each homeologous copy of CenH3 should be 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>To control for the FWER (Family-wise Error Rate) at α = 0.05, the Bonferroni correction was determine the significance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Expression estimation via RNA-seq </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>To assess CenH3 gene expression, we analyzed previously generated leaf transcriptome data (SRA BioProject PRJNA171342) [79] for both model diploid parents, an F1 hybrid of G. arboreum (A2 genome) and G. raimondii (D5 genome), a colchicine doubled F1 hybrid of G. arboreum and G. thurberi (D1 genome), and two accessions of the allopolyploid (AD genome) G. hirsutum (G. hirsutum var yucatanense, a wild accession; G. hirsutum cv Maxxa, a domesticated accession). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Raw reads were trimmed with sickle (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/najoshi/sickle">https://github.com/najoshi/sickle</ext-link>), and mapped to the generated CenH3 sequences using GSNAP (batch 4, novel splicing on) [80] in conjunction with a CenH3-specific SNP index to efficiently map sequences from different species and subgenomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The SNP indices were manually curated from Sanger sequencing of the cDNA’s and gene sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>For sequences from the hybrid and polyploid, PolyCat [81] was used to partition A- and D-genome derived reads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>The significance for homeolog bias was calculated using a paired, Student’s T-test with log2 transformation to ensure the normality in expression values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Availability of supporting data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>CenH3 gene sequence data have been submitted to GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers can be found in Additional file 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec20"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM1_ESM.docx" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Genomic sequence lengths of CenH3 in Gossypium and Gossypioides. Gossypium CenH3 accession numbers and gene lengths. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM2_ESM.docx" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetically informative alternative splicing variants in Gossypium allopolyploids. Splicing variants of Gossypium grouped informatively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM3_ESM.tiff" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Gossypium CenH3 Phylogeny. A CenH3 phylogeny of Gossypium diploids and polyploids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Phylogeny of Gossypium using genomic CenH3 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>The Gossypium phylogeny is in agreement with previously published phylogenies [19], excluding the polytomy seen in the AT sub-tree, which was the result of too few informative SNPs in the CenH3 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>A is G. arboreum, B is G. anomalum, C is G. robinsonii, D is G. raimondii, E is G. stocksii, F is G. longicalyx, G is G. bickii, K is G. exiguum [K], AD1 is G. hirsutum, AD2 is G. barbadense, AD3 is G. tomentosum, AD4 is G. mustelinum, AD5 is G. darwinii, Gk is Gossypioides kirkii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>A scale bar is provided at the bottom; numbers at each node are bootstrap support values. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM4_ESM.docx" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>The number of clones for each sub-genome in allopolyploid Gossypium . Counts of CenH3 clones allocated to each subgenome in Gossypium allopolyploids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM5_ESM.jpeg" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Percentage of clones with splicing variations in each polyploid genome. The percentage of the total number of clones that contained splicing variants in each polyploid genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Percent of splicing variants found in clones from each species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Total number of clones from each species was the sum total of the clones from bud and leaf tissue, if both were available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>AD1-AD5 denote G. hirsutum, G. barbadense, G. tomentosum, G. mustelinum, and G. darwinii, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM6_ESM.docx" id="MOESM6"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences for genomic and cDNA amplification. Primer sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="12870_2014_383_MOESM7_ESM.docx" id="MOESM7"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Accessions downloaded from GenBank and Phytozome. Species names and accession numbers of Brassica and Oryza CenH3 sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>RM was involved in experimental design, the gene sequencing, cloning, and expression analyses, and drafted the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>JG was involved in the conception of the evolutionary analysis and statistics, performed the phylogenetic analysis, and participated in drafting the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>JJ cloned and sequenced many of the CenH3 genes and participated in drafting the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>SRB was involved in experimental design and supervision for the CoGE and meme analysis, as well as being involved in drafting the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>CG participated in the experimental design and helped draft the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>LG participated in parts of the cloning, performed all of the statistical analyses, and wrote the methods for these analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>JW participated in the experimental design, evolutionary analyses, and helped draft the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>The authors thank Patrick Edger for comments and suggestions with Brassica, Guanjing Hu for help with the Gossypium experimental work, and Matt Hufford for assistance with the evolutionary analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Research was supported by the NSF Plant Genome Program and by Cotton Incorporated. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>1.HirschCDJiangJWendelJFGreilhuberJDolezelJLeitchIJCentromeres: sequences, structure, and biology plant genome diversityPlant Genome Diversity2012ViennaSpringer5970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>2.HenikoffSAhmadKMalikHSThe centromere paradox: stable inheritance with rapidly evolving DNAScience200129355321098110210.1126/science.1062939<?supplied-pmid 11498581?>11498581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>3.WillardHFWayeJSChromosome-specific subsets of human alpha satellite DNA: Analysis of sequence divergence within and between chromosomal subsets and evidence for an ancestral pentameric repeatJ Mol Evol198725320721410.1007/BF02100014<?supplied-pmid 2822935?>2822935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>4.JiangJBirchlerJAParrottWAKelly DaweRA molecular view of plant centromeresTrends Plant Sci200381257057510.1016/j.tplants.2003.10.011<?supplied-pmid 14659705?>14659705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>5.MeltersDPBradnamKRYoungHATelisNMayMRRubyJGSebraRPelusoPEidJRankDComparative analysis of tandem repeats from hundreds of species reveals unique insights into centromere evolutionGenome Biol2013141R1010.1186/gb-2013-14-1-r10<?supplied-pmid 23363705?>23363705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>6.MeraldiPMcAinshADRheinbayESorgerPKPhylogenetic and structural analysis of centromeric DNA and kinetochore proteinsGenome Biol200673R2310.1186/gb-2006-7-3-r23<?supplied-pmid 16563186?>16563186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>7.ClevelandDWMaoYSullivanKFCentromeres and kinetochores: from epigenetics to mitotic checkpoint signalingCell2003112440742110.1016/S0092-8674(03)00115-6<?supplied-pmid 12600307?>12600307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>8.MalikHSVermaakDHenikoffSRecurrent evolution of DNA-binding motifs in the Drosophila centromeric histoneProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20029931449145410.1073/pnas.032664299<?supplied-pmid 11805302?>11805302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>9.TalbertPBMasuelliRTyagiAPComaiLHenikoffSCentromeric localization and adaptive evolution of an Arabidopsis histone H3 variantPlant Cell20021451053106610.1105/tpc.010425<?supplied-pmid 12034896?>12034896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>10.MalikHSHenikoffSAdaptive evolution of CID, a centromere-specific histone in DrosophilaGenetics2001157312931298<?supplied-pmid 11238413?>11238413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>11.AllshireRCKarpenGHEpigenetic regulation of centromeric chromatin: old dogs, new tricks?Nat Rev Genet200891292393710.1038/nrg2466<?supplied-pmid 19002142?>19002142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>12.SongCLiuSXiaoJHeWZhouYQinQZhangCLiuYPolyploid organismsSci China Life Sci201255430131110.1007/s11427-012-4310-2<?supplied-pmid 22566086?>22566086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>13.Heslop-HarrisonJSGenome evolution: extinction, continuation or explosion?Curr Opin Plant Biol201215211512110.1016/j.pbi.2012.03.006<?supplied-pmid 22465161?>22465161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>14.Van de PeerYMaereSMeyerAThe evolutionary significance of ancient genome duplicationsNat Rev Genet2009101072573210.1038/nrg2600<?supplied-pmid 19652647?>19652647 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>15.WendelJFGenome evolution in polyploidsPlant Mol Biol200042122524910.1023/A:1006392424384<?supplied-pmid 10688139?>10688139 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>16.SoltisDEAlbertVALeebens-MackJBellCDPatersonAHZhengCSankoffDde PamphilisCWWallPKSoltisPSPolyploidy and angiosperm diversificationAm J Bot200996133634810.3732/ajb.0800079<?supplied-pmid 21628192?>21628192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>17.AdamsKLWendelJFPolyploidy and genome evolution in plantsCurr Opin Plant Biol20058213514110.1016/j.pbi.2005.01.001<?supplied-pmid 15752992?>15752992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>18.AdamsKLCronnRPercifieldRWendelJFGenes duplicated by polyploidy show unequal contributions to the transcriptome and organ-specific reciprocal silencingProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200310084649465410.1073/pnas.0630618100<?supplied-pmid 12665616?>12665616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>19.WendelJFFlagelLEAdamsKLSoltisPSSoltisDEJeans, genes, and genomes: cotton as a model for studying polyploidyPolyploidy and Genome Evolution2012New YorkSpringer181207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>20.WendelJFDoyleJJPolyploidy and evolution in plantsCurr Opin Plant Biol2005813514110.1016/j.pbi.2005.01.001<?supplied-pmid 15752992?>15752992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>21.SoltisDESoltisPSPolyploidy: recurrent formation and genome evolutionTrends Eco Evol199914934835210.1016/S0169-5347(99)01638-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>22.ChenZJNiZMechanisms of genomic rearrangements and gene expression changes in plant polyploidsBioessays200628324025210.1002/bies.20374<?supplied-pmid 16479580?>16479580 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>23.ChenZJGenetic and epigenetic mechanisms for gene expression and phenotypic variation in plant polyploidsAnnu Rev Plant Biol20075837740610.1146/annurev.arplant.58.032806.103835<?supplied-pmid 17280525?>17280525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>24.AdamsKLWendelJFNovel patterns of gene expression in polyploid plantsTrends Genet2005211053954310.1016/j.tig.2005.07.009<?supplied-pmid 16098633?>16098633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>25.ScannellDRByrneKPGordonJLWongSWolfeKHMultiple rounds of speciation associated with reciprocal gene loss in polyploid yeastsNature2006440708234134510.1038/nature04562<?supplied-pmid 16541074?>16541074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>26.TownCDCheungFMaitiRCrabtreeJHaasBJWortmanJRHineEEAlthoffRArbogastTSTallonLJComparative genomics of Brassica oleracea and Arabidopsis thaliana reveal gene loss, fragmentation, and dispersal after polyploidyPlant Cell Online20061861348135910.1105/tpc.106.041665 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>27.KuH-MVisionTLiuJTanksleySDComparing sequenced segments of the tomato and Arabidopsis genomes: large-scale duplication followed by selective gene loss creates a network of syntenyProc Natl Acad Sci U S A200097169121912610.1073/pnas.160271297<?supplied-pmid 10908680?>10908680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>28.DoyleJJFlagelLEPatersonAHRappRASoltisDESoltisPSWendelJFEvolutionary genetics of genome merger and doubling in plantsAnn Rev Genet200842144346110.1146/annurev.genet.42.110807.091524<?supplied-pmid 18983261?>18983261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>29.BarkerMSKaneNCMatvienkoMKozikAMichelmoreRWKnappSJRiesebergLHMultiple paleopolyploidizations during the evolution of the Compositae reveal parallel patterns of duplicate gene retention after millions of yearsMol Biol Evol200825112445245510.1093/molbev/msn187<?supplied-pmid 18728074?>18728074 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>30.HirschCDWuYYanHJiangJLineage-specific adaptive evolution of the centromeric protein CenH3 in diploid and allotetraploid Oryza speciesMol Biol Evol200926122877288510.1093/molbev/msp208<?supplied-pmid 19741004?>19741004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>31.Lermontova I, Schubert I: CenH3 for establishing and maintaining centromeres. In: Plant Centromere Biology. Oxford, UK: Wiley-Blackwell; 2013: 67–82. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>32.WangGHeQLiuFChengZTalbertPJinWCharacterization of CenH3 proteins and centromere-associated DNA sequences in diploid and allotetraploid Brassica speciesChromosoma2011120435336510.1007/s00412-011-0315-z<?supplied-pmid 21394438?>21394438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>33.U. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>NGenome analysis in Brassica with special reference to the experimental formation of B. napus and peculiar mode of fertilizationJapan J Bot19357389452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>34.GeSSangTLuB-RHongD-YPhylogeny of rice genomes with emphasis on origins of allotetraploid speciesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A19999625144001440510.1073/pnas.96.25.14400<?supplied-pmid 10588717?>10588717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>35.GroverCGruppKWanzekRWendelJAssessing the monophyly of polyploid Gossypium speciesPlant Syst Evol201229861177118310.1007/s00606-012-0615-7 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>36.LuoSMachJAbramsonBRamirezRSchurrRBaronePCopenhaverGFolkertsOThe cotton centromere contains a Ty3-gypsy-like LTR retroelementPLoS One201274e3526110.1371/journal.pone.0035261<?supplied-pmid 22536361?>22536361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>37.SmithSADonoghueMJRates of molecular evolution are linked to life history in flowering plantsScience20083225898868910.1126/science.1163197<?supplied-pmid 18832643?>18832643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>38.LibradoPRozasJDnaSP v5: a software for comprehensive analysis of DNA polymorphism dataBioinformatics200925111451145210.1093/bioinformatics/btp187<?supplied-pmid 19346325?>19346325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>39.MurrellBWertheimJOMoolaSWeighillTSchefflerKPondSLKDetecting individual sites subject to episodic diversifying selectionPLoS Genet201287e100276410.1371/journal.pgen.1002764<?supplied-pmid 22807683?>22807683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>40.HuiLLuLHengYQinRXingYJinWExpression of CENH3 alleles in synthesized allopolyploid Oryza speciesJ Genet Genomics2010371070371110.1016/S1673-8527(09)60088-621035096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>41.SalmonAFlagelLYingBUdallJAWendelJFHomoeologous nonreciprocal recombination in polyploid cottonNew Phytol2010186112313410.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.03093.x<?supplied-pmid 19925554?>19925554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>42.FlagelLWendelJUdallJDuplicate gene evolution, homoeologous recombination, and transcriptome characterization in allopolyploid cottonBMC Genomics201213130210.1186/1471-2164-13-302<?supplied-pmid 22768919?>22768919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>43.ZhangTTalbertPBZhangWWuYYangZHenikoffJGHenikoffSJiangJThe CentO satellite confers translational and rotational phasing on CenH3 nucleosomes in rice centromeresProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201311050E4875E488310.1073/pnas.1319548110<?supplied-pmid 24191062?>24191062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>44.TakeuchiKNishinoTMayanagiKHorikoshiNOsakabeATachiwanaHHoriTKurumizakaHFukagawaTThe centromeric nucleosome-like CENP–T–W–S–X complex induces positive supercoils into DNANucleic Acids Res20144231644165510.1093/nar/gkt1124<?supplied-pmid 24234442?>24234442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>45.CarrollCWMilksKJStraightAFDual recognition of CENP-A nucleosomes is required for centromere assemblyJ Cell Biol201018971143115510.1083/jcb.201001013<?supplied-pmid 20566683?>20566683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>46.VermaakDHaydenHSHenikoffSCentromere targeting element within the histone fold domain of CidMol Cell Biol200222217553756110.1128/MCB.22.21.7553-7561.2002<?supplied-pmid 12370302?>12370302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>47.CooperJLHenikoffSAdaptive evolution of the histone fold domain in centromeric histonesMol Biol Evol20042191712171810.1093/molbev/msh179<?supplied-pmid 15175412?>15175412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>48.ShelbyRDVafaOSullivanKFAssembly of CENP-A into centromeric chromatin requires a cooperative array of nucleosomal DNA contact sitesJ Cell Biol1997136350151310.1083/jcb.136.3.501<?supplied-pmid 9024683?>9024683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>49.LermontovaISchubertVFuchsJKlatteSMacasJSchubertILoading of Arabidopsis centromeric histone CENH3 occurs mainly during G2 and requires the presence of the histone fold domainPlant Cell200618102443245110.1105/tpc.106.043174<?supplied-pmid 17028205?>17028205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>50.BlackBEFoltzDRChakravarthySLugerKWoodsVLClevelandDWStructural determinants for generating centromeric chromatinNature2004430699957858210.1038/nature02766<?supplied-pmid 15282608?>15282608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>51.LermontovaIKorolevaORuttenTFuchsJSchubertVMoraesIKoszegiDSchubertIKnockdown of CenH3 in Arabidopsis reduces mitotic divisions and causes sterility by disturbed meiotic chromosome segregationPlant J2011681405010.1111/j.1365-313X.2011.04664.x<?supplied-pmid 21635586?>21635586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>52.RaviMShibataFRamahiJSNagakiKChenCMurataMChanSWMeiosis-specific loading of the centromere-specific histone CENH3 in Arabidopsis thalianaPLoS Genet201176e100212110.1371/journal.pgen.1002121<?supplied-pmid 21695238?>21695238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>53.ChenYBakerREKeithKCHarrisKStolerSFitzgerald-HayesMThe N terminus of the centromere H3-like protein Cse4p performs an essential function distinct from that of the histone fold domainMol Cell Biol200020187037704810.1128/MCB.20.18.7037-7048.2000<?supplied-pmid 10958698?>10958698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>54.Bailey AO, Panchenko T, Sathyan KM, Petkowski JJ, Pai P-J, Bai DL, Russell DH, Macara IG, Shabanowitz J, Hunt DF, Black BE, Foltz DR: Posttranslational modification of CENP-A influences the conformation of centromeric chromatin.Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2013, 110(29):11827–11832. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>55.SeelananTSchnabelAWendelJFCongruence and consensus in the cotton tribeSys Bot19972225929010.2307/2419457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>56.WangKWangZLiFYeWWangJSongGYueZCongLShangHZhuSThe draft genome of a diploid cotton Gossypium raimondiiNat Genet201244101098110310.1038/ng.2371<?supplied-pmid 22922876?>22922876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>57.GoodsteinDMShuSHowsonRNeupaneRHayesRDFazoJMitrosTDirksWHellstenUPutnamNPhytozome: a comparative platform for green plant genomicsNucleic Acids Res201240D1D1178D118610.1093/nar/gkr944<?supplied-pmid 22110026?>22110026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>58.BensonDAKarsch-MizrachiILipmanDJOstellJWheelerDLGenBankNucleic Acids Res200836suppl 1D25D30<?supplied-pmid 18073190?>18073190 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>59.DelportWPoonAFFrostSDPondSLKDatamonkey 2010: a suite of phylogenetic analysis tools for evolutionary biologyBioinformatics201026192455245710.1093/bioinformatics/btq429<?supplied-pmid 20671151?>20671151 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>60.LysakMAKochMAPecinkaASchubertIChromosome triplication found across the tribe BrassiceaeGenome Res200515451652510.1101/gr.3531105<?supplied-pmid 15781573?>15781573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>61.CronnRCSmallRLHaselkornTWendelJFRapid diversification of the cotton genus (Gossypium: Malvaceae) revealed by analysis of sixteen nuclear and chloroplast genesAm J Botany200289470772510.3732/ajb.89.4.70721665671 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>62.SandersonMA nonparametric approach to estimating divergence times in the absence of rate constancyMol Biol Evol19971412121810.1093/oxfordjournals.molbev.a025731 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>63.Jacquemin J, Ammiraju JSS, Haberer G, Billheimer DD, Yu Y, Liu LC, Rivera LF, Mayer K, Chen M, Wing RA: Fifteen million years of evolution in theOryzagenus shows extensive gene family expansion.Mol Plant 2013, 7(4):642–656. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>64.SenchinaDSAlvarezICronnRCLiuBRongJNoyesRDPatersonAHWingRAWilkinsTAWendelJFRate variation among nuclear genes and the age of polyploidy in GossypiumMol Biol Evol200320463364310.1093/molbev/msg065<?supplied-pmid 12679546?>12679546 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>65.LyonsEFreelingMHow to usefully compare homologous plant genes and chromosomes as DNA sequencesPlant J200853466167310.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03326.x<?supplied-pmid 18269575?>18269575 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>66.LyonsEPedersenBKaneJAlamMMingRTangHWangXBowersJPatersonALischDFinding and comparing syntenic regions among Arabidopsis and the outgroups papaya, poplar, and grape: CoGe with rosidsPlant Physiol200814841772178110.1104/pp.108.124867<?supplied-pmid 18952863?>18952863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>67.CarvalhoMRHerreraFAJaramilloCAWingSLCallejasRPaleocene Malvaceae from northern South America and their biogeographical implicationsAm J Bot20119881337135510.3732/ajb.1000539<?supplied-pmid 21821594?>21821594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>68.ThompsonJDHigginsDGGibsonTJCLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choiceNucleic Acids Res199422224673468010.1093/nar/22.22.4673<?supplied-pmid 7984417?>7984417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>69.HallTABioEdit: a user-friendly biological sequence alignment editor and analysis program for Windows 95/98/NTNucleic Acids Symposium Series19999598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>70.DarribaDTaboadaGLDoalloRPosadaDjModelTest 2: more models, new heuristics and parallel computingNat Methods20129877210.1038/nmeth.2109<?supplied-pmid 22847109?>22847109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>71.GuindonSGascuelOA simple, fast, and accurate algorithm to estimate large phylogenies by maximum likelihoodSyst Biol200352569670410.1080/10635150390235520<?supplied-pmid 14530136?>14530136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>72.KumarSNeiMDudleyJTamuraKMEGA: a biologist-centric software for evolutionary analysis of DNA and protein sequencesBrief Bioinform20089429930610.1093/bib/bbn017<?supplied-pmid 18417537?>18417537 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>73.TamuraKStecherGPetersonDFilipskiAKumarSMEGA6: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0Mol Biol Evol201330122725272910.1093/molbev/mst197<?supplied-pmid 24132122?>24132122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>74.MaJWingRABennetzenJLJacksonSAPlant centromere organization: a dynamic structure with conserved functionsTrends Genet200723313413910.1016/j.tig.2007.01.004<?supplied-pmid 17275131?>17275131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>75.KällbergMWangHWangSPengJWangZLuHXuJTemplate-based protein structure modeling using the RaptorX web serverNat Protocols2012781511152210.1038/nprot.2012.085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>76.PengJXuJA multiple-template approach to protein threadingProteins20117961930193910.1002/prot.23016<?supplied-pmid 21465564?>21465564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>77.PengJXuJRaptorx: exploiting structure information for protein alignment by statistical inferenceProteins201179S1016117110.1002/prot.23175<?supplied-pmid 21987485?>21987485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>78.AdamsKLPercifieldRWendelJFOrgan-specific silencing of duplicated genes in a newly synthesized cotton allotetraploiddGenetics200416842217222610.1534/genetics.104.033522<?supplied-pmid 15371349?>15371349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>79.YooMJSzadkowskiEWendelJFHomoeolog expression bias and expression level dominance in allopolyploid cottonHeredity2013110217118010.1038/hdy.2012.94<?supplied-pmid 23169565?>23169565 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>80.WuTDNacuSFast and SNP-tolerant detection of complex variants and splicing in short readsBioinformatics201026787388110.1093/bioinformatics/btq057<?supplied-pmid 20147302?>20147302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>81.PageJTGingleARUdallJAPolyCat: a resource for genome categorization of sequencing reads from allopolyploid organismsG320133351752510.1534/g3.112.005298<?supplied-pmid 23450226?>23450226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
