
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Hum Mutat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Hum. Mutat</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">humu</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Human Mutation</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1059-7794</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-1004</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BlackWell Publishing Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Oxford, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4285182</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.22589</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Structural Genomic Variation as Risk Factor for Idiopathic Recurrent Miscarriage </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nagirnaja</surname><given-names>Liina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palta</surname><given-names>Priit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kasak</surname><given-names>Laura</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rull</surname><given-names>Kristiina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>Ole B</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>Henriette S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steffensen</surname><given-names>Rudi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Esko</surname><given-names>Tõnu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au9">9</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au10">10</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au11">11</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Remm</surname><given-names>Maido</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au12">12</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Laan</surname><given-names>Maris</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Human Molecular Genetics Research Group, Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of Tartu</institution><addr-line>Tartu, Estonia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Bioinformatics, Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of Tartu</institution><addr-line>Tartu, Estonia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Institute for Molecular Medicine Finland (FIMM), University of Helsinki</institution><addr-line>Helsinki, Finland</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Wellcome Trust Genome Campus</institution><addr-line>Cambridge, United Kingdom</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><label>5</label><institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, University of Tartu</institution><addr-line>Tartu, Estonia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><label>6</label><institution>The Fertility Clinics, Rigshospitalet, Copenhagen University Hospital</institution><addr-line>Copenhagen, Denmark</addr-line></aff><aff id="au7"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Obstetrics and Gynaecology, Aalborg University Hospital</institution><addr-line>Aalborg, Denmark</addr-line></aff><aff id="au8"><label>8</label><institution>Department of Clinical Immunology, Aalborg University Hospital</institution><addr-line>Aalborg, Denmark</addr-line></aff><aff id="au9"><label>9</label><institution>Estonian Genome Center, University of Tartu</institution><addr-line>Tartu, Estonia</addr-line></aff><aff id="au10"><label>10</label><institution>Children's Hospital Boston</institution><addr-line>Boston, Massachusetts</addr-line></aff><aff id="au11"><label>11</label><institution>Medical and Population Genetics, Broad Institute</institution><addr-line>Cambridge, Massachusetts</addr-line></aff><aff id="au12"><label>12</label><institution>Estonian Biocentre</institution><addr-line>Tartu, Estonia</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* Correspondence to: Maris Laan, Human Molecular Genetics Research Group, Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of Tartu, Riia 23, 51010 Tartu, Estonia. E-mail: <email>maris.laan@ut.ee</email></corresp><fn><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Contract grant sponsors: Wellcome Trust International Senior Research Fellowship (070191/Z/03/A) in Biomedical Science in Central Europe; Estonian Ministry of Education and Research Core Grants (SF0180022s12, SF0180026s09, SF0180142s08); European Union through the European Regional Development Fund (project HAPPY PREGNANCY, 3.2.0701.12-0047); Estonian Science Foundation Grant (ETF9030); EU ERDF through the Estonian Centre of Excellence in Genomics; European Commission FP7 project (gEUVADIS, 261123). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>35</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>972</fpage><lpage>982</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>4</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 The Authors. *<italic>Human Mutation</italic> published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Recurrent miscarriage (RM) is a multifactorial disorder with acknowledged genetic heritability that affects ∼3% of couples aiming at childbirth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>As copy number variants (CNVs) have been shown to contribute to reproductive disease susceptibility, we aimed to describe genome-wide profile of CNVs and identify common rearrangements modulating risk to RM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide screening of Estonian RM patients and fertile controls identified excessive cumulative burden of CNVs (5.4 and 6.1 Mb per genome) in two RM cases possibly increasing their individual disease risk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Functional profiling of all rearranged genes within RM study group revealed significant enrichment of loci related to innate immunity and immunoregulatory pathways essential for immune tolerance at fetomaternal interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>As a major finding, we report a multicopy duplication (61.6 kb) at 5p13.3 conferring increased maternal risk to RM in Estonia and Denmark (meta-analysis, n = 309/205, odds ratio = 4.82, P = 0.012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Comparison to Estonian population-based cohort (total, n = 1000) confirmed the risk for Estonian female cases (P = 7.9 × 10−4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Datasets of four cohorts from the Database of Genomic Variants (total, n = 5,846 subjects) exhibited similar low duplication prevalence worldwide (0.7%–1.2%) compared to RM cases of this study (6.6%–7.5%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The CNV disrupts PDZD2 and GOLPH3 genes predominantly expressed in placenta and it may represent a novel risk factor for pregnancy complications. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>recurrent miscarriage</kwd><kwd>fetomaternal interface</kwd><kwd>immune dysfunction</kwd><kwd>placenta</kwd><kwd><italic>GOLPH3</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>PDZD2</italic></kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Miscarriage is the most common pregnancy complication affecting up to 15% of all clinically recognized pregnancies [Stirrat, 1990]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The risk of miscarriage increases with age and is enhanced by a trend in developed countries to postpone childbearing to late 30s and early 40s with declined fertility rates [Nybo Andersen et al., 2000; Group TECW, 2010]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Recurrent miscarriage (RM), defined as ≥3 consecutive pregnancy losses before 22nd gestational week, is a heterogeneous disorder affecting up to 3% of couples aiming at childbirth [Christiansen et al., 2008]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>It is a distressing condition for affected couples as each subsequent miscarriage leads to elevated risk of experiencing further pregnancy loss [Ogasawara et al., 2000] and increased probability of other pregnancy complications such as preterm delivery or small for gestational age newborns [Jivraj et al., 2001; van Oppenraaij et al., 2009]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Although a spectrum of factors is known to increase the risk to RM, including immune system dysfunction and thrombophilic disorders, the underlying etiology remains undetermined in about half of the cases [Rai and Regan, 2006; Allison and Schust, 2009]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>A familial segregation of RM has been observed highlighting the contribution of the genetic predisposition to the disease [Christiansen et al., 1990; Kolte et al., 2011]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>So far, majority of the studies focusing on the genetic susceptibility to RM have addressed single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) in more than 100 RM candidate genes, often providing conflicting results and no identified risk variants with confirmed strong effect [Nagirnaja et al., 2012; Rull et al., 2012, 2013]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>More recently, paternal DNA fragmentation, epigenetic disturbances, and DNA copy number variants (CNVs) have been suggested to modify predisposition to RM [Rajcan-Separovic et al., 2010; Uuskula et al., 2010; Robinson et al., 2012]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>CNVs represent deletions or duplications of &gt;50 bp DNA sequence that disrupt around 13% of RefSeq genes [McCarroll et al., 2008; Zhang et al., 2009; Conrad et al., 2010]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It has been estimated that 17.7% of variability in gene expression may be attributed to these DNA variants and, subsequently, a growing number of genic CNVs and increased global burden of CNVs have been linked to several complex disorders [Stranger et al., 2007; Zhang et al., 2009; Girirajan et al., 2011]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Studies focusing on structural variation predisposing to pregnancy complications have been scarce and represent single reports addressing disease-associated CNVs in unexplained stillbirths and preeclampsia [Harris et al., 2011; Zhao et al., 2012, 2013]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>A single study has addressed the contribution of CNVs in RM using array comparative genomic hybridization to screen 26 placentas from RM pregnancies for rare CNVs to identify candidate genes, which could be causative for the specific miscarriage [Rajcan-Separovic et al., 2010]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In the current genome-wide study, we set forward to address the role of CNVs in predisposing to RM among the couples of unexplained RM from Estonia and Denmark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>The collaborative effort involved 558 RM cases with ≥3 consecutive miscarriages (in total, 309 RM female and 249 male partners), fertile multiparous control women (n = 205), and population-based samples from Estonian Biobank, Estonian Genome Center, University of Tartu (EGCUT; n = 1,000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We aimed to (A) assess the contribution of genome-wide burden of CNVs and (B) identify and characterize novel common CNVs in modulating the risk of RM (Fig.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>We determined excessive cumulative burden of all CNVs (5.4 and 6.1 Mb per genome) in two RM cases possibly increasing their individual risk of the disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The genomic CNV profile within the RM study group was significantly enriched for CNVs predominantly affecting genes related to innate immunity signaling and immunoregulatory interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>As a major finding, we identified a multicopy duplication CNV (61.6 kb) at 5p13.3 conferring high, almost fivefold increased maternal risk of RM and disrupting two novel RM candidate genes, PDZD2 and GOLPH3, associated with pregnancy maintenance for the first time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Study design and procedures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Following initial CNV discovery phase in a subsample of Estonian subjects, whole-genome profiling of all identified CNVs and association study of discrete CNV regions were performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Three CNVRs were taken forward to be analyzed in the full Estonian sample set to identify potential risk-conferring rearrangements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>For the duplication at 5p13.3, genetic Association testing 1 in the full Estonian sample and Association testing 2 using Estonian cohort (EGCUT) control samples were then undertaken, followed by Replication study in the Danish sample set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Comparative prevalence data from the Database of Genomic Variants (DGV) were collected followed by detailed duplication breakpoint characterization and confirmation of duplication carriership of all RM cases and fertile controls of the study using duplication-specific junction-spanning PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Expression profiling in human tissues was performed for the genes PDZD2 and GOLPH3 disrupted by the 5p13.3 rearrangement. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="humu0035-0972-f1"/></fig></SecTag></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Study Subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>RM cases and fertile control samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>RM cases and fertile controls have been recruited in two North European countries Estonia and Denmark, and the applied sample sets have been well characterized and previously exploited in RM research [Kruse et al., 2004; Rull et al., 2008, 2013; Kolte et al., 2011]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the Ethics Review Committee on Human Research of the University of Tartu, Estonia, and the Danish Central National Committee on Biomedical Research Ethics. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>As both maternal and paternal genetic information determine the development of the fetus and the placenta, as well as the outcome of a pregnancy, the patient group consisted of female patients and their male partners experiencing idiopathic RM (≥3 consecutive miscarriages before week 22 of gestation without any identified cause). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>In total, the current study included 558 RM patients from Estonia (80 female and 39 male partners) and Denmark (229 female and 210 male cases) (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>For all recruited cases, known clinical risk factors of RM have been excluded (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The female patients were further subphenotyped as either primary (Estonia, n = 46; Denmark, n = 113) or secondary RM (Estonia, n = 34; Denmark, n = 116) based on the occurrence of consecutive miscarriages either before (if any) live births or following one or more live births, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>The control group consisted of 205 fertile females from Estonia (n = 90) and Denmark (n = 115) with no history of miscarriages and at least two (Denmark) or three (Estonia) successful pregnancies ending with live birth (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Male partners of fertile female controls were not included into the study due to limited information on their previous reproductive history. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Population-based cohort samples from Estonian Biobank (EGCUT) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The carrier status of the identified RM-associated risk CNV at 5p13.3 was additionally determined for population-based cohort samples (n = 1,000; 504 men, 496 women) drawn from the Estonian population-based Biobank (EGCUT; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biobank.ee">www.biobank.ee</ext-link>; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods) and previously subjected to SNP genotyping with Human370CNV-Duo SNP array (Illumina Inc., San Diego, CA) [Nelis et al., 2009] and genome-wide CNV calling (Priit Palta, unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Discovery Phase: Genome-Wide SNP Genotyping and CNV Detection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>The study design is schematically outlined in Figure1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>In the discovery phase, proportionally one-third subsample (n = 70; fertile controls, n = 27; RM cases, n = 43; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Table S2) of all Estonian study subjects (n = 209) was genotyped using Illumina Human370CNV-Quad SNP array (Genotyping Core Facility, Estonian Biocentre). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>For each sample, calling of CNVs from the resulting genome-wide genotyping data was performed in parallel with two algorithms, QuantiSNP and PennCNV [Colella et al., 2007; Wang et al., 2007] (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The initial CNV calls from the two algorithms were merged and only CNVs that were called by both algorithms for the same individual in the same genomic loci were considered in the subsequent global analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Discrete CNV regions (CNVRs) were defined by merging overlapping CNV calls across all individuals in a study group as described previously [Redon et al., 2006; Perry et al., 2008]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Genomic distribution of identified CNVRs was visualized using Circos software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://circos.ca/">http://circos.ca/</ext-link>) [Krzywinski et al., 2009]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The genome-wide CNV data of this study have been submitted to the Database of Genomic Variants (DGV; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://projects.tcag.ca/variation/">http://projects.tcag.ca/variation/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>For the EGCUT population-based cohort samples, the microarray data were processed in identical manner using parallel analysis of QuantiSNP and PennCNV and by considering only CNV calls that were made by both algorithms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Accurate CNV copy number for the 5p13.3 duplication locus was drawn from the QuantiSNP data due to its higher precision in copy number estimation in this locus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Functional Enrichment Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>In order to acquire the up-to-date genomic annotation data for functional enrichment analysis, all CNVR breakpoint coordinates were converted to the latest version of the human reference sequence (from NCBI36/hg18 to GRCh37/hg19) (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The list of genes within the identified CNV regions (extended by 10 kb on either side of the CNVR) was then acquired from the Ensembl database (version 69; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ensembl.org/index.html">http://www.ensembl.org/index.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Functional enrichment analysis of subsequent gene sets was carried out separately for fertile controls and RM patients using g:Profiler gGOSt web-based software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biit.cs.ut.ee/gprofiler/">http://biit.cs.ut.ee/gprofiler/</ext-link>) [Reimand et al., 2007, 2011] (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Two outlier cases with increased genomic burden of CNVs (RM-M45 and RM-F4) were excluded from the analysis to avoid biased results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Results of Gene Ontology (GO) and Reactome (REAC) datasets with up to third relative hierarchy level were taken into account and enrichment for functional terms was considered significant if the multiple testing corrected enrichment P-value was &lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Prioritization of CNVRs for Experimental Confirmation and Subsequent Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Discrete CNV regions identified in the discovery phase based on the whole genome SNP array genotyping data (full list of CNVRs in Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Table S3) were selected for experimental confirmation and further analysis if the following criteria were met: CNVR was (1) present in &gt;1 individual (criterion met by 118 out of 423 nonoverlapping CNVRs), (2) found only among RM patients or overrepresented in RM patients with odds ratio (OR) ≥1.5 (45/118 CNVRs), and (3) intersected with or located in the proximity (up to approximately 200 kb) of biological candidate genes with a potential impact on the course of pregnancy based on previously published literature (9/45 CNVRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>As our study aimed to identify common rearrangements predisposing to RM, previous reports in the DGV database for the prioritized CNVRs of this study were considered as confirmation of true CNV loci, rather than as an exclusion criterion due to unknown reproductive success of the genotyped individuals in these reports. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Experimental Copy Number Estimation of Prioritized CNVRs Using TaqMan qPCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>For experimental testing, TaqMan quantitative PCR (qPCR) was performed with one assay for seven of the prioritized CNVRs and with two assays in parallel for the two largest CNV loci as described in Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Ten nanograms of genomic DNA was amplified using predesigned TaqMan copy number assays (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Table S5) or previously published TaqMan qPCR primers and FAM-tagged probe (6p21.33 CNVR; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Table S6) [Parajes et al., 2007]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Copy number was normalized to the reference RNase P and population-specific pool of control DNAs (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The diploid genomic copy number was calculated by multiplying the normalized TaqMan qPCR copy number estimates by two. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Because of limitations of TaqMan qPCR assay to accurately determine very high diploid copy numbers, individuals with estimated locus copy number larger than four were assigned into copy number class “&gt;4 copies per diploid genome.” </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Experimental Fine Mapping and Characterization of the 5p13.3 Rearrangement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The confirmation of the 5p13.3 duplication endpoints estimated by SNP array was performed with four EvaGreen qPCR assays (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Table S6; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>S1) flanking the predicted breakpoints and using samples with known 5p13.3 copy number based on the data of TaqMan qPCR copy number typing (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Copy number was estimated using absolute quantification method and normalized to the reference gene ALB and population-specific pool of control DNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The exact position of duplication breakpoint junction in three 5p13.3 duplication carriers was determined using DNA sequencing by primer walking and targeting breakpoint junction region (5.8 kb) defined based on EvaGreen mapping (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>A control PCR spanning the identified breakpoint junction of the 5p13.3 tandem duplication (BP-PCR) was applied to confirm the duplication carriership in all Estonian and Danish RM case-control samples previously addressed with TaqMan qPCR (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The DNA sequences flanking the identified duplication breakpoints (±1,000 bp) were screened for repetitive elements using RepeatMasker software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.repeatmasker.org/">http://www.repeatmasker.org/</ext-link>) and searched for the non-B DNA motifs including direct and inverted repeats, short-tandem repeats, and cruciform motifs using non-B DNA motifs search tool (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nonb.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/apps/nBMST/default/">http://nonb.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/apps/nBMST/default/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Expression Profile Analysis of PDZD2 and GOLPH3 Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>The expression analysis was performed using human tissue cDNA panels Human MTC panel I and II (BD Biosciences Clontech, Palo Alto, CA) consisting of pools of samples for each tissue (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>The expression profile of the GOLPH3 and PDZD2 genes was determined with TaqMan qPCR approach using predesigned TaqMan gene expression assays (Applied Biosystems) and normalization to the reference transcript of HPRT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Copy Number Assignment of TaqMan qPCR Values </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The copy number assignment for simple deletion and/or duplication polymorphisms was performed manually, whereas for the multicopy 5p13.3 locus, average copy number ratio of two TaqMan assays located within the rearranged region was used for the assignment of each sample into a distinct copy number cluster with k-means clustering method in the statistical package R (ver. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>2.15.0; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org/">http://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>) (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The resulting grouping was confirmed using EvaGreen qPCR performed with assay “EvaGr assay 2” located within the rearranged region (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the 5p13.3 duplication carriership was confirmed in all Estonian and Danish RM cases and fertile controls using the duplication junction-specific control PCR (BP-PCR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Subsequent groups of carriers versus noncarriers were subject to genetic association testing (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Genetic Association Testing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Genetic association of the 5p13.3 duplication with the clinical diagnosis of RM was tested using logistic regression model in the statistical package R (version 2.15.0) in the Estonian and Danish RM cases/fertile control sample sets with. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Subjects were assigned as either carriers or noncarriers (wild type) of the tandem duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The obtained population-specific results were subsequently combined in the classical meta-analysis approach based on effect size estimates (beta-statistic) and standard errors and performed with the inverse-variance method under fixed-effects model in the statistical package R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, to correct for the asymmetric case/control ratio in the Estonian and Danish sample sets, a z-score-based meta-analysis was performed combining the logistic regression P-values, effect directions, and effective sample sizes using METAL software as described by Willer et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>(2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>In Estonians, the RM patient group was further tested against Estonian Biobank population-based cohort samples using logistic regression analysis as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Results with P-values &lt;0.05 were considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Increased Genomic Burden of CNVs in Two RM Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>In the discovery phase, the whole-genome screening (Illumina Human370CNV-Quad SNP array) for structural variants was performed in one-third subset of Estonian case-control samples (n = 70; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>On average, 13.3 CNVs were determined per individual in RM cases (n = 43) and 12.6 CNVs in fertile female controls (n = 27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Among all detected CNVs (n = 915) in the full discovery sample, a 2.1-fold excess of deletions compared to duplications was observed consistent with previously reported ratios [Redon et al., 2006; Conrad et al., 2010]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>However, the median length of duplications exceeded significantly the size of deletions (60.8 kb vs. 26.1 kb; Mann–Whitney U test, P = 1.82 × 10−13). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Genomic burden analysis of all detected CNVs per individual revealed two outlier RM patients RM-F4 and RM-M45 with increased cumulative size of CNVs exceeding the rest of the RM cases more than fivefold (6.1 Mb and 5.4 Mb vs. median of 1.0 Mb, respectively) (Fig.2; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>The case RM-F4 was the carrier of only heterozygous deletions (n = 19; Fig.2, Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>S4A) with the majority being longer than 100 kb (n = 15; median 313 kb) and deleting altogether 50 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Remarkably, the 5.4 Mb of CNVs (in total, n = 29; Fig.2, Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>S4A) in the case RM-M45 rearranged a total of 378 genes of which 113 duplicated and five deleted genes were located within the genomic region of immunoglobulin heavy chain (IGH) gene cluster at 14q32.33 potentially regulating the immune function during pregnancy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Additionally, heterozygous deletions of genes related to spermatogenesis (SOHLH1; MIM# 610224, SPATC1; MIM# 610874) [Goto et al., 2010; Suzuki et al., 2012] and known RM candidate genes (such as C4A (MIM# 120810), C4B (MIM# 120820), and IGF2 (MIM# 147470)) [Laitinen et al., 1991; Ostojic et al., 2008] were identified in this male patient potentially increasing the individual's risk of RM disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Both patients were from couples suffering from unexplained primary RM with no prior live births at the time of recruitment and had experienced three (RM-M45) or four (RM-F4) consecutive miscarriages occurring before gestational week 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>The available medical records for the male partner RM-M45 do not report any other diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>During the postrecruitment period, the female patient RM-F4 carrying 50 hemizygous genes has experienced further miscarriages (n = 3) but also live births (n = 2) as a result of clinical management. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Additionally, she has developed insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus and euthyroid goiters potentially also attributable to the large cumulative burden of deletions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Genomic burden of all CNVs in the Estonian discovery phase sample set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Cumulative length of all deletions and duplications is presented per individual in RM patients (n = 43) and fertile controls (n = 27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The outlier cases with increased cumulative burden of all CNVs (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>S3) are indicated with asterisk. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Female and male patients with identical number codes represent RM couples (e.g., RM-F45 and RM-M45). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>FFC, fertile female control; RM-F, female RM patient; RM-M, male RM patient. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="humu0035-0972-f2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Functional Profiling of Genes Disrupted by CNVRs Reveals Enrichment of Immune Signaling Pathways among RM Cases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The CNVs identified in the discovery phase clustered into 423 nonoverlapping CNVRs in RM cases and fertile controls that were uniformly distributed across the genome (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Table S3, Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>S4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Functional profiling analysis of all genes disrupted by these CNVRs in either RM patient group (excluding two outlier cases with increased CNV burden) or among controls (1151 and 553 genes, respectively) was undertaken to identify pathways and processes significantly modulated by the rearrangements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>In RM patients, the analysis specifically highlighted the role of impaired immune signaling, antigen binding, and immunoregulatory interactions at the fetomaternal interface in recurrent pregnancy loss (Table1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Notably, alterations in the REAC pathways of “innate immunity signaling” (9.3% of genes rearranged in the pathway, P = 9.15 × 10−3), “Complement cascade” (13.0% of genes, P = 1.11 × 10−3), and “Fc gamma receptors interact with antigen-bound IgG” (21.1% of genes rearranged by CNVs, P = 2.60 × 10−4) were specific to RM cases as none of the genes belonging to these categories were affected by structural variants in fertile controls (Table1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Pathway Analysis of Genes Affected by CNVs Identified by Genome-Wide Screening of Estonian Discovery Sample Set </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf1-1"><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The list of rearranged genes in either patients (n = 43) or controls (n = 27) was subjected to functional enrichment analysis using g:Profiler software (Reimand et al., 2007) and included Gene Ontology (GO) and Reactome (REAC) functional categories up to third relative hierarchical level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>gProfiler performs statistical enrichment analysis to identify functional groups and/or biological pathways that are significantly overrepresented in the user-provided gene list. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf1-2"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Two outlier cases RM-F4 and RM-M45 with increased genomic burden of CNVs (Fig.2) removed from the analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf1-3"><label>b</label><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Multiple testing corrected enrichment P-value. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf1-4"><label>c</label><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>None of the genes in this functional category were disrupted by CNVs among controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf1-5"><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>GPCR, G protein coupled receptor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Among the controls, the analyzed CNVRs likely represent benign rearrangements as only biological pathways of general cellular function were identified, including signaling of olfactory receptors (“olfactory signaling pathway,” REAC:381753, P = 9.99 × 10−7), a large class of genetically diverse proteins in humans known to be affected by CNVs in healthy individuals [Wong et al., 2007; Hasin-Brumshtein et al., 2009; Mills et al., 2011]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Experimental Testing of Prioritized CNVRs Detected by SNP Array </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>In order to identify common distinct CNV regions increasing the risk of RM, nine prioritized CNVRs were selected based on the genome-wide CNV screening results (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Table S3; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods) and subjected to copy number typing using TaqMan qPCR in the discovery sample set (n = 70) (see also Fig.1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Precise copy number estimation by TaqMan qPCR assays was observed for four prioritized CNVRs, identifying all CNV carriers predicted based on microarray analysis with no false positives (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Table S4, Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>S5; false negative rate across regions 1.4%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Three CNV regions— IGKV (immunoglobulin kappa variable cluster at 2p11.2; MIM# 146980), DKK2 (Dickkopf 2 homolog at 4q25; MIM# 605415), and PDZD2:GOLPH3 (PDZ domain containing 2; MIM# 610697; golgi phosphoprotein 3 at 5p13.3; MIM# 612207)—were carried onto the next experimental stage to analyze the full Estonian RM case-control sample set using the established TaqMan qPCR approach (Fig.1). SEPT14 CNVR (septin 14 at 7p11.2; MIM# 612140) was excluded from the next stage due to its restricted testis-specific expression [Peterson et al., 2007]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Although confirmed as copy number variable by TaqMan qPCR, precise locus copy number estimation of the remaining five prioritized CNVRs (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Table S4) was most likely hindered due to complex genomic architecture and rearrangements of the region as also evident based on previous CNV studies (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>S6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Thus, these CNVRs were excluded from further genetic association testing. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Significantly Increased Prevalence of PDZD2:GOLPH3 Duplication in Estonian and Danish RM Cases </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Among the three CNVRs (PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication, IGKV deletion/duplication, and DKK2 deletion) tested in the full Estonian sample set (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Table S1), PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication detected in up to four copies per diploid genome exhibited the strongest effect (OR = 7.28) with a higher prevalence of duplication carriers among the RM cases compared to fertile controls (9/119, 7.6% vs. 1/90, 1.1%, respectively) (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Table S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The Replication study of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 CNVR performed in Danish RM cases and fertile controls (in total, n = 554; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Table S1) confirmed the increased carrier frequency of the rearrangement (RM patients, 19/439, 4.3%; controls, 2/115, 1.7%; Table2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>However, a sex-stratified analysis of the Danish RM patients revealed the higher prevalence only among the female patients (6.6%) that was comparable to Estonian female cases (7.5%) (Fig.3A, Table2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>The PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication reached statistically significant association with an increased risk of RM (OR = 4.82, P = 0.012) in the meta-analysis combining the results of the Estonian and Danish female patient-control samples (in total, cases n = 309, controls n = 205). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>The high prevalence of the duplication observed among Estonian male RM partners was not replicated in Denmark (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Table S8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The observed differences could be attributed to the different size of the Estonian and Danish sample sets (n = 208 and n = 558, respectively). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>These North European subjects have been recruited according to similar clinical criteria minimizing the interstudy heterogeneity and used in parallel in previous collaborative research [Nagirnaja et al., 2012; Rull et al., 2013]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Maternal Risk of Recurrent Miscarriage Associated with the PDZD2:GOLPH3 CNV at 5p13.3 in Estonia and Denmark </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf2-1"><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Association testing was performed with duplication carriers versus noncarriers as established based on TaqMan qPCR and confirmed by junction-spanning PCR for RM cases and fertile controls and estimated by QuantiSNP based on SNP genotyping and CNV calling data for EGCUT samples (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf2-2"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Association testing was performed using logistic regression analysis in Estonia and Denmark separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The results were subsequently combined in the meta-analysis using inverse-variance method under fixed-effects model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Results with P-value &lt;0.05 were considered significant and are indicated in bold. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Copy number distribution of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication at 5p13.3 among female study subjects and experimental characterization of the locus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>A: Copy number distribution of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 CNV carriers and carrier frequency among female RM cases and female fertile controls from Estonia and Denmark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>CNV carriers have three to four copies of the duplication per genome in Estonia and three to more than four copies per genome in Denmark (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Dup, duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>B: Genomic context of 5p13.3 involving PDZD2 and GOLPH3 genes based on UCSC database (hg19). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>The opposite transcription of the PDZD2 and GOLPH3 genes is indicated with blue and green arrows, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>DGV Struc Var, structural variation data from the Database of Genomic Variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>C: Schematic representation of the 5p13.3 CNV locus with or without tandem duplication. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Experimentally confirmed duplication endpoints are indicated with red arrowheads and dotted lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The breakpoint junction of the tandem duplication is marked with red arrow tail and the breakpoint junction spanning region (5.8 kb) targeted with sequencing by primer walking is indicated with black bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Ex, exon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>D: Alignment of the acquired DNA sequence of the duplication breakpoint junction to the sequences of the proximal breakpoint region in PDZD2 intron 23 and distal breakpoint region in GOLPH3 intron 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>The microhomology of 1 bp determined at the junction of the duplication endpoints (red arrow tail) is shown with bold red letter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>E: Gene expression profile of the PDZD2 and GOLPH3 genes in the human cDNA tissue panels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Expression level is given relative to the reference gene HPRT and as average of three amplification reactions ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Gene expression levels in reproductive tissues are highlighted with gray bars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Each tissue sample is compiled of a pool of cDNAs (range, n = 2–98; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods) with n = 8 for placenta, n = 15 for ovary, n = 98 for prostate, and n = 45 for testis sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="humu0035-0972-f3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Notably, the strongest effect of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 CNV was detected among the subgroup of women with primary RM (Estonian cases: n = 46, CNV carrier frequency 8.7%; Danish, n = 113, 8.0%) defined as ≥3 consecutive miscarriages and no preceding live births (meta-analysis, n = 159; OR = 5.86, P = 0.007) (Table2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>A z-score-based meta-analysis correcting for the asymmetric case/control ratio provided consistent results in association testing including all female cases (P = 0.011) or only cases of primary RM (P = 0.006; Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Table S9). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>The two CNVRs (IGKV locus, Del/Dup; DKK2 locus, Del) with small differences in carrier frequencies in the full Estonian case-control sample (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Table S7) likely represent benign common copy number variation with no major effect on the RM phenotype in our study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Low Prevalence of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 Duplication in Worldwide Cohorts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The high risk of RM associated with the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication was further confirmed when Estonian RM cases were compared to the Estonian Biobank (EGCUT) cohort samples (in total, n = 1,000) (Table2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The most significant association among the subgroups of cases was observed for female patients tested against female cohort subjects (n = 496; prevalence 1.0%; OR = 7.96, P = 7.9 × 10−4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the carrier frequency of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication in the whole EGCUT cohort (9/1,000; 0.9%) was as low as observed among the Estonian and Danish controls (Table3) and similar carrier frequency has been consistently reported for various large worldwide population-based cohorts in the DGV (sample size range: n = 776–2,026; in total, n = 5846; duplication carrier frequency from 0.7% to 1.2%) (Table3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>5p13.3 CNV Carrier Frequency among Estonian and Danish Control Individuals of This Study and in the Populations Reported in the Database of Genomic Variants </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3-1"><label>a</label><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>In case of multiple studies targeting an identical study group (e.g., HapMap collection), results for the largest sample collection are presented. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-2"><label>b</label><p><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Only carrier frequencies from studies applying SNP array copy number estimations are included from the DGV database. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-3"><label>c</label><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Data for multiple overlapping nonrecurrent CNVs in 5p13.3 identified in the study are merged. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-4"><label>d</label><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>CNV sizes of all overlapping CNVs in the region identified in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-5"><label>e</label><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>HGDP: cohort of the Human Genome Diversity Panel, 51 world populations, n = 1,064; NINDS, neurological disease controls of European descent from National Institute for Neurological Disorders and Stroke, n = 790. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-6"><label>f</label><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>HapMap: healthy individuals from four populations—parent–offspring trios of the Yoruba from Nigeria (YRI; n = 30), parent–offspring trios of European descent from Utah (CEU; n = 30), unrelated Japanese from Tokyo, Japan (JPT; n = 45), and unrelated Han Chinese from Beijing, China (CHB; n = 45); PopGen: unrelated healthy individuals from Northern Schleswig-Holstein (Northern Germany), n = 506. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-7"><label>g</label><p><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>The cohort included 1,492 unrelated individuals, 80 mother–father–child trios, 325 mother–child and 140 father–child duos, 59 siblings, and 10 twins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tf3-8"><p><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>Dup, duplication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Fine-Scale Experimental Mapping of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 Duplication CNV </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Experimental fine-scale mapping of the 5p13.3 duplication confirmed the extent of the CNV predicted by the discovery SNP microarray data from the last intron of the PDZD2 to the first intron of the GOLPH3 genes, which are transcribed from the opposite DNA strands (Fig.3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Subsequent sequencing of the breakpoint junction-spanning region in the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication carriers refined the exact genomic coordinates of the CNV as Chr5: 32106204 – 32167777 and length as 61.6 kb (compared to 52.4 kb based on SNP array estimation) (Fig.3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>The presence of identical recurrent tandem duplication was detected in all North European carriers of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 CNV independent of the duplicon copy number. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The flanking genomic context of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication endpoints were characterized by a high number of repetitive elements in the proximity and overlapping with both breakpoint sites (Supp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>S7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>The proximal duplication endpoint was located within the DNA repetitive sequence MER1A and the distal endpoint in the AluJb element, whereas no extensive DNA sequence homology between the two repeat elements was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Also, no DNA sequences leading to non-B DNA conformation were identified and only a microhomology of one nucleotide was determined at the junction of the duplication endpoints by sequencing (Fig.3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Thus, repeat-mediated rearrangement mechanisms other than nonallelic homologous recombination have possibly contributed to the occurrence of this recurrent duplication (reviewed in [Hastings et al., 2009]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Expression Analysis of PDZD2 and GOLPH3 Genes in Human Tissues Reveals the Highest Expression in Placenta </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Although GOLPH3 was ubiquitously expressed in all tested tissues (human MTC panels I and II), it exhibited the highest transcript level in the placenta (average expression relative to reference HPRT, 2.99 ± 0.06 SEM), followed by prostate, ovary, and leucocytes (relative expression 1.50 ± 0.05, 1.13 ± 0.02, and 1.12 ± 0.04; respectively) (Fig.3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>In general, the level of PDZD2 transcripts was low in all tissues; however, the highest expression was also determined for the placenta exceeding fourfold the detected mRNA quantities in the two other sites of highest expression, heart and ovary (relative expression 1.33 ± 0.05 vs. 0.36 ± 0.01 and 0.34 ± 0.0, respectively) (Fig.3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Overall, the expression profile of these genes points to their functional relevance in the placenta and potentially in other reproductive organs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>In this study, we have addressed the effect of genome-wide CNVs and contribution of selected CNV regions in modulating the predisposition to RM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>The genome-wide CNV profiling revealed a significant enrichment of rearranged genes linked to innate immune signaling and immunoregulatory interactions within the RM study group, indicative of a potential effect on early pregnancy maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>As a main result, we report a novel duplication locus at 5p13.3 conferring high risk of RM among the female subjects of both Estonia and Denmark, and disrupting the PDZD2 and GOLPH3 genes predominantly expressed in placenta and associated with pregnancy maintenance for the first time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The large cumulative burden of CNVs and specifically long deletions may modify an individual's predisposition to RM due to increased chances of disrupting specific key genes or pathways essential for early pregnancy maintenance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>A case-by-case analysis performed in this study identified two RM cases RM-F4 and RM-M45 distinguished by heavy burden of CNVs and accumulation of several long deletions in RM-F4 (n = 15 out of 19 CNVs; Fig.2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Several potential or known RM candidate genes that may independently or synergistically elevate the risk of RM were rearranged within these cases, including immunomodulatory loci such as 119 genes from the IGH cluster and the previously reported RM-associated C4A and C4B genes [Laitinen et al., 1991]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>A subset of patients may thus exhibit increased risk of RM disease attributable to excessive genomic burden of CNVs; however, the finding remains to be confirmed by future studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>The detailed functional enrichment analysis of genes under CNVs within the RM study group confirmed the highly specific overrepresentation of pathways related to immune function and highlighted the processes most sensitive to CNV alterations in early pregnancy such as antigen binding, immunoregulatory interactions, innate immunity signaling, and complement cascade pathway associated with RM previously (Table1) [Li and Huang, 2009; Denny et al., 2013]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>The CNV profile modifying the repertoire of presented antigens and alloimmune responses may affect the subtle balance of the immunological tolerance at the fetomaternal interface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>As mother is carrying a semiallogeneic fetus expressing paternally inherited alloantigens, maternal immune rejection has been implicated in the etiology of preeclampsia and RM previously [Wilczynski, 2006; Guleria and Sayegh, 2007; Faridi and Agrawal, 2011]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>The major contribution of fetomaternal immune function in the development of RM has also been demonstrated in gene expression profiling of the maternal decidual tissue and chorionic villi of aborted fetuses [Baek et al., 2002; Krieg et al., 2012]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>As a major outcome of this study, a common multicopy duplication at 5p13.3 was identified conferring increased maternal risk to RM in North European populations, Estonians and Danes (meta-analysis OR = 4.82, P = 0.012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 CNV was detected with more than fivefold higher frequency in the female RM patients compared to fertile women (6.6%–7.5% vs. 1.1%–1.7%) or worldwide population cohorts (0.7%–1.2%; Tables2 and 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>The largest effect of GOLPH3:PDZD2 duplication as a risk factor was detected among the subgroup of women diagnosed with primary RM (meta-analysis, OR = 5.86, P = 0.007; Table2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>The duplication breakpoints of the identified PDZD2:GOLPH3 recurrent CNV (61.6 kb in size) occurring in up to &gt;4 diploid copies (Fig.3A) were positioned within the PDZD2 and GOLPH3 genes transcribed in the opposite directions (Fig.3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Although the 5p13.3 duplication does not directly alter the copy number of entire coding regions of the genes, the modifications in the local genomic context may nevertheless interfere with the transcription leading to dysregulation of the involved or neighboring genes as reported previously [Henrichsen et al., 2009a, 2009b]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The potential functional relevance of the identified rearrangement in pregnancy was supported by the expression profiling of PDZD2 and GOLPH3 in the human tissue panels revealing mutually high transcription levels in the placenta (two to fourfold increase compared to other tissues) but also in the maternal reproductive organ ovary (Fig.3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>We speculate that the significantly increased predisposition to RM among the female duplication carriers may be attributed to the joint effect in maternal reproductive tissues and in the placental tissue carrying a maternally inherited duplication CNV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>The mechanism of action and joint effect of the 5p13.3 CNV remains to be addressed further due to current limited availability of ovarian and early miscarriage placental samples carrying the 5p13.3 CNV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Most importantly, a recent study addressing the contribution of maternal CNVs in cases of preeclampsia (PE)—a severe late pregnancy disorder originating from placental dysfunction—identified the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication as the genetic risk factor of the disease [Zhao et al., 2013]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>The reported 50.4 kb duplication colocalized with the CNV identified in the current study and occurred with the prevalence of 8.3% among the affected and 1.6%–1.9% among unaffected female subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The identified risk to PE (OR = 4.80, P &lt; 0.05) is close to the effect detected for the RM susceptibility in this study (Table2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The possible common origin of various pregnancy disorders has been acknowledged previously, including overlapping causality of RM and PE [Li and Huang, 2009; Baig et al., 2013]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the dosage-sensitive gene GLUT3 (MIM# 138170) have been reported as the common genetic risk factor leading to either early pregnancy loss or fetal growth restriction [Ganguly et al., 2007]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Thus, it is plausible that the identified PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication may represent a pleiotropic risk factor in the genetic etiology of not only RM but also other pregnancy complications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Neither of the novel RM-associated genes PDZD2 or GOLPH3 has been linked to placental function or pregnancy maintenance previously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The function of PDZD2 is poorly defined and has mainly been addressed as a tumor suppressor [Yeung et al., 2003; Tam et al., 2006]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>More extensively studied conserved GOLPH3 is essential for Golgi trafficking and maintenance of its structure [Dippold et al., 2009; Wood et al., 2012]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Recently, genomic amplification of the GOLPH3 gene was linked to oncogenic features [Scott et al., 2009; Wang et al., 2012; Hu et al., 2013] and was shown to activate the signaling pathway of mechanistic target of rapamycin (mTOR), an essential component of mammalian reproductive function [Murakami et al., 2004; Wen et al., 2005; Busch et al., 2009; Yu et al., 2011; Gonzalez et al., 2012; Tanwar et al., 2012]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Alterations in mTOR signaling have been associated with multiple reproductive disorders in mice and human, including RM [Roos et al., 2007; Adhikari et al., 2010; Hirota et al., 2011; Leconte et al., 2011; Vatin et al., 2012], thus providing the potential functional link between the amplification of GOLPH3 and development of RM disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>In summary, the findings of this study highlight the genetic heterogeneity of RM not only by characterizing the potential predisposing effect of the cumulative burden of genome-wide CNVs, but also by identifying a common PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication, as RM risk factor detected in two independent North European sample sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Importantly, the identified PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication may represent a novel genetic risk factor for several pregnancy complications. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>The underlying functional effect of the PDZD2:GOLPH3 duplication in reproductive organs, placenta, and potentially in tumorigenesis remains to be addressed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><p>We appreciate all the study participants from Estonia and Denmark. We are thankful to Professor Andres Metspalu for suggestions on the manuscript and providing genotyping data of population-based controls from the Estonian Biobank in the Estonian Genome Center of the University of Tartu. We acknowledge Dr. Jüri Reimand for advice on functional enrichment analysis.</p><p><italic>Disclosure statement</italic>: The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>AdhikariDZhengWShenYGorreNHamalainenTCooneyAJHuhtaniemiILanZJLiuKTsc/mTORC1 signaling in oocytes governs the quiescence and activation of primordial folliclesHum Mol Genet20101939741019843540 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>AllisonJLSchustDJRecurrent first trimester pregnancy loss: revised definitions and novel causesCurr Opin Endocrinol Diabetes Obes20091644645019779333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>BaekKHChoiBCLeeJHChoiHKLeeSHKimJWHillJAChungHMKoJJChaKYComparison of gene expression at the feto-maternal interface between normal and recurrent pregnancy loss patientsReprod Fertil Dev20021423524012219946 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>BaigSLimJYFernandisAZWenkMRKaleASuLLBiswasAVasooSShuiGChoolaniMLipidomic analysis of human placental syncytiotrophoblast microvesicles in adverse pregnancy outcomesPlacenta20133443644223465879 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>BuschSRenaudSJSchleussnerEGrahamCHMarkertURmTOR mediates human trophoblast invasion through regulation of matrix-remodeling enzymes and is associated with serine phosphorylation of STAT3Exp Cell Res20093151724173319331815 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>ChristiansenOBMathiesenOLauritsenJGGrunnetNIdiopathic recurrent spontaneous abortion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Evidence of a familial predispositionActa Obstet Gynecol Scand1990695976012094140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>ChristiansenOBSteffensenRNielsenHSVarmingKMultifactorial etiology of recurrent miscarriage and its scientific and clinical implicationsGynecol Obstet Invest20086625726718679035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>ColellaSYauCTaylorJMMirzaGButlerHCloustonPBassettASSellerAHolmesCCRagoussisJQuantiSNP: an Objective Bayes Hidden-Markov Model to detect and accurately map copy number variation using SNP genotyping dataNucleic Acids Res2007352013202517341461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>ConradDFPintoDRedonRFeukLGokcumenOZhangYAertsJAndrewsTDBarnesCCampbellPFitzgeraldTHuMOrigins and functional impact of copy number variation in the human genomeNature201046470471219812545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>DennyKJWoodruffTMTaylorSMCallawayLKComplement in pregnancy: a delicate balanceAm J Reprod Immunol20136931122925193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>DippoldHCNgMMFarber-KatzSELeeSKKerrMLPetermanMCSimRWihartoPAGalbraithKAMadhavarapuSFuchsGJMeerlooTGOLPH3 bridges phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate and actomyosin to stretch and shape the Golgi to promote buddingCell200913933735119837035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>DiskinSJLiMHouCYangSGlessnerJHakonarsonHBucanMMarisJMWangKAdjustment of genomic waves in signal intensities from whole-genome SNP genotyping platformsNucleic Acids Res200836e12618784189 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>FaridiRMAgrawalSKiller immunoglobulin-like receptors (KIRs) and HLA-C allorecognition patterns implicative of dominant activation of natural killer cells contribute to recurrent miscarriagesHum Reprod20112649149721159685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>GangulyAMcKnightRARaychaudhuriSShinBCMaZMoleyKDevaskarSUGlucose transporter isoform-3 mutations cause early pregnancy loss and fetal growth restriction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Am J PhysiolEndocrinol Metab2007292E1241E1255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>GirirajanSBrkanacZCoeBPBakerCVivesLVuTHShaferNBernierRFerreroGBSilengoMWarrenSTMorenoCSRelative burden of large CNVs on a range of neurodevelopmental phenotypesPLoS Genet20117e100233422102821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>GonzalezIMMartinPMBurdsalCSloanJLMagerSHarrisTSutherlandAELeucine and arginine regulate trophoblast motility through mTOR-dependent and independent pathways in the preimplantation mouse embryoDev Biol201236128630022056783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>GotoMO'BrienDAEddyEMSperiolin is a novel human and mouse sperm centrosome proteinHum Reprod2010251884189420542897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Group TECWEurope the continent with the lowest fertilityHum Reprod Update20101659060220603286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>GuleriaISayeghMHMaternal acceptance of the fetus: true human toleranceJ Immunol20071783345335117339426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>HarrisRAFerrariFBen-ShacharSWangXSaadeGVan Den VeyverIFacchinettiFAagaard-TilleryKGenome-wide array-based copy number profiling in human placentas from unexplained stillbirthsPrenat Diagn20113193294421732394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Hasin-BrumshteinYLancetDOlenderTHuman olfaction: from genomic variation to phenotypic diversityTrends Genet20092517818419303166 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>HastingsPJLupskiJRRosenbergSMIraGMechanisms of change in gene copy numberNat Rev Genet20091055156419597530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>HenrichsenCNChaignatEReymondACopy number variants, diseases and gene expressionHum Mol Genet2009a18R1R819297395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>HenrichsenCNVinckenboschNZollnerSChaignatEPradervandSSchutzFRuediMKaessmannHReymondASegmental copy number variation shapes tissue transcriptomesNat Genet2009b4142442919270705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>HirotaYChaJYoshieMDaikokuTDeySKHeightened uterine mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1) signaling provokes preterm birth in miceProc Natl Acad Sci USA2011108180731807822025690 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>HuBSHuHZhuCYGuYLLiJPOverexpression of GOLPH3 is associated with poor clinical outcome in gastric cancerTumour Biol20133451552023132295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b82"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>ItsaraACooperGMBakerCGirirajanSLiJAbsherDKraussRMMyersRMRidkerPMChasmanDIPopulation analysis of large copy number variants and hotspots of human genetic diseaseAm J Hum Genet200984214816119166990 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>JivrajSAnstieBCheongYCFairlieFMLairdSMLiTCObstetric and neonatal outcome in women with a history of recurrent miscarriage: a cohort studyHum Reprod20011610210611139545 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>KimSYKimJHChungYJEffect of combining multiple CNV defining algorithms on the reliability of CNV calls from SNP genotyping dataGenomics Inform20121019419923166530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>KolteAMNielsenHSMoltkeIDegnBPedersenBSundeLNielsenFCChristiansenOBA genome-wide scan in affected sibling pairs with idiopathic recurrent miscarriage suggests genetic linkageMol Hum Reprod20111737938521257601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>KriegSAFanXHongYSangQXGiacciaAWestphalLMLathiRBKriegAJNayakNRGlobal alteration in gene expression profiles of deciduas from women with idiopathic recurrent pregnancy lossMol Human Reprod201218442450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>KruseCSteffensenRVarmingKChristiansenOBA study of HLA-DR and -DQ alleles in 588 patients and 562 controls confirms that HLA-DRB1*03 is associated with recurrent miscarriageHum Reprod2004191215122115070884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>KrzywinskiMScheinJBirolIConnorsJGascoyneRHorsmanDJonesSJMarraMACircos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomicsGenome Res2009191639164519541911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>LaitinenTLokkiMLTulppalaMYlikorkalaOKoskimiesSIncreased frequency of complement C4 'null' alleles in recurrent spontaneous abortionsHum Reprod19916138413871770131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>LeconteMNiccoCNgoCChereauCChouzenouxSMarutWGuibourdencheJArkwrightSWeillBChapronCDoussetBBatteuxFThe mTOR/AKT inhibitor temsirolimus prevents deep infiltrating endometriosis in miceAm J Pathol201117988088921718677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>LiMHuangSJInnate immunity, coagulation and placenta-related adverse pregnancy outcomesThromb Res200912465666219683334 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>McCarrollSAKuruvillaFGKornJMCawleySNemeshJWysokerAShaperoMHde BakkerPIMallerJBKirbyAElliottALParkinMIntegrated detection and population-genetic analysis of SNPs and copy number variationNat Genet2008401166117418776908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>MillsREWalterKStewartCHandsakerREChenKAlkanCAbyzovAYoonSCYeKCheethamRKChinwallaAConradDFMapping copy number variation by population-scale genome sequencingNature2011470596521293372 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>MurakamiMIchisakaTMaedaMOshiroNHaraKEdenhoferFKiyamaHYonezawaKYamanakaSmTOR is essential for growth and proliferation in early mouse embryos and embryonic stem cellsMol Cell Biol2004246710671815254238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>NagirnajaLVenclovasCRullKJonasKCPeltoketoHChristiansenOBKairysVKiviGSteffensenRHuhtaniemiITLaanMStructural and functional analysis of rare missense mutations in human chorionic gonadotrophin beta-subunitMol Hum Reprod20121837939022554618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>NelisMEskoTMagiRZimprichFZimprichATonchevaDKarachanakSPiskackovaTBalascakIPeltonenLJakkulaERehnstromKGenetic structure of Europeans: a view from the North-EastPloS One20094e547219424496 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Nybo AndersenAMWohlfahrtJChristensPOlsenJMelbyeMMaternal age and fetal loss: population based register linkage studyBMJ20003201708171210864550 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>OgasawaraMAokiKOkadaSSuzumoriKEmbryonic karyotype of abortuses in relation to the number of previous miscarriagesFertil Steril20007330030410685533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>OstojicSPerezaNVolkMKapovicMPeterlinBGenetic predisposition to idiopathic recurrent spontaneous abortion: contribution of genetic variations in IGF-2 and H19 imprinted genesAm J Reprod Immunol20086011111718573128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>ParajesSQuinterioCDominguezFLoidiLA simple and robust quantitative PCR assay to determine CYP21A2 gene dose in the diagnosis of 21-hydroxylase deficiencyClin Chem2007531577158417634211 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>PerryGHBen-DorATsalenkoASampasNRodriguez-RevengaLTranCWSchefferASteinfeldITsangPYamadaNAParkHSKimJIThe fine-scale and complex architecture of human copy-number variationAm J Hum Genet20088268569518304495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>PetersonEAKalikinLMSteelsJDEsteyMPTrimbleWSPettyEMCharacterization of a SEPT9 interacting protein, SEPT14, a novel testis-specific septin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>MammGenome200718796807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>PintoDDarvishiKShiXRajanDRiglerDFitzgeraldTLionelACThiruvahindrapuramBMacdonaldJRMillsRPrasadANoonanKComprehensive assessment of array-based platforms and calling algorithms for detection of copy number variantsNat Biotechnol20112951252021552272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>PintoDPagnamentaATKleiLAnneyRMericoDReganRConroyJMagalhaesTRCorreiaCAbrahamsBSAlmeidaJBacchelliEFunctional impact of global rare copy number variation in autism spectrum disordersNature201046636837220531469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b83"><text><SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>PintoDMarshallCFeukLSchererSWCopy-number variation in control population cohortsHum Mol Genet200716Spec No. 2R168R17317911159 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>RaiRReganLRecurrent miscarriageLancet200636860161116905025 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Rajcan-SeparovicEDiego-AlvarezDRobinsonWPTysonCQiaoYHarvardCFawcettCKalousekDPhilippTSomervilleMJStephensonMDIdentification of copy number variants in miscarriages from couples with idiopathic recurrent pregnancy lossHum Reprod2010252913292220847186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>RedonRIshikawaSFitchKRFeukLPerryGHAndrewsTDFieglerHShaperoMHCarsonARChenWChoEKDallaireSGlobal variation in copy number in the human genomeNature200644444445417122850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>ReimandJArakTViloJg:Profiler–a web server for functional interpretation of gene lists (2011 update)Nucleic Acids Res201139W307W31521646343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>ReimandJKullMPetersonHHansenJViloJg:Profiler–a web-based toolset for functional profiling of gene lists from large-scale experimentsNucleic Acids Res200735W193W20017478515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>RobinsonLGallosIDConnerSJRajkhowaMMillerDLewisSKirkman-BrownJCoomarasamyAThe effect of sperm DNA fragmentation on miscarriage rates: a systematic review and meta-analysisHum Reprod2012272908291722791753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>RoosSJanssonNPalmbergISaljoKPowellTLJanssonTMammalian target of rapamycin in the human placenta regulates leucine transport and is down-regulated in restricted fetal growthJ Physiol200758244945917463046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>RullKChristiansenOBNagirnajaLSteffensenRMargusTLaanMA modest but significant effect of CGB5 gene promoter polymorphisms in modulating the risk of recurrent miscarriageFertil Steril20139971930193623499152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>RullKNagirnajaLLaanMGenetics of recurrent miscarriage: challenges, current knowledge, future directionsFront Genet201233422457663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>RullKNagirnajaLUlanderVMKelgoPMargusTKaareMAittomakiKLaanMChorionic gonadotropin beta-gene variants are associated with recurrent miscarriage in two European populationsJ Clin Endocrinol Metab2008934697470618782867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>ScottKLKabbarahOLiangMCIvanovaEAnagnostouVWuJDhakalSWuMChenSFeinbergTHuangJSaciAGOLPH3 modulates mTOR signalling and rapamycin sensitivity in cancerNature20094591085109019553991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b84"><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>ShaikhTHGaiXPerinJCGlessnerJTXieHMurphyKO'HaraRCasalunovoTConlinLKD'ArcyMHigh-resolution mapping and analysis of copy number variations in the human genome: a data resource for clinical and research applicationsGenome Res20091991682169019592680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>StirratGMRecurrent miscarriageLancet19903366736751975862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>StrangerBEForrestMSDunningMIngleCEBeazleyCThorneNRedonRBirdCPde GrassiALeeCTyler-SmithCCarterNRelative impact of nucleotide and copy number variation on gene expression phenotypesScience200731584885317289997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>SuzukiHAhnHWChuTBowdenWGasseiKOrwigKRajkovicASOHLH1 and SOHLH2 coordinate spermatogonial differentiationDev Biol201236130131222056784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>TamCWChengASMaRYYaoKMShiuSYInhibition of prostate cancer cell growth by human secreted PDZ domain-containing protein 2, a potential autocrine prostate tumor suppressorEndocrinology20061475023503316873542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>TanwarPSKaneko-TaruiTZhangLTeixeiraJMAltered LKB1/AMPK/TSC1/TSC2/mTOR signaling causes disruption of Sertoli cell polarity and spermatogenesisHum Mol Genet2012214394440522791749 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>UuskulaLRullKNagirnajaLLaanMMethylation allelic polymorphism (MAP) in chorionic gonadotropin beta5 (CGB5) and its association with pregnancy successJ Clin Endocrinol Metab201096E199E20720962020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66"><text><SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>van OppenraaijRHJauniauxEChristiansenOBHorcajadasJAFarquharsonRGExaltoNPredicting adverse obstetric outcome after early pregnancy events and complications: a reviewHum Reprod Update20091540942119270317 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67"><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>VatinMBurgioGRenaultGLaissuePFirlejVMondonFMontagutelliXVaimanDSerresCZiyyatARefined mapping of a quantitative trait locus on chromosome 1 responsible for mouse embryonic deathPloS One20127e4335622916247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68"><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>WangJHChenXTWenZSZhengMDengJMWangMZLinHXChenKLiJYunJPLuoRZSongLBHigh expression of GOLPH3 in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma correlates with poor prognosisPloS One20127e4562223056210 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69"><text><SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>WangKLiMHadleyDLiuRGlessnerJGrantSFHakonarsonHBucanMPennCNV: an integrated hidden Markov model designed for high-resolution copy number variation detection in whole-genome SNP genotyping dataGenome Res2007171665167417921354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70"><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>WenHYAbbasiSKellemsREXiaYmTOR: a placental growth signaling sensorPlacenta200526Suppl AS63S6915837070 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71"><text><SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>WilczynskiJRImmunological analogy between allograft rejection, recurrent abortion and pre-eclampsia–the same basic mechanism?Hum Immunol20066749251116829304 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72"><text><SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>WillerCJLiYAbecasisGRMETAL: fast and efficient meta-analysis of genomewide association scansBioinformatics2010262190219120616382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73"><text><SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>WinchesterLYauCRagoussisJComparing CNV detection methods for SNP arraysBrief Funct Genomic Proteomic2009835336619737800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74"><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>WongKKdeLeeuwRJDosanjhNSKimmLRChengZHorsmanDEMacAulayCNgRTBrownCJEichlerEELamWLA comprehensive analysis of common copy-number variations in the human genomeAm J Hum Genet2007809110417160897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75"><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>WoodCSHungCSHuohYSMousleyCJStefanCJBankaitisVFergusonKMBurdCGLocal control of phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphate signaling in the Golgi apparatus by Vps74 and Sac1 phosphoinositide phosphataseMol Biol Cell2012232527253622553352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76"><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>YeungMLTamTSTsangACYaoKMProteolytic cleavage of PDZD2 generates a secreted peptide containing two PDZ domainsEMBO Rep2003441241812671685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77"><text><SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>YuJYabaAKasimanCThomsonTJohnsonJmTOR controls ovarian follicle growth by regulating granulosa cell proliferationPloS One20116e2141521750711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b78"><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>ZhangFGuWHurlesMELupskiJRCopy number variation in human health, disease, and evolutionAnnu Rev Genomics Hum Genet20091045148119715442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b79"><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>ZhaoLBrackenMBDewanATGenome-Wide Association Study of Pre-Eclampsia Detects Novel Maternal Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms and Copy-Number Variants in Subsets of the Hyperglycemia and Adverse Pregnancy Outcome (HAPO) Study CohortAnn Hum Genet20132013Apr 2. doi: 10.1111/ahg.12021. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>[Epub ahead of print] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b80"><text><SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>ZhaoLTricheEWWalshKMBrackenMBSaftlasAFHohJDewanATGenome-wide association study identifies a maternal copy-number deletion in PSG11 enriched among preeclampsia patientsBMC Pregnancy Childbirth2012126122748001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b81"><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>ZogopoulosGHaKCNaqibFMooreSKimHMontpetitARobidouxFLaflammePCotterchioMGreenwoodCGerm-line DNA copy number variation frequencies in a large North American populationHum Genet20071223–434535317638019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article.</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="pdf" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="humu0035-0972-SD1.pdf" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e6338" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></back></article>
