
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Mol Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijms</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1422-0067</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4307340</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25599529</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms16011894</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijms-16-01894</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Isolation and Expression of NAC Genes during Persimmon Fruit Postharvest Astringency Removal </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-16-01894">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Miao-Miao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Hongxun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijms-16-01894">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Xiaofen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grierson</surname><given-names>Donald</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-ijms-16-01894">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Xue-Ren</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref><xref rid="c1-ijms-16-01894" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Kun-Song</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijms-16-01894">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Iriti</surname><given-names>Marcello</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijms-16-01894"><label>1</label>Laboratory of Fruit Quality Biology/The State Agriculture Ministry Laboratory of Horticultural Plant Growth, Development and Quality Improvement, Zhejiang University, Zijingang Campus, Hangzhou 310058, China; E-Mails: <email>11016045@zju.edu.cn</email> (T.M.); <email>wmm@zju.edu.cn</email> (M.-M.W.); <email>0013915@zju.edu.cn</email> (X.L.); <email>21216047@zju.edu.cn</email> (F.F.); <email>donald.grierson@nottingham.ac.uk</email> (D.G.); <email>akun@zju.edu.cn</email> (K.-S.C.)</aff><aff id="af2-ijms-16-01894"><label>2</label>College of Food Science and Engineering, Wuhan Polytechnic University, Changqing Campus, Wuhan 430023, China; E-Mail: <email>hongxunwang1977@gmail.com</email></aff><aff id="af3-ijms-16-01894"><label>3</label>Plant &amp; Crop Sciences Division, School of Biosciences, University of Nottingham, Sutton Bonington Campus, Loughborough LE12 5RD, UK</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijms-16-01894"><label>*</label>Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: <email>xuerenyin@zju.edu.cn</email>; Tel.: +86-571-8898-2461.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>1894</fpage><lpage>1906</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>09</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2015 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license><license-p>This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>NAC genes have been characterized in numerous plants, where they are involved in responses to biotic and abiotic stress, including low oxygen stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>High concentration of CO2 is one of the most effective treatments to remove astringency of persimmon fruit owing to the action of the accumulated anoxia metabolite acetaldehyde. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In model plants, NAC genes have been identified as being responsive to low oxygen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>However, the possible relationship between NAC transcription factors and persimmon astringency removal remains unexplored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In the present research, treatment with a high concentration of CO2 (95%) effectively removed astringency of “Mopan” persimmon fruit by causing decreases in soluble tannin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Acetaldehyde content increased in response to CO2 treatment concomitantly with astringency removal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Using RNA-seq and Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE), six DkNAC genes were isolated and studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional analysis indicated DkNAC genes responded differentially to CO2 treatment; DkNAC1, DkNAC3, DkNAC5 and DkNAC6 were transiently up-regulated, DkNAC2 was abundantly expressed 3 days after treatment, while the DkNAC4 was suppressed during astringency removal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>It is proposed that DkNAC1/3/5/6 could be important candidates as regulators of persimmon astringency removal and the roles of other member are also discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>persimmon</kwd><kwd>deastringency</kwd><kwd><italic>NAC</italic></kwd><kwd>low oxygen stress</kwd><kwd>transcription factor</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Proanthocyanidins (PAs) are secondary metabolites and phenolic oligomers that result from the condensation of flavan-3-ol units. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>PAs have a variety of uses and are beneficial for human health owing to their antioxidant properties, which include anti-allergic, anti-tumor, anti-aging properties, and the prevention of cardiovascular disease [1,2,3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Moreover, they can be used to detoxicate snake venom and have been used to adsorb radioactive compounds from nuclear waste and recycle the heavy metals from electronic waste [4,5,6,7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Persimmon (Diospyros kaki) is a unique fruit that accumulates PAs in abundance [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Persimmon fruit can be divided into astringent and nonastringent types, and most of the commercial cultivars in China are of the astringent type [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Astringent persimmons accumulate abundant PAs in the fruit flesh even at maturity and soluble PAs cause astringency, which severely affects the industry and consumer acceptance [9,10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Thus, astringency removal is critical for the persimmon industry. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Due to the importance of astringency removal for commercial production, a range of technologies has been developed, such as CO2 and N2 [11,12,13]; C2H4 and alternate freezing and thawing [14,15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Among these, high concentration CO2 treatment is very commonly used and its underlying physiological and molecular mechanisms of astringency removal are much more clearly understood than for the other treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>It has been suggested that acetaldehyde, which accumulates during anaerobic respiration induced by high CO2, causes soluble tannins to become insoluble during the treatment, thus reducing astringency [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Alcohol dehydrogenase (ADH) and Pyruvate decarboxylase (PDC) enzyme activities increased during deastringency and this was associated with acetaldehyde biosynthesis [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Our previous results indicated that ADH and PDC enzyme were both induced by CO2 and C2H4 treatments, and DkADH1, DkPDC1, DkPDC2 and DkPDC3 expression was up-regulated in response to both ethylene and high CO2 treatments [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>When DkPDC2 was transiently over-expressed in persimmon leaves, they showed a lower level of soluble tannins, compared with leaves infiltrated with an empty vector, suggesting that DkPDC2 is a key gene regulating soluble tannins and astringency removal [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These results suggested CO2 driven astringency removal requires acetaldehyde metabolism, brought about by modulation of ADH and PDC enzymes and genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>However, understanding of the molecular basis of persimmon astringency removal is still limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>In model plants, a few transcription factors have been reported to be involved in the hypoxia response, such as NAC and ethylene response factors (ERF) [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>As mentioned above, persimmon fruit astringency removal by CO2 treatment is considered to operate mainly via the hypoxia fermentation pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In persimmon fruit, the only transcription factors analyzed during persimmon fruit astringency removal have been the ERF gene family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Recently, four ERF genes, DkERF9, DkERF10, DkERF19 and DkERF22, were shown to manifest trans-activation of DkADH and DkPDC genes [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>However, the relations between other transcription factors and astringency removal have rarely been reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In addition to ERFs, NAC genes are the main transcription factors reported to be involved in the plant hypoxia response, which indicated their potential to be involved in persimmon astringency removal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>The NAC designation is based on highly conserved consensus sequences in the N-terminal region of a Petunia gene (NAM), Arabidopsis ATAF1/2 and CUC2 proteins [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>More than 100 NAC genes have been identified and characterized in Arabidopsis [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Among them, ANAC019, ANAC055 and ANAC072 enhanced tolerance to drought stress in Arabidopsis [23], and ANAC2 is involved in response to plant hormones [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In addition, ANAC102 was shown to be induced by low oxygen (0.1%), and overexpression of ANAC102 up-regulated ADH expression [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Since treatment with a high concentration of CO2 triggered expression of ADH/PDC genes and acetaldehyde metabolism in persimmon, this suggested that the Arabidopsis low oxygen responsive transcription factors such as ANAC102 had the potential to be involved in astringency removal, but experimental evidence for this was lacking in persimmon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>In the present research, six DkNAC genes were isolated from “Mopan” persimmon fruit based on differentially expressed genes (DEG) in an RNA-seq database using Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE) technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>High CO2 (95%) treatment was applied to the fruit and DkNAC transcripts were analyzed during the deastringency process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Some DkNAC genes were found to be positively correlated with persimmon fruit deastringency, and the possible roles of these and other DkNAC genes are discussed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS,DISCUSS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Results and Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Fruit Deastringency </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The soluble tannin content remained almost constant during storage in the control fruit, whereas in contrast, the CO2 treatment caused a rapid decrease in the concentration of soluble tannin from 0.917% at day 0% to 0.229% at day 1 (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Soluble tannins content was measured both by the Folin phenol method, and also visualized by tannin printing, using filter paper soaked with 5% FeCl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The extent, and location, of soluble tannin content was revealed by the tissue printing, and was substantially lower in CO2 treated fruit, compared with control fruit (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Acetaldehyde, the main compound responsible for insolublization of soluble tannin, was also analyzed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>The results indicated that there was a very obvious increase (approx. five fold) in acetaldehyde accumulation in CO2 treated fruit one day after the start of treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>However, such differences were abolished, following cessation of the treatment (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>By utilizing soluble tannin and tanning printing assays, 95% CO2 treatment was shown to be effective in inducing deastringency in postharvest “Mopan” cultivar persimmon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>These results confirm and extend our previous findings [18] and other reports using various persimmon cultivars [11,12,18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A burst of acetaldehyde production during deastringency treatment has been widely reported in various persimmon cultivars, such as “Rojo Brillante”, “Kaki Tipo”, “Lycopersicon” [25,26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Thus, the transient accumulation of acetaldehyde further supports the role and effectiveness of 95% CO2 treatment on persimmon fruit deastringency. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-01894-f001" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Effect of CO2 treatment on soluble tannin of “Mopan” fruit at 20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Mature fruit were treated with CO2 (~95%, v/v, open circles, one day) and air (control, open squares), separately. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent standard error from three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-01894-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-01894-f002" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Comparison of tannin printing of control and CO2 treated “Mopan” fruit at 2 days in storage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-01894-g002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-01894-f003" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Effect of CO2 treatment on acetaldehyde content of “Mopan” fruit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Mature fruit were treated with CO2 (~95%, v/v, white bars, one day) and air (control, black bars), separately at 20 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent standard error from three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-01894-g003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-01894-f004" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Amino acid sequence alignment of the DkNAC proteins with Arabidopsis and rice NAC proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>DkNAC proteins were aligned with Arabidopsis ANAC019 (At1g52890.1), ANAC042 (At2g43000.1), ANAC043 (At2g46770.1), ANAC102 (AT5G63790.1) and rice ONAC022 (AK107090). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Identical and similar amino acids are indicated by black and grey shading, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Gaps were introduced to optimize alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The five highly conserved amino acid motifs (A–E) are indicated by black lines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-01894-g004"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>NAC Genes Isolation and Sequence Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Six novel putative NAC genes were isolated from persimmon fruit, five of which were full-length sequences and one partial CDS, and designated as DkNAC1-6 (GenBank accession nos. KP222303–KP222308). DkNAC1-5 were predicted to encode proteins of 303, 266, 242, 214 and 194 amino acid (aa), respectively, however, the protein encoded by DkNAC6 could not be predicted from the partial CDS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Alignment analysis with the deduced proteins encoded by the DkNAC genes showed that they contained the NAC conserved domain in their N-terminal regions, which was divided into five subdomains (A–E) [27] (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>However, the C-terminal regions showed less similarity between different members of the NAC family (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>To examine the phylogenetic relationship between the NAC proteins in persimmon and Arabidopsis, a phylogenetic tree was constructed based on their translated amino acid sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>As shown in Figure 5, DkNAC1 and DkNAC6 were homologous with, and closely related to ANAC102, which is involved in the viability of Arabidopsis seeds following low-oxygen treatment [19]; DkNAC2 and DkNAC3 share the same branch, and are closely related to ANAC029, which was reported to play an important role in leaf senescence in Arabidopsis [28]; DkNAC4 was clustered with ANAC013, which has been reported to be involved in mitochondrial retrograde regulation of the oxidative stress response in Arabidopsis [29]; DkNAC5 was similar to ANAC104, which was identified as part of the leaf senescence transcriptome [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these data suggested that DkNAC1-6 may exhibit diverse functions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-01894-f005" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of NAC genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Persimmon DkNAC genes are highlighted in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The amino acid sequences of the Arabidopsis ERF family were obtained from TAIR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree was constructed with figtree (version 3.1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-01894-g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate the possible roles of NAC transcription factors in persimmon fruit deastringency, six differentially expressed DkNAC genes were identified by RNA-seq data [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the six DkNAC proteins showed that they shared a highly conserved N-terminal region, containing five consensus subdomains, which are termed the NAC domains [27]. NAC genes have been classified previously into two groups based on similarities of NAC domain structures in Arabidopsis thaliana and rice [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Group I proteins are composed of 14 subgroups, including TERN, ONAC022, SENU5, NAP, AtNAC3, ATAF, OsNAC3, NAC2, ANAC011, TIP, OsNAC8, OsNAC7, NAC1 and NAM, and group II can be divided into four subgroups, namely ANAC011, ONAC003, ONAC001 and ANAC063 [27]. DkNAC1 and DkNAC6 belong to group I (ATAF subfamily). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>ANAC102 belongs to the ATAF subgroup [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>DkNAC2-4 also belongs to group I, whereas DkNAC2 and DkNAC3 belong to the NAP subfamily and DkNAC4 belongs to the NAC2 subfamily and DkNAC5 belongs to group II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Thus, phylogenetic and structural analyses indicated that DkNAC1 and DkNAC6 were mostly likely to be involved in persimmon deastringency, as indicated by the high similarity with ANAC102. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>NAC Genes Expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The six NAC genes had different expression patterns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Transcripts of DkNAC1, DkNAC5 and DkNAC6 were transiently induced by the CO2 treatment, peaking after one day, and the expression of DkNAC3 peaked after two days. DkNAC5 was the most strongly up-regulated, with its mRNA increasing in abundance approximately 1200-fold following the treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Unlike DkNAC1/3/5/6, transcripts of DkNAC2 increased at four days (three days after treatment was stopped). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Unlike the other DkNAC genes, the expression of DkNAC4 was decreased during CO2 treatment and then recovered by day 4 (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ijms-16-01894-f006" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional analysis of DkNAC genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Transcripts of DkNAC genes were measured by real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Fruit were treated with 95% CO2 for one day at 20 °C in sealed container, while control fruit was sealed in a similar container without any treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Day 0 fruit values were set as 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Error bars indicate standard error from three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijms-16-01894-g006"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>One of most interesting results was that DkNAC1, DkNAC3, DkNAC5 and DkNAC6 were up-regulated by CO2 treatment, and that this occurred concomitantly with the decrease in soluble tannin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>This indicates that in persimmons, expression of DkNAC1, DkNAC3, DkNAC5 and DkNAC6 is highly correlated with fruit deastringency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The expression pattern of DkNAC1 and DkNAC6 further supported the prediction from phylogenetic and structural analyses, that ANAC102 homologs might be important regulators of the hypoxia response, which benefit deastringency in persimmon fruit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Besides DkNAC1 and DkNAC6, DkNAC3 and DkNAC5 were also observed to increase in expression in response to 95% CO2 treatment; however, DkNAC3 and DkNAC5 belong to the NAP subfamily and group II, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>These results may indicate that more subfamilies might be involved in the deastringency response in persimmon fruit and more generally in the hypoxia response in plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Although hypoxia-responsive NAC genes have rarely been reported, the results from the studies on ANAC102 also indicated that additional NAC genes might exist for the hypoxia response, as ANAC102 knockout lines did not show altered ADH gene transcription in Arabidopsis [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Taken together, results from persimmon and previous finding in Arabidopsis indicate that additional NAC genes are potentially involved in the hypoxia response in plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>In addition to the four above-mentioned DkNAC genes, DkNAC2 and DkNAC4 expression also exhibited interesting features. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Unlike the positively regulated NAC genes, DkNAC4 mRNA levels were negatively correlated with astringency removal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, no repressive domain, such as an EAR motif, was observed within the coding region of DkNAC4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>The increase in DkNAC2 mRNA occurred on the third day after treatment was removed, after the fruit had lost their astringency and started to senescence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>These results indicated that DkNAC2 might be involved in fruit ripening or senescence-related processes, but not astringency removal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Similar results were also reported in other fruit, such as banana, where transcripts of MaNAC1 and MaNAC2 were up-regulated in banana post-harvest ripening, and it was suggested that MaNAC genes may be involved in banana fruit ripening via interaction with ethylene signalling components [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>It was also reported in Arabidopsis siliques that AtNAP, a NAC gene whose expression increased with the progression of silique senescence, played a key role in its senescence [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Experimental Section </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Materials and Treatments </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The “Mopan” (astringent cultivar) persimmon fruit were harvested from a commercial orchard (Fangshan, Beijing) in 2013, with mean firmness of 47 N, and then transported to the laboratory the next day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Fruits with no defects and uniform size were chosen for treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>CO2 (95%) and control treatments were performed according to our previous report [18] (Min et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>After firmness measurement at each sampling point, fruit flesh was removed from the peel and shredded, then frozen with liquid nitrogen and kept in −80 °C refrigerator until required. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Soluble Tannins Assay and Tannin Printing </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>The content of soluble tannins, the most important index for astringency, was measured using Folin-Ciocalteu reagent according to the method described in our previous report [14] (Yin et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The printing method, a convenient way of identifying persimmon astringency location and loss, was also used for the examination of soluble tannins in the fruit flesh according to [33] Hu et al., (2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Filter papers were soaked with 5% FeCl2 for about 5–10 min, then moved to a 60 °C oven until dry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The whole fruit was cut into two parts and printed on the processed filter paper. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The black color indicated soluble tannins and the intensity of black reflected the soluble tannins content. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Acetaldehyde Determination </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Acetaldehyde production was determined with a gas chromatograph Instrument (Agilent 6890N, Folsom, CA, USA) with a FID column (HP-INNOWAX, 0.25 mm, 30 m, 0.25 μm, Agilent J&amp;W, Folsom, CA, USA) according to the method described previously [20] (Min et al., 2014) with some modification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The injector, detector and oven temperatures were 150, 160, and 100 °C, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Sec-butyl alcohol was added to each vial as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The results were calculated using standard curves for acetaldehyde and ethanol, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>3.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>RNA Extraction and cDNA Synthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was prepared according to the method used previously [18] (Min et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Traces of contaminating genomic DNA in total RNA were removed with TURBO DNase (Life Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>One microgram DNA-free RNA was used for cDNA synthesis by iScript cDNA Synthesis kit (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) following the manufacturer’s protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>For each sampling point, three biological replicates were used for RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>3.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Gene Isolation and Sequence Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The NAC genes were isolated based on RNA-Seq data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>RNA-Seq was performed by the Beijing Genome Institute (BGI) (Shenzhen, China) according to our previous paper [20] (Min et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>Rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE) was chosen to amplify the 3' and/or 5' end Untranslated region (UTR) of NAC, using a SMART™ RACE cDNA Amplification Kit (Clontech, Palo Alto, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The sequences of primers used for RACE are listed in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>The gene sequences were translated with online software (http://web.expasy.org/translate/) and were confirmed with the BLAST methods in Genbank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic tree of NAC genes was generated using ClustalX (v 1.81) [34] and calculated using Figtree (v1.3.1, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, UK). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>The deduced amino acid sequences of homologous genes of Arabidopsis were obtained from TAIR (The Arabidopsis Information Resource). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ijms-16-01894-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijms-16-01894-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Sequences of the primers used for gene isolation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>3.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotide Primers and Real-Time PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Oligonucleotide primers for real-time PCR analysis were designed with primer3 (v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>0.4.0, http://frodo.wi.mit.edu/cgi-bin/primer3/primer3_www.cgi). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The specificity of primers was determined by melting curves and PCR products resequencing as described in [35] Yin et al. (2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The sequences of oligonucleotide primers are listed in Table 2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ijms-16-01894-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijms-16-01894-t002_Table 2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Sequences of the primers used for real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR was carried out with Ssofast EvaGreen Supermix kit (Bio-Rad) and CFX96 instrument (Bio-Rad) for gene expression studies according to our previous report [18] (Min et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>The relative abundance of each gene was calibrated with samples from day 0 fruit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Actin, a housekeeping gene, was used as the internal control [9] (Akagi et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>3.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Origin 8.0 (OriginLab, Northampton, MA, USA) was used to prepare the figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance of differences was calculated with least significant difference (LSD) using DPS software (v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>3.11, Zhejiang University, Hangzhou, China). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, soluble tannins and acetaldehyde assay results showed that a high concentration of CO2 treatment was effective in inducing deastringency of “Mopan” persimmon fruit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Six DkNAC genes were isolated and the transcriptional level of DkNAC1, DkNAC3, DkNAC5 and DkNAC6 were highly correlated with fruit deastringency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Finally, DkNAC1/3/5/6 are identified as prime candidates for further transcriptional regulatory analysis in persimmon fruit to understand the molecular control of astringency removal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>This research was supported by the Special Fund for Agro-scientific Research in the Public Interest (no. 201203047), National Natural Science Foundation of China (no. 31372114), Program of International Science and Technology Cooperation (2011DFB31580) and the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities (no. 2014QNA6015). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Ting Min, Xue-Ren Yin and Kun-Song Chen participated in the design of the study; Ting Min, Miao-Miao Wang, Fang Fang and Xiaofen Liu participated in carrying out the experiments; Ting Min, Xue-Ren Yin and Xiaofen Liu participated in data analysis; Ting Min and Hongxun Wang and Xue-Ren Yin participated in drafting the manuscript; Xue-Ren Yin, Kun-Song Chen, Hongxun Wang and Donald Grierson read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>1. AhmadN.GuptaS.MukhtarH. Green tea polyphenol epigallocatechin-3-gallate differentially modulates nuclear factor κB in cancer cells versus normal cells Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Biophys. 2000 76 338 346 10.1006/abbi.2000.1742 10775421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>2. PatakiT.BakI.KovacsP.BagchiD.DasK.TosakiA. Grape seed proanthocyanidins improved cardiac recovery during reperfusion after ischemia in isolated rat hearts Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Nutr. 2002 75 894 895 <?supplied-pmid 11976164?>11976164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>3. SerafiniM.BugianesiR.MaianiG.ValtuenaS.de SantisS.CrozierA. Plasma antioxidants from chocolate Nature 2003 424 1013 10.1038/4241013a <?supplied-pmid 12944955?>12944955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>4. GuH.F.LiangJ.LiC.M.ZhangJ.DouH.L. Study on inhibitory effects of persimmon tannins on activities of major enzymes from several snake venoms and its mechanism Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Agric. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Sin. 2008 41 910 917  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>5. InoueK.KawakitaH.OhioK.OshimaT. Adsorptive removal of uranium and thorium with a crosslinked persimmon peel gel J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Radioanal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Nucl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Chem. 2006 267 435 442 10.1007/s10967-006-0067-z  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>6. ParajuliD.KawakitaH.InoueK.OhtoK.KajiyamaK. Persimmon peel gel for the selective recovery of gold Hydrometallurgy 2007 87 133 139 10.1016/j.hydromet.2007.02.006  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>7. XiongY.AdhikariC.R.KawakitaH.OhtoK.InoueK.HaradaH. Selective recovery of precious metals by persimmon waste chemically modified with dimethylamine Bioresour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Technol. 2009 100 4083 4089 10.1016/j.biortech.2009.03.014 <?supplied-pmid 19386489?>19386489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>8. LuoC.ZhangQ.L.LuoZ.R. Genome-wide transcriptome analysis of Chinese pollination-constant nonastringent persimmon fruit treated with ethanol BMC Genomics 2014 15 112 10.1186/1471-2164-15-112 <?supplied-pmid 24507483?>24507483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>9. Akagi.T.IkegamiA.TsujimotoT.KobayashiS.SatoA.KonoA.YonemoriK. DkMyb4 is a Myb transcription factor involved in proanthocyanidin biosynthesis in persimmon fruit Plant Physiol. 2009 151 2028 2045 19783643 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>10. YonemoriK.SuzukiY. Differences in three-dimensional distribution of tannin cells in flesh tissue between astringent and non-astringent type persimmon Acta Hortic. 2008 833 119 124  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>11. ArnalL.Del-RíoM.A. Removing astringency by carbon dioxide and nitrogen-enriched atmospheres in persimmon fruit cv. “Rojo brillante” J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Food Sci. 2003 68 1516 1518 10.1111/j.1365-2621.2003.tb09676.x  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>12. SalvadorA.ArnalL.BesadaC.LarreaV.QuilesA.Pérez-MunueraI. Physiological and structural changes during ripening and deastringency treatment of persimmon fruit cv. “Rojo Brillante” Postharvest Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Technol. 2007 46 181 188 10.1016/j.postharvbio.2007.05.003  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>13. YamadaM.TairaS.OhtsukiM.SatoA.IwanamiH.YakushijiH.WangR.Z.YangY.LiG.C. Varietal differences in the ease of astringency removal by carbon dioxide gas and ethanol vapor treatments among oriental astringent persimmons of Japanese and Chinese origin Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Hortic. 2002 94 63 72 10.1016/S0304-4238(01)00367-3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>14. YinX.R.ShiY.N.MinT.LuoZ.R.YaoY.C.XuQ.FergusonI.B.ChenK.S. Expression of ethylene response genes during persimmon fruit astringency removal Planta 2012 235 895 906 10.1007/s00425-011-1553-2 <?supplied-pmid 22101946?>22101946 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>15. TairaS.OnoM.OtsukiM. Effects of freezing rate on astringency reduction in persimmon during and after thawing Postharvest Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Technol. 1998 14 317 324 10.1016/S0925-5214(98)00057-X  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>16. MatsuoT.ItoS. On mechanisms of removing astringency in persimmon fruits by carbon dioxide treatment I. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Some properties of the two processes in the de-astringency Plant Cell Physiol. 1997 18 17 25  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>17. TamuraF.TanabeK.ItaiA.HasegawaM. Characteristics of acetaldehyde accumulation and removal of astringency with ethanol and carbon dioxide treatments in “Saijo” persimmon fruit J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Jpn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Hortic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Sci. 1999 68 1178 1183 10.2503/jjshs.68.1178  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>18. MinT.YinX.R.ShiY.N.LuoZ.R.YaoY.C.GriersonD.FergusonI.B.ChenK.S. Ethylene-responsive transcription factors interact with promoters of ADH and PDC involved in persimmon (Diospyros kaki) fruit de-astringency J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Bot. 2012 63 6393 6405 10.1093/jxb/ers296 <?supplied-pmid 23095993?>23095993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>19. ChristiansonJ.A.WilsonI.W.LlewellynD.J.DennisE.S. The low-oxygen-induced NAC domain transcription factor ANAC102 affects viability of Arabidopsis seeds following low-oxygen treatment Plant Physiol. 2009 149 1724 1738 10.1104/pp.108.131912 <?supplied-pmid 19176720?>19176720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>20. MinT.FangF.GeH.ShiY.N.LuoZ.R.YaoY.C.GriersonD.YinX.R.ChenK.S. Two novel anoxia-induced ethylene response factors that interact with promoters of deastringency-related genes from persimmon PLoS One 2014 e97043 10.1371/journal.pone.0097043 24805136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>21. AidaM.IshidaT.FukakiH.FujisawaH.TasakaM. Genes involved in organ separation in Arabidopsis: An analysis of the cup-shaped cotyledon mutant Plant Cell 1997 9 841 857 10.1105/tpc.9.6.841 <?supplied-pmid 9212461?>9212461 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>22. NuruzzamanM.ManimekalaiR.SharonA.M.SatohK.KondohH.OokaH.KikuchiS. Genome-wide analysis of NAC transcription factor family in rice Gene 2010 465 30 44 10.1016/j.gene.2010.06.008 <?supplied-pmid 20600702?>20600702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>23. TranL.S.P.NakashimaK.SakumaY.SimpsonS.D.FujitaY.MaruyamaK.FujitaM.SekiM.ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK. Isolation and functional analysis of Arabidopsis stress-inducible NAC transcription factors that bind to a drought-responsive cis-element in the early responsive to dehydration stress 1 promoter Plant Cell 2004 16 2481 2498 10.1105/tpc.104.022699 <?supplied-pmid 15319476?>15319476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>24. HeX.J.MuR.L.CaoW.H.ZhangZ.G.ZhangJ.S.ChenS.Y. AtNAC2, a transcription factor downstream of ethylene and auxin signaling pathways, is involved in salt stress response and lateral root development Plant J. 2005 44 903 916 10.1111/j.1365-313X.2005.02575.x <?supplied-pmid 16359384?>16359384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>25. SalvadorA.CuquerellaJ.Martínez-JávegaJ.M.MonterdeA.NavarroP. 1-MCP preserves the firmness of stored persimmon “Rojo Brillante” J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Food Sci. 2004 69 69 73  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>26. HribarJ.ZavrtanikM.SimčičM.VidrihR. Changes during storing and astringency removal of persimmon fruit (Diospyros Kaki L.) Acta Aliment. 2000 29 123 136 10.1556/AAlim.29.2000.2.3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>27. OokaH.SatohK.DoiK.NagataT.OtomoY.MurakamiK.MatsubaraK.OsatoN.KawaiJ.CarninciP. Comprehensive analysis of NAC family genes in Oryza sativa and Arabidopsis thaliana DNA Res. 2003 10 239 247 10.1093/dnares/10.6.239 <?supplied-pmid 15029955?>15029955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>28. GuoY.F.GanS.S. AtNAP, a NAC family transcription factor, has an important role in leaf senescence Plant J. 2006 46 601 612 10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02723.x <?supplied-pmid 16640597?>16640597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>29. ClercqI.D.VermeirssenV.van AkenO.VandepoeleK.MurchaM.W.LawS.R.InzéA.NgS.IvanovaA.RombautD. The membrane-bound NAC transcription factor ANAC013 functions in mitochondrial retrograde regulation of the oxidative stress response in Arabidopsis. Plant Cell 2013 25 3472 3490 10.1105/tpc.113.117168 <?supplied-pmid 24045019?>24045019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>30. GuoY.CaiZ.GanS. Transcriptome of Arabidopsis leaf senescence Plant Cell Environ. 2004 27 521 549 10.1111/j.1365-3040.2003.01158.x  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>31. ShanW.KuangJ.F.ChenL.XieH.PengH.H.XiaoY.Y.LiX.P.ChenW.X.HeQ.G.ChenJ.Y. Molecular characterization of banana NAC transcription factors and their interactions with ethylene signalling component EIL during fruit ripening J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Bot. 2012 63 5171 5187 10.1093/jxb/ers178 <?supplied-pmid 22888129?>22888129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>32. KouX.H.WatkinsC.B.GanS.-S. Arabidopsis AtNAP regulates fruit senescence J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Bot. 2012 63 6139 6147 10.1093/jxb/ers266 <?supplied-pmid 23066145?>23066145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>33. HuQ.LuoC.ZhangQ.L.LuoZ.R. Isolation and characterization of a laccase gene potentially involved in proanthocyanidin polymerization in oriental persimmon (Diospyros kaki Thunb.) fruit Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Rep. 2013 40 2809 2820 10.1007/s11033-012-2296-2 <?supplied-pmid 23224657?>23224657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>34. ThompsonJ.D.GibsonT.J.PlewniakF.JeanmouginF.HigginsD.G. The ClustalX windows interface: Flexible strategies for multiple sequence alignment aided by quality analysis tools Nucleic Acids Res. 1997 24 4876 4882 10.1093/nar/25.24.4876 9396791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35-ijms-16-01894"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>35. YinX.R.ChenK.S.AllanA.C.WuR.M.ZhangB.LalluN.FergusonI.B. Ethylene-induced modulation of genes associated with the ethylene signalling pathway in ripening kiwifruit J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Bot. 2008 59 2097 2108 10.1093/jxb/ern067 <?supplied-pmid 18535296?>18535296 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
