
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4229192</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25389780</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-24337</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Proteins</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Structure</subject><subj-group><subject>Protein Folding</subject><subject>Protein Misfolding</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Macromolecular Structure Analysis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Comparative Analysis of Human γD-Crystallin Aggregation under Physiological and Low pH Conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Aggregation Behavior of Human γD-Crystallin at pH 2.0 and 7.0</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Josephine W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Mei-Er</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Wen-Sing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Wei-An</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Chien-Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Chih-Kai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>Chun-Hsien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Hwai-Shen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Steven S.-S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Optometry, Central Taiwan University of Science and Technology, Taichung 40601, Taiwan</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Entomology, National Chung Hsing University, Taichung 402, Taiwan</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Chemical Engineering, National Taiwan University, Taipei 10617, Taiwan</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>Rizwan H.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Aligarh Muslim University, India</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>107658@ctust.edu.tw</email> (JWW); <email>sswang@ntu.edu.tw</email> (SSW)</corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: JWW SSW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: MEC WSW WAC CTL CKC CHL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: JWW WSW CKC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: HSL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Contributed to the writing of the manuscript: JWW SSW. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e112309</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Wu et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wu et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Cataract, a major cause of visual impairment worldwide, is the opacification of the eye’s crystalline lens due to aggregation of the crystallin proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>The research reported here is aimed at investigating the aggregating behavior of γ-crystallin proteins in various incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Thioflavin T binding assay, circular dichroism spectroscopy, 1-anilinonaphthalene-8-sulfonic acid fluorescence spectroscopy, intrinsic (tryptophan) fluorescence spectroscopy, light scattering, and electron microscopy were used for structural characterization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Molecular dynamics simulations and bioinformatics prediction were performed to gain insights into the γD-crystallin mechanisms of fibrillogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>We first demonstrated that, except at pH 7.0 and 37°C, the aggregation of γD-crystallin was observed to be augmented upon incubation, as revealed by turbidity measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Next, the types of aggregates (fibrillar or non-fibrillar aggregates) formed under different incubation conditions were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>We found that, while a variety of non-fibrillar, granular species were detected in the sample incubated under pH 7.0, the fibrillogenesis of human γD-crystallin could be induced by acidic pH (pH 2.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In addition, circular dichroism spectroscopy, 1-anilinonaphthalene-8-sulfonic acid fluorescence spectroscopy, and intrinsic fluorescence spectroscopy were used to characterize the structural and conformational features in different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Our results suggested that incubation under acidic condition led to a considerable change in the secondary structure and an enhancement in solvent-exposure of the hydrophobic regions of human γD-crystallin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Finally, molecular dynamics simulations and bioinformatics prediction were performed to better explain the differences between the structures and/or conformations of the human γD-crystallin samples and to reveal potential key protein region involved in the varied aggregation behavior. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics analyses revealed that the initiation of amyloid formation of human γD-crystallin may be associated with a region within the C-terminal domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>We believe the results from this research may contribute to a better understanding of the possible mechanisms underlying the pathogenesis of senile nuclear cataract. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the grants from the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan (MOST 102-2221-E-002-161 and MOST 103-2221-E-002-208 to SSW, and NSC 101-2113-M-166-001-MY2 and MOST 103-2113-M-166-001-MY2 to JWW). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="17"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>It is widely accepted that aggregation is a universal phenomenon that can occur to proteins of all types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Protein aggregation arises from a common mechanism whereby the normally folded proteins change conformation and results in partially unfolded intermediates that eventually aggregate by auto assembly to form either amorphous and/or fibril species [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Not only is protein aggregation a major problem in biotechnology products relating to protein expression, purification, and storage [3], it is also responsible for more than 40 human protein-deposition diseases that have been well documented to this day [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Among these so called protein conformational diseases is cataract, a major cause of visual impairment worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Based on the World Health Organization (2011), cataract makes up 33% of global visual impairment (next to uncorrected refractive errors at 43%) and is the leading cause of blindness in middle and low-income countries [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Cataract is the opacification of the eye’s crystalline lens due to aggregation and precipitation of the crystallin proteins [6], [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In the normal eye, the lens is a transparent refractive structure that serves to focus light onto the retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>It is capable of retaining transparency owing to a high concentration of crystallins that are arranged into short-range order. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>The absence of cellular organelles in the mature lens fiber cells also helps to minimize light scatter [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Additional contribution to lens transparency is provided by the unique structural and functional properties of the crystallins themselves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>There are three types of crystallins in the mammalian lens: α-, β-, and γ- crystallins. α-Crystallin is a heat shock protein that function as a molecular chaperone to prevent other proteins from aggregating and insolubilizing under stressful conditions [9], [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>To stay true to its chaperone function, the protein has adopted high conformational flexibility and structural disorder to accommodate its interactions with target proteins, which includes the β- and γ- crystallins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Both β &amp; γ-crystallins belong to the same superfamily and are considered structural proteins that, when maintained in their native globular state and arranged in densely-packed fashion, are responsible for preserving clarity of the crystalline lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>As the eye lens ages, structures of the crystallin proteins begin to change due to a variety of environmental factors, hence disrupting the orderly arrangements of protein packing that kept the lens in its transparent state. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Several theories on the mechanisms of cataract formation at the molecular level have been put forth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>As the lens ages, crystallins are subjected to environmental insults that result in structural modifications or damages, leading to incorrect interactions, unfolding, oligomerization, and aggregation of proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Processes that can occur in the aging lens and have detrimental effects on the native structures of lens proteins include photooxidation (by UV radiation), deamidation, disulfide bond formation, and cleavage [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Oxidative damage is the process whereby reactive oxygen species are coupled with photooxidation and/or conversion of sulfhydryl groups to form half-cystine disulfide groups [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>It has been found to be a major contributor to cataract formation in aged lens in which the level of glutathione is significantly reduced [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Another common process that causes damages to the crystallins is deamidation, where negative charge is introduced at the site of glutamine and asparagine causing the proteins to form cataractous aggregates [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Protease cleavage of crystallins that involves calpains has also been observed to be associated with senile nuclear cataract [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>The consequence of the above-mentioned mechanisms of cataractogenesis is the disruption of the orderly arrangement within the crystalline fiber cells and the development of opacity in the once transparent lens structure, hence cataract. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Of the crystallin proteins, γ-crystallin has the simplest structure, existing as a monomer of four Greek key motifs rich in anti-parallel β-sheets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The molecular weight of the protein is approximately 20 kDa (173 amino acids), with a fold akin to many immunoglobulins [16], [17]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Human gamma D-crystallin (HγD-crys) is the third most commonly expressed γ-crystallin in the human lens [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>It is highly stable at neutral pH, but like many proteins, can form aggregation under certain conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Although the main form of aggregates found in the cataractous lens is of the amorphous type, HγD-crys has recently been observed to form amyloid fibrils as well. In vitro aggregation of HγD-crys has been noted in guanidine hydrochloride (GdnHCl) under physiological temperature and pH [17], as well as under acidic pH [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Low pH condition, without the presence of denaturant, leads to partially or fully unfolded species that form amyloid fibrils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>These fibril aggregates have previously been characterized by various biophysical methods (e.g., Congo red, FTIR, X-ray diffraction, TEM, and 2D-IR) [10], [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>In any case, both full protein and (to a lesser extent) isolated C-terminal and N-terminal domains of HγD-crys are capable of forming amyloid fibrils under acidic pH condition [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The above-mentioned findings are proofs of concept demonstrating that despite high structural stability, HγD-crys (like many other proteins) also has the potential to reorganize and form amyloid structure in destabilizing conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it has been suggested that this pathway may be an additional process contributing to the development of cataract with aging [10]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Of the various hypotheses that have been proposed on the mechanisms behind the development of age-related cataract, one that has not been fully explored is the possibility of low pH-induced cataract. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Currently, two views exist in regards to acidic pH and cataractogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>One involves the possibility of partially degraded HγD-crys forming fibrillar aggregates in the low pH environment of lysozomal compartment during lens fiber cell differentiation, which may be involved in the early stages of cataract formation [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Another hypothesis has to do with the decreased pH in the lens nucleus overtime leading to loss of α-crystallin chaperone capability to protect HγD-crys from aggregation, thus resulting in senile nuclear cataract formation [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Regardless of the mechanisms of cataract formation, the only accepted form of treatment currently available is the surgical removal of the opaque lens and replacement with an artificial lens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>However, such procedure is not without risks of complications and is often inaccessible in low and middle-income countries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in order to seek for other potential therapeutic strategies to treating cataract, a more thorough understanding of the crystallin aggregation process leading to cataractogenesis is imperative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The current study is aimed at a more extensive investigation into HγD-crys aggregation in neutral and low pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We first demonstrated that, except at physiological condition of pH 7.0 and 37°C, the aggregation of HγD-crys was observed to be augmented upon incubation, as revealed by turbidity measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Next, the types of aggregates (fibrillar or non-fibrillar aggregates) formed under different incubation conditions were identified using ThT fluorescence spectroscopy and transmission electron microscopy (TEM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>We found that HγD-crys can be induced to form amyloid fibrillar species at acidic pH but not neutral pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In addition, a number of spectroscopic techniques including far-UV circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy, 1-anilinonaphthalene-8-sulfonic acid (ANS) fluorescence spectroscopy, and intrinsic or tryptophan fluorescence spectroscopy, were used to characterize the structural and conformational features in different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Finally, molecular dynamics (MD) simulations were performed to gain some insights into the molecular mechanism of the initial stage in the process of HγD-crys fibril formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Not only does our work compare HγD-crys aggregation under different pH and temperature conditions, it is also the first to fully characterize its fibrillogenesis under low pH setting and brings all past studies of its kind into perspective. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Salts, tryptone, yeast extract, and chromatography columns were purchased from Sigma (USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Kanamycin, imidazole, and isopropyl β-D-thiolgalactorpyranoside (IPTG) were obtained from Biobasic (Canada). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>EZ Ni-agarose 6 resin was obtained from Lamda Biotech (USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>All other chemicals were of reagent grade and obtained from Sigma (USA) unless otherwise specified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Expression and purification of HγD-crys protein </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Bacterial expression and purification of the recombinant proteins has been described previously [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The plasmid pQE1 containing the 6×His-tagged HγD-crys gene was provided by Dr. Jonathan King’s laboratory at Massachusetts Institute of Technology [23], [24] and was transformed into E. coli strain BL21 (DE3) using the heat shock method with high transformation efficiency. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>The 6×His-HγD-crys gene fragment from plasmid pQE1 was amplified by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using primers that introduced NdeI and BamHI restriction sites (forward primer, 5′-GAGGAGAAATTAACATATGAAACATCACCATCA-3′; reverse primer, 5′-GCTTTGTTAGCAGCCGGATCCAAATTAAGAA-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>The PCR procedure comprised a denaturation step at 94°C for 5 min, followed by 15 cycles of denaturation at 94°C for 1 min, annealing at 55°C for 40 sec, and extension at 72°C for 90 sec. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The PCR products and pET30b(+) were digested with restriction enzymes (NdeI and BamHI) and purified by electrophoresis through a 1.3% agarose gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The resultant purified PCR products were ligated to the resultant digested plasmid pET30b(+) in a reaction containing 2 µL of T4 ligase, 2 µL of 10 mM ATP, and 10 µL of 2X T4 ligase reaction buffer, resulting in the generation of pEHisHγD-crys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The resultant pEHisHγD-crys, transformed into the E. coli strain BL21 (DE3) using the heat shock method, procured a high transformation efficiency and was used to express the 6×His-HγD-crys protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>In a typical experiment, a single colony of E. coli strain BL21 (DE3) harboring plasmid pEHisHγD-crys was inoculated in 50 mL LB medium (10% tryptone, 5% yeast extract, 10% NaCl) containing the appropriate antibiotic (kanamycin 30 µg/mL) and grown with shaking at 200 rpm at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>1 mL overnight cultures were used to inoculate 100 mL of fresh LB medium, and these cultures were grown at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>After reaching an optimal OD600 nm, bacterial cultures were induced at 30°C by the addition of IPTG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Cell lysis was performed by ultrasonication (1 s of plus-on and 1 s plus-off for 30 min) and the insoluble material was removed by centrifugation (13000 rpm for 30 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The supernatant (the soluble part) was collected and passed through a Supelco liquid chromatography column (Sigma-Aldrich, USA) and EZ Ni-agarose 6 resin (Lamda Biotech, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>The purified recombinant protein solution was dialyzed against salt solution (136.7 mM NaCl, 2.68 mM KCl, 0.01% (w/v) sodium azide, pH 7.0) and the resultant 6×His-HγD-crys stock solution was stored at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Preparation of HγD-crys sample solutions and determination of protein concentration </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For the sake of comparison with previous studies on HγD-crys aggregation associated with cataract formation done by our group and others [10], [25], 1 mg/mL HγD-crys protein concentration was chosen for the aggregation experiments under various pH and temperature conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>The sample solutions were prepared by diluting the stock solutions with salt solution (136.7 mM NaCl, 2.68 mM KCl, 0.01% (w/v) sodium azide, pH 7.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The protein concentrations of HγD-crys sample solutions were determined by the bicinchoninic acid assay (BCA) using bovine serum albumin (BSA) as a standard [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Turbidity measurement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Turbidity measurements of samples were performed by monitoring the absorbance at 360 nm [27], [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>1 mL of HγD-crys samples (1 mg/mL) taken at different times were added to a 1 cm light-path quartz cuvette. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>The analyses were carried out using a Cary Eclipse UV/VIS spectrophotometer (Varian, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Three measurements were performed, and the mean and standard deviation were obtained. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Thioflavin T (ThT) fluorescence measurement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>The stock solution of ThT at a concentration of 20 mM was prepared in ethanol protected from light prior to use, and the concentration was determined spectrophotometrically using the molar extinction coefficient at 416 nm of 26600 M−1 cm−1 [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Phosphate buffered saline (PBS) with 0.01% (w/v) sodium azide was used to dissolve ThT to a final concentration of 20 µM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>40 µL of protein samples taken at different times were added to 960 µL of ThT solution (20 µM) and briefly mixed with vortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The ThT fluorescence emission intensity at 485 nm of the resultant mixture was recorded for 60 sec using the excitation wavelength of 440 nm on a Cary Eclipse Fluorescence Spectrophotometer (Varian, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>An aliquot of 5 µL of HγD-crys samples for TEM analysis were withdrawn from the working solutions and applied on a carbon-stabilized, formvar coated grid for 30 sec. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Excess samples were removed by applying ashless filter papers at the edge of the grids and the grids were negatively stained with 1% uranyl acetate in distilled de-ionized water (Electron Microscopy Sciences, USA) for another 30 sec. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>After removing the excess stain, the grids were left to air-dry for at least 30 min and then examined and photographed on a Hitachi H-7650 transmission electron microscope with a Gantan model 782 CCD Camera (Tokyo, Japan) at an accelerating voltage of 100 kV. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Far-UV circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>The secondary structural changes of HγD-crys sample solutions were evaluated by far-UV CD spectroscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>CD spectra of HγD-crys samples (0.1 mg/mL) were recorded after diluting 10-fold with de-ionized water over the wavelength range of 190–260 nm using a J-815 spectrometer (JASCO, Japan) with a 0.2 cm path length sample cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>All CD measurements were collected at room temperature using a bandwidth of 1.0 nm, a step interval of 0.1 nm, and a scanning speed of 50 nm/min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Each CD spectrum was the average of three scans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The secondary structure contents of HγD-crys samples were estimated using the CDSSTR algorithm with appropriate reference sets available from the DICROWEB website [30], [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Control buffer scans were run in duplicate, averaged, and then subtracted from the sample spectra. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The results have been plotted as ellipticity (mdeg) versus wavelength (nm). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>1-Anilinonaphthalene-8-sulfonic acid (ANS) fluorescence spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>100 µL HγD-crys sample solutions were mixed with 900 µL ANS working solution of 20 µM in PBS solution, and then the mixtures were incubated in the dark for 30 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>ANS fluorescence intensities were recorded by exciting samples at 380 nm and emissions were recorded between 420 and 580 nm on a Cary Eclipse fluorescence spectrophotometer (Varian, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>All measurements were repeated at least three times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>The representative ANS fluorescence intensity was taken at the average emission wavelength (AEW), which accounts for both changes in intensity and spectrum envelop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The determination of AEW was carried out using the following equation:where F i is the ANS fluorescence emission intensity at wavelength λ i. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Intrinsic or tryptophan fluorescence spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Intrinsic or tryptophan fluorescence intensities of HγD-crys sample solutions at 0.1 mg/mL were recorded with a Cary Eclipse fluorescence spectrophotometer (Varian, USA) using a quartz cuvette with a path length of 1 cm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The spectra between 300 and 400 nm were recorded upon exciting the samples at 280 nm (for intrinsic fluorescence) or 295 nm (for tryptophan fluorescence). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The excitation and emission slits were both set to 5 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Thermally induced equilibrium denaturation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of HγD-crys’s thermal stability was accomplished by heating HγD-crys samples under different conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The thermally induced unfolding transition of the protein samples (0.1 mg/mL) was determined by monitoring the changes in intrinsic fluorescence emission over the range of 15–100°C with a heating rate of 1°C/min and an equilibrium time of 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Intrinsic fluorescence spectra were recorded every 2°C between 300 and 420 nm at the excitation wavelength of 280 nm on a Cary Eclipse fluorescence spectrophotometer (Varian, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Given that AEW is more sensitive than total fluorescence intensity in characterizing the structural change of local environment [32], the average emission wavelength (AEW) instead of the total fluorescence intensity of HγD-crys intrinsic fluorescence spectra was used as the key variable. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2k"><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Dynamic light scattering (DLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>DLS experiments were used to characterize the size distribution of HγD-crys samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>HγD-crys samples were poured into small-volume (4 mL) disposable cuvettes with a 1 cm light path. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>DLS measurements were carried out using a Zetasizer Nano-ZS (Malvern Instruments, U.K.) with the appropriate settings of viscosity and refractive index at 0.89 centipoises and 1.59, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Samples were illuminated with a laser at the wavelength of 633 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The DLS intensities of samples at a 173° scattering angle in kilo counts per second were collected for 20 runs with 20-s duration each run and then averaged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The collected data were analyzed to obtain the size distributions using the Non-negative Least Squares (NNLS) method. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2l"><title><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatics prediction of potential protein-protein interaction sites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>The Protein–Protein Interface Prediction (PPIPRED) server (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bmbpcu36.leeds.ac.uk/ppi_pred/">http://bmbpcu36.leeds.ac.uk/ppi_pred/</ext-link>) [33] was used to predict the potential protein-protein interaction sites on the HγD-crys structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The application uses support vector machine to train datasets of proteins with known binding sites, then cross reference the results with surface patch analysis to predict protein-protein binding sites base on criteria, such as surface topography, sequence conservation, electrostatic potential, hydrophobicity, residue interface propensity, solvent accessible surface area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>PPIPRED scores potential interaction sites on three levels: the most probable interaction sites (highlighted in red), the next most likely sites (in yellow) and the third most likely sites (in green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>With over 60 citations, its performance measure has been tested on large number of datasets throughout the years. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2m"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations and analyses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>3D coordinate file of HγD-crys (PDB code: 1HK0) was used as a starting structure for the MD simulation runs performed with GROMACS v. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>4.5.3 software [34], [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Simulations were carried out under the isothermal-isobaric (NPT) ensemble with a set pressure of 1 bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Particle Mesh Ewald (PME) method was used to account for long-range electrostatic interactions [36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Radius cutoff of 1.4 nm was used for Lennard-Jones interactions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Bond lengths were constrained with the LINCS algorithm [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Each protein was solvated in a 7 nm×7 nm×7 nm cubic box with spc model under periodic boundary conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>HγD-crys in pH 2 condition has a total charge of +1, while neutrally charged in pH 7; each system was neutralized by replacing water molecules with sodium counterions that simulated the experimental setting (see under Preparation of HγD-crys sample solutions and determination of protein concentration for detail). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Simulations were performed using GROMOS energy function (GROMOS 96 45a3 force field) with 2 fs time steps [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>At least eight separate simulation runs of 150 ns each were obtained through 75 million simulation steps. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>HγD-crys in pH 7 and pH 2 were simulated under various temperature settings ranging from 310 K∼425 K with a total simulation time of more than 1 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Simulations under various temperature settings were performed to get a general picture of the trend in the protein structural changes and to find the optimal temperature condition in which molecular insights can be gained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>As the overall character and order of events in protein unfolding process are known to be conserved across temperatures [39], we mainly present the results obtained from the 343 K trajectory as it is the temperature that is closest to the experimental condition used (55°C) and allows for detailed observable conformational changes in the time scale used in our study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Graphical visualization was performed with Discovery Studio 3.5 visualizer (Accelrys Inc., San Diego, CA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Analyses of backbone root-mean-square deviation (RMSD) and secondary structure based on DSSP were performed for all trajectories to examine the conformational changes that occur between the different pH settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Structures averaged throughout simulation time was calculated in reference to the initial structure in RMSD, while secondary structure was monitored according to the criteria of Kabsch and Sander [40]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2n"><title><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>All data are expressed as means ± standard deviations (S.D.) of n independent determinations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>If Xi refers to the individual data points, M is the mean, then standard deviation (SD) can be calculated by the following formula: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The standard deviations, which describe the typical average difference between the data points and their mean, were used as the error bars shown in the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Specific n values (n≥5) are reported in the figure legends. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>The significance of the results was determined with one tailed Student’s t-test assuming unequal variances given n independent measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Unless otherwise noted, significance was determined as p&lt;0.01. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>The statistical analyses were conducted using Excel or KaleidaGraph software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Effects of incubation temperature and pH on the aggregation of HγD-crys as revealed by turbidity measurement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The extent of HγD-crys aggregation as a function of incubation time at various pH and temperatures was evaluated by measuring the turbidity of HγD-crys samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate in Figure 1 that HγD-crys sample showed no significant change in the absorbance at 360 nm under the physiological condition (37°C, neutral pH) spanning over 2 days, suggesting that aggregated species were not produced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>However, when the incubation pH dropped (from 7.0 to 2.0) or temperature elevated (from 37°C to 55°C), the turbidity of HγD-crys samples dramatically increased with prolonging incubation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>For example, at the onset of incubation, the absorbance at 360 nm of 1 mg/mL HγD-crys was found to be ∼0.047, ∼0.048, or ∼0.041 at pH 7.0 and 55°C, pH 2.0 and 37°C, or pH 2.0 and 55°C, respectively, whereas the absorbance was raised to ∼0.075, ∼0.084, or ∼0.087 at pH 7.0 and 55°C, pH 2.0 and 37°C, or pH 2.0 and 55°C, respectively, after incubation for 48 hr (see Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Our findings suggest that, when the incubation temperature increases and/or pH drops from the physiological condition (pH 7.0 and 37°C), prolonged incubation leads to HγD-crys aggregation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Turbidity measurement of the human γD-crystallin (HγD-crys) samples measured as a function of incubation time. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Samples of HγD-crys at 1 mg/mL (45 µM) were incubated in different conditions (temperature = 37 or 55°C; pH = 2.0 or 7.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The turbidity of the samples was evaluated by monitoring the absorbance of the sample solutions at the wavelength of 360 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>After 2 days of incubation, aggregates were formed in all samples except for the ones under pH 7.0 and 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The means ± standard deviations (S.D.) of at least 5 independent measurements (n≥5) are presented in the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>The error bars used in the figure are the standard deviations of the data obtained from all independent measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The values of standard deviations were calculated by the formula listed in the Statistical Analysis of Materials and Methods section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Effects of incubation temperature and pH on the formation of HγD-crys amyloid fibrils as revealed by ThT fluorescence spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Our turbidity results clearly showed the formation of HγD-crys aggregates at acidic pH and/or high temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>To further explore if the aggregated species are of the unordered amorphous aggregates or ordered amyloid fibril type, we monitored the changes of ThT fluorescence emissions of HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>ThT, a standard fluorescent dye that exhibits an increase in fluorescence intensity upon binding to amyloid structures, was introduced as a molecular probe to detect the formation of amyloid fibrils. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>While the exact mode of binding is not completely clear, ThT is believed to bind to the grooves formed on the surface of amyloid fibrils by aligned rows of side chains [41]. Figure 2 depicts the time evolved ThT fluorescence intensity of HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>As shown in the figure, all HγD-crys samples exhibited comparable fluorescence intensity at the onset of incubation (t = 0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>It is evident that the ThT fluorescence emission intensity of HγD-crys sample at pH 2.0 significantly increased in 10 min and reached a plateau thereafter, thus indicating the presence of amyloid structure when HγD-crys was incubated under the condition of pH 2.0 and 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>A similar trend in the profile of ThT fluorescence emission versus incubation period was observed in the samples upon incubation at a higher temperature 55°C, although with a faster growth rate during the initial incubation period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, regardless of the incubation temperature used, almost no increase in ThT fluorescence signal was noted at pH 7.0 as well as for the dissolving solvent alone under the assay conditions (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate that the observed elevation in emitted ThT fluorescence is associated with acidic conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>In addition, HγD-crys sample incubated at pH 2.0 and 55°C displayed the highest ThT fluorescence emission intensity among all groups tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Assuming that increased ThT fluorescence is correlated with the formation of amyloid fibril, our ThT fluorescence results would strongly suggest that low pH induces fibrillogenesis of HγD-crys. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>ThT fluorescence emission intensity measurement of HγD-crys sample measured as a function of incubation time. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Samples of HγD-crys at 1 mg/mL (45 µM) were incubated in different conditions (temperature = 37 or 55°C; pH = 2.0 or 7.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Regardless of temperature, the ThT fluorescence emission intensity was observed to increase for the samples incubated in pH 2.0, but remained the same for the ones in pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>Data points are presented as the means ± standard deviations (S.D.) of at least 5 independent measurements (n≥5) in the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>The error bars shown in the figure are the standard deviations of the data obtained from all independent measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>The values of standard deviations were calculated by the formula listed in the Statistical Analysis of Materials and Methods section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g002"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Morphological characterization of HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions as revealed by transmission electron microscopy (TEM) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Our preceding results suggest that the ThT fluorescence emission of HγD-crys sample under pH 2.0 was markedly increased, which is a positive indication of amyloid fibrillogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Given that a number of factors have been reported to interfere with ThT fluorescence [42], it would be reckless to conclude that HγD-crys has a bona fide amyloid fibril-forming ability in acidic condition soley based on the observed ThT fluorescence enhancement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Therefore, transmission electron microscopy (TEM) was performed to provide further supporting evidence for the acid-induced HγD-crys fibrillogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Presented in Figure 3 are representative micrographs of HγD-crys samples at pH 2.0/37°C, pH 2.0/55°C, pH 7.0/37°C, and pH 7.0/55°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>It is evident that, after 1 hr-incubation at pH 2.0 and 37°C, HγD-crys sample showed the morphological features of typical un-branched amyloid fibrils with approximately 10 nm in diameter and several µm in length, as seen in Figure 3A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>In addition, TEM visualization of the HγD-crys sample taken from the pH 2.0 and 55°C condition revealed that a greater amount of fibrillar species was observed relative to that obtained at pH 2.0 and 37°C (see Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In contrast, while a variety of granular species (∼25–50 nm in diameter) appeared in the sample incubated at higher temperature of 55°C and pH 7.0, no fibrillar species were detected in the samples of HγD-crys incubated under neutral pH (shown in Figures 3C and 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the TEM analysis reproducibly demonstrates a positive connection between the ThT fluorescence emission results and the amount of fibrils observed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Representative negative staining transmission electron micrographs (TEM) of HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>(A) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0, 37°C for 1 hr; (B) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0, 55°C for 1 hr; (C) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0, 37°C for 1 hr; and (D) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0, 55°C for 1 hr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Aggregation formed under pH 2.0 conditions resembles fibril morphology, while retaining granular appearance under pH 7.0 conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>The scale bar represents 100 nm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Effects of incubation temperature and pH on the tertiary structure of HγD-crys samples as revealed by ANS fluorescence spectroscopy and tryptophan/intrinsic fluorescence spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>To gain insights into the effects of incubation temperature and pH on the conformational changes of HγD-crys, ANS and tryptophan/intrinsic fluorescence spectra of HγD-crys were also recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>We recorded the time evolution of ANS fluorescence emission at the average emission wavelength upon excitation at 380 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The hydrophobic fluorescent dye, ANS, has been commonly utilized to demonstrate the presence of partially folded conformations of globular proteins and probe for structural properties and solvent exposure of the hydrophobic surfaces [43]–[45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The preferential binding of ANS to hydrophobic clusters gives rise to an enhancement in fluorescence emission accompanying a blue shift of the spectral maximum or average emission wavelength [43], [44], [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We show in Figures 4A and 4B that, under the condition of pH 7.0 (37 or 55°C), both average emission wavelength (AEW) and ANS fluorescence intensity remained almost unchanged during the 2 days of incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, as seen in Figure 4B, the ANS fluorescence intensities at the average emission wavelength (or surface hydrophobicity) of HγD-crys samples were remarkably low, signifying that protein hydrophobic sites are hidden inside the compactly folded protein structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>However, incubating HγD-crys at pH 2.0 led to a drastic blue-shift in the average emission wavelength (AEW) and a pronounced enhancement in ANS fluorescence emission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>These changes suggest that more hydrophobic regions were solvent-exposed in HγD-crys under the acidic conditions, probably due to conformational changes in the protein leading to a partial loss of tertiary structure. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>ANS fluorescence intensity measurement of HγD-crys samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Surface hydrophobicity of HγD-crys samples were monitored by (A) Average emission wavelength (AEW) of HγD-crys sample as a function of incubation time and (B) ANS fluorescence emission intensity of HγD-crys sample as a function of incubation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Samples were incubated under temperatures of 37 and 55°C; pH settings of 2.0 and 7.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Incubation under pH 2.0 settings resulted in a blue-shift in AEW and an increase in ANS fluorescence emission not detected in samples under pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Data points are presented as the means ± standard deviations (S.D.) of at least 5 independent measurements (n≥5) in the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>The error bars used in the figure are the standard deviations of the data obtained from all independent measurements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>The values of standard deviations were calculated by the formula listed in the Statistical Analysis of Materials and Methods section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Tryptophan fluorescence of protein, mainly due to high sensitivity of tryptophan to changes in its microenvironment, can be measured when samples are excited at 295 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>This method has been widely employed in studies involving ligand binding, folding-unfolding, and protein conformational changes [47]–[49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>To further gain insights into the differences in conformation of HγD-crys incubated under various conditions, the intrinsic fluorescence spectra of samples (measured under excitation wavelength of 280 nm) were also recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>We show in Figure 5A that there was almost no change in the tryptophan fluorescence spectra of the HγD-crys samples incubated under neutral pH and 37°C condition for 2 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>However, for samples under the same pH condition but incubation at 55°C (Figure 5C), a noticeable increase in the fluorescence emission and wavelengths of emission maximum were observed after 1 day of incubation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>As for the samples incubated in pH 2 conditions (Figures 5B and 5D), a much greater increase in the maximum tryptophan fluorescence intensity was observed in comparison to the samples incubated in neutral pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>This change occurred as early as 30 minutes into the incubation time regardless of temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>It is interesting to note that under pH 2 and 55°C, the peak intensity begins to diminish slightly with longer incubation time past 30 minutes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>We speculate that this phenomenon may be due to the rapid formation of larger aggregates in this high temperature that eventually precipitated out of the solution phase, thereby reducing the amount of samples that could be measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>In addition to a pronounced increase in fluorescence emission, prolonged incubation at pH 2.0 led to a considerable red-shift in the wavelengths of emission maximum (λmax) (i.e., λmax was found to increase from ∼328 nm at 0 hr to ∼349 nm at 2 day). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>This clearly indicates an extensive exposure of tryptophan residues to solvent upon incubation under the acidic condition [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>Likewise, our HγD-crys samples excited at 280 nm revealed similar trends in the fluorescence spectra (shown in Figure S1A–D) as the ones obtained from tryptophan fluorescence spectroscopy with excitation wavelength at 295 nm (shown in Figure 5A–D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Tryptophan fluorescence intensity measurement of HγD-crys samples (0.1 mg/mL) under different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>(A) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0, 37°C; (B) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0, 37°C; (C) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0, 55°C; and (D) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0, 55°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence spectra between 300 and 400 nm were recorded upon exciting the samples at 295 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Incubation under pH 2.0 settings resulted in a rapid and greater increase in fluorescence emission, as well as a more noticeable red-shift in the wavelengths of emission maximum than those of the samples under pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g005"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>From our ANS fluorescence and intrinsic/tryptophan fluorescence findings, we can conclude that tryptophans and, in general, hydrophobic regions are greatly solvent-exposed in the HγD-crys samples incubated at pH 2.0, clearly demonstrating that the conformation (or tertiary structure) of native HγD-crys was markedly affected by the decrease in pH [51]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>Effects of incubation temperature and pH on the secondary structure of HγD-crys samples as revealed by circular dichroism (CD) spectroscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>To further understand the role that incubation temperature and pH play in the secondary structural changes of HγD-crys, the far-UV circular dichroism spectra of HγD-crys samples under different conditions were monitored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>At the beginning of incubation time, native HγD-crys sample shows a predominance of β-sheet secondary structure as manifested by the far-UV CD spectrum (shown in Figures 6A and 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>The absorption minimum is at ∼218 nm and the overall profile is in agreement with previous published results [52], [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Regardless of incubation period (0–2 day) and temperature, a negligible difference in the CD spectra of HγD-crys samples was perceived in pH 7.0 (Figure 6A) indicating that changes in secondary structure were insignificant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>However, we show in Figure 6B that, when the incubation pH dropped to 2.0, HγD-crys samples exhibited a structural transition, resulting in a prominent alteration in the relative secondary structural proportions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Regardless of the incubation temperature used, the far-UV CD spectra at pH 2.0 displayed a substantially different shape in which a shift in absorption minimum from ∼218 nm to ∼207 nm was observed along with a pronounced increase in signal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>From 2 hr of incubation and on, the intensity of the absorption minimum remained consistent indicating that the changes in secondary structure were insignificant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>To better quantify the structural transition, the far-UV CD spectra of all HγD-crys samples obtained at 0 and 2 hr were further de-convoluted using the software available from the DICROWEB website [30] and the results of secondary structure content of HγD-crys samples incubated at different pH values for 2 hr are listed as follows: (1) at pH 2.0: 7% α-helix, 32% β-sheet, 17% turns, and 44% unordered; (2) at pH 7.0: 4% α-helix, 43% β-sheet, 22% turns, and 31% unordered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Far-UV CD spectra of HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>(A) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0 and (B) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>The incubation temperatures used were 37 and 55°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>The incubation periods were 0, 2 hr, and 2 day. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Incubation under pH 2.0 settings resulted in a large shift in absorption minimum and an increase in signal intensity not seen in samples under pH 7. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Effects of incubation temperature and pH on the size distribution of HγD-crys samples as revealed by dynamic light scattering (DLS) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>We determined the size distribution of the HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions using dynamic light scattering (DLS) and the results are depicted in Figures S1A–S1F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate in Figure S2A and S2D that, regardless of the incubation pH used, the distribution of species with similar sizes were observed at the beginning of incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>However, under the same incubation temperature (37 or 55°C), HγD-crys samples that were subjected to the conditions of pH 2.0 and pH 7.0 displayed considerably different size distributions after two days of incubation, as shown in Figures S2B–C and S2E–F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Evidently, aggregation of HγD-crys in acidic conditions at 55°C seemed to yield a single broader population of species existing in a range of sizes between ∼10 and ∼200 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>In contrast, a bimodal distribution of population size (with peaks positioned at ∼30 nm and ∼200 nm) was detected in HγD-crys samples upon incubation at pH 7.0 and 55°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3g"><title><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Thermal denaturation behaviors of HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>To explore the effects of incubation condition (e.g., pH and temperature) on the conformational stability of HγD-crys, thermally induced equilibrium unfolding of the HγD-crys samples under different incubation conditions was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Given that the average emission wavelength (AEW) is a more sensitive probe for structural changes of local environment than the total intrinsic fluorescence, we monitored the AEW of recorded intrinsic fluorescence spectra as a function of temperature to obtain the thermal unfolding profiles/curves for the HγD-crys samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>Our spectral results revealed the temperature-induced structural unfolding of HγD-crys as demonstrated in Figure S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>The sigmoidal dependence of AEW with temperature was observed in all the HγD-crys samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Our data evidently suggested that the thermally induced denaturation/unfolding from the folded to denatured/unfolded state of HγD-crys under the condition of pH 2.0 or 7.0 can be adequately described by a simple two-state model/process with cooperative characteristics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the AEW-versus-temperature curves of HγD-crys samples indicated that the unfolding/denaturation curve shifted toward left when the incubation pH dropped from 7.0 to 2.0, suggesting that the HγD-crys sample at pH 2.0 exhibits lower thermal stability than that at pH7.0 [54]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3h"><title><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Potential mechanism of HγD-crys fibrillogenesis as revealed by molecular dynamics simulations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>HγD-crys is highly stable at neutral pH due to its unique structural arrangement consisting of two domains (N-terminal and C-terminal) each harboring two Greek key anti-parallel β-sheet motifs (shown in Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>The two structurally similar domain pairs with high internal symmetry of primary and tertiary structures are believed to have been form during the course of evolution by gene duplication and fusion [55], [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Such structural fold is highly stable and has been found repeatedly in a wide variety of β-sheet-rich proteins [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>An important contribution to the stability of the HγD-crys monomer is the hydrophobic interface between the N-terminal domain (Ntd) motif 2 and C-terminal domain (Ctd) motif 4, which has been shown to play a crucial role in holding the two domains intact [58]–[61]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>We first verify the accuracy of the PPIPRED tool by predicting the potential protein-protein interaction sites on the HγD-crys structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the previous studies [62]–[65], residues around and at the domain interface region of Ntd motif 2 and Ctd motif 4 (shown in Figure 7) were identified as the most probable sites for protein-protein interaction based on the six properties listed in the methods section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>The second most probable sites were found, for the most part, in motifs 2 and 4 (regions surrounding the interdomain interface) as well as part of Ntd motif 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The third most probable sites are located predominantly in Ctd motif 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g007</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>Potential protein-protein interaction sites predicted by PPIPRED based on surface topography, sequence conservation, electrostatical potential, hydrophobicity, residue interface propensity, and solvent accessible surface area. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>The three highest probable binding sites are color-coded red, yellow, and green. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>The regions are mapped onto the 3D-structure and residue sequence of HγD-crys. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g007"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>To gain a better understanding of the structural changes that occur at low pH and high temperature, we performed MD simulations at both low and neutral pH (pH 2.0 and 7.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Under physiological conditions (pH 7.0 and 310 K), the RMSD values remained stable at around 0.17 nm (shown in Figure 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>As for the pH 2.0 condition, the RMSD began to rise around 70 ns, reaching a plateau of about 0.33 nm at 100 ns. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Although the RMSD values increased for both pH conditions at the temperature of 343 K (shown in Figure 8B), they reached a plateau around 0.25 nm at pH 7.0 while peaking and remaining equilibrated at 0.37 nm starting from an earlier time frame ∼55 ns at pH 2.0. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>These results show that our MD simulations follow a general trend found in our experimental results, whereby HγD-crys undergoes greater conformational change at pH 2.0 than at pH 7.0, and that this change occurs more rapidly at higher temperature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g008</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Root mean square deviation (RMSD) of HγD-crys in pH 7 and 2 under (A) 310 K and (B) 343 K as a function of 150 ns simulation time. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>RMSD values of HγD-crys increased up to the ranges of 0.35∼0.40 nm for HγD-crys under pH 2 settings and remained within the ranges of 0.2∼0.3 nm under pH 7 settings. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g008"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>We, then, examined the secondary structural changes in the two different pH and temperature settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>In 310 K condition, HγD-crys under both pH settings exhibited no significant structural changes, except for some transitions from helix to turn and vice versa in certain loop regions (Figures S5A–B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>This is further evidenced when we superimposed the three dimensional structures of the HγD-crys every 10 ns to get a better picture of how the secondary structures change overall throughout the simulation time (Figures 9A and 9B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>As can be seen, the conformations under pH 7.0 condition did not deviate greatly from the original structure at the beginning of the simulation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>Although at pH 2.0, slightly more deviation from the original structure was perceived throughout the duration of the simulation, the overall predominant secondary β-structure of the Greek key motif was still retained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>The minute changes in secondary structures detected under physiological temperature for both pH settings reinforces the concept that HγD-crys has a highly stable conformation and the structure remained intact within the 150 ns of simulation time, even under low pH 2.0 setting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the results from past biophysical denaturation/unfolding study showing that γD-crys is resistant up to one week of incubation in acidic pH under physiological temperature [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>However, heating accelerates the formation of amyloid fibril, as seen in other experiments as well as ours [10], [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>We, therefore, also raised the temperature of our simulation to speed up the process of protein conformational change under the two pH settings examined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0112309-g009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0112309.g009</object-id><label>Figure 9</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Superimposed HγD-crys structures throughout 150 ns simulation time. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>Snapshots of structures in 310 K, (A) pH 7 and (B) pH 2, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>Frames are taken every 10 ns with the starting structure displayed in red and the last structure in green. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Snapshots of structures in 343 K, (C) pH 7 and (D) pH 2, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>Frames are taken every 50 ns with the starting structure displayed in red, 50 ns in yellow, 100 ns in green, and 150 ns in cyan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Structures in pH 7 and 2 under 310 K show no noticeable changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Greater structural changes are observed in 343 K, with the appearance of antiparallel β-strands spanning residues 153–160 in the last 30 ns of simulation for HγD-crys in pH 2 condition. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0112309.g009"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>When the temperature was raised to 343 K, most of the β-structure was still retained under pH 7.0 condition (see Figures S5C and 9C), but underwent greater structural deviation in pH 2.0 (see Figures S4D and 9D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>Specifically, β-structures spanning residues 43–53 began to undergo a change in conformation, in which parts of the β-strands and turn within the region became bend structure starting around 40 ns of simulation time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>In addition, the region spanning residues 144–160 (that was predominantly helical) became turns/bends and developed a region of antiparallel β-strands corresponding to residues 153–160 in the last 30 ns seconds of simulation time (depicted in Figure S5D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>This β-structure development from α-helix is clearly seen in the conformation acquired from the last nanosecond of simulation time (shown in Figure 9D, structure in cyan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Incidentally, residues spanning 155−157 within this segment were also previously identified by PPIPRED as one of the second most likely potential sites of protein-protein interaction next to the domain-domain interface that was predicted as the most probable site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>Various investigations have indicated that amyloid fibrillogenesis is a process that can occur in crystallin proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>For instance, the presence of amyloid fibrils has been noted in the interior fiber cells of normal murine lenses through the binding and/or staining of amyloidophilic dyes, Congo red and Thioflavin T [66]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>These fibrils were identified to be of γ-crystallin origin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Sandilands et al. (2002) have reported that an inherited γ-crystallin mutant caused early onset murine cataract in mice and formed inclusions containing filamentous material in the lens that displayed high Congo red binding affinity, which is indicative of the presence of amyloid fibrillar species [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>The same group also found that the purified truncated protein (a mutant of murine γB-crystallin with its fourth Greek key motif absent) exhibited amyloid fibril-forming propensity in vitro [67]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>Using the wild-type bovine α-, β-, and γ-crystallins as the models, Meehan and coworkers experimentally examined the in vitro fibrillogenic/aggregative properties of these proteins upon exposure to denaturing/destabilizing conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>They observed that the full-length bovine α- and β-crystallins assembled to form amyloid fibrils, whereas fibrils derived from bovine γ-crystallin proteins were composed of both full-length and fragmented bovine γ-crystallin proteins [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>In addition, it has been shown that mutant crystallin protein has a higher propensity for amyloid fibril formation than its wild-type counterpart [68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>Further experimental evidence originating from recent studies using individual γ-crystallins and/or their subunits has demonstrated that HγD-crys and human γC-crystallin (HγC-crys) are prone to fibrillate in the acidic environment [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>The fact that HγD-crys proteins are capable of forming amyloid fibrils both in vivo and in vitro may imply a potential role in the pathogenesis of cataract. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>Based on one theory, amyloid fibril formation of HγD-crys under acidic pH is highly relevant to the low pH lysosomal compartment of differentiating lens fiber cells where damaged HγD-crys are degraded [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Under such condition, the damaged proteins, which may have the potential of being amyloidogenic partially-unfolded intermediates, can serve as nucleating centers for fibril formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon has also been described for other proteins such as transtherytin [69]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Thus, the process initiates the early stages of cataract by disrupting the fiber cell organization causing light scatter and image degradation at the retina. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>It may take decades for this process to begin and develop into cataract on the macroscopic scale, thus in order to achieve a more thorough understanding of how HγD-crys behaves under the different aggregated states relevant to cataractogenesis, pH 2 was chosen as the setting to procure the fibril form of aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Although the physiological pH within the cell (even within the lysosomal compartment) does not go as low as pH 2, this pH was chosen because we found it to be the optimal pH condition that will promote fibrillogenesis of HγD-crys, thus allowing for a full comparison with the aggregation behavior under physiological pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>After testing out various pH settings (data not shown), we found that pH 2 procures the most favorable condition for amyloidogenesis of HγD-crys; thus, providing the basis for our subsequent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>HγD-crys with 6×His tag was purified and used in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Although there may be a concern that the fusion partner may interfere with the outcome of the experiments performed, it was previously reported that the presence of 6×His tag on recombinant HγD-crys neither affect the expression of the protein itself nor the ability of the protein to fold into the native state during the purification process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Moreover, analyses using fluorescence and circular dichroism spectroscopies revealed almost no difference in the structures between HγD-crys with and without 6×His tags [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>We also conducted experiments, in which the N-terminal 6×His tag was first removed using dipeptidyl aminopeptidase I (DAPase-I), the enzyme that was reportedly utilized to cleave His-tag from recombinant proteins [70], [71] The untagged HγD-crys was then purified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>The structural features of the resulting untagged HγD-crys and its 6×His-tagged counterpart were further compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that both the His-tagged and untagged HγD-crys gave almost identical CD spectra (data not shown) and intrinsic fluorescence spectra (data not shown), suggesting that the inclusion of 6×His tag has negligible influence on the secondary and tertiary structures of HγD-crys [22], which further supports the previous report. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Due to the highly stable nature of the Greek key motifs in HγD-crys, it may take a long time for the protein to form aggregation if left alone under physiological condition (pH 7.0 and 37°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in order to better understand and compare the differences in aggregation behaviors of HγD-crys under varied pH in a reasonable time frame, we sped up the process by thermally inducing aggregation at the temperature of 55°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>Although we could have arbitrarily picked any temperature that is higher than the physiological 37°C for our comparison, we settled on 55°C because this was the temperature that allows the extent of aggregation in HγD-crys under both pH conditions to reach similar states within the 2-day time period tested (see Figure 1), thus enabling us to perform a thorough comparison of the effects of varied environment on the structural changes/aggregation behavior of HγD-crys protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>As seen in our TEM results, elevating the incubation temperature did not alter the aggregation pathways that the proteins were predestined for in the different pH settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>Under neutral pH, HγD-crys forms granular aggregates of various sizes ranging from ∼25–50 nm with hydrophobic sites buried within the tightly packed protein structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Based on our turbidity measurements, the aggregation process is slower under neutral environment than acidic environment, again signifying the inherent stability of the native HγD-crys conformation in physiological pH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Whereas HγD-crys aggregation is of the amorphous kind in neutral pH, low pH induced amyloidosis with partially unfolded structure of increased solvent-exposed hydrophobic regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>This is reminiscent of the HγD-crys fibrous aggregates induced by guanidinium hydrochloride [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>It is known that the bulk of protein material removed from cataractus lens is in the form of amorphous aggregates [72], [73]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>This may not come as a surprise when one considers that the lowest pH of 6.5 detected in the nucleus [20], [72] is not too different from the neutral pH of 7.0 explored by our study, which also induces amorphous aggregation in HγD-crys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>While our experimental condition is an over simplified model of what’s going on in the lens, it is undeniable that the inherent aggregation property of HγD-crys under neutral pH is of the amorphous kind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>However, as previously mentioned, fibrils that may form in the lysozomal compartments of lens cortex during lens cell development and maturation may eventually move into the lens nucleus if they are not completely degraded before the lens cells mature and become devoid of their intracellular organelles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>It is possible that remnants of these fibrils in the cells become precursors that provide the seeds to initiate the formation of amorphous aggregates under close to neutral pH of the lens nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>As the line dividing amorphous and fibrous aggregation is a thin one [74], the possibility is there that one form may trigger the mass production of another when the condition is right. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>It was found previously that, in certain cases, global structural unfolding is unnecessary for the initiation of protein aggregation [75]–[77]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Simply altering the environment, thus changing the solvent exposure of certain aggregation-prone regions in the native protein, is enough to allow protein-protein interactions to commence leading to massive aggregation formation [4], [78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Thus, localized regions can serve as nucleation sites for β-amyloid formation in near native proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Although the Greek key motifs in HγD-crys are predominantly β-structures, we hypothesize that a possible reorganization of localized region(s) leads to the formation of exposed β-structures capable of initiating aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the findings of a recent study that examined the structure of acid-induced HγD-crys amyloid fibrils by two-dimensional (2D) IR spectroscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The results from the study showed that nucleation and extension of fibrils were mainly contributed by part of the protein’s Ctd [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>According to the structural model suggested by Moran et.al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>(2012), each protein molecule provides two β-strands from the Ctd to form β-sheets of the amyloid fibril core, while rest of the protein’s secondary structure assumes a disordered state of loops and coil. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>As the main structural fold of HγD-crys is in the form of four homologous Greek-key motifs comprised of antiparallel β-sheets, the native conformation is already dominated by β-structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Therefore, in the process of amyloid fibrillogenesis, localized structural reorganization may require majority of the native β-sheets to unfold and allow certain regions to reform into β-sheets characteristics of amyloid fibrils, as suggested by the IR spectroscopy study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>This is also consistent with our far-UV CD results showing an overall decrease in β-structures and increase in unordered structure in the process of HγD-crys fibril formation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Despite the fact that previous 2D IR spectroscopy study has revealed that Ctd forms β-sheets of the acid-induced HγD-crys fibril, specific region(s) within the domain involved in the fibril formation is still unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>We, therefore, performed bioinformatic prediction and MD simulations to give us further insights into this matter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>From the results obtained through our computational approaches, we speculate that a region in Ctd motif 4 corresponding to residues 153−160, which forms anti-parallel β-strands during our simulation under low pH setting, may play an important role in the initiation of amyloid fibril formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Further analysis is warranted to understand how it contributes to the mechanism of acid-induced HγD-crys fibrillogenesis and its implication in the formation of age-related nuclear cataract. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0112309.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Intrinsic fluorescence intensity measurement of HγD-crys samples (0.1 mg/mL) under different incubation conditions. (A) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0, 37°C; (B) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0, 37°C; (C) HγD-crys incubated at pH 7.0, 55°C; and (D) HγD-crys incubated at pH 2.0, 55°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence spectra between 300 and 400 nm were recorded upon exciting the samples at 280 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Incubation under pH 2.0 settings resulted in a rapid and greater increase in fluorescence emission, as well as a more noticeable red-shift in the wavelengths of emission maximum than those of the samples under pH 7.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0112309.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0112309.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>The effect of incubation condition on size distribution of human γD-crystallin (HγD-crys) samples. Samples of HγD-crys at 1 mg/mL (45 µM) were incubated in different conditions (temperature = 37 or 55°C; pH = 2.0 or 7.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>The turbidity of HγD-crys sample was evaluated using dynamic light scattering (DLS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>(A) pH 7.0, t = 0 hr; (B) pH 7.0, 37°C, t = 2 days; (C) pH 7.0, 55°C, t = 2 days; (D) pH 2.0, t = 0 hr; (E) pH 2.0, 37°C, t = 2 days; and (F) pH 2.0, 55°C, t = 2 days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0112309.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0112309.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Thermal unfolding/denaturation profiles of HγD-crys as a function of temperature. The average emission wavelengths for samples incubated at pH 2.0 or 7.0 were extracted from intrinsic fluorescence spectra to monitor for changes over the incubation period of 2 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>The intrinsic fluorescence spectra between 300 and 400 nm of all HγD-crys samples were recorded at the excitation wavelength of 280 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Fitting of the apparent thermodynamic values followed a two-state model with a shift toward lower temperatures from pH 7.0 to pH 2.0 conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0112309.s003.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0112309.s004"><label>Figure S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>Structure of the HγD-crys monomer with the two domains specified in red dashed boxes and the four Greek key motifs labeled. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0112309.s004.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0112309.s005"><label>Figure S5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Time evolution of secondary structure during 150 ns of simulation time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0112309.s005.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>We are grateful to the staffs of Technology Commons, College of Life Science, National Taiwan University (NTU) for help with transmission electron microscopy (TEM). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0112309-Dobson1"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>1 DobsonCM (1999) Protein misfolding, evolution and disease. Trends Biochem Sci 24: 329–332.10470028 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Fink1"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>2 FinkAL (1998) Protein aggregation: folding aggregates, inclusion bodies and amyloid. Fold Des 3: R9–23.9502314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Chennamsetty1"><text><SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>3 ChennamsettyN, VoynovV, KayserV, HelkB, TroutBL (2009) Design of therapeutic proteins with enhanced stability. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 106: 11937–11942.19571001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Chiti1"><text><SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>4 ChitiF, DobsonCM (2006) Protein misfolding, functional amyloid, and human disease. Annu Rev Biochem 75: 333–366.16756495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Organization1"><text><SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>5Organization WH (2011) Visual impairment and blindness report. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>Fact Sheet N 282: WHO. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Shearer1"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>6 ShearerTR, MaH, FukiageC, AzumaM (1997) Selenite nuclear cataract: review of the model. Mol Vis 3: 8.9238097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Santhoshkumar1"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>7 SanthoshkumarP, UdupaP, MurugesanR, SharmaKK (2008) Significance of interactions of low molecular weight crystallin fragments in lens aging and cataract formation. J Biol Chem 283: 8477–8485.18227073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Oyster1"><text><SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>8Oyster CW (1999) The human eye structure and function: Sinauer Associates, Inc. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Horwitz1"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>9 HorwitzJ (1992) Alpha-crystallin can function as a molecular chaperone. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 89: 10449–10453.1438232 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Meehan1"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>10 MeehanS, BerryY, LuisiB, DobsonCM, CarverJA, et al (2004) Amyloid fibril formation by lens crystallin proteins and its implications for cataract formation. J Biol Chem 279: 3413–3419.14615485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Hanson1"><text><SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>11 HansonSR, HasanA, SmithDL, SmithJB (2000) The major in vivo modifications of the human water-insoluble lens crystallins are disulfide bonds, deamidation, methionine oxidation and backbone cleavage. Exp Eye Res 71: 195–207.10930324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Takemoto1"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>12 TakemotoL (1996) Increase in the intramolecular disulfide bonding of alpha-A crystallin during aging of the human lens. Exp Eye Res 63: 585–590.8994362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Truscott1"><text><SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>13 TruscottRJ (2005) Age-related nuclear cataract-oxidation is the key. Exp Eye Res 80: 709–725.15862178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Hains1"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>14 HainsPG, TruscottRJ (2010) Age-dependent deamidation of lifelong proteins in the human lens. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 51: 3107–3114.20053973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Biswas1"><text><SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>15 BiswasS, HarrisF, DennisonS, SinghJ, PhoenixDA (2004) Calpains: targets of cataract prevention? Trends Mol Med 10: 78–84.15102361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Crabbe1"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>16 CrabbeMJ, GoodeD (1995) Protein folds and functional similarity; the Greek key/immunoglobulin fold. Comput Chem 19: 343–349.8528592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-KosinskiCollins1"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>17 Kosinski-CollinsMS, KingJ (2003) In vitro unfolding, refolding, and polymerization of human gammaD crystallin, a protein involved in cataract formation. Protein Sci 12: 480–490.12592018 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Papanikolopoulou1"><text><SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>18 PapanikolopoulouK, Mills-HenryI, TholSL, WangY, GrossAA, et al (2008) Formation of amyloid fibrils in vitro by human gammaD-crystallin and its isolated domains. Mol Vis 14: 81–89.18253099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Moran1"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>19 MoranSD, WoysAM, BuchananLE, BixbyE, DecaturSM, et al (2012) Two-dimensional IR spectroscopy and segmental 13C labeling reveals the domain structure of human gammaD-crystallin amyloid fibrils. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 109: 3329–3334.22328156 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Eckert1"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>20 EckertR (2002) pH gating of lens fibre connexins. Pflugers Arch 443: 843–851.11889584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Poon1"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>21 PoonS, RybchynMS, Easterbrook-SmithSB, CarverJA, PankhurstGJ, et al (2002) Mildly acidic pH activates the extracellular molecular chaperone clusterin. J Biol Chem 277: 39532–39540.12176985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Wen1"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>22 WenWS, HsiehMC, WangSSS (2011) High-level expression and purification of human gamma D-crystallin in Escherichia coli. Journal of the Taiwan Institute of Chemical Engineers 42: 547–555. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-KosinskiCollins2"><text><SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>23 Kosinski-CollinsMS, FlaughSL, KingJ (2004) Probing folding and fluorescence quenching in human gammaD crystallin Greek key domains using triple tryptophan mutant proteins. Protein Sci 13: 2223–2235.15273315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Pande1"><text><SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>24 PandeA, PandeJ, AsherieN, LomakinA, OgunO, et al (2000) Molecular basis of a progressive juvenile-onset hereditary cataract. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 97: 1993–1998.10688888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Wang1"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>25 WangY, PettyS, TrojanowskiA, KneeK, GouletD, et al (2010) Formation of amyloid fibrils in vitro from partially unfolded intermediates of human gammaC-crystallin. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 51: 672–678.19684009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Smith1"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>26 SmithPK, KrohnRI, HermansonGT, MalliaAK, GartnerFH, et al (1985) Measurement of protein using bicinchoninic acid. Anal Biochem 150: 76–85.3843705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Wang2"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>27 WangSS, WenWS (2010) Examining the influence of ultraviolet C irradiation on recombinant human gammaD-crystallin. Mol Vis 16: 2777–2790.21197112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Ellozy1"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>28 EllozyAR, CegerP, WangRH, DillonJ (1996) Effect of the UV modification of alpha-crystallin on its ability to suppress nonspecific aggregation. Photochemistry and Photobiology 64: 344–348.8760574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Darghal1"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>29 DarghalN, Garnier-SuillerotA, SalernoM (2006) Mechanism of thioflavin T accumulation inside cells overexpressing P-glycoprotein or multidrug resistance-associated protein: Role of lipophilicity and positive charge. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications 343: 623–629.16554036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Whitmore1"><text><SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>30 WhitmoreL, WallaceBA (2004) DICHROWEB, an online server for protein secondary structure analyses from circular dichroism spectroscopic data. Nucleic Acids Research 32: W668–W673.15215473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Whitmore2"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>31 WhitmoreL, WallaceBA (2008) Protein secondary structure analyses from circular dichroism spectroscopy: Methods and reference databases. Biopolymers 89: 392–400.17896349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Wang3"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>32 WangGZ, DongXY, SunY (2009) The role of disulfide bond formation in the conformational folding kinetics of denatured/reduced lysozyme. Biochemical Engineering Journal 46: 7–11. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Bradford1"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>33 BradfordJR, WestheadDR (2005) Improved prediction of protein-protein binding sites using a support vector machines approach. Bioinformatics 21: 1487–1494.15613384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-VanDerSpoel1"><text><SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>34 Van Der SpoelD, LindahlE, HessB, GroenhofG, MarkAE, et al (2005) GROMACS: fast, flexible, and free. J Comput Chem 26: 1701–1718.16211538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Abraham1"><text><SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>35 AbrahamMJ, GreadyJE (2011) Optimization of parameters for molecular dynamics simulation using smooth particle-mesh Ewald in GROMACS 4.5. J Comput Chem 32: 2031–2040.21469158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Essmann1"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>36 EssmannU, PereraL, BerkowitzML, DardenT, LeeH, et al (1995) A Smooth Particle Mesh Ewald Method. Journal of Chemical Physics 103: 8577–8593. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Hess1"><text><SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>37 HessB, BekkerH, BerendsenHJC, FraaijeJGEM (1997) LINCS: A linear constraint solver for molecular simulations. Journal of Computational Chemistry 18: 1463–1472. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Schuler1"><text><SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>38 SchulerLD, DauraX, Van GunsterenWF (2001) An improved GROMOS96 force field for aliphatic hydrocarbons in the condensed phase. Journal of Computational Chemistry 22: 1205–1218. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Day1"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>39 DayR, BennionBJ, HamS, DaggettV (2002) Increasing temperature accelerates protein unfolding without changing the pathway of unfolding. J Mol Biol 322: 189–203.12215424 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Kabsch1"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>40 KabschW, SanderC (1983) Dictionary of protein secondary structure: pattern recognition of hydrogen-bonded and geometrical features. Biopolymers 22: 2577–2637.6667333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Bourhim1"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>41 BourhimM, KruzelM, SrikrishnanT, NicoteraT (2007) Linear quantitation of A beta aggregation using Thioflavin T: Reduction in fibril formation by colostrinin. Journal of Neuroscience Methods 160: 264–268.17049613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Hudson1"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>42 HudsonSA, EcroydH, KeeTW, CarverJA (2009) The thioflavin T fluorescence assay for amyloid fibril detection can be biased by the presence of exogenous compounds. Febs Journal 276: 5960–5972.19754881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Liu1"><text><SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>43 LiuCP, LiZY, HuangGC, PerrettS, ZhouJM (2005) Two distinct intermediates of trigger factor are populated during guanidine denaturation. Biochimie 87: 1023–1031.15927341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Smoot1"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>44 SmootAL, PandaM, BrazilBT, BuckleAM, FershtAR, et al (2001) The binding of bis-ANS to the isolated GroEL apical domain fragment induces the formation of a folding intermediate with increased hydrophobic surface not observed in tetradecameric GroEL. Biochemistry 40: 4484–4492.11284705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Sirangelo1"><text><SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>45 SirangeloI, BismutoE, TavassiS, IraceG (1998) Apomyoglobin folding intermediates characterized by the hydrophobic fluorescent probe 8-anilino-1-naphthalene sulfonate. Biochim Biophys Acta 1385: 69–77.9630524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Semisotnov1"><text><SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>46 SemisotnovGV, RodionovaNA, RazgulyaevOI, UverskyVN, GripasAF, et al (1991) Study of the “molten globule” intermediate state in protein folding by a hydrophobic fluorescent probe. Biopolymers 31: 119–128.2025683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Eftink1"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>47 EftinkMR (1991) Fluorescence Techniques for Studying Protein-Structure. Methods of Biochemical Analysis 35: 127–205.2002770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Eftink2"><text><SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>48 EftinkMR (1998) The use of fluorescence methods to monitor unfolding transitions in proteins. Biochemistry-Moscow 63: 276–284.9526124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-DiStasio1"><text><SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>49 Di StasioE, BizzarriP, MisitiF, PavoniE, BrancaccioA (2004) A fast and accurate procedure to collect and analyze unfolding fluorescence signal: the case of dystroglycan domains. Biophysical Chemistry 107: 197–211.14962600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Varshney1"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>50 VarshneyA, AhmadB, RabbaniG, KumarV, YadavS, et al (2010) Acid-induced unfolding of didecameric keyhole limpet hemocyanin: detection and characterizations of decameric and tetrameric intermediate states. Amino Acids 39: 899–910.20213446 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Rabbani1"><text><SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>51 RabbaniG, AhmadE, ZaidiN, KhanRH (2011) pH-dependent conformational transitions in conalbumin (ovotransferrin), a metalloproteinase from hen egg white. Cell Biochem Biophys 61: 551–560.21833676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-KosinskiCollins3"><text><SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>52 Kosinski-CollinsMS, FlaughSL, KingJ (2004) Probing folding and fluorescence quenching in human gammaD crystallin Greek key domains using triple tryptophan mutant proteins. Protein Sci 13: 2223–2235.15273315 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Pande2"><text><SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>53 PandeA, PandeJ, AsherieN, LomakinA, OgunO, et al (2000) Molecular basis of a progressive juvenile-onset hereditary cataract. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 97: 1993–1998.10688888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Rabbani2"><text><SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>54 RabbaniG, KaurJ, AhmadE, KhanRH, JainSK (2014) Structural characteristics of thermostable immunogenic outer membrane protein from Salmonella enterica serovar Typhi. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 98: 2533–2543.23949993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Wistow1"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>55 WistowG (1990) Evolution of a protein superfamily: relationships between vertebrate lens crystallins and microorganism dormancy proteins. J Mol Evol 30: 140–145.2107329 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Rosinke1"><text><SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>56 RosinkeB, RennerC, MayrEM, JaenickeR, HolakTA (1997) Ca2+-loaded spherulin 3a from Physarum polycephalum adopts the prototype gamma-crystallin fold in aqueous solution. J Mol Biol 271: 645–655.9281431 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Ohno1"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>57 OhnoA, TateS, SeeramSS, HiragaK, SwindellsMB, et al (1998) NMR structure of the Streptomyces metalloproteinase inhibitor, SMPI, isolated from Streptomyces nigrescens TK-23: another example of an ancestral beta gamma-crystallin precursor structure. J Mol Biol 282: 421–433.9735297 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Mills1"><text><SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>58 MillsIA, FlaughSL, Kosinski-CollinsMS, KingJA (2007) Folding and stability of the isolated Greek key domains of the long-lived human lens proteins gammaD-crystallin and gammaS-crystallin. Protein Sci 16: 2427–2444.17905830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Moreau1"><text><SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>59 MoreauKL, KingJ (2009) Hydrophobic core mutations associated with cataract development in mice destabilize human gammaD-crystallin. J Biol Chem 284: 33285–33295.19758984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Das1"><text><SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>60 DasP, KingJA, ZhouR (2011) Aggregation of gamma-crystallins associated with human cataracts via domain swapping at the C-terminal beta-strands. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 108: 10514–10519.21670251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Das2"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>61 DasP, KingJA, ZhouR (2010) beta-Strand interactions at the domain interface critical for the stability of human lens gammaD-crystallin. Protein Sci 19: 131–140.19937657 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Flaugh1"><text><SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>62 FlaughSL, Kosinski-CollinsMS, KingJ (2005) Contributions of hydrophobic domain interface interactions to the folding and stability of human gammaD-crystallin. Protein Sci 14: 569–581.15722442 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Flaugh2"><text><SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>63 FlaughSL, Kosinski-CollinsMS, KingJ (2005) Interdomain side-chain interactions in human gammaD crystallin influencing folding and stability. Protein Sci 14: 2030–2043.16046626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Flaugh3"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>64 FlaughSL, MillsIA, KingJ (2006) Glutamine deamidation destabilizes human gammaD-crystallin and lowers the kinetic barrier to unfolding. J Biol Chem 281: 30782–30793.16891314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Kong1"><text><SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>65 KongF, KingJ (2011) Contributions of aromatic pairs to the folding and stability of long-lived human gammaD-crystallin. Protein Sci 20: 513–528.21432932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Frederikse1"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>66 FrederiksePH (2000) Amyloid-like protein structure in mammalian ocular lenses. Current Eye Research 20: 462–468.10980658 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Sandilands1"><text><SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>67 SandilandsA, HutchesonAM, LongHA, PrescottAR, VrensenG, et al (2002) Altered aggregation properties of mutant gamma-crystallins cause inherited cataract. The EMBO journal 21: 6005–6014.12426373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>68Zhang W, Cai HC, Li FF, Xi YB, Ma X, et al.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>(2011) The congenital cataract-linked G61C mutation destabilizes gamma D-crystallin and promotes non-native aggregation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Plos One 6. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Colon1"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>69 ColonW, KellyJW (1992) Partial denaturation of transthyretin is sufficient for amyloid fibril formation in vitro. Biochemistry 31: 8654–8660.1390650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Block1"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>70 BlockH, KubicekJ, LabahnJ, RothU, SchaferF (2008) Production and comprehensive quality control of recombinant human Interleukin-1beta: a case study for a process development strategy. Protein Expr Purif 57: 244–254.18053740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Kingsbury1"><text><SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>71 KingsburyJS, KlimtchukES, ThebergeR, CostelloCE, ConnorsLH (2007) Expression, purification, and in vitro cysteine-10 modification of native sequence recombinant human transthyretin. Protein Expr Purif 53: 370–377.17317215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-AlGhoul1"><text><SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>72 Al-GhoulKJ, LaneCW, TaylorVL, FowlerWC, CostelloMJ (1996) Distribution and type of morphological damage in human nuclear age-related cataracts. Exp Eye Res 62: 237–251.8690033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Gilliland1"><text><SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>73 GillilandKO, FreelCD, LaneCW, FowlerWC, CostelloMJ (2001) Multilamellar bodies as potential scattering particles in human age-related nuclear cataracts. Mol Vis 7: 120–130.11435998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Rousseau1"><text><SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>74 RousseauF, SchymkowitzJ, SerranoL (2006) Protein aggregation and amyloidosis: confusion of the kinds? Current Opinion in Structural Biology 16: 118–126.16434184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Brubaker1"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>75 BrubakerWD, FreitesJA, GolchertKJ, ShapiroRA, MorikisV, et al (2011) Separating instability from aggregation propensity in gammaS-crystallin variants. Biophys J 100: 498–506.21244846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Chiti2"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>76 ChitiF, DobsonCM (2009) Amyloid formation by globular proteins under native conditions. Nat Chem Biol 5: 15–22.19088715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Sahin1"><text><SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>77 SahinE, JordanJL, SpataraML, NaranjoA, CostanzoJA, et al (2011) Computational design and biophysical characterization of aggregation-resistant point mutations for gammaD crystallin illustrate a balance of conformational stability and intrinsic aggregation propensity. Biochemistry 50: 628–639.21184609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0112309-Wu1"><text><SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>78 WuJW, LiuHL (2012) In silico Investigation of the Disease-Associated Retinoschisin C110Y and C219G Mutants. J Biomol Struct Dyn 29: 1–23. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
