
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4076580</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20132486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20132486</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The linear ubiquitin assembly complex (LUBAC) is essential for NLRP3 inflammasome activation </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Linear ubiquitination regulates NLRP3/ASC assembly</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>Mary A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bowman</surname><given-names>James W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>Hiroaki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Orazio</surname><given-names>Nicole</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Mude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Qiming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amatya</surname><given-names>Rina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>Thomas J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>Kazuhiro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>Jenny</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>Jae U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Molecular Microbiology and Immunology, Keck School of Medicine, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA 90033</institution></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Graduate School of Medicine, Kyoto University, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto 606-8501, Japan</institution></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution>Department of Microbiology-Immunology, Lineberger Comprehensive Cancer Center, Center for Translational Immunology and Institute for Inflammatory Diseases, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, NC 27599</institution></aff><author-notes><corresp>CORRESPONDENCE Jae U. Jung: <email>jaeujung@med.usc.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>30</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>211</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>1333</fpage><lpage>1347</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>12</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Rodgers et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike–No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution–Noncommercial–Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:role="icon" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="JEM_20132486_thumb.gif"/><abstract abstract-type="precis"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Independent of its known role in NF-κB transcription, the HOIL-1L containing LUBAC is required for assembly and activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome via linear ubiquitination of ASC. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Linear ubiquitination is a newly discovered posttranslational modification that is currently restricted to a small number of known protein substrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The linear ubiquitination assembly complex (LUBAC), consisting of HOIL-1L, HOIP, and Sharpin, has been reported to activate NF-κB–mediated transcription in response to receptor signaling by ligating linear ubiquitin chains to Nemo and Rip1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Despite recent advances, the detailed roles of LUBAC in immune cells remain elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate a novel HOIL-1L function as an essential regulator of the activation of the NLRP3/ASC inflammasome in primary bone marrow–derived macrophages (BMDMs) independently of NF-κB activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Mechanistically, HOIL-1L is required for assembly of the NLRP3/ASC inflammasome and the linear ubiquitination of ASC, which we identify as a novel LUBAC substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Consequently, we find that HOIL-1L−/− mice have reduced IL-1β secretion in response to in vivo NLRP3 stimulation and survive lethal challenge with LPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Together, these data demonstrate that linear ubiquitination is required for NLRP3 inflammasome activation, defining the molecular events of NLRP3 inflammasome activation and expanding the role of LUBAC as an innate immune regulator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, our observation is clinically relevant because patients lacking HOIL-1L expression suffer from pyogenic bacterial immunodeficiency, providing a potential new therapeutic target for enhancing inflammation in immunodeficient patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>The innate immune response is precisely gated by regulatory mechanisms during both detection of a threat to the host and also the resulting responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Such control is essential for preventing inappropriate or prolonged innate immune responses, which may damage the host as much as the pathogen or damaging signal itself. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Specifically, posttranslational modification of substrate proteins by ubiquitination has been reported for many targets in innate immune signaling pathways as a mechanism of regulating their functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The diversity of effects on target protein degradation, binding partner affinity, or localization resulting from ubiquitination modification is dependent on the lysine linkage position and length of the ubiquitin chain attached by a ubiquitin ligase enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>As a central pathway downstream from many innate and adaptive immune receptors, the NF-κB signaling pathway is highly regulated by lysine 48 (K48), K63, and linear ubiquitination modifications that are required for the ultimate release of the p50/p65 NF-κB transcription factor to the nucleus where it can turn on the expression of proinflammatory genes (Iwai and Tokunaga, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>After receptor stimulation by CD40 ligand, TNF, or IL-1β, the cIAP-mediated K63 ubiquitination of Rip1 or TRAF6 leads to recruitment of the linear ubiquitin assembly complex (LUBAC), consisting of HOIP and HOIL-1L or Sharpin, or both (Haas et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>LUBAC is required for the linear ubiquitination of Rip1 and Nemo, resulting in the activation of the IKK kinase (Iwai and Tokunaga, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of IκBα by IKK is required for the K48 ubiquitination of IκBα, which leads to proteasomal degradation of IκBα and release of the p50/p65 NF-κB transcription factor for translocation to the nucleus (Iwai and Tokunaga, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Although many protein substrates have been described for K48 and K63 ubiquitination, few have been described for linear ubiquitination, with only Rip1 and Nemo being the best characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Negative regulators of linear ubiquitination-dependent NF-κB activation have recently been reported, including the FAM105B (otulin) and CYLD linear ubiquitin-specific deubiquitinases (DUBs) and A20, which specifically binds the linear ubiquitin moiety and edits Rip1 ubiquitination to inhibit its activation (Wertz et al., 2004; Tokunaga et al., 2012; Verhelst et al., 2012; Keusekotten et al., 2013; Rivkin et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Because many receptor signaling pathways converge on Nemo activation, linear ubiquitination is expected to be required for the NF-κB–dependent gene expression of various pattern recognition receptor (PRR) pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Indeed, TLRs, such as TLR2, 3, 4, 7/8, and 9, have been shown to require LUBAC for NF-κB–dependent gene expression due to the linear ubiquitination of Nemo (Zak et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The NOD2 (nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain-containing protein 2)-dependent activation of NF-κB in response to muramyl dipeptide (MDP) also requires LUBAC, which is recruited by the XIAP-mediated K63 ubiquitination of RIPK2 (Damgaard et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the HOIL-1L subunit of LUBAC is a negative regulator of the RIG-I intracellular virus-sensing PRR that competitively binds RIG-I and targets TRIM25 for degradation, thus stopping the TRIM25-mediated ubiquitination and activation of RIG-I as a potential feedback inhibitory pathway (Inn et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that LUBAC plays important roles in various surface and intracellular PPR pathways as a positive and negative factor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>The inflammasome family of PRRs detects cytosolic pathogens and danger signals, such as potassium efflux and mitochondrial damage, in myeloid-lineage cells and responds by forming an oligomer signaling complex that includes an adapter protein, such as ASC or Naip5, which can bind to pro–caspase-1 (Franchi et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The inflammasome complex subsequently potentiates the autocatalytic cleavage of pro–caspase-1 to its active p10 and p20 subunits, which enzymatically cleaves pro–IL-1β and pro–IL-18 to active cytokines for immediate secretion and inflammatory action (Schroder and Tschopp, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Expression of the pro–IL-1β gene is NF-κB–dependent, and is triggered by a second PRR stimulation, such as TLRs, in macrophage cells (Schroder and Tschopp, 2010; Franchi et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Regulation of inflammasomes by ubiquitination has previously been shown for the NLRP3 and AIM2 inflammasomes, which both use the ASC adapter protein (Franchi et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>The deubiquitination of NLRP3 by the BRCC3 complex is required for NLRP3 activation (Juliana et al., 2012; Lopez-Castejon et al., 2013; Py et al., 2013), and the K63-linked ubiquitination of ASC targets the AIM2–ASC inflammasome complex for destruction in autophagosomes (Shi et al., 2012; Shimada et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>However, given the complexity of the regulation of the NF-κB pathway by a combination of K63, K48, and linear ubiquitination, further analysis of ubiquitination-mediated regulation is necessary to fully understand inflammasome-induced innate immune pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Besides its role in TLR-induced NF-κB activation, LUBAC-mediated linear ubiquitination may also participate in the inflammasome activation pathway for caspase-1 activation and IL-1β secretion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>However, the roles of LUBAC have so far been defined through the study of mouse embryonic fibroblasts (MEFs), B cells and keratinocytes of HOIL-1L−/− and Sharpincpdm (null point mutant) mice, or human embryonic kidney (HEK293T) reporter cells with gene overexpression of knockdown conditions (Tokunaga et al., 2009, 2011; Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011) that do not express all of the subunits of the inflammasome family of PRRs, thus making the role of LUBAC in inflammasome pathways elusive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In this study, we thus examined the role of the HOIL-1L subunit of LUBAC in NLRP3 inflammasome pathway in primary BM-derived macrophages (BMDMs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We demonstrate that HOIL-1L is essential for NLRP3 inflammasome activation independently of NF-κB activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Specifically, HOIL-1L is required for ASC linear ubiquitination and NLRP3 inflammasome assembly, thus expanding the role of LUBAC as an innate immune regulator. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Cell type–specific roles of HOIL-1L in NF-κB activation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>To test whether NF-κB is regulated by LUBAC in macrophage cells, we first examined NF-κB activation in WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs and MEFs upon stimulation with LPS or TNF (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>Similarly to previous studies (Tokunaga et al., 2009, 2011; Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011), HOIL-1L−/− MEFs showed delayed kinetics of IκBα degradation compared with WT MEFs upon LPS or TNF treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In distinct contrast, HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs had similar kinetics of IκBα degradation to WT BMDMs (Fig. 1 a), suggesting that HOIL-1L may function in a cell type–dependent manner as previously shown in human patient samples (Boisson et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>As a result of reduced NF-κB activation, HOIL-1L−/− MEFs had reduced expression of the IL-6, IκBα, and ICAM1 genes as compared with WT MEFs after 2 h of LPS treatment (Fig. 1 b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The relative abundances of IL-6 transcripts in BMDMs and MEFs resulted in similar levels of IL-6 cytokine secretion in WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs but significantly reduced IL-6 cytokine secretion in HOIL-1L−/− MEFs compared with WT MEFs after 24 h of LPS stimulation (Fig. 1 c), suggesting that HOIL-1L has cell type–specific functions for NF-κB activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L has cell type–specific roles in NF-κB activation. (a) WT and HOIL-1L−/− MEFs and BMDMs were stimulated with 1 ng/ml TNF or 10 ng/ml LPS for 0, 15, or 30 min and probed for indicated protein levels by immunoblotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>(b) The mRNA transcript abundance for selected NF-κB–regulated genes was quantified after 2 h of 10 ng/ml LPS stimulation by qRT-PCR (biological n = 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>(c) IL-6 secretion was quantified by ELISA at 24 h after LPS treatment (biological n = 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Data are representative of three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Protein size markers are indicated in kD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>All data are presented as the mean ± SEM by a Student’s t test. *, P = 0.013; **, P = 0.015; ***, P = 0.034; #, P = 10−6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig1"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>To further define the role of HOIL-1L in NF-κB–dependent and –independent gene expression, we examined global mRNA transcripts by microarray and found that HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs had generally similar transcriptional profiles to WT BMDMs with or without LPS or TNF treatment (4 h; Fig. 2 a), whereas a small number of transcripts were differentially regulated in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs compared with WT BMDMs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1" id="supp1">Tables S1</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1" id="supp2">S2</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>These transcripts might be directly regulated by HOIL-1L because HOIL-1L was originally identified as a DNA-binding protein, although the transcripts regulated by HOIL-1L were not previously identified (Tatematsu et al., 1998; Tokunaga et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Specific comparison of the selected NF-κB–regulated transcripts further revealed equivalent or higher levels of their expression in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs than in WT BMDMs, and pathway analysis confirmed that the NF-κB pathway was regulated in a similar manner in WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs (Fig. 2 b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>These expression profiles were additionally confirmed by quantitative PCR (qPCR) in WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDM (Fig. 2 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Notably, IL-1β transcript levels were similar in HOIL-1L−/− and WT BMDMs upon LPS treatment, confirming that LPS treatment is a suitable priming signal for inflammasome activation experiments in these cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Previous microarray data of TLR2-activated WT and Sharpincpdm BMDMs showed an obvious defect in NF-κB–dependent gene expression (Zak et al., 2011), including a strong reduction of IL-1β transcript levels in Sharpincpdm BMDMs (Zak et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Therefore, we did not include these cells for further study of inflammasome activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Global transcriptional profiles of WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs in response to LPS and TNF. (a) Heat map of genes with fivefold or greater changes in expression by whole genome microarray comparison were grouped by hierarchal clustering for WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs treated with 1 ng/ml TNF for 4 h, 10 ng/ml LPS for 4 h, or untreated for 4 h (biological n = 2, data for both individual replicates are presented as samples 1 and 2 for each condition). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>(b) Heat map of selected NF-κB genes compared by hierarchal clustering (biological n = 2, data for both individual replicates are presented as samples 1 and 2 for each condition). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(c) Analysis of mRNA transcript abundance by qRT-PCR for selected genes as indicated in WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs stimulated as in a (biological n = 2 and analytical n = 2 for each biological replicate). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>All data are presented as the mean ± SEM by a Student’s t test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig2"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L is required for ASC-dependent inflammasome activation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>To determine whether HOIL-1L is a regulator of inflammasome-mediated caspase-1 activation, WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs were primed with LPS to induce the TLR4-dependent expression of pro–IL-1β protein, and subsequent activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome was achieved by treatment with nigericin, a potassium ionophore, silica particles, monosodium urate crystals (MSUs), or the peptidoglycan component MDP, followed by ATP treatment (Dostert et al., 2008; Hornung et al., 2008; Schroder and Tschopp, 2010; Kovarova et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>The AIM2 inflammasome was stimulated by double-stranded plasmid DNA (dsDNA) and the NLCR4 inflammasome was stimulated by cytosolic delivery of purified Salmonella typhimurium–derived flagellin or infection with Legionella pneumophila without any additional priming. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Compared with WT BMDMs, HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs had a defect in mature IL-1β secretion upon NLRP3 stimulation, reduced IL-1β secretion upon AIM2 stimulation, but similar IL-1β secretion upon NLRC4 stimulation (Fig. 3 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the AIM2 (Fernandes-Alnemri et al., 2009; Rathinam et al., 2010) and NLRP3 (Martinon et al., 2002; Pan et al., 2007; Franchi et al., 2012) inflammasomes both require the adapter protein ASC, whereas the NLRC4 inflammasome is only enhanced by ASC (Broz et al., 2010; Miao et al., 2010; Zhao et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Thus, these results indicate that HOIL-1L may specifically be required for ASC-dependent inflammasome activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Although the IL-1β secretion induced by both NLRP3 and AIM2 inflammasomes were affected in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs, the effect was much more pronounced for NLRP3 stimulation than for AIM2 stimulation, leading us to further characterize the mechanism of HOIL-1L–mediated regulation of NLRP3–ASC inflammasome activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Although WT BMDMs had NLRP3 stimulation-dependent caspase-1 activity, as measured by pro–caspase-1 cleavage to the p10 subunit, HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs showed a defect in pro–caspase-1 cleavage under the same stimulation conditions (Fig. 3 b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Similarly, when BMDMs were stained with FAM-YVAD-FMK (FLICA), a fluorescent caspase-1 substrate peptide which selectively binds cleaved and active caspase-1 enzyme, only WT BMDMs contained FLICA-staining positive active caspase-1 upon NLRP3 stimulation, whereas HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs had reduced FLICA staining (Fig. 3 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Together, these data demonstrate that LUBAC is a critical regulator for the NLRP3 stimulation-dependent activation of caspase-1 activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>LUBAC is required for NLRP3 inflammasome activation in BMDMs. (a) IL-1β secretion as determined by ELISA of WT or HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs primed with LPS overnight and stimulated with nigericin, silica, MSU, MDP followed by ATP, dsDNA transfected by lipofectamine, or infected with adenovirus-Flagellin as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Unprimed BMDMs were infected with L. pneumophila at indicated multiplicities of infection (MOIs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as the mean ± SEM by a Student’s t test (biological n = 3 and are representative of two independent experiments; *, P &lt; 0.00033; #, P = 0.011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>(b) Protein expression and caspase-1 cleavage of WT or HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs untreated or primed with LPS and stimulated with nigericin was analyzed by immunoblotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>(c) BMDMs primed with LPS and stimulated with nigericin were treated with FAM-YVAD-FLICA fluorescent caspase-1 substrate during MDP treatment, fixed, and then stained for caspase-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The percentage of FLICA-positive cells was determined for 250 total cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Arrows point to FLICA-stained spots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Bars, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>(d–h) WT or HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs were complemented with lentiviral vectors expressing mutants described in d and analyzed for: (e) IL-1β secretion by ELISA (biological n = 3 and analytical n = 2; data presented as the mean ± SEM; **, P &lt; 0.0075; #, P &lt; 0.013 by a Student’s t test); (f) mRNA quantification by qRT-PCR; (g) protein expression by immunoblot; and (h) quantification of FLICA staining for active caspase-1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>All data are representative of three independent experiments except for c and h, which depict combined data for all three experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Protein size markers are indicated in kD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486R_Fig3"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>To define the role of linear ubiquitination in inflammasome activation, we complemented the HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs with HA-tagged WT or mutant HOIL-1L (Fig. 3 d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>These mutants are as follows: the ΔUBL mutant carrying deletion of the ubiquitin-like (UBL) domain that is required for binding to HOIP to achieve linear ubiquitination activity (Kirisako et al., 2006; Stieglitz et al., 2012); the ΔNZF and TF mutants carrying deletion and T203L/F204V point mutations, respectively, of the Npl4 type-zinc-finger (NZF) domain that is required for binding to ubiquitin (Haas et al., 2009; Sato et al., 2011); and the ΔRBR mutant carrying deletion of the Ring-between-Ring (RBR) domain that is an E3 ubiquitin ligase domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>As expected, pro–IL-1β mRNA and protein levels were not affected by WT or mutant HOIL-1L gene expression (Fig. 3, f and g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Complementation of HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs with WT HOIL-1L fully rescued pro–caspase-1 cleavage, caspase-1 activity, and IL-1β secretion (Fig. 3, e–h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>However, deletion of the UBL, NZF, or RBR domain of HOIL-1L failed to restore pro–caspase-1 cleavage, caspase-1 activity, or IL-1β secretion (Fig. 3, e–h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Together, these data indicate that nearly all the functional components of HOIL-1L, including the N-terminal HOIP interaction, the central ubiquitin interaction, and the C-terminal ubiquitination ligase activity, are critical for pro–caspase-1 cleavage and enzymatic activity in NLRP3-inflammasome activation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L is required for NLRP3/ASC inflammasome assembly </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We next examined whether linear ubiquitination was important for inflammasome activation events occurring upstream of caspase-1 cleavage, namely, ASC cytoplasmic foci formation and NLRP3–ASC complex assembly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Similarly to previous reports (Bryan et al., 2009; Shi et al., 2012; Proell et al., 2013), ASC had diffuse localization in unstimulated WT BMDMs and could be found in distinct cytoplasmic foci upon NLRP3 stimulation (Fig. 4, a and b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, when WT BMDMs were stained with a linear ubiquitin-specific antibody, ASC foci effectively colocalized with linear ubiquitination-containing compartments; Z-stack confocal imaging revealed that the linear ubiquitination-containing compartments appeared to be in the center of the ASC foci (Fig. 4 c and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1" id="supp3">Video 1</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Complementation of HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs with HOIL-1L fully rescued ASC foci formation and the colocalization of ASC foci with linear ubiquitin stains to nearly the same levels as WT BMDMs (Fig. 4, d and e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Although linear ubiquitination-containing compartments were detectable in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs, they did not colocalize with the ASC that remained diffuse throughout the cytoplasm in either untreated or NLRP3-stimulation conditions (Fig. 4 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, immune purification showed the efficient formation of the NLRP3–ASC complex in LPS-primed, nigericin-stimulated WT BMDMs (Fig. 4 f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>By marked contrast, the formation of the NLRP3–ASC complex was reduced to background levels in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs under the same conditions (Fig. 4 f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>These results indicate a critical role of LUBAC in ASC foci formation and NLRP3–ASC inflammasome assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Assembly of the NLRP3/ASC inflammasome requires HOIL-1L. (a) Representative images of ASC foci formation (arrows) upon NLRP3 stimulation in WT or HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs with ASC staining in green, linear ubiquitin in red, and nuclei in blue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Bar, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Images are from one of four independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>(b) Quantification of ASC foci in 100 cells counted from images in a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>(c) Z-stack of WT BMDMs in a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Bar, 10 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>(d) Representative images of ASC foci formation (arrows) upon NLPR3 stimulation in HOIL-1L−/− and WT BMDMs infected with indicated lentiviruses and stained as described for a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Bar, 20 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Images are from one of two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>(e) Quantification of ASC foci from 30 cells combined from three experiments from images in d. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>(f) IP of ASC from untreated WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs or after LPS priming and nigericin stimulation, data are representative of four independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Protein size markers are indicated in kD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig4"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>ASC is linear ubiquitinated by LUBAC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Because ASC foci colocalized with linear ubiquitin-containing compartments in WT BMDMs upon NLRP3 stimulation, we evaluated by five different assays whether ASC is a potential LUBAC substrate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>First, we used a linear ubiquitin-specific antibody to immunoprecipitate linear ubiquitin from 293T cells transfected with the LUBAC subunits HOIL-1L and HOIP, along with a C-terminal Flag-tagged ASC (ASC-Flag) in 5M urea denaturation buffer conditions as optimized (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1" id="supp4">Fig. S1</ext-link>) and as previously described (Matsumoto et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Linear ubiquitin-specific immunoblotting indicated that high levels of linear ubiquitinated proteins were produced upon LUBAC expression (Fig. 5 a) and that ASC was detected as multi-laddered and high molecular weight bands in the linear ubiquitin immunoprecipitations (IPs), suggesting that ASC is a LUBAC substrate (Fig. 5 a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>In addition, NEMO was also detected in the linear ubiquitin IP (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>S1) consistent with previous results (Tokunaga et al., 2009), whereas AIM2 and NLRP3 showed no linear ubiquitination (Fig. 5 a), demonstrating the substrate selectivity of LUBAC-mediated linear ubiquitination in 293T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the E3-ligase activity in cells co-expressing different combinations of the WT or E3 ligase-defective “cs” mutants of HOIP and HOIL-1L—which have cysteine to serine point mutations at conserved residues of the RING domains in the C-terminal RBR region (Kirisako et al., 2006; Inn et al., 2011; Stieglitz et al., 2012)—revealed that the E3 ligase activities of both HOIP and HOIL-1L were required for the efficient linear ubiquitination of ASC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Specifically, expression of the HOIL-1L cs mutant markedly reduced levels of ASC linear ubiquitination, and expression of the HOIP cs mutant led to undetectable levels of ASC linear ubiquitination (Fig. 5 b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Linear ubiquitination does not appear to lead to the degradation of ASC by the proteasome because inhibition of the proteasome with MG132 did not affect levels of total or linear ubiquitinated ASC (Fig. 5 c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Consistently, endogenous ASC protein levels were comparable in WT and HOIL-1L−/− cell lysates (Fig. 4 f; and Fig. 6, a and b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>These data are consistent with the presumed nondegradative effect of linear ubiquitination on the Nemo and Rip1 substrates (Iwai and Tokunaga, 2009; Tokunaga et al., 2009), and indicate that both the HOIP and HOIL-1L E3 ligase activities are required for the efficient linear ubiquitination of ASC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>ASC is linear ubiquitinated by LUBAC in 293T cells and in vitro. (a) Flag-tagged ASC, AIM2, or NLRP3 were cotransfected with HOIL-1L-HA and myc-HOIP into 293T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Linear ubiquitinated proteins were immunoprecipitated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>WCL (whole cell lysate) or immunoprecipitates (IP Lin Ub) were immunoblotted for Flag and linear ubiquitin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>(b) 293T cells were transfected with a panel of WT HOIL-1L-HA and Flag-HOIP or RBR E3 ligase domain cysteine to serine point mutants (cs) and probed by linear ubiquitin IP for ASC-V5, HA, and Flag as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>(c) Transfected 293T cells were treated for 6 h with 20 µM MG132 or an equivalent volume of DMSO before lysates were collected and immunoprecipitated with linear ubiquitin antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitates were probed for linear ubiquitin, Flag, and ubiquitin as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>(d) Bacterially purified GST-CoZi wt and rre proteins were incubated with lysates from 293T cells transfected with ASC-Flag, HOIL-1L-HA, and myc-HOIP or vector control plasmids (left, input). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Proteins that were pulled down by WT or rre mutant GST-CoZi were probed for linear ubiquitin or Flag by immunoblotting (right, GST-Cozi PD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>(e) ASC-Flag and NLRP3-Flag were purified from 293T lysates in a nondenaturing high salt buffer (500 mM NaCl) and combined as indicated with E1 (Ube1), E2 (UbcH5c), and LUBAC (HOIL-1L/HOIP) purified from bacteria in a linear ubiquitination reaction that was incubated for 18 h at 37°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Reactions were stopped by the addition of loading dye and immunoblotted for Flag. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Membranes were then stripped and reprobed for linear ubiquitin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>(f) Deubiquitinase treatment of linear ubiquitin immunoprecipitates from 293T cell lysates overexpressing HOIL-1L-HA, myc-HOIP, and ASC-V5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Reactions were immunoblotted for linear ubiquitin and V5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Control purified ubiquitin chains were incubated in parallel in deubiquitinase reactions that were immunoblotted with a linkage nonspecific antibody against ubiquitin (Ub). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>All data are representative of a minimum of three independent experiments. * indicates unmodified size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Protein size markers are indicated in kD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Endogenous mouse ASC is linear ubiquitinated in BMDMs. (a) WT BMDMs were untreated or primed with LPS overnight and stimulated with nigericin for 2 h before IP with a linear ubiquitin-specific antibody in 5M urea denaturing conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitates (IP Lin Ub) and whole cell lysates (WCL) were immunoblotted for ASC and linear ubiquitin (Lin Ub). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>(b) WT and HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs were primed with LPS overnight and stimulated with nigericin for 2 h before IP with an ASC-specific antibody and extensive washing in high salt buffer (500 mM NaCl). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitates and WCLs were immunoblotted for ASC and linear ubiquitin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>(c) WT BMDMs were primed with LPS overnight and stimulated with nigericin for 2 h before IP with a linear ubiquitin-specific antibody or an equivalent amount of control human antibody in 5M urea denaturing conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitates and WCL were immunoblotted for linear ubiquitin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>(d) WCL extracts from lysates in c were immunoblotted for ubiquitin with a linkage nonspecific antibody (Ub). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>All data are representative of two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Protein size markers are indicated in kD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig6"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In a second method for testing whether ASC is a LUBAC substrate, we purified linear ubiquitinated proteins from transfected 293T lysates with a bacterially produced GST fusion to the coiled zipper (CoZi) domain of NEMO that has been shown to specifically bind to both K63 and linear ubiquitin chains (Komander et al., 2009; Rahighi et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>In parallel, a GST-CoZi mutant fusion containing the R309A, R312A, E313A (rre) mutant, which cannot bind to linear ubiquitin chains but is capable of binding to K63-linked ubiquitin chains in vitro (Komander et al., 2009), was included as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Consistent with the linear ubiquitin IPs, the GST-CoZi purification pulled down ASC-Flag with multi-laddered high molecular weights in a LUBAC expression dependent manner, whereas the GST-CoZi rre mutant did not (Fig. 5 d), further supporting the LUBAC-mediated linear ubiquitination of ASC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Moreover, ASC linear ubiquitination was exclusively detected when HOIL-1L and HOIP were coexpressed, indicating that the linear ubiquitination of ASC is LUBAC-dependent (Fig. 5 d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>In a third method, an in vitro ubiquitination assay also showed that HOIP-HOIL-1L co-purified from a bacterial expression system specifically ubiquitinated ASC-Flag protein to levels that were comparable to the previously identified Nemo substrate (Tokunaga et al., 2009; Fig. 5 e), indicating that the LUBAC, E1, and E2 enzymes are sufficient for the linear ubiquitination of ASC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>When NLRP3-Flag was included as a control, no detectable in vitro linear ubiquitination of NLRP3 was observed under the same conditions (Fig. 5 e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In a fourth assay, linear ubiquitin immunoprecipitates were treated with the linear linkage-specific deubiquitinase Otulin, or the K63 linkage-specific deubiquitinase AMSH, to determine whether the ubiquitin chains on ASC were simply linear linkage or a mixture of K63 and linear linkages, which has previously been reported for other LUBAC substrates (Emmerich et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Only the Otulin treatment reduced high molecular weight ASC, whereas the AMSH treatment had no effect (Fig. 5 f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Lastly, in a fifth assay, the linear ubiquitin IP of BMDM lysates indicated that overall linear ubiquitin levels increased in WT BMDMs upon NLRP3 stimulation but were reduced in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs, whereas total ubiquitin levels remained the same (Fig. 6, a–d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Linear ubiquitin IP from WT BMDMs in 5M urea buffer precipitated the high molecular weight ASC protein, which was enhanced by NLRP3 stimulation (Fig. 6 a), indicating that endogenous ASC is linear ubiquitinated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, levels of total linear ubiquitin and the linear ubiquitinated ASC were considerably reduced in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs under NLRP3 stimulation conditions when compared with those in WT BMDMs (Fig. 6 b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these results demonstrate that ASC is a specific substrate of LUBAC in overexpression and endogenous conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Role of HOIL-1L in NLRP3-induced IL-1β production and inflammation in vivo </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Previous reports of the MDP-induced peritonitis mouse model (Bruey et al., 2007; Pan et al., 2007; Shenoy et al., 2012) have demonstrated that NOD2, a cytosolic PRR in the NLR family, is required for NF-κB–mediated IL-6 production, whereas NLRP3 is required for IL-1β secretion and neutrophil recruitment in i.p. cavity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Thus, we tested whether HOIL-1L was important for proinflammatory cytokine production and neutrophil recruitment in the MDP-induced peritonitis mouse model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>As expected, WT mice had increased IL-6 and IL-1β production and neutrophil recruitment to the IP cavity after injection with MDP (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, IL-1β production and neutrophil recruitment were significantly reduced in HOIL-1L−/− mice compared with WT mice, whereas IL-6 production was similar in WT and HOIL-1L−/− mice (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that HOIL-1L is required for NLRP3-dependent IL-1β production and neutrophil recruitment, but not for NOD2-dependent IL-6 production, in MDP-induced peritonitis in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L is required for MDP-induced peritonitis in vivo. WT and HOIL-1L−/− mice were injected i.p. with PBS or MDP to induce peritonitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>5 h later, IP wash fluid was analyzed for IL-1β (a) and IL-6 (b) levels by ELISA and infiltrating Ly6G/CD11b double-positive neutrophils (c and d) were quantified by flow cytometry (biological n = 8 from three independent experiments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>All data are presented as the mean ± SEM. *, P &lt; 0.00015 by a Student’s t test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig7"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>We also examined the role of HOIL-1L in an LPS-induced systemic inflammation mouse model in vivo, which is dependent on several inflammatory signaling molecules including TLR4, NLRP3, ASC, and IL-1β (McNamara et al., 1993; Mariathasan et al., 2004, 2006; Joosten et al., 2010; Kayagaki et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>The WT control mice rapidly succumbed to LPS challenge beginning at 24 h after injection and continuing until 72 h after injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>The WT mice also showed high levels of inflammation as measured by hematoxylin, eosin, and apoptotic marker Annexin V staining of spleen sections at 24 h after injection (Fig. 8, a and b), indicating that excessive inflammation contributed to the deaths of the WT mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>In contrast, 100% of the HOIL-1L−/− mice survived LPS challenge despite significant weight loss (Fig. 8, a and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L−/− mice also had significantly lower serum IL-1β levels and Annexin-V staining of splenic sections at 24 h after injection (Fig. 8, b and d), suggesting the HOIL-1L−/− mice had reduced inflammatory responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Because NLRP3−/− and ASC−/− mice are also resistant to LPS in this mouse model (Mariathasan et al., 2004, 2006), the role of HOIL-1L in NLRP3 inflammasome activation characterized here may also contribute to the survival of HOIL-1L−/− mice in the LPS-induced lethal inflammation model in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L is required for lethal inflammation upon LPS challenge in vivo. (a) Survival curve for WT or HOIL-1L−/− mice challenged with 30 mg/kg LPS (n = 10, combined from three independent experiments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>(b) Apoptotic marker Annexin-V (red) and hematoxylin-eosin (H&amp;E)–stained spleen sections from mice in a, sacrificed 24 h after LPS injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Images are representative of three analyzed mice for each condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Bar, 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>(c) Weight curve of mice from a. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>(d) Serum IL-1β levels from WT and HOIL-1L−/− mice sacrificed 24 h after LPS injection were determined by ELISA (n = 4, combined from 2 independent experiments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as the mean ± SEM. *, P &lt; 0.0001 by a Log-rank Mantel-Cox test; **, P = 0.0015; ***, P &lt; 0.008 by a Student’s t test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JEM_20132486_Fig8"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Here, we demonstrate that HOIL-1L is specifically required for NLRP3 inflammasome-dependent IL-1β secretion in BMDMs independently of NF-κB activation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Mechanistically, the assembly of the NLRP3/ASC inflammasome and linear ubiquitination of the novel LUBAC substrate, ASC, both require HOIL-1L expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>The loss of these functions in HOIL-1L−/− mice results in resistance to MDP-induced peritonitis and contributes to survival upon LPS-induced systemic inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This is the first demonstration that linear ubiquitination is required for NLRP3/ASC-dependent inflammasome activation, thus expanding the role of LUBAC as an innate immune regulator. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>This work is also the first to compare the role of HOIL-1L in MEF and macrophage cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Our data indicate that HOIL-1L is critical for NF-κB activation in MEF cells, consistent with the literature (Fig. 1; Tokunaga et al., 2009; Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>However, this activity is cell type specific because HOIL-1L is not required for NF-κB activation or NF-κB–dependent gene expression in BMDMs (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>1 and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>These observations are likely clinically relevant because patients lacking functional HOIL-1L expression had an IL-6 response to LPS that was equivalent to control patient levels when whole blood cells were stimulated (Boisson et al., 2012), which is similar to our results in BMDMs (Fig. 2, b and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>However, IL-6 production was attenuated in fibroblast cells of HOIL-1L–deficient patients (Boisson et al., 2012) similarly to our results with HOIL-1L−/− MEFs (Fig. 1 c), indicating that the tissue-specific functions for HOIL-1L also exist in humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>Because HOIL-1L–deficient patients were prone to pyogenic bacterial infections (Boisson et al., 2012), we predict that a defect likely exists in NLRP3 inflammasome assembly in these patients, similar to what we have observed in BMDMs from HOIL-1L−/− mice, leading to ineffective innate immunity upon exposure to bacterial pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>In addition to cell type–specific functions for HOIL-1L, the LUBAC subunit Sharpin may also have tissue-specific roles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that Sharpincpdm MEFs (Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011; Tokunaga et al., 2011) and BMDMs (Zak et al., 2011) have defects in NF-κB signaling, yet skin cells from Sharpincpdm mice have elevated NF-κB activation (Liang, 2011; Liang et al., 2011), suggesting that Sharpin has unique functions in skin cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In fact, the dermatitis phenotype observed in Sharpincpdm mice is reversed by NF-κB inhibitor treatment (Liang et al., 2011) or knockout of the TNF gene (Gerlach et al., 2011), further supporting cell type–dependent roles for Sharpin. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Our microarray data results indicated that expression of several genes was up-regulated in HOIL-1L−/− BMDM relative to WT BMDM in response to LPS and TNF stimulation (Fig. 2 a and Table S2), suggesting that HOIL-1L is perhaps a negative regulator of LPS- and TNF-mediated signaling in BMDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>It is possible that our list of genes for which transcription levels are significantly different in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs compared with WT BMDMs includes those that HOIL-1L may directly regulate as a potential transcription factor (Tatematsu et al., 1998; Tokunaga et al., 1998; Tables S1 and S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>However, the majority of genes in the list are uncharacterized, making the relevance of HOIL-1L–mediated regulation of their gene expression unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>A previous microarray compared WT and Sharpincpdm BMDMs upon stimulation of TLR2 with bacterial lipoprotein Pam3CSK4 and found a significant defect in NF-κB–dependent transcription in Sharpincpdm BMDMs (Zak et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Because HOIL-1L−/− mice do not exhibit the severe dermatitis phenotypes of the Sharpincpdm mice (Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011), it is not surprising to find that these LUBAC members have different roles in various signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>In contrast to our observation that IL-6 secretion is not impaired in HOIL-1L−/− mice in response to MDP (Fig. 7), a previous study reported that Sharpincpdm BMDMs have a defect in MDP-dependent IL-6 secretion, although an in vivo peritonitis model was not used in this study (Damgaard et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>This difference could also be due to the use of lipid modified MDP (L18-MDP) in the previous study, or it could indicate that HOIL-1L and Sharpin may have different roles in NOD2 stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Additional reports that LUBAC is recruited to the NOD2 receptor complex in response to MDP suggest that this recruitment requires XIAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>However, the role of LUBAC was not directly tested in these studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>In addition, the defects in XIAP-deficient cells and Otulin-expressing cells could be due to LUBAC-independent functions of XIAP or difference of nonmacrophage cell types used in these studies (Damgaard et al., 2013; Keusekotten et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Further study is necessary to resolve the detailed roles of LUBAC in gene expression regulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Ubiquitination is a posttranslational modification that creates versatility in intracellular signaling. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Specifically, K63 linkage is exclusively responsible for ubiquitin-mediated nondegradative signaling functions and linear linkage is crucial in various receptor and PRR pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Our discovery of ASC as a LUBAC substrate is related to a previous report that ASC is ubiquitinated upon AIM2 stimulation (Shi et al., 2012), although K63-linked ubiquitination was reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Because K63 antibodies can cross-detect linear ubiquitination (Matsumoto et al., 2012) and the K63 E3 ligase or ASC lysine targets were not identified, it may be possible that the ubiquitination in this previous study was actually linear ubiquitination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Ubiquitination of NLRP3 has also been reported (Lopez-Castejon et al., 2013; Py et al., 2013); however, this ubiquitination is not likely to be linear because the N-terminal His-tagging of ubiquitin used in this study would eliminate the possibility of a linear methionine-to-glycine linkage (Gerlach et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Previous characterization of Nemo as a LUBAC substrate used 293T overexpression systems, reporter assays, and in vitro assays (Tokunaga et al., 2009, 2011; Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Our results demonstrate that ASC is a LUBAC substrate using similar assays, with additional endogenous evidence in BMDMs (Figs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>5 and 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Previous mapping of the Nemo protein led to the identification of two lysine targets for LUBAC, which were functionally required for NF-κB activation in MEF cells (Tokunaga et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>We also expect that two linear ubiquitination sites may exist on ASC based on the results from our deubiquitination assay (Fig. 5 f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Because Otulin can more efficiently cleave linear ubiquitin linkages than ubiquitin-substrate linkages, the two higher molecular weight ASC bands that remained after Otulin treatment (Fig. 5 f) may correspond to two direct ubiquitination sites on ASC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>However, our attempts to map the ubiquitinated residues of ASC indicate that mutagenesis of the lysines in ASC affects protein–protein interactions independently of linear ubiquitination, making finer evaluation of the role of ASC linear ubiquitination for inflammasome activation difficult. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, as shown in the Nemo linear ubiquitination studies (Tokunaga et al., 2009, 2011; Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011), the levels of endogenous linear ubiquitination of Nemo seem to be very low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Thus, additional technical advances are necessary to define the specific roles of linear ubiquitination in intracellular signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Our data supports the hypothesis that each type of inflammasome has unique regulatory mechanisms, although the detailed mechanisms for these events have not been completely described. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>In particular, the NLRP3 inflammasome is distinct from other inflammasome sensors because it responds to a wide variety of triggers instead of one or two specific ligands like AIM2 or NLRC4 (Schroder and Tschopp, 2010; Franchi et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Although mitochondrial damage is a common source for the potential NLRP3 stimulating signals, including mitochondrial ROS, oxidized mitochondrial DNA, and mitochondrial cardiolipin (Nakahira et al., 2011; Shimada et al., 2012; Iyer et al., 2013), the molecular events preceding the NLRP3/ASC interaction are not well characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>Thus, it remains unknown what triggers HOIL-1L–containing LUBAC to linear ubiquitinated ASC upon NLRP3 stimulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>A recent report identified the phosphorylation of ASC as a trigger for the NLRP3 and AIM2 inflammasomes, although it is not clear whether this phosphorylation event affects the ubiquitination of ASC (Hara et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Because the molecular events triggering caspase-1 cleavage are also unclear, the mechanisms of NLRP3 activation must be further defined to characterize which events happen first. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, our work has added linear ubiquitination to the sequence of events that precede NLRP3/ASC inflammasome assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>The resistance of HOIL-1L−/− mice to lethal inflammation (Fig. 8) emphasizes the role of HOIL-1L as a critical regulator of inflammation in vivo despite the absence of dermatitis phenotype that is observed in the Sharpincpdm mice (Gerlach et al., 2011; Ikeda et al., 2011; Tokunaga et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Given that the accurate mechanisms responsible for the symptoms of lethal inflammation in mouse models are not fully understood (Kayagaki et al., 2013; Seok et al., 2013), it is likely that HOIL-1L−/− mice are resistant to death because of complex multifaceted roles of HOIL-1L in inflammation, but not due to its action in a single pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Thus, the overall survival of the HOIL-1L−/− mice is likely due to a combination of various roles of HOIL-1L in different pathways, including NLRP3 activation, NF-κB–dependent TNF, IL-1β, CD40, and NOD2 receptor signaling (Haas et al., 2009; Iwai and Tokunaga, 2009; Tokunaga et al., 2009; Zak et al., 2011; Damgaard et al., 2012), protein kinase C activity (Nakamura et al., 2006), RIG-I activation (Inn et al., 2011), and transcriptional regulation as a DNA-binding protein (Tatematsu et al., 1998; Tokunaga et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the HOIL-1L−/− mice never displayed any behavioral symptoms of LPS-induced lethal inflammation (lethargy or shivering) even though they had considerably more weight loss as WT mice (Fig. 8 b), which suggests that perhaps these two sets of symptoms have independent mechanisms, with lethargy and fever caused by HOIL-1L–dependent inflammation and weight loss being due to an as yet unidentified factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The HOIL-1L–dependent assembly of the NLRP3 inflammasome and linear ubiquitination of ASC likely contribute to the resistance of the HOIL-1L−/− mice upon LPS challenge because mice lacking functional NLRP3 inflammasomes or ASC are also resistant to LPS challenge (Mariathasan et al., 2004, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the MDP-induced peritonitis model confirmed that HOIL-1L is indeed important for NLRP3 inflammasome activation in vivo (Fig. 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>Altogether, our data indicates that the regulation of inflammasome activation is achieved through complex ubiquitin linkage codes that in turn may have distinct consequences in response to stimuli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Our work has identified new members of a growing network of ubiquitin-mediated regulation, which is an increasingly appreciated mechanism for PRR signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title/><sec><title><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>WT C57BL/6 mice were purchased from Charles River. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L−/− mice have been previously described and were bred as homozygotes (Inn et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>For BMDM isolation, 6–8-wk-old male mice were sacrificed and BM cells were frozen as previously described (Marim et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>For MDP experiments, 7–10-wk-old female age-matched mice were injected in the i.p. cavity with 1 mg MDP (Sigma-Aldrich) in 100 µl PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>5 h after injection, a 1-ml PBS wash of the i.p. cavity was collected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>Cells were pelleted from this wash for flow cytometry and supernatants were probed for cytokines by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>For sepsis experiments, 6–14-wk-old age-matched and sex-matched mice were injected in the i.p. cavity with 30 mg/kg ultrapure LPS (Escherichia coli 0111:B4; Sigma-Aldrich) suspended in PBS and animals were monitored twice daily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Mice were given DietGel 76A supplemental liquid food at the beginning of weight loss. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Mice were euthanized if they did not respond, were immobile, or lost &gt;25% body mass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>Survivors were euthanized 1 wk after the i.p. injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>For serum cytokine and spleen collection, animals were euthanized 24 h after i.p. injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>All animal protocols were performed in accordance with the approval of the USC Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>BMDM cell culture, lentivirus infection, and stimulation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>BM cells were thawed and plated at a density of 106/well of a 24-well plate in DMEM supplemented with 10% FCS, 100 U/ml penicillin, 100 µg/ml streptomycin, and 10% L929 culture supernatant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Cells were differentiated for 1 wk with a media change on day 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>For IP experiments, BMDMs were trypsinized and plated on 10-cm dishes on day 4 after thawing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Priming with 5 µg/ml LPS (E. coli 0127:B8; Sigma-Aldrich) was done overnight in fresh media on day 6 after thawing for all experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Stimulation with 10 µg/ml MDP (N-Acetylmuramyl-l-alanyl-d-isoflutamine hydrate; Sigma-Aldrich) was done for 1 h in DMEM followed by a 30-min pulse with 5 mM ATP (Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Stimulation with 10 µM Nigericin (Sigma-Aldrich) was done for 4 h (for caspase-1 cleavage and IL-1β secretion experiments) or 2 h (for IP and ASC foci experiments) in DMEM after overnight priming with 5 µg/ml LPS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Stimulation with 200 µg/ml silica or MSU (InvivoGen) was done during the last 8 h of the 11-h priming with LPS treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>Stimulation with dsDNA was done for 4 h after LPS priming by Lipofectamine 2000 (Life Technologies)–mediated transfection with pEGFP-N1 (Takara Bio Inc.) vector DNA at a ratio of 1.5 µg DNA to 2 µl lipofectamine per well of a 24-well plate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Cells were stimulated with flagellin by infection at MOI 300 with Ad5-Flagellin or Ad5 control adenoviruses for 24 h after LPS priming. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Cells were stimulated with L. pneumophila at MOI 1 or 10 for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Adenoviruses were a gift from S.-Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Chen (University of Southern California) and L. pneumophila stocks were a gift from F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>Shao (National Institute of Biological Sciences, Beijing, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Lentiviruses were produced in 293T cultured in DMEM supplemented with 10% FCS, 100 U/ml penicillin, and 100 µg/ml streptomycin using the pCDH-CMV-MCS-EF1-puro system (System Biosciences) and standard calcium phosphate transfection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>BMDMs were infected with lentivirus on day 3 or 4 after thawing in 24-well plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>BMDMs were infected by centrifugation for 30 min at 2,000 rpm in fresh media containing 8 µg/ml polybrene and 60–100 µl of virus stock per well as determined by titration of lentiviruses for equal protein expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>The inoculum was exchanged for fresh media after overnight incubation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>Stimulations of lentivirus-infected BMDM were performed 7 d after thawing cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Microarray hybridization and analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>RNA was isolated from BMDMs cultured in 10-cm dishes and treated with media alone, 10 ng/ml LPS, or 1 ng/ml TNF for 4 h on day 7 of differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>RNA was prepared by an RNeasy kit (QIAGEN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>For each condition, 2 separate 10-cm dishes were used to generate 2 separate RNA preparations, n = 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>8 × 60k array hybridizations (Agilent Technologies) were performed by UCLA Clinical Microarray Core according to standard protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Data were analyzed using the Genomics Suite (6.4; Partek). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>We used the RMA algorithm for data normalization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>Thresholds for selecting significant genes were set at twofold or greater and FDR P &lt; 0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>Genes met both criteria simultaneously were considered as significant changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>NF-κB pathway analyses were performed using Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (Ingenuity Systems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>The complete microarray dataset is accessible at NCBI GEO (<ext-link ext-link-type="NCBI:geo" xlink:href="GSE57180">GSE57180</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>RNA was isolated from BMDM or MEF cells with 1 ml Tri Reagent (Sigma-Aldrich) and treated with 1 U RNase free DNase I (Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>cDNA was generated from 250 ng of total RNA (iScript; Bio-Rad Laboratories), diluted 1:10 with nuclease-free water, and quantified by real-time qPCR using the iQ SYBR Green Supermix kit (Bio-Rad Laboratories), according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Reactions were cycled and analyzed on a CFX96 PCR machine (Bio-Rad Laboratories). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>Cycling conditions were a single step at 95°C for 5 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 s and 60°C for 30 s, followed by melt curve analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>Primer sequences are summarized in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1" id="supp5">Table S3</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>Threshold cycle (Ct) ratios were determined by normalizing to 18S RNA and a WT control sample using the following equation: relative expression = 100*2−(ΔΔCt), where ΔΔCt = (Ctgene − Ct18S) − (ΔCtWT unstimulated). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>Cytokine quantification. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>Cytokines in cell culture supernatants were quantified by mouse IL-6 (BD) and mouse IL-1β ELISA kits (eBioscience). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>IL-1β levels in mouse sera were quantified using a custom multiplexing Milliplex MAP mouse cytokine assay (Millipore) and analyzed on a Bio-Plex plate reader using Bio-Plex Manager software (Bio-Rad Laboratories) at the USC Norris Immune Monitoring Core. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>Cell pellets from mouse IP washes were stained with Ly6G-PE and cd11b-APC antibodies (BioLegend) at a dilution of 1:250. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry was performed on a FACS Canto II (BD) followed by analysis using FlowJo software (Tree Star). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>IP. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>293T cells were transfected with cesium chloride purified preparations DNA plasmids by PEI as previously described (Inn et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Cell lysates were collected 24 h after transfection in linear ubiquitination IP buffer (LUIP: 5M Urea, 135 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-100, 1.5 mM MgCl2, 2 mM N-ethyl maleimide, and complete protease inhibitor cocktail [Roche]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>For BMDM experiments, cells were thawed in non-TC–treated dishes and cultured for 7 d in the presence of 10% L929. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>Cells were plated on TC-coated 10-cm dishes on day 4 after thawing and one dish was used per condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>Cell lysates were collected in IP buffer (1% NP-40, 50 mM Tris, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate, and complete protease inhibitor cocktail [Roche]) and sonicated for 20 s at 10%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>Lysates were precleared and incubated with antibody overnight at 4°C (IP) or room temperature (LUIP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>For LUIP, 0.25 µg of antibody was used (Genentech) per 10-cm dish of cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>For BMDM IPs, 2 µg rabbit antibody was used for ASC (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>Protein A/G beads were incubated with lysate/antibody mixtures for 2 h before washing 3 times in IP buffer or 2 times in LUIP buffer followed by 2 PBS washes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>IP beads were boiled in 2× Laemmli dye for 10 min and LUIP beads were incubated at 70°C for 10 min in LDS dye (Invitrogen) supplemented with fresh 5 mM DTT to elute protein complexes for Western blotting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>Cell lysates were collected in RIPA buffer (IP buffer + 0.1% SDS) and quantified by Bradford protein assay (Thermo Fisher Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>Proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to PVDF membrane (Bio-Rad Laboratories) by semi-dry transfer at 25V for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>For linear ubiquitin Western blots, SDS-PAGE was transferred to nitrocellulose (Bio-Rad Laboratories) by wet transfer at 4°C for 2 h at 30V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>All membranes were blocked in 5% milk in PBST and probed overnight with indicated antibodies in 3% BSA, except for the linear ubiquitin antibody, which was incubated at room temperature for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>Primary antibodies included: mouse IκBα (1:1,000; Cell Signaling Technology), mouse IL-1β (1:1,000; R&amp;D), mouse caspase-1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), actin (clone C4; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), ASC (1:1,000; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), human HOIP (1:250; Acris), V5 (1:2,000; Life Technologies), Flag (1:2,000; Sigma-Aldrich), and HA (1:2,000; Covance). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>Antibodies against HOIL-1L have been previously described (Tokunaga and Iwai, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>The linear ubiquitin antibody was a gift from Genentech and has been previously characterized in detail (Matsumoto et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>In brief, samples for linear ubiquitin immunoblots were separated by SDS-PAGE and transferred to nitrocellulose by wet transfer at 4°C, 30 V, for 2 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>Membranes were blocked in 5% milk in PBST, probed with primary antibody (1:2,000) for 1 h at room temperature, washed, probed with TrueBlot-HRP (1:300; Thermo Fisher Scientific), and then developed with ECL (Thermo Fisher Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>For all other antibodies, appropriate HRP-conjugated secondary antibodies were incubated on membranes and bands were developed with ECL reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and imaged on an LAS-4000 imager (Fuji). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>For IP with Western blots, the Clean Blot HRP secondary (1:300; Thermo Fisher Scientific) was substituted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>FAM-YVAD-FLICA (FLICA; ImmunoChemistry Technologies) was reconstituted and diluted according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>FLICA was added to cells in DMEM containing 10 µg/µl MDP and 10% L929. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>300 µl of this solution was added per well of a 24-well plate containing BMDM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>After 2 h, ATP was added to the media at a concentration of 2.5 mM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>30 min later, the supernatant was removed and the cells were washed three times with PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>The fixative provided by the manufacturer was added to the cells for 15 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>For antibody staining, cells were fixed with methanol, washed three times, and permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 for 10 min at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>Blocking buffer (3% BSA in PBS) was applied for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated with anti–Caspase-1 (1:100; Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.), anti-linear ubiquitin (1F11/3F5/Y102L, 1 µg/ml; Genentech), anti-ASC (AL177, 1:100; Enzo), and/or anti-HA (MMS-101P, 1:500; Covance) for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed three times in PBS and incubated with Alexa Fluor–coupled secondary antibodies (1:500; Invitrogen) for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed three times in PBS and incubated with Hoechst stain (1:1,000; Molecular Probes) for 10 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Cells were mounted in ProLong Gold Antifade media and imaged with a confocal microscope (LSM510; Carl Zeiss) equipped with an EC Plan-Apochromat 63×/1.4 oil objective or a Plan-Apochromat 100×/1.4 oil DIC objective. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>Images were processed using LSM 510 Version 4.2 SP1 acquisition software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Z-stack images were taken with a Plan-Apochromat 100×/1.4 oil DIC objective. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Immunohistochemistry. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>Spleens were fixed in 10% formalin and embedded in paraffin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Sectioning, hematoxylin, eosin, and Annexin V (1:50; Novus Biologicals) staining were performed by the USC Immunohistochemistry Core facility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>Images were acquired on a microscope (IX71; Olympus) using the 10× (Plan C 10×/0.25 PhC; Olympus) and 40× (SLC Plan F1 40×/0.55 Ph2; Olympus) objectives as indicated with a Digital Sight DS-Fi1 camera (Nikon). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>GST-CoZi pulldown. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>The CoZi domain of human Nemo (Lee et al., 2012) was cloned into the BamHI and XhoI sites of the pGEX-6P-1 vector and the R309A, R312A, E313A triple mutant was generated through standard serial PCR with mutant oligos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>BL21 bacteria were transformed with WT and rre Cozi pGEX plasmids and protein expression was induced with 0.3 mM IPTG when cells reached OD600 0.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>After 90 min, cells were pelleted and lysed in HEPES-CHAPS buffer (20 mM Hepes, pH 8.0, 200 mM NaCl, and 15 mM CHAPS) supplemented with a complete protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>After sonication and removal of the pellet, lysates were precleared for 1 h with Sepharose beads (GE Healthcare) and then incubated with GST4b beads (GE Healthcare) for 2 h at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Beads were washed extensively in Hepes-CHAPS buffer and then IP buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>In parallel, lysates from 293T cells transfected with pIRES-ASC-3xFlag, pCDNA3.1-HOIL-1L-HA, and pCDNA3.1-Myc-HOIP plasmids (or empty vector controls) as indicated were collected in IP buffer supplemented with complete protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche) and 2 mM N-ethylmaleimide (NEM; Sigma-Aldrich) and precleared for 1 h with GST4b beads (GE Healthcare). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Finally, 293T lysates were incubated with WT or rre Cozi GST beads overnight at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>Beads were washed in IP buffer and boiled in 2× Laemmli dye for Western blotting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>In vitro linear ubiquitination assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>ASC-Flag and NLRP3-Flag were purified from 293T cells by M2 beads (Sigma-Aldrich) in high salt buffer (500 mM NaCl, 1% NP-40, and 50 mM Tris, pH 8.0) and eluted with Flag peptide (Sigma-Aldrich), followed by 10 kD MWCO dialysis in excess TBS overnight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L-6xHIS and HOIP-6xHIS were cloned into the pET-duet-1 vector, coexpressed in BL21 DE3 RIPL (Agilent Technologies) bacteria, and purified from cultures grown in the presence of 0.2 mM ZnCl2 and 0.5 mM IPTG at 16°C for 24 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>Cells were lysed in native buffer (50 mM Tris, PH 8.0, and 100 mM NaCl) and HOIL-1L/HOIP were co-purified on cobalt beads (Thermo Fisher Scientific) with 150 mM imidazole elution and overnight dialysis in lysis buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>HOIL-1L/HOIP (LUBAC) purification preps were stored at 4°C and never frozen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>E1 (Ube1), E2 (UbcH5c), and ubiquitin were purchased from Boston Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>In vitro linear ubiquitination assays contained 200 ng E1, 400 ng E2, 1 µg HOIL-1L/HOIP-6xHIS purification prep, 20 mM Tris, pH 7.5, 5 mM DTT, 5 mM MgCl2, 2 mM MgATP (Boston Biochem), 10 µg ubiquitin, and 0.5 µg purified Flag-tagged substrate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>Deubiquitinase assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Beads from one linear ubiquitin IP from 293T cells expressing HOIL-1L-HA, myc-HOIP, and ASC-V5 were split into three tubes that were treated with reaction buffer (20 mM Hepes, pH 8.0, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgCl2, and 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol), 0.8 µM Otulin (Boston Biochem), or 0.04 mg/ml AMSH (Boston Biochem) at 30°C for 1 h in a total volume of 25 µl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Samples were diluted to 1× LDS loading dye (Life Technologies) and analyzed by Western blotting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>All experiments were performed three times and a representative experiment is presented here, except for BMDM IPs, which were performed on lysates combined from several mice in two separate experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>For experiments with statistical analysis, a two-tailed Student’s t test and p-values of &lt;0.05 were considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>Online supplemental material. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>Table S1 lists transcripts with a lower abundance in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs and Table S2 lists transcripts with a higher abundance in HOIL-1L−/− BMDMs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="358" pm="."><plain>Table S3 lists the primers used for qPCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="359" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="360" pm="."><plain>S1 shows immunoblot and IP controls for the linear ubiquitin antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="361" pm="."><plain>Video 1 shows the Z-stacks for Fig. 4 c. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="362" pm="."><plain>Online supplemental material is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1">http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20132486/DC1</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="363" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="364" pm="."><plain>Supplemental Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_211_7_1333__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_jem.20132486_JEM_20132486_sm.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="text" mime-subtype="plain" xlink:href="supp_jem.20132486_JEM_20132486_V1.mp4"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="365" pm="."><plain>We thank Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="366" pm="."><plain>Vishva Dixit (Genentech), Junying Yuan (Harvard Medical School), Si-Yi Chen (University of Southern California), Feng Shao (National Institute of Biological Sciences, Beijing, China), and Blossom Damania (University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill) for reagents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="367" pm="."><plain>We thank the USC Norris Comprehensive Cancer Center Beckman Center for Immune Monitoring for running the multiplex cytokine assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="368" pm="."><plain>We thank the USC Pathology Immunohistochemistry core for spleen sectioning and staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="369" pm="."><plain>We thank the Cell and Tissue Imaging Core of USC Research Center for Liver Diseases for providing microscopy services (National Institutes of Health grants P30 DK048522 and S10 RR022508). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="370" pm="."><plain>Finally, we thank all of J.J’.s laboratory members for their discussions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="371" pm="."><plain>This work was partly supported by 1F32AI096698 (M.A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="372" pm="."><plain>Rodgers); CA180779, CA082057, CA31363, CA115284, AI073099, AI083025, HL110609, GRL, Hastings Foundation, and Fletcher Jones Foundation (J.U. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="373" pm="."><plain>Jung); and CA156330 and AI029564 (J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="374" pm="."><plain>Ting). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="375" pm="."><plain>The authors declare no competing financial interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="376" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations used:BMDMBM-derived macrophageCoZicoiled zipperdsDNAdouble-stranded DNAFLICAFAM-YVAD-FMKIPimmunoprecipitationLUBAClinear ubiquitin assembly complexMDPmuramyl dipeptideMEFmouse embryonic fibroblastMSUmonosodium urate crystalsNZFNpl4 type-zinc-fingerPRRpattern recognition receptorqPCRquantitative PCRRBRRING between RINGUBLubiquitin like </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="bib1"><text><SENT sid="377" pm="."><plain>BoissonB.LaplantineE.PrandoC.GilianiS.IsraelssonE.XuZ.AbhyankarA.IsraëlL.Trevejo-NunezG.BogunovicD. 2012 Immunodeficiency, autoinflammation and amylopectinosis in humans with inherited HOIL-1 and LUBAC deficiency. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="378" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 13:1178–1186 10.1038/ni.245723104095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib2"><text><SENT sid="379" pm="."><plain>BrozP.von MoltkeJ.JonesJ.W.VanceR.E.MonackD.M. 2010 Differential requirement for Caspase-1 autoproteolysis in pathogen-induced cell death and cytokine processing. Cell Host Microbe. 8:471–483 10.1016/j.chom.2010.11.00721147462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib3"><text><SENT sid="380" pm="."><plain>BrueyJ.M.Bruey-SedanoN.LucianoF.ZhaiD.BalpaiR.XuC.KressC.L.Bailly-MaitreB.LiX.OstermanA. 2007 Bcl-2 and Bcl-XL regulate proinflammatory caspase-1 activation by interaction with NALP1. Cell. 129:45–56 10.1016/j.cell.2007.01.04517418785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib4"><text><SENT sid="381" pm="."><plain>BryanN.B.DorfleutnerA.RojanasakulY.StehlikC. 2009 Activation of inflammasomes requires intracellular redistribution of the apoptotic speck-like protein containing a caspase recruitment domain. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="382" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 182:3173–3182 10.4049/jimmunol.080236719234215 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib5"><text><SENT sid="383" pm="."><plain>DamgaardR.B.NachburU.YabalM.WongW.W.FiilB.K.KastirrM.RieserE.RickardJ.A.BankovackiA.PeschelC. 2012 The ubiquitin ligase XIAP recruits LUBAC for NOD2 signaling in inflammation and innate immunity. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="384" pm="."><plain>Cell. 46:746–758 10.1016/j.molcel.2012.04.01422607974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib6"><text><SENT sid="385" pm="."><plain>DamgaardR.B.FiilB.K.SpeckmannC.YabalM.zur StadtU.Bekker-JensenS.JostP.J.EhlS.MailandN.Gyrd-HansenM. 2013 Disease-causing mutations in the XIAP BIR2 domain impair NOD2-dependent immune signalling. EMBO Mol Med. 5:1278–1295 10.1002/emmm.20130309023818254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib7"><text><SENT sid="386" pm="."><plain>DostertC.PétrilliV.Van BruggenR.SteeleC.MossmanB.T.TschoppJ. 2008 Innate immune activation through Nalp3 inflammasome sensing of asbestos and silica. Science. 320:674–677 10.1126/science.115699518403674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib8"><text><SENT sid="387" pm="."><plain>EmmerichC.H.OrdureauA.StricksonS.ArthurJ.S.PedrioliP.G.KomanderD.CohenP. 2013 Activation of the canonical IKK complex by K63/M1-linked hybrid ubiquitin chains. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="388" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="389" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="390" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="391" pm="."><plain>USA. 110:15247–15252 10.1073/pnas.131471511023986494 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib9"><text><SENT sid="392" pm="."><plain>Fernandes-AlnemriT.YuJ.-W.DattaP.WuJ.AlnemriE.S. 2009 AIM2 activates the inflammasome and cell death in response to cytoplasmic DNA. Nature. 458:509–513 10.1038/nature0771019158676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib10"><text><SENT sid="393" pm="."><plain>FranchiL.Muñoz-PlanilloR.NúñezG. 2012 Sensing and reacting to microbes through the inflammasomes. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="394" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 13:325–332 10.1038/ni.223122430785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib11"><text><SENT sid="395" pm="."><plain>GerlachB.CordierS.M.SchmukleA.C.EmmerichC.H.RieserE.HaasT.L.WebbA.I.RickardJ.A.AndertonH.WongW.W.L. 2011 Linear ubiquitination prevents inflammation and regulates immune signalling. Nature. 471:591–596 10.1038/nature0981621455173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib12"><text><SENT sid="396" pm="."><plain>HaasT.L.EmmerichC.H.GerlachB.SchmukleA.C.CordierS.M.RieserE.FelthamR.VinceJ.WarnkenU.WengerT. 2009 Recruitment of the linear ubiquitin chain assembly complex stabilizes the TNF-R1 signaling complex and is required for TNF-mediated gene induction. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="397" pm="."><plain>Cell. 36:831–844 10.1016/j.molcel.2009.10.01320005846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib13"><text><SENT sid="398" pm="."><plain>HaraH.TsuchiyaK.KawamuraI.FangR.Hernandez-CuellarE.ShenY.MizuguchiJ.SchweighofferE.TybulewiczV.MitsuyamaM. 2013 Phosphorylation of the adaptor ASC acts as a molecular switch that controls the formation of speck-like aggregates and inflammasome activity. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="399" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 14:1247–1255 10.1038/ni.274924185614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib14"><text><SENT sid="400" pm="."><plain>HornungV.BauernfeindF.HalleA.SamstadE.O.KonoH.RockK.L.FitzgeraldK.A.LatzE. 2008 Silica crystals and aluminum salts activate the NALP3 inflammasome through phagosomal destabilization. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="401" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 9:847–856 10.1038/ni.163118604214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib15"><text><SENT sid="402" pm="."><plain>IkedaF.DeribeY.L.SkånlandS.S.StieglitzB.GrabbeC.Franz-WachtelM.van WijkS.J.L.GoswamiP.NagyV.TerzicJ. 2011 SHARPIN forms a linear ubiquitin ligase complex regulating NF-κB activity and apoptosis. Nature. 471:637–641 10.1038/nature0981421455181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib16"><text><SENT sid="403" pm="."><plain>InnK.-S.GackM.U.TokunagaF.ShiM.WongL.-Y.IwaiK.JungJ.U. 2011 Linear ubiquitin assembly complex negatively regulates RIG-I- and TRIM25-mediated type I interferon induction. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="404" pm="."><plain>Cell. 41:354–365 10.1016/j.molcel.2010.12.02921292167 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib17"><text><SENT sid="405" pm="."><plain>IwaiK.TokunagaF. 2009 Linear polyubiquitination: a new regulator of NF-κB activation. EMBO Rep. 10:706–713 10.1038/embor.2009.14419543231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib18"><text><SENT sid="406" pm="."><plain>IyerS.S.HeQ.JanczyJ.R.ElliottE.I.ZhongZ.OlivierA.K.SadlerJ.J.Knepper-AdrianV.HanR.QiaoL. 2013 Mitochondrial cardiolipin is required for Nlrp3 inflammasome activation. Immunity. 39:311–323 10.1016/j.immuni.2013.08.00123954133 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib19"><text><SENT sid="407" pm="."><plain>JoostenL.A.B.Van De VeerdonkF.L.VonkA.G.BoermanO.C.KeuterM.FantuzziG.VerschuerenI.Van Der PollT.DinarelloC.A.KullbergB.-J. 2010 Differential susceptibility to lethal endotoxaemia in mice deficient in IL-1α, IL-1β or IL-1 receptor type I. APMIS. 118:1000–1007 10.1111/j.1600-0463.2010.02684.x21091783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib20"><text><SENT sid="408" pm="."><plain>JulianaC.Fernandes-AlnemriT.KangS.FariasA.QinF.AlnemriE.S. 2012 Non-transcriptional priming and deubiquitination regulate NLRP3 inflammasome activation. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="409" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="410" pm="."><plain>Chem. 287:36617–36622 10.1074/jbc.M112.40713022948162 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib21"><text><SENT sid="411" pm="."><plain>KayagakiN.WongM.T.StoweI.B.RamaniS.R.GonzalezL.C.Akashi-TakamuraS.MiyakeK.ZhangJ.LeeW.P.MuszyńskiA. 2013 Noncanonical inflammasome activation by intracellular LPS independent of TLR4. Science. 341:1246–1249 10.1126/science.124024823887873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib22"><text><SENT sid="412" pm="."><plain>KeusekottenK.ElliottP.R.GlocknerL.FiilB.K.DamgaardR.B.KulathuY.WauerT.HospenthalM.K.Gyrd-HansenM.KrappmannD. 2013 OTULIN antagonizes LUBAC signaling by specifically hydrolyzing Met1-linked polyubiquitin. Cell. 153:1312–1326 10.1016/j.cell.2013.05.01423746843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib23"><text><SENT sid="413" pm="."><plain>KirisakoT.KameiK.MurataS.KatoM.FukumotoH.KanieM.SanoS.TokunagaF.TanakaK.IwaiK. 2006 A ubiquitin ligase complex assembles linear polyubiquitin chains. EMBO J. 25:4877–4887 10.1038/sj.emboj.760136017006537 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib24"><text><SENT sid="414" pm="."><plain>KomanderD.Reyes-TurcuF.LicchesiJ.D.OdenwaelderP.WilkinsonK.D.BarfordD. 2009 Molecular discrimination of structurally equivalent Lys 63-linked and linear polyubiquitin chains. EMBO Rep. 10:466–473 10.1038/embor.2009.5519373254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib25"><text><SENT sid="415" pm="."><plain>KovarovaM.HeskerP.R.JaniaL.NguyenM.SnouwaertJ.N.XiangZ.LommatzschS.E.HuangM.T.TingJ.P.-Y.KollerB.H. 2012 NLRP1-dependent pyroptosis leads to acute lung injury and morbidity in mice. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="416" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 189:2006–2016 10.4049/jimmunol.120106522753929 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib26"><text><SENT sid="417" pm="."><plain>LeeS.H.TothZ.WongL.Y.BruloisK.NguyenJ.LeeJ.Y.ZandiE.JungJ.U. 2012 Novel phosphorylations of IKKγ/NEMO. MBio. 3:e00411–e00412 10.1128/mBio.00411-1223131831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib27"><text><SENT sid="418" pm="."><plain>LiangY. 2011 SHARPIN negatively associates with TRAF2-mediated NFκB activation. PLoS ONE. 6:e21696 10.1371/journal.pone.002169621829440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib28"><text><SENT sid="419" pm="."><plain>LiangY.SeymourR.E.SundbergJ.P. 2011 Inhibition of NF-κB signaling retards eosinophilic dermatitis in SHARPIN-deficient mice. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="420" pm="."><plain>Invest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="421" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 131:141–149 10.1038/jid.2010.25920811394 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib29"><text><SENT sid="422" pm="."><plain>Lopez-CastejonG.LuheshiN.M.CompanV.HighS.WhiteheadR.C.FlitschS.L.KirovA.PrudovskyI.SwantonE.BroughD. 2013 Deubiquitinases regulate the activity of caspase-1 and interleukin-1β secretion via assembly of the inflammasome. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="423" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="424" pm="."><plain>Chem. 288:2721–2733 10.1074/jbc.M112.42223823209292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib30"><text><SENT sid="425" pm="."><plain>MariathasanS.NewtonK.MonackD.M.VucicD.FrenchD.M.LeeW.P.Roose-GirmaM.EricksonS.DixitV.M. 2004 Differential activation of the inflammasome by caspase-1 adaptors ASC and Ipaf. Nature. 430:213–218 10.1038/nature0266415190255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib31"><text><SENT sid="426" pm="."><plain>MariathasanS.WeissD.S.NewtonK.McBrideJ.O’RourkeK.Roose-GirmaM.LeeW.P.WeinrauchY.MonackD.M.DixitV.M. 2006 Cryopyrin activates the inflammasome in response to toxins and ATP. Nature. 440:228–232 10.1038/nature0451516407890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib32"><text><SENT sid="427" pm="."><plain>MarimF.M.SilveiraT.N.LimaD.S.JrZamboniD.S. 2010 A method for generation of bone marrow-derived macrophages from cryopreserved mouse bone marrow cells. PLoS ONE. 5:e15263 10.1371/journal.pone.001526321179419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib33"><text><SENT sid="428" pm="."><plain>MartinonF.BurnsK.TschoppJ. 2002 The inflammasome: a molecular platform triggering activation of inflammatory caspases and processing of proIL-beta. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="429" pm="."><plain>Cell. 10:417–426 10.1016/S1097-2765(02)00599-312191486 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib34"><text><SENT sid="430" pm="."><plain>MatsumotoM.L.DongK.C.YuC.PhuL.GaoX.HannoushR.N.HymowitzS.G.KirkpatrickD.S.DixitV.M.KelleyR.F. 2012 Engineering and structural characterization of a linear polyubiquitin-specific antibody. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="431" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="432" pm="."><plain>Biol. 418:134–144 10.1016/j.jmb.2011.12.05322227388 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib35"><text><SENT sid="433" pm="."><plain>McNamaraM.J.NortonJ.A.NautaR.J.AlexanderH.R. 1993 Interleukin-1 receptor antibody (IL-1rab) protection and treatment against lethal endotoxemia in mice. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="434" pm="."><plain>Surg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="435" pm="."><plain>Res. 54:316–321 10.1006/jsre.1993.10508331925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib36"><text><SENT sid="436" pm="."><plain>MiaoE.A.MaoD.P.YudkovskyN.BonneauR.LorangC.G.WarrenS.E.LeafI.A.AderemA. 2010 Innate immune detection of the type III secretion apparatus through the NLRC4 inflammasome. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="437" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="438" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="439" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="440" pm="."><plain>USA. 107:3076–3080 10.1073/pnas.091308710720133635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib37"><text><SENT sid="441" pm="."><plain>NakahiraK.HaspelJ.A.RathinamV.A.K.LeeS.-J.DolinayT.LamH.C.EnglertJ.A.RabinovitchM.CernadasM.KimH.P. 2011 Autophagy proteins regulate innate immune responses by inhibiting the release of mitochondrial DNA mediated by the NALP3 inflammasome. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="442" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 12:222–230 10.1038/ni.198021151103 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib38"><text><SENT sid="443" pm="."><plain>NakamuraM.TokunagaF.SakataS.-i.IwaiK. 2006 Mutual regulation of conventional protein kinase C and a ubiquitin ligase complex. Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="444" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="445" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="446" pm="."><plain>Commun. 351:340–347 10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.09.16317069764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib39"><text><SENT sid="447" pm="."><plain>PanQ.MathisonJ.FearnsC.KravchenkoV.V.Da Silva CorreiaJ.HoffmanH.M.KobayashiK.S.BertinJ.GrantE.P.CoyleA.J. 2007 MDP-induced interleukin-1beta processing requires Nod2 and CIAS1/NALP3. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="448" pm="."><plain>Leukoc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="449" pm="."><plain>Biol. 82:177–183 10.1189/jlb.100662717403772 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib40"><text><SENT sid="450" pm="."><plain>ProellM.GerlicM.MaceP.D.ReedJ.C.RiedlS.J. 2013 The CARD plays a critical role in ASC foci formation and inflammasome signalling. Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="451" pm="."><plain>J. 449:613–621 10.1042/BJ2012119823110696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib41"><text><SENT sid="452" pm="."><plain>PyB.F.KimM.S.Vakifahmetoglu-NorbergH.YuanJ. 2013 Deubiquitination of NLRP3 by BRCC3 critically regulates inflammasome activity. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="453" pm="."><plain>Cell. 49:331–338 10.1016/j.molcel.2012.11.00923246432 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib42"><text><SENT sid="454" pm="."><plain>RahighiS.IkedaF.KawasakiM.AkutsuM.SuzukiN.KatoR.KenscheT.UejimaT.BloorS.KomanderD. 2009 Specific recognition of linear ubiquitin chains by NEMO is important for NF-κB activation. Cell. 136:1098–1109 10.1016/j.cell.2009.03.00719303852 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib43"><text><SENT sid="455" pm="."><plain>RathinamV.A.K.JiangZ.WaggonerS.N.SharmaS.ColeL.E.WaggonerL.VanajaS.K.MonksB.G.GanesanS.LatzE. 2010 The AIM2 inflammasome is essential for host defense against cytosolic bacteria and DNA viruses. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="456" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 11:395–402 10.1038/ni.186420351692 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib44"><text><SENT sid="457" pm="."><plain>RivkinE.AlmeidaS.M.CeccarelliD.F.JuangY.C.MacLeanT.A.SrikumarT.HuangH.DunhamW.H.FukumuraR.XieG. 2013 The linear ubiquitin-specific deubiquitinase gumby regulates angiogenesis. Nature. 498:318–324 10.1038/nature1229623708998 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib45"><text><SENT sid="458" pm="."><plain>SatoY.FujitaH.YoshikawaA.YamashitaM.YamagataA.KaiserS.E.IwaiK.FukaiS. 2011 Specific recognition of linear ubiquitin chains by the Npl4 zinc finger (NZF) domain of the HOIL-1L subunit of the linear ubiquitin chain assembly complex. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="459" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="460" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="461" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="462" pm="."><plain>USA. 108:20520–20525 10.1073/pnas.110908810822139374 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib46"><text><SENT sid="463" pm="."><plain>SchroderK.TschoppJ. 2010 The inflammasomes. Cell. 140:821–832 10.1016/j.cell.2010.01.04020303873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib47"><text><SENT sid="464" pm="."><plain>SeokJ.WarrenH.S.CuencaA.G.MindrinosM.N.BakerH.V.XuW.RichardsD.R.McDonald-SmithG.P.GaoH.HennessyL., Inflammation and Host Response to Injury, Large Scale Collaborative Research Program. 2013 Genomic responses in mouse models poorly mimic human inflammatory diseases. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="465" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="466" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="467" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="468" pm="."><plain>USA. 110:3507–3512 10.1073/pnas.122287811023401516 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib48"><text><SENT sid="469" pm="."><plain>ShenoyA.R.WellingtonD.A.KumarP.KassaH.BoothC.J.CresswellP.MacMickingJ.D. 2012 GBP5 promotes NLRP3 inflammasome assembly and immunity in mammals. Science. 336:481–485 10.1126/science.121714122461501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib49"><text><SENT sid="470" pm="."><plain>ShiC.S.ShenderovK.HuangN.N.KabatJ.Abu-AsabM.FitzgeraldK.A.SherA.KehrlJ.H. 2012 Activation of autophagy by inflammatory signals limits IL-1β production by targeting ubiquitinated inflammasomes for destruction. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="471" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 13:255–263 10.1038/ni.221522286270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib50"><text><SENT sid="472" pm="."><plain>ShimadaK.CrotherT.R.KarlinJ.DagvadorjJ.ChibaN.ChenS.RamanujanV.K.WolfA.J.VergnesL.OjciusD.M. 2012 Oxidized mitochondrial DNA activates the NLRP3 inflammasome during apoptosis. Immunity. 36:401–414 10.1016/j.immuni.2012.01.00922342844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib51"><text><SENT sid="473" pm="."><plain>StieglitzB.Morris-DaviesA.C.KoliopoulosM.G.ChristodoulouE.RittingerK. 2012 LUBAC synthesizes linear ubiquitin chains via a thioester intermediate. EMBO Rep. 13:840–846 10.1038/embor.2012.10522791023 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib52"><text><SENT sid="474" pm="."><plain>TatematsuK.TokunagaC.NakagawaN.TanizawaK.KurodaS.KikkawaU. 1998 Transcriptional activity of RBCK1 protein (RBCC protein interacting with PKC 1): requirement of RING-finger and B-Box motifs and regulation by protein kinases. Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="475" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="476" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="477" pm="."><plain>Commun. 247:392–396 10.1006/bbrc.1998.87959642138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib53"><text><SENT sid="478" pm="."><plain>TokunagaF.IwaiK. 2009 [Involvement of LUBAC-mediated linear polyubiquitination of NEMO in NF-κB activation]. Tanpakushitsu Kakusan Koso. 54:635–64219348259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib54"><text><SENT sid="479" pm="."><plain>TokunagaC.KurodaS.TatematsuK.NakagawaN.OnoY.KikkawaU. 1998 Molecular cloning and characterization of a novel protein kinase C-interacting protein with structural motifs related to RBCC family proteins. Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="480" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="481" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="482" pm="."><plain>Commun. 244:353–359 10.1006/bbrc.1998.82709514928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib55"><text><SENT sid="483" pm="."><plain>TokunagaF.SakataS.-i.SaekiY.SatomiY.KirisakoT.KameiK.NakagawaT.KatoM.MurataS.YamaokaS. 2009 Involvement of linear polyubiquitylation of NEMO in NF-κB activation. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="484" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 11:123–132 10.1038/ncb182119136968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib56"><text><SENT sid="485" pm="."><plain>TokunagaF.NakagawaT.NakaharaM.SaekiY.TaniguchiM.SakataS.-i.TanakaK.NakanoH.IwaiK. 2011 SHARPIN is a component of the NF-κB-activating linear ubiquitin chain assembly complex. Nature. 471:633–636 10.1038/nature0981521455180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib57"><text><SENT sid="486" pm="."><plain>TokunagaF.NishimasuH.IshitaniR.GotoE.NoguchiT.MioK.KameiK.MaA.IwaiK.NurekiO. 2012 Specific recognition of linear polyubiquitin by A20 zinc finger 7 is involved in NF-κB regulation. EMBO J. 31:3856–3870 10.1038/emboj.2012.24123032187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib58"><text><SENT sid="487" pm="."><plain>VerhelstK.CarpentierI.KreikeM.MeloniL.VerstrepenL.KenscheT.DikicI.BeyaertR. 2012 A20 inhibits LUBAC-mediated NF-κB activation by binding linear polyubiquitin chains via its zinc finger 7. EMBO J. 31:3845–3855 10.1038/emboj.2012.24023032186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib59"><text><SENT sid="488" pm="."><plain>WertzI.E.O’RourkeK.M.ZhouH.EbyM.AravindL.SeshagiriS.WuP.WiesmannC.BakerR.BooneD.L. 2004 De-ubiquitination and ubiquitin ligase domains of A20 downregulate NF-κB signalling. Nature. 430:694–699 10.1038/nature0279415258597 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib60"><text><SENT sid="489" pm="."><plain>ZakD.E.SchmitzF.GoldE.S.DiercksA.H.PeschonJ.J.ValvoJ.S.NiemistöA.PodolskyI.FallenS.G.SuenR. 2011 Systems analysis identifies an essential role for SHANK-associated RH domain-interacting protein (SHARPIN) in macrophage Toll-like receptor 2 (TLR2) responses. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="490" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="491" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="492" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="493" pm="."><plain>USA. 108:11536–11541 10.1073/pnas.110757710821709223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="bib61"><text><SENT sid="494" pm="."><plain>ZhaoY.YangJ.ShiJ.GongY.-N.LuQ.XuH.LiuL.ShaoF. 2011 The NLRC4 inflammasome receptors for bacterial flagellin and type III secretion apparatus. Nature. 477:596–600 10.1038/nature1051021918512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
