<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Plant Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Plant Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2229</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5706331</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1157</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12870-017-1157-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Similar, but different: structurally related azelaic acid and hexanoic acid trigger differential metabolomic and transcriptomic responses in tobacco cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Djami-Tchatchou</surname><given-names>Arnaud T.</given-names></name><address><email>arnaudthierry2002@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ncube</surname><given-names>Efficient N.</given-names></name><address><email>efficientncube@yahoo.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>Paul A.</given-names></name><address><email>pasteenkamp@telkomsa.net</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9079-4769</contrib-id><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>Ian A.</given-names></name><address><email>idubery@uj.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0109 131X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412988.e</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry, </institution><institution>University of Johannesburg, </institution></institution-wrap>Auckland Park, 2006 South Africa </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>29</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>227</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">Plants respond to various stress stimuli by activating an enhanced broad-spectrum defensive ability. The development of novel resistance inducers represents an attractive, alternative crop protection strategy. In this regard, hexanoic acid (Hxa, a chemical elicitor) and azelaic acid (Aza, a natural signaling compound) have been proposed as inducers of plant defense, by means of a priming mechanism. Here, we investigated both the mode of action and the complementarity of Aza and Hxa as priming agents in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells in support of enhanced defense.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">Metabolomic analyses identified signatory biomarkers involved in the establishment of a pre-conditioned state following Aza and Hxa treatment. Both inducers affected the metabolomes in a similar manner and generated common biomarkers: caffeoylputrescine glycoside, <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid, feruloylglycoside, feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine glycoside and feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine conjugate. Subsequently, quantitative real time-PCR was used to investigate the expression of inducible defense response genes: <italic>phenylalanine ammonia lyase, hydroxycinnamoyl CoA quinate transferase</italic> and <italic>hydroxycinnamoyl transferase</italic> to monitor activation of the early phenylpropanoid pathway and chlorogenic acids metabolism, while <italic>ethylene response element-binding protein, small sar1 GTPase, heat shock protein 90, RAR1, SGT1, non-expressor of PR genes 1</italic> and <italic>thioredoxin</italic> were analyzed to report on signal transduction events. <italic>Pathogenesis-related protein 1a</italic> and <italic>defensin</italic> were quantified to investigate the activation of defenses regulated by salicylic acid and jasmonic acid respectively. The qPCR results revealed differential expression kinetics and, in general (except for <italic>NPR1, Thionin</italic> and <italic>PR1a</italic>), the relative gene expression ratios observed in the Hxa-treated cells were significantly greater than the expression observed in the cells treated with Aza.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par3">The results indicate that Aza and Hxa have a similar priming effect through activation of genes involved in the establishment of systemic acquired resistance, associated with enhanced synthesis of hydroxycinnamic acids and related conjugates.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-017-1157-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Augmented defense</kwd><kwd>Azelaic acid</kwd><kwd>Hexanoic acid</kwd><kwd>Hydroxycinnamic acids</kwd><kwd>Priming</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001321</institution-id><institution>National Research Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>95818</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par36">As an adaptation to harmful organisms, plants have developed sophisticated immune system strategies for defense [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The plant immune system is multilayered and includes a combination of constitutive and inducible defense mechanisms to counteract colonization by microbial pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In addition, inducible plant responses triggered by non-self recognition of common microbial structures (microbial/pathogen-associated molecular patterns, M/PAMPs) and by highly pathogen-specific effectors, which lead to M/PAMP-triggered and effector-triggered immunity (M/PTI and ETI) respectively, ensure the basis of plant resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Generally, when the basal resistance fails to prevent the entry of pathogens, plants activate another chain of defense responses called pathogen-induced resistance. Systemic acquired resistance (SAR) and induced systemic resistance (ISR) are two forms of pathogen-induced resistance wherein plant defenses are pre-conditioned by prior infection or pathogen exposure, resulting in enhanced resistance to subsequent pathogen attack [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par37">Plants can be sensitized by an initial pathogen attack, treatment with pathogen-derived molecules such as M/PAMPs or even natural or synthetic compounds. This results in more rapid and intense mobilization of defense responses, thereby leading to enhanced resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Plants that have been exposed to a priming process shown the ability to exhibit a defense state that can be maintained, thus having a form of &#8216;plant immunological memory&#8217; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Priming of defense thus complements innate immunity and contributes to increased resistance during SAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">As priming agents, many natural compounds including amides, aromatic compounds, carboxylic acids, glycosides, oligosaccharides and vitamins tend to be better tolerated by plants than most of the tested synthetic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Azelaic acid (Aza) is a nine carbon dicarboxylic acid that acts as a natural inducer of plant defenses by means of a priming mechanism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Aza is a derivative of oleic acid or the desaturated derivatives, linoleic and linolenic acid, but the biosynthesis pathway is largely unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants, Aza was suggested to induce SAR by priming salicylic acid (SA) biosynthesis which resulted in a faster and stronger induction response to pathogen inoculation with higher accumulation of SA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. It was also shown that pathogen-induced SA accumulation and <italic>PR1</italic> gene expression were faster and stronger in plants treated with Aza, suggesting that the latter is a priming factor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par39">Another carboxylic acid compound not derived or related to plant defensive pathways, and with proven activity as an inducer of plant defenses, is hexanoic acid (Hxa) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Hxa is a potent natural priming agent with demonstrated efficiency in a wide range of host plants and pathogens. It can induce the early activation of broad-spectrum defenses by inducing callose deposition and the SA - and jasmonic acid (JA) pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Hxa has been reported to prime tomato plants against the hemibiotrophic bacterium <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. tomato and against necrotrophic <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Hxa treatment has also been found to protect <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> plants against <italic>B. cinerea</italic> with changes in the JA-signaling pathway upon infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The induction of many genes that characterize the Hxa priming effect, especially those related to defense, the signaling network and oxidative stress control, was revealed by microarray data of Hxa-treated plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. As such, the aim of this study was to follow an untargeted metabolomics approach to investigate and compare the priming-related responses in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells triggered by Aza and Hxa.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Metabolomic analyses</title><p id="Par40">Metabolomics aims to detect and identify the chemical compounds that drive and participate in biological processes. As such, a metabolomic approach was used to compare the effect of Aza to Hxa in an attempt to qualitatively and quantitatively evaluate the biochemical effects on the cells at the metabolite level. Thus, the two priming agents were exogenously applied to the cells 3 d after sub-culturing and harvested at treatment time-points of 0, 6, 12 and 24&#160;h. The liquid chromatography coupled to mass spectrometry (LC-MS)-based metabolomic workflow was then carried out, generating data that was analyzed by multivariate statistics and chemometric modeling.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Chromatographic analysis</title><p id="Par41">Representative chromatograms acquired using ultra-high performance liquid chromatography coupled to a quadrupole time-of-flight mass spectrometer (UHPLC-qTOF-MS) in electrospray ionization (ESI) negative mode are presented as, Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Figure S1 and Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2. Visual inspection of the base peak intensity (BPI) chromatograms indicated the responsiveness of the cells to the treatments over a 24&#160;h period. Previous metabolite fingerprinting studies of phenolic compounds and -derivatives have mostly been carried out in ESI negative ionization mode [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. As such, only these data sets were processed for further analyses. Multivariate data models were generated to reveal the underlying differences in the dynamic metabolic responses of tobacco cells treated with Aza and Hxa, respectively.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Multivariate data analysis</title><p id="Par42">The data matrices obtained from the MarkerLynx XS&#8482; software (Waters Corporation, Manchester, UK) were exported to SIMCA (Soft Independent Modelling of Class Analogy) software, version 14 (Umetrics, Ume&#229;, Sweden) for multivariate data analysis (MVDA). Generated models include principal component analyses (PCA)-derived score &#8211; and loadings plots, and orthogonal projection to latent structures-discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA)-derived score plots and S-plots. The former shows co-variation and correlation among the samples whereas the latter allows for the extraction of the significant biomarkers responsible for the differences between the various treatment groups (i.e. metabolites perturbed by or associated with the Aza and Hxa treatments) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. As such, the PCA score plots are presented in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a and c</xref>, whereas the OPLS-DA score plots are presented in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b and d</xref> and compare the 0 and 12&#160;h time points. The models are statistically significant since the PCA plots explain total variation (R<sup>2</sup>X) and have predictability power (Q<sup>2</sup>X)&#8201;&gt;&#8201;50%, and the generated OPLS-DA plots have a cross-validated (CV) Anova <italic>p</italic>-value of &lt;0.05 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Clustering of the same treated groups at different time-points can be seen in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a and c</xref>, indicating that the cells respond to both Aza and Hxa treatments in a time-dependent manner reflective of ongoing metabolic events.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Multivariate data models depicting the metabolomic perturbations in tobacco cells in response to elicitation with 100&#160;&#956;M azelaic acid (Aza) and hexanoic acid (Hxa). <bold>a</bold> Principal components (PC1 vs. PC2) analysis shows clustering, based on differences in the metabolomes, at 0, 6, 12 and 24&#160;h post-treatment, and (<bold>b</bold>) OPLS-DA score plots (0 vs. 12&#160;h) of analytes present in extracts for the of Aza-treated cells. Equivalent graphs for extracts from Hxa-treated cells are shown in (<bold>c</bold>) and (<bold>d</bold>) respectively. The x-axes of the OPLS-DA score plots correspond to the predictive component t [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] whereas the y-axes represents the orthogonal component, to[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The ellipse represents Hoteling&#8217;s T2 at 95% confidence interval</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par43">The respective S-plots of the OPLS-DA score plots were generated (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a and c</xref>). The selected ions at the top right corner (in the red rectangle) are positively correlated to the treatment whereas the selected ions at the bottom left corner (in the green rectangle) are negatively correlated to the treatment. Extracted ions representing significant biomarkers (cut off: &#177; 0.10) responsible for the difference between the control and treated cells were 11 and 9 for Aza and Hex respectively. Variable importance in projection (VIP) plots (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b and d</xref>) were also generated to confirm the significance of the selected ions, where a <italic>p</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;1.0 on the y-axis was set as the minimum value for relevance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Subsequently, these biomarkers were putatively annotated as listed in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. A compilation of the various extracted ion chromatograms (EICs) for bio-markers <bold>1</bold> to <bold>7</bold> are presented in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Identification of signatory biomarkers associated with the response of tobacco cells to 100&#160;&#956;M of the inducing agents azelaic acid (Aza) and hexanoic acid (Hxa). Shown are the (<bold>a</bold>) OPLS-DA S-plots and (<bold>b</bold>) VIP plots of analytes (Rt and <italic>m/z</italic> values) present in extracts derived from 12&#160;h Aza-treated cells in comparison to the 0&#160;h controls. Equivalent graphs for extracts from Hxa-treated cells (0&#160;h vs. 12&#160;h) are shown in (<bold>c</bold>) and (<bold>d</bold>) respectively. The x-axes of the OPLD-DA S-plots represent the modeled covariance or p [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and the y-axes the modeled correlation or p(corr) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The rectangles indicate the extraction of ions representing significant biomarkers (cut off: &#177; 0.10) responsible for the difference between the control and treated cells. The VIP plots are annotated with Rt and <italic>m/z</italic> values</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>List of tentatively annotated biomarkers associated with the pre-conditioned state in cultured tobacco cells treated with 100&#160;&#956;M azelaic - and hexanoic acid respectively as priming agents</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p>Note: the mass to charge ratio of the ions are customarily presented as m/z in italics</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>UHPLC-QTOF-MS chromatograms (extracted ion traces in ESI negative mode) indicating the chromatographic separation and mass spectrometric detection of azelaic &#8211; and hexanoic acid responsive biomarkers in extracts corresponding to the 12&#160;h treatments: [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] caffeoylputrescine glycoside, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] feruloylglycoside, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] azelaic acid glycoside, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine glycoside, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine conjugate and [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine. The numbers of the structures correspond to those in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3 and Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Perturbations in the levels of these metabolites are shown in Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Annotation of biomarkers</title><p id="Par44">The tentative annotation of the signatory biomarker metabolites that were correlated with the treatment of Aza and Hxa was carried out as previously described, by comparing the fragmentation patterns of the spectra to published literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Accurate annotation of structurally similar isomers of hydroxycinnamic acid (HCA) derivatives has proven to be a difficult task. However, LC-MS was chosen as the analytical platform as it is capable of discriminating between the structurally similar positional and geometric isomers of HCA derivatives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. In addition, the LC-MS based hierarchical key developed by Clifford et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] facilitated the identification of chlorogenic acids (CGAs). As a result, a total of 7 biomarkers were characterized and putatively annotated as shown in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> with structures in Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Characterization of the annotated biomarkers</title><p id="Par45">The MS fragmentation patterns of the mentioned biomarkers are supplied in the Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>: Figure S4 and Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>: Figure S5 respectively. Biomarker <bold>1</bold> at Rt 3.37&#160;min was putatively annotated as caffeoylputrescine glycoside (412&#160;Da) with a peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 411.1667 [M-H]<sup>&#8722;</sup> and a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 249.1153 [M-H-caffeoylputrescine-162]<sup>&#8722;</sup> due to the loss of a glucosyl moiety (162&#160;Da). The other MS-produced fragments were seen at <italic>m/z</italic> 321.1487 and <italic>m/z</italic> 135.0402 [M-H-caffeoyl-COO]<sup>&#8722;</sup> that represent a decarboxylated caffeic acid moiety. Biomarker <bold>2</bold> at Rt 4.43&#160;min was putatively annotated as <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid (354&#160;Da) with a [M-H]<sup>&#8722;</sup> peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 353.0735 and a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 191.0412 [M-quinic acid-18]<sup>&#8722;</sup> due to the loss of a dehydrated quinic acid moiety. The other MS-produced fragment observed at <italic>m/z</italic> 135.0376 [M-H-caffeoyl-COO]<sup>&#8722;</sup> represents a decarboxylated caffeic acid moiety. The putative annotation of these molecules, considering both regio- and geometric isomerization, was based on the hierarchical diagnostic fragmentation as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Accordingly, the molecule was annotated as <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid because of elution order and the presence of the base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 191, indicative of a 5-acyl position [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Biomarker <bold>3</bold> at Rt 5.35&#160;min was annotated as feruloylglycoside (356&#160;Da) with a [M-H]<sup>&#8722;</sup> peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 355.0933 and a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 193.0430 [M-H-ferulic acid]<sup>&#8722;</sup> due to the loss of a glucosyl moiety (162&#160;Da) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Biomarker <bold>4</bold> was annotated as azelaic acid glycoside (350&#160;Da) with a [M-H]<sup>&#8722;</sup> peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 349.1389 and a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 187.0883, indicative of azelaic acid [M-H-azelaic acid-162]<sup>&#8722;</sup> due to the loss of a glucosyl moiety (162&#160;Da). Expectedly, this ion is only present in the azelaic acid-treated samples (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Biomarker <bold>5</bold> at Rt 8.34&#160;min was annotated as feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine glycoside (505&#160;Da) with a peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 504.1638 [M-H]<sup>&#8722;</sup> and a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 342.1240 [M-H-feruloyl-3-methyltyramine-162]<sup>&#8722;</sup> due to the loss of a glucosyl moiety (162&#160;Da). Biomarker <bold>6</bold> at 8.90&#160;min was annotated as feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine conjugate (547&#160;Da) with a peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 546.1868 [M-H]<sup>&#8722;</sup> and a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 342.1231 [M-H-feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine-203]<sup>&#8722;</sup> due to the loss of a conjugate of 203&#160;Da. Biomarke<bold>r 7</bold> at 9.70&#160;min was annotated as feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine (343&#160;Da) with a base peak at <italic>m/z</italic> 342.1231 [M-H-feruloyl-3-methyltyramine]<sup>&#8722;</sup>. The annotation of the feruloyl-methoxytyramine conjugated molecules (biomarkers <bold>5, 6</bold> and <bold>7</bold>) were as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Relative quantification of annotated biomarkers</title><p id="Par46">The box-and-whiskers plots show the relative concentrations of the annotated metabolites after different time points (0, 6, 12, and 24&#160;h post-treatment) in the Aza- and Hxa-treated samples (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This relative quantitative analysis (based on peak intensities) shows a general trend of an increase in concentration from 0 to 24&#160;h post-treatment, with some metabolites having the highest relative concentrations at 6, 12 or 24&#160;h. The differential effect on metabolite kinetics is illustrated in the case of compound [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], caffeoylputrescine, where the relative levels were found to decrease initially in Aza-treated cells between 0 and 12&#160;h, but recovered to basal levels by 24&#160;h. In the case of the Hxa-treated cells, there was a slight decrease at 6&#160;h, followed by an increase greater than basal levels up to 24&#160;h.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Box-and-whiskers plots of time-dependent changes in the levels of signatory biomarkers identified in extracts from tobacco cells treated with 100&#160;&#956;M azelaic acid. Shown are the relative concentrations of (<bold>a</bold>) caffeoylputrescine glycoside&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], (<bold>c</bold>) feruloylglycoside&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], (<bold>d</bold>) azelaic acid glycoside&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], (<bold>e</bold>) feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine glycoside&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], (<bold>f</bold>) feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine conjugate&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], and (<bold>g</bold>) feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The numbers of the structures correspond to those in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3 and Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Values represent the mean of three biological replicates and three technical replicates, <italic>n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;9)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Box-and-whiskers plots of time-dependent changes in the levels of signatory biomarkers identified in extracts from tobacco cells treated with 100&#160;&#956;M hexanoic acid. Shown are the relative concentrations of (<bold>a</bold>) caffeoylputrescine glycoside&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], (<bold>c</bold>) feruloylglycoside&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], (<bold>d</bold>) feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine glycoside [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] &#160;and (<bold>e</bold>) feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine conjugate&#160;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. The numbers of the structures correspond to those in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>: Figure S3 and Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Values represent the mean of three biological replicates and three technical replicates, n&#8201;=&#8201;9)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par47">In order to profile the gene expression in tobacco cells in response to the priming effect of Aza and Hxa treatments, total RNA was isolated after 0, 6, 12 and 24&#160;h elicitation. Quantitative expression analysis of twelve genes which included: (a) <italic>Phenylalanine ammonia lyase (PAL),</italic> (b) <italic>Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase (HQT),</italic> (c) <italic>Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate/quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase (HCT),</italic> (d) <italic>Ethylene response element-binding protein (EREBP),</italic> (e) <italic>Small Sar1 GTPase (SAR1-GTPase),</italic> (f) <italic>Thioredoxin (THIO),</italic> (g) <italic>Heat shock protein 90 (HSP90),</italic> (h) <italic>Required for Mla12</italic> Resistance (RAR1), (i) Suppressor of the G2 allele of Skp1 (SGT1), (j) <italic>Non-expressor of PR genes 1 (NPR1),</italic> (k) <italic>Pathogenesis-related protein 1a (PR-1a)</italic> and (l) <italic>Defensin</italic>, was performed as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and normalized against <italic>Elf &#945;</italic> and <italic>18S rRNA</italic> to give the relative gene expression. The results (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> a-l) indicate that the transcripts exhibited different expression kinetics that can be described as early- (6&#160;h), mid- (12&#160;h) and late- (&gt;12&#160;h) responses. The fold-expression varied from relatively low (&gt;2 fold) to high (&gt;10 fold), compared to the basal levels of non-treated cells. In general, except for <italic>NPR1</italic>, <italic>Thionin</italic> and <italic>PR1a</italic>, the relative gene expression ratios observed in the Hxa treated cells was significantly greater than the expression observed in the cells treated with Aza.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Differential gene expression analysis in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells following induction with Aza (in white) and Hxa (in grey). The data was normalized using <italic>Elf &#945;</italic> and <italic>18S</italic> to give the relative gene expression where the error bars represent the standard error of mean. <bold>a</bold>
<italic>Phenylalanine ammonia lyase (PAL),</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) <italic>Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase (HQT),</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) <italic>Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate/quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase (HCT),</italic> (<bold>d</bold>) <italic>Ethylene response element-binding</italic> protein (EREBP), (<bold>e</bold>) <italic>Small Sar1 GTPase</italic> (<italic>SAR1-GTPase),</italic> (<bold>f</bold>) Thioredoxin (THIO), (<bold>g</bold>) <italic>Heat shock protein 90 (HSP90),</italic> (<bold>h</bold>) <italic>Required for Mla12 Resistance (RAR1)</italic>, (<bold>i</bold>) <italic>Suppressor of the G2 allele of</italic> Skp1 (SGT1), (<bold>j</bold>) <italic>Non-expressor of PR genes 1 (NPR1),</italic> (<bold>k</bold>) <italic>Pathogenesis-related protein 1a (PR-1a)</italic> and (<bold>l</bold>) <italic>Defensin</italic>. Increases indicated by a single asterix (*) indicates a significant difference with <italic>p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 and (**) indicates a highly significant difference with <italic>p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par48">Priming shares some metabolic features with acquired/induced resistance with the aim of faster and stronger activation of stress-inducible defense reactions upon a subsequent pathogen challenge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Since investigations of priming in plants started with molecular tools, it has improved the understanding of the activation of the plant innate immune system through the identification of defense genes and analysis of signaling pathways leading to SAR and ISR. Many natural and synthetic compounds have been shown to be critical regulators of acquired/induced resistance by means of a priming mechanism, or as direct activators of induced immunity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. In addition to the acceleration of the plant&#8217;s ability to activate defense responses, the emerging picture is that priming represents an important adaptation or survival mechanism in plants to cope with abiotic and biotic stresses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Although recent results started to unravel the molecular mechanism behind priming, it is still relatively poorly understood. Within this context the present study was undertaken to perform a comparative metabolomics investigation regarding the mode(s) of action and effectiveness of Aza and Hxa as inducers of resistance in <italic>N. tabacum</italic> cells in support of priming, with the focus on genes and secondary metabolites likely to be involved in host defense. Our findings revealed that the response of cells to treatment with Aza and Hxa is time-dependent, with differential effects on the up- or down-regulation of metabolites as well as altered expression kinetics of selected genes involved in the activation and execution of the plant defense response.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Metabolomic analyses</title><p id="Par49">Metabolomics is a qualitative and/ or quantitative approach for the analysis of metabolites under certain physiological states in a biological system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. In essence, as the ultimate recipients of biological information flow in cells, the spectrum and level of metabolites not only play a crucial role in the expression of genes and stability of proteins, but also determines the phenotypic properties of the cell or organism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Ultimately, this approach significantly contributes to the understanding of unassigned and unidentified compounds from undefined metabolic pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Metabolomics has therefore been used in various recent studies that reported on the physiological processes of plant stress biology, the plant immune system and plant-microbe interactions. The exogenous application of priming agents to plant tissues or cultured cells has shown to be effective models to investigate up- or down-regulation of genes involved in defense-related cellular pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. In this way plant bioactive secondary metabolites resulting from these pathways can be rapidly biosynthesized, extracted and analyzed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Secondary metabolites and the defensive roles of the annotated metabolites</title><p id="Par50">Secondary plant metabolites constitute a formidable contributor to the chemical defenses of plants, either as phytoanticipins or phytoalexins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. These metabolites include phenylpropanoids, terpenoids, alkaloids and glucosinolates, depending on the particular species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. These metabolites play an important role in plant defense systems and environmental adaptation, and their presence fluctuates in response to different environmental stimuli [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The knowledge on the accumulation of secondary metabolites in response to infection, has been utilized to study the underlying biochemical responses to stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p><p id="Par51">The obtained results indicate that the exogenous treatment of tobacco cells with both Aza and Hxa led to the production of mainly HCA compounds (conjugates of caffeic acid and ferulic acid) listed in Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. This is in accordance with our previous results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. PAL is the key enzyme at the entry point of the phenylpropanoid pathway, leading to the production of cinnamic acid that is further metabolized to various phenolic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Noteworthy, in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>, there is up-regulation of <italic>PAL</italic> gene transcripts post 12&#160;h Aza and Hxa elicitation. As a major part of the phytoalexins, phenylpropanoid compounds play a huge role in plant defense against stressors such as hostile environmental conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. In addition, biological functions of these compounds include structural support (phenylpropanoid-based polymers) and signaling in plant defense [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. As such, priming of plants by biotechnological induction of the phenylpropanoid pathway is an effective means of increasing resistance against stress conditions.</p><p id="Par52">HCA-related metabolites have been shown to be widely distributed in plants and compounds such as caffeic acid and ferulic acid naturally occur either in conjugated or non-conjugated forms. Solanum species such as <italic>N. tabacum, S. tuberosum</italic> and <italic>S. lycopersicum</italic> are known to produce HCA ester and - amide conjugates. Putrescine, a polyamine, often conjugates to HCAs to give rise to compounds such as caffeoylputrescine and feruloylputrescine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]. The decarboxylation of tyrosine results in tyramine which is also often conjugated to HCAs upon pathogen infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. In addition, an ester bond can be formed between HCAs and a quinic acid to result in compounds known as chlorogenic acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].</p><p id="Par53">In this context, caffeoylputrescine glycoside (biomarker <bold>1</bold>) was found to be induced by Hxa whereas the levels of <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid (biomarker <bold>2</bold>), feruloylglycoside (biomarker <bold>3</bold>), feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine glycoside (biomarker <bold>5</bold>), feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine conjugate (biomarker <bold>6</bold>) and feruloyl-3-methoxytyramine (biomarker <bold>7</bold>) increased after either 6 or 12&#160;h of post-elicitation with both Aza and Hxa (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). In comparison, there was an increase of azelaic glycoside (biomarker <bold>4</bold>) at 6&#160;h and further at 12&#160;h, and a decrease at 24&#160;h following Aza elicitation. This is indicative that upon uptake and accumulation of Aza, the cells conjugated the molecules with glucose, possibly as a detoxification mechanism or for storage purposes.</p><p id="Par54">Although quantitatively different, the effect of Hxa as a priming agent is qualitatively similar to that of Aza with regard to up-regulation of the early phenylpropanoid pathway, resulting in the biosynthesis of similar derivatives of caffeic acid and ferulic acid. The dynamic responses can be attributed to active metabolism, including synthesis, interconversion and degradation of stored conjugates as a mechanism to rapidly supply demands for HCAs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Quantitative gene expression analysis</title><p id="Par55">Quantitative expression analyses of twelve genes which included: (i) <italic>PAL, HQT</italic> and <italic>HCT</italic>; (ii) <italic>EREBP, SAR1-GTPase</italic> and <italic>THIO;</italic> (iii) <italic>HSP90, RAR1</italic> and <italic>SGT1</italic>; (iv) <italic>NPR1, PR-1a</italic> and <italic>Defensin</italic>, were performed. The results indicate that the transcripts, associated with the various functional categories discussed below, exhibited different expression kinetics that can be described as early, mid and late responses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Metabolism</title><p id="Par56">Activation of signal transduction networks after pathogen recognition results in reprogramming of cellular metabolism, which leads to a large change in gene activity. Phenylalanine is synthesized via the shikimate pathway that also leads to the synthesis of quinic acid. PAL is the enzyme involved in the deamination of phenylalanine to <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamic acid, thus linking primary metabolism to secondary metabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. The quinic acid pool acts as a reservoir that can be reversibly injected into the main pathway for esterification reactions with HCAs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The production of <italic>trans</italic>-cinnamic acid (and the HCA derivatives) occurs in response to stress-induced increases in PAL activity, and this represents the first step in the biosynthesis of various phenylpropanoids involved in plant defense: hydroxylated and methoxylated cinnamates, chlorogenic acids, coumarins, flavonoids and lignin precursors.</p><p id="Par57">We investigated the expression of <italic>PAL, HCT</italic> and <italic>HQT.</italic> The expression of <italic>PAL</italic> was significantly up-regulated at 12&#160;h in the cells treated with Aza as well as at 12 and 24&#160;h in the cells treated with Hxa (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a</xref>). HQT is one of the crucial enzymes for the synthesis of 5-caffeoylquinic acid (a CGA), catalyzing the transesterification reaction of caffeoyl-CoA with quinic acid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. CGAs and related derivatives exhibit radical scavenging activity and have been identified as phytoanticipins and resistance biomarkers, as well as non-antimicrobial defense compounds that interferes with infection processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. The expression of <italic>HQT</italic> was significantly up-regulated at 6&#160;h in the cells treated with Aza and at 12&#160;h in those treated with Hxa (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6b</xref>). HCT functions in an alternative route to CGA synthesis where <italic>p</italic>-coumaroyl-CoA is first <italic>trans</italic>-esterified with quinic acid before hydroxylation to yield 5-caffeoylquinic acid and, similarly, plays a critical role in the phenylpropanoid biosynthetic pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Our study showed that following Hxa treatment of the cells, the expression of <italic>HCT</italic> was significantly up-regulated from 6 to 24&#160;h, with maximum expression at 12&#160;h (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>). In cells treated with Aza, <italic>HCT</italic> was significantly up-regulated only at 12&#160;h. Based on the differential expression of the <italic>PAL, HQT</italic> and <italic>HCT</italic> genes, we suggest that the priming action of Aza and Hxa involves activation of the early shikimate/phenylpropanoid pathway in support of the chemical defenses associated with disease resistance in plants.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Signal perception and transduction</title><p id="Par58">Priming for enhanced defense against biotic/abiotic stress requires specific cellular signaling components upon treatment with an inducing agent. <italic>SAR1-GTPase</italic> (a small monomeric GTP-binding protein belonging to the <italic>Rho</italic> subfamily), associated with plant signaling events, was significantly up-regulated in the tobacco cells treated with Aza from 6 to 12&#160;h as well as cells treated with Hxa from 12 to 24&#160;h. The maximum expression was observed in the cells treated with both Aza and Hxa at 12&#160;h (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e</xref>). SAR1-GTPase acts as a molecular switch and is involved in intracellular signaling pathways downstream of inducible lectin domain receptor-like kinases, possible receptors for recognition of extracellular pathogen-derived P/MAMPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. As such, treatment with Aza and Hxa triggered the expression of <italic>SAR1-GTPase</italic> which plays a positive role in plant immunity as seen previously in the tobacco cells treated with isonitrosoacetophenone (INAP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The results indicate that Aza triggered the expression of <italic>SAR1-GTPase</italic> earlier than Hxa, but with the latter lasting longer than the Aza effect. However as stated, with both treatments the highest expression level of <italic>SAR1-GTPase</italic> was observed at 12&#160;h. The results indicate that the mode of action of Aza might be similar to that of Hxa on this key gene.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Transcription factors</title><p id="Par59">Transcription factors play an important regulatory function in the onset of priming [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. EREBP is known to be involved in transcriptional activation and in the cells treated with Aza an up-regulation was observed at 6&#160;h post-elicitation. Up-regulation was also observed for <italic>EREBP</italic> transcripts in the cells treated with Hxa at 12 and 24&#160;h, with a maximum 10-fold expression at 12&#160;h (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d</xref>). The results thus indicated that Aza triggered the expression of <italic>EREBP</italic> earlier than Hxa, but with the latter effect lasting longer and with the highest expression level observed at 12&#160;h. Previous findings revealed that, during plant-pathogen interactions, the rate of ethylene biosynthesis (which is mediated by EREBP) increases rapidly and is linked to the induced transcription of some basic-type <italic>PR</italic> defense genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. Therefore, EREBP plays an important regulatory role in the onset of priming as also observed previously in <italic>N. tabacum</italic> cells primed with INAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Since some defense mechanisms are not directly activated upon induction of the primed state, it can be assumed that the up-regulated expression of <italic>EREBP</italic> transcripts resulted in the activation of the defense response that is marked by the transcription of the appropriate defense-related genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Molecular chaperones</title><p id="Par60">The HSP90, SGT1 and RAR1 proteins form a molecular chaperone complex involved in diverse biological signaling including innate immunity and <italic>R</italic> gene-mediated disease resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. This complex coordinately contributes to the stability of the nucleotide-binding leucine-rich repeat (NB-LRR)-containing proteins which are a group of receptors mediating innate immune responses to microbial pathogens. In addition, the HSP90-SGT1-RAR1 complex is crucial in the activation of R proteins and therefore a critical component of the plant immune response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>]. In this study, the expression pattern of <italic>HSP90, RAR1</italic> and <italic>SGT1</italic> in the cells treated with Hxa showed an up-regulation from 12 to 24&#160;h, with a maximum expression of each gene at 12&#160;h resulting in 4-, 18- and 14-fold increases respectively for each gene (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> g,h,i). In the cells treated with Aza, up-regulation was observed in the expression of <italic>SGT1</italic> at 6&#160;h, and <italic>HSP90</italic> and <italic>RAR1</italic> at 12&#160;h. Similar expression patterns showing up-regulation was observed for <italic>HSP90</italic> and <italic>RAR1</italic> in the cells treated with both priming agents at 12&#160;h. These results indicate the involvement of the HSP90-SGT-RAR1 complex in the responses triggered by Aza and Hxa treatment. Furthermore, the findings also showed that the mode of action of Aza and Hxa is similar on <italic>HSP90</italic> and <italic>RAR1</italic> at 12&#160;h (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> g,h), but that at other time points the effect on these gene transcripts differed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Response regulators</title><p id="Par61">The treatment of tobacco cells with Aza and Hxa resulted in the induction of the <italic>NPR1</italic> gene. NPR1 is an important defense regulator protein that is required for SAR establishment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>], which is regulated by the endogenous accumulation of the signal molecule SA with NPR1 positioned at the cross-roads of multiple defense pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>]. Upon SAR induction a biphasic change in cellular reduction potential occurs, leading in reduction of NPR1 to a monomeric form which accumulates in the nucleus and induces the expression of some <italic>PR</italic> defense genes via SA pathways [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. A functional <italic>NPR1</italic> gene is required for priming and the NPR1 protein is suggested to be one of the receptors for SA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Previously we reported that <italic>NPR1</italic> was significantly induced in <italic>N. tabacum</italic> cells from 2 to 12&#160;h, with a 10-fold increase at 8&#160;h, following the induction of INAP as priming agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In this study, the treatment of tobacco cells with Aza led to a significant up-regulation of <italic>NPR1</italic> transcripts from 6 to 12&#160;h with a maximum 18-fold increase in expression at 6&#160;h. In comparison, the treatment with Hxa led to a notable up-regulation of <italic>NPR1</italic> from 6 to 24&#160;h with a maximum expression of 18-fold increase at 12&#160;h (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6j</xref>). Knowing that the transcripts levels of <italic>NPR1</italic> are responsive following SA treatment/accumulation to activate <italic>PR</italic>-gene expression and SAR, this suggests that the SA signaling pathway is also involved in the tobacco cellular response to Aza and Hxa treatment. Finally, the results showed a similar mode of action of Aza and Hxa to trigger enhanced expression of <italic>NPR1</italic>, although the maximum expression was observed at different time points.</p><p id="Par62">Thioredoxins are known to function in redox signaling, thereby affecting NPR1 and thus also involved in defense responses. In addition, these enzymes act as chaperones and disulphide isomerases in protein folding of newly synthesized proteins [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Here, up-regulation was observed for <italic>Thioredoxin</italic> at 6&#160;h in cells treated with Aza, and at 12 and 24&#160;h in the cells treated with Hxa, indicating differential responsiveness to the two priming agents (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6f</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Defense-related proteins</title><p id="Par63">Two important gene transcripts found to be induced by Aza and Hxa are <italic>PR-1a</italic> and <italic>Defensin,</italic> the accumulation of which results upon treatment with resistance-inducing agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. PR-1 proteins have routinely been used as molecular markers of SA-dependent SAR, and contribute to increase pathogen resistance by directly exerting harmful effects to microbial invaders during SAR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In contrast, Defensin, that exhibits antifungal and antibacterial activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>], is controlled by JA/ET-dependent pathways and is regarded as a marker for JA signaling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. We have previously reported that <italic>PR-1a</italic> and <italic>PR-1b</italic> transcripts were induced during SAR establishment in tobacco cells following the priming action of INAP which confers resistance to <italic>P. syringae</italic> pv. <italic>tabaci</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Here, our findings also revealed that there was a significant up-regulation in the expression of <italic>PR-1a</italic> at 6&#160;h and a highly significant up-regulation at 24&#160;h in the cells treated with Aza. In contrast, the cells treated with Hxa showed only a slight / non-significant increase of the expression of <italic>PR-1a</italic> at all time-points (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6k</xref>). In addition, the qPCR data showed that the <italic>Defensin</italic> transcripts were significantly up-regulated at 6 and 12&#160;h, with a maximum 14-fold increase in expression in cells treated with Hxa (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6l</xref>). In contrast to the Hxa action, the cells treated with Aza displayed no differential expression of <italic>Defensin</italic> from 6 to 12&#160;h, but rather a significant down-regulation at 24&#160;h. The differential changes in the transcript levels of <italic>PR-1a</italic> and <italic>Defensin</italic> indicate that the corresponding genes were responsively dissimilar to the treatments, with <italic>PR1a</italic> responding to Aza and <italic>Defensin</italic> responding to Hxa, thus implying differential actions of SA and JA/ET in the action mechanisms of the two inducers.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par64">The concept of priming can encompass various induced-resistance phenomena in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] that offers protection against a wide spectrum of abiotic and biotic stresses. However, the molecular mechanisms and metabolic basis of this stress-imprinting on plant immunity is not fully elucidated, and may vary between plants from different families. In the case of <italic>N. tabacum</italic> and other members of the <italic>Solanaceae,</italic> it could depend on the controlled, dynamic balance between biosynthesis and degradation of phenolic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The phenylpropanoid pathway with HCA intermediates represents an important link to resistance for the production of different phenolics in free or conjugated forms. Our results add further support for this viewpoint, involving the modulation and mobilization of phenolic compounds and enhanced synthesis of some of the conjugates, since both Aza and Hxa resulted in the biosynthesis of caffeoyl- and feruloyl-HCAs, conjugated to quinic acid, putrescine, tyramine and glucose. The commonalities between the biomarkers identified in response to Aza and Hxa elicitation indicates very similar changes to the respective metabolomes. This indicates a high interconnectivity between the signatory biomarkers, again demonstrating the centrality of the early shikimate/phenylpropanoid pathway in the altered metabolism due to Aza and Hxa.</p><p id="Par65">This study also revealed that Aza and Hxa are able to induce several genes of importance to signaling, priming and defense-related responses in plants. At the transcriptome level, and at equimolar concentrations, Hxa generated higher transcript levels of the genes investigated. The different changes in the transcript levels of SA- and JA/ET-responsive marker genes suggest differential action mechanisms for the two inducers. However, the combined results indicate that Aza and Hxa both lead to a priming effect associated with enhanced synthesis of HCAs and related conjugates, and activation of genes involved in the establishment of acquired resistance.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec22"><title>Plant material and growth conditions</title><p id="Par66">
<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cv Samsun cell cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>] were established from callus derived from sterile, in vitro grown tobacco plants grown from seeds (Agriculture Research Council, Roodeplaat, South Africa). For callus induction, stem and leaf sections were placed on Murashige and Skoog (MS) medium containing 0.25&#160;mg/L 2,4-dichlorophenoxyacetic acid and 0.25&#160;mg/L kinetin (pH&#160;5.8). Cell suspensions were grown in liquid MS medium with the same hormone composition, whilst continuously shaking at 120&#160;rpm in the dark at 25&#160;&#176;C [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Cells were sub-cultured into fresh medium every 7 d. All of the experiments were conducted 2&#8211;3 d after sub-culturing, during the logarithmic stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Experimental design, elicitation and harvesting</title><p id="Par67">Each experiment was conducted a minimum of three times in order to generate the required minimum number of biological replicates required for metabolomics analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. Cell suspensions, as described above, were treated with equimolar concentrations of Aza and Hxa (final concentrations of 100&#160;&#956;M) (Sigma Aldrich, Germany). The two inducers were prepared as 10&#160;mM stock solutions, dissolved in MS medium and with the pH adjusted to 5.8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Na&#239;ve (non-treated / non-stimulated cells) exhibited no changes over the 24&#160;h time period and served as a negative controls. Cells were harvested at the selected time points (0, 6, 12 and 24&#160;h) by filtration onto 55&#160;mm circle filter papers using a vacuum filtration system (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). The cells were transferred into Falcon tubes and cold, sterile MS medium (without any vitamins, hormones and inducing agents) was added to 50&#160;mL to wash the cells free of any original culture medium. Thereafter, the cells were filtered again as described, weighed and processed for extraction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Metabolite extraction</title><p id="Par68">The washed and filtered cells were weighed to obtain 1&#160;g of each sample and resuspended in a volume of 10&#160;mL (1:10&#160;m/v) 100% methanol. The suspensions were homogenized using a probe sonicator (Bandelin Sonopuls, Berlin, Germany) set at 55% power for 15&#160;s with 4&#160;cycles. The homogenates were centrifuged at 5100 x <italic>g</italic> for 15&#160;min at room temperature and the supernatants concentrated to approximately 1&#160;mL on a rotary evaporator set at 50&#176;C. The resulting volumes were transferred into 2&#160;mL Eppendorf tubes and dried to completeness in a heating block set at 50&#176;C overnight. The dried residues were reconstituted in 500&#160;&#956;L 50% (<italic>v</italic>/v) UHPLC-grade methanol (Romil Chemistry, Cambridge, UK) in autoclaved milli-Q water, and filtered through a 0.22&#160;&#956;m nylon syringe filter into 300&#160;&#956;L inserts fitted into glass vials with slitted caps. The filtrates were stored at &#8722;20&#176;C until analysis. To ensure reproducibility and account for analytical variability, the obtained results were from three independent biological repeats, each analyzed in triplicate (i.e. three technical repeats) for all samples. During data acquisition, pooled samples were used for quality control (QC) checks. Sample acquisition was randomized and the QC sample analyzed every 10 injections to monitor and correct changes in the instrument response.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Chromatographic &#8211; And mass spectrometric analyses</title><p id="Par69">UHPLC-MS analyses were performed on a Waters Acquity UHPLC system coupled in tandem to a SYNAPT G1 HDMS qTOF mass spectrometer (Waters Corporation, Milford, MA, USA). The liquid chromatography was carried out on a HSS T3 C18 Acquity UHPLC column (Waters, Milford, MA, USA) thermostatted at 60&#160;&#176;C using a gradient elution profile over a total run time of 20&#160;min. The binary solvents utilized consisted of UHPLC grade water (eluent A) and acetonitrile (eluent B) (Romil Pure Chemistry, Cambridge, UK), both containing 0.1% formic acid. The initial conditions were 5% A and gradient elution was introduced to change the chromatographic conditions to 90% B at 16&#160;min and the conditions were kept constant for 1&#160;min; the gradient was then dropped to the initial conditions and held for 2&#160;min. The flow rate was 0.4&#160;mL/min whilst an injection volume of 3 &#956;L was used. Separated analytes were detected using a photodiode array detector; scanning range from 200 to 500&#160;nm with 1.2&#160;nm resolution and a sampling rate of 20 points/s.</p><p id="Par70">The mass spectrometry component used for the detection of separated analytes was a SYNAPT G1 high definition qTOF-MS, used in V-optics and operated in the electrospray ionization (ESI) positive and negative modes. A reference calibrant of leucine enkephalin (50&#160;pg/mL) was used to obtain typical mass accuracies between 1 and 3 mDa. The following parameters were also set up: a capillary voltage of 2.5&#160;kV and the sampling cone voltage at 30&#160;V, trap collision 3&#160;V and the extraction cone at 4&#160;V. The scan time was 0.1&#160;s covering the 100 to 1000&#160;Da range. The source temperature was 120&#160;&#176;C whereas the desolvation temperature was set at 450&#160;&#176;C. Nitrogen gas was used as the nebulization gas at a flow rate of 800&#160;L/h. The MassLynx XS&#8482; 4.1 software (Waters Corporation, Manchester, UK) was used for the pre-processing and pre-treatment of the obtained raw data. The raw data files, together with the study description, have been deposited onto the online data repository, MetaboLights, an open-access general-purpose repository for metabolomics studies and associated meta-data, (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/metabolights">www.ebi.ac.uk/metabolights/</ext-link>) with accession number MTBLS559.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Multivariate data analysis</title><p id="Par71">The MassLynx XS&#8482; software parameters were set to analyse the 3&#8211;10&#160;min retention time (Rt) range of the chromatograms, mass range 100&#8211;900&#160;Da, mass tolerance 0.01&#160;Da, mass window 0.05&#160;Da and a Rt window of 0.20&#160;min. The MarkerLynx&#8482; data matrix (of Rt-<italic>m/z</italic> variable pairs, with the <italic>m/z</italic> peak intensities for each sample), was exported to the SIMCA (Soft Independent Modeling of Class Analogy) software, version 14 (Umetrics, Ume&#229;, Sweden) for principal component analysis (PCA) using <italic>Pareto</italic> scaling and orthogonal projection to latent structures discriminant analysis (OPLS-DA) modeling also using <italic>Pareto</italic> scaling. PCA is an explorative non-biased model that reduces the multi-dimensionality of the complex raw data matrix obtained from the analysis whereas OPLS-DA is a biased model that allows for the extraction of the metabolites responsible between the separations of the differentially treated groups (e.g. control vs. treated) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The selected mass ions from the OPLS-DA-derived S-plots and Variable Importance in Projection (VIP) plots were putatively annotated using the spectral fragmentation patterns (compared to literature) as well as the calculated putative empirical formulae and structures, which were further searched in databases such as the Dictionary of Natural Products (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dnp.chemnet">www.dnp.chemnet</ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://base.com">base.com</ext-link>), ChemSpider (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chemspider.com">www.chemspider.com</ext-link>) and Knapsack (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://kanaya.naist.jp/KNApSAcK">http://kanaya.naist.jp/KNApSAcK/</ext-link>). Relative quantification was achieved using the SPSS software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/za/analytics/spss/">http://www-01.ibm.com/software/za/analytics/spss/</ext-link>) to generate box-and-whiskers plots of relative peak intensity against time points.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Total RNA extraction</title><p id="Par72">Following elicitation, total RNA was extracted from harvested cells (100&#160;mg) using the Trizol-reagent method (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). The extracted RNA samples were subjected to DNase treatment using DNase I (Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). Concentrations were determined using a NanoDrop&#174; ND-1000&#8482;Spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Inc., Wilmington, DE, USA). The RNA integrity of all samples was examined by electrophoresis on a 1.5% agarose gel in 1X Tris-Borate-EDTA (TBE) buffer containing 0.5&#160;&#956;g/mL ethidium bromide before use. The gels were visualized under UV light using a Bio-Rad Image Analyzer and Quantity One&#8482; Version 4.6.1 Software (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Johannesburg, South Africa). The total RNA samples were divided into aliquots and stored at &#8722;80&#160;&#176;C for later use.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Quantification of the expression of target genes</title><p id="Par73">Real time PCR (qPCR) was used for the gene expression analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>]. Prior to quantification of gene expression levels, the DNase-treated RNA isolated from cells harvested at the different time points were reverse-transcribed to cDNA using a RevertAid&#8482; Premium First Strand cDNA synthesis kit (Fermentas, Thermo Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA). The selected genes included: <italic>Phenylalanine ammonia lyase</italic> (PAL), <italic>Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase</italic> (HQT)<italic>, Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate/quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase</italic> (HCT), <italic>Ethylene response element-binding protein</italic> (EREBP)<italic>, Small Sar1 GTPase</italic> (SAR1-GTPase), <italic>Non-expressor of PR genes 1</italic> (NPR1)<italic>, Thioredoxin</italic> (THIO), <italic>Heat shock protein 90</italic> (HSP90)<italic>, Required for Mla12 Resistance</italic> (RAR1)<italic>, Suppressor of the G2 allele of Skp1</italic> (SGT1), <italic>Pathogenesis-related protein 1a</italic> (PR-1a) and <italic>Defensin</italic>. The choice of genes was based on our previous study where the response of tobacco cells towards isonitrosoacetophenone (INAP), a chemical inducer of defense responses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], was investigated at transcriptome level [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The primer pairs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] were designed using the &#8216;Primer Quest&#8217; tool (Integrated DNA Technologies, Coralville, IA, USA) from sequences obtained in on-line data bases (GenBank NCBI, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank">www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>). qPCR was performed to analyze the expression of each gene using a Rotor Gene-3000A instrument (Qiagen, Venlo, Netherlands) and the SensiFAST SYBR No-ROX Kit (Bioline, London, UK) according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions. Ten &#956;L of SensiFAST SYBR, 1&#160;&#956;L forward primer (1&#160;&#956;M final concentration), 1&#160;&#956;L reverse primer (1&#160;&#956;M final concentration) and 6&#160;&#956;L of DNase-free water were added to 2&#160;&#956;L of cDNA for amplification in a total volume of 20&#160;&#956;L. The cycling conditions were as follows: initial denaturation for 10&#160;min at 95&#160;&#176;C followed by amplification and quantification cycle repeated 40 times each consisting of 5&#160;s denaturing at 95&#160;&#176;C, 10&#160;s annealing at primer-specific temperatures, 20&#160;s extension at 72&#160;&#176;C. The experimental design included three biological repeats with two technical repeats of each. Quantification of the relative changes in gene expression was performed using the relative standard curve method with <italic>elongation factor 1-alpha</italic> and <italic>actin 8</italic> as references genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Data sets were statistically compared between non-treated samples and treated samples at each time point using one-way analysis of variation (ANOVA) with the statistical analysis software GraphPad inStat 3 (GraphPad software, San Diego, CA, USA). The confidence level of all analyses was set at 95%, and values with <italic>p</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec29"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_MOESM1_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 1: Figure S1.</label><caption><p>UHPLC-MS (ESI negative) base peak intensity (BPI) chromatograms of azelaic acid-treated <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cell extracts at 24&#160;h (a), 12&#160;h (b), 6&#160;h (c) and 0&#160;h (d) post-treatment. The most intense peaks at a specific retention time (Rt) are indicated with <italic>m/z</italic> values. (TIFF 84 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_MOESM2_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 2: Figure S2.</label><caption><p>UHPLC-MS (ESI negative) base peak intensity (BPI) chromatograms of hexanoic acid-treated <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cell extracts at 24&#160;h (a), 12&#160;h (b), 6&#160;h (c) and 0&#160;h (d) post-treatment. The most intense peaks at a specific retention time (Rt) are indicated with <italic>m/z</italic> values. (TIFF 299 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_MOESM3_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 3: Figure S3.</label><caption><p>Structures of annotated biomarkers: (1) caffeoylputrescine glycoside, (2) <italic>cis</italic>-5-caffeoylquinic acid, (3) feruloylglycoside, (4) azelaic acid glycoside, (5) feruloyl-3-methyltyramine glycoside, (6) feruloyl-3-methyltyramine conjugate and (7) feruloyl-3-methyltyramine. (TIFF 25 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_MOESM4_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 4: Figure S4.</label><caption><p>UHPLC-MS spectra showing MS/MS fragmentation patterns for biomarkers 1&#8211;4. (TIFF 615 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12870_2017_1157_MOESM5_ESM.tif"><label>Additional file 5: Figure S5.</label><caption><p>UHPLC-MS spectra showing MS/MS fragmentation patterns for biomarkers 5&#8211;7. (TIFF 574 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>Aza</term><def><p id="Par4">Azelaic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>BPI</term><def><p id="Par5">Base peal intensity</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CGAs</term><def><p id="Par6">Chlorogenic acids</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CV Anova</term><def><p id="Par7">Cross-validated analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EREBP</term><def><p id="Par8">Ethylene response element-binding protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ESI</term><def><p id="Par9">Electrospray ionization</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ET</term><def><p id="Par10">Ethylene</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCA</term><def><p id="Par11">Hydroxycinnamic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HCT</term><def><p id="Par12">Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:shikimate/quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HQT</term><def><p id="Par13">Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA:quinate hydroxycinnamoyl transferase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HSP90</term><def><p id="Par14">Heat shock protein 90</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Hxa</term><def><p id="Par15">Hexanoic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ISR</term><def><p id="Par16">Induced systemic resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JA</term><def><p id="Par17">Jasmonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>M/PAMPs</term><def><p id="Par18">Microbial/pathogen-associated molecular patterns</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NB-LRR</term><def><p id="Par19">Nucleotide-binding leucine-rich repeats</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NPR1</term><def><p id="Par20">Non-expressor of PR genes 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OPLS-DA</term><def><p id="Par21">Orthogonal projection to latent structures discriminant analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAL</term><def><p id="Par22">Phenylalanine ammonia lyase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCA</term><def><p id="Par23">Principal component analysis</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PR-1a</term><def><p id="Par24">Pathogenesis-related protein 1a</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>qRT-PCR</term><def><p id="Par25">quantitative real-time PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RAR1</term><def><p id="Par26">Required for Mla12 resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SA</term><def><p id="Par27">Salicylic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAR</term><def><p id="Par28">Systemic acquired resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SAR1-GTPase</term><def><p id="Par29">Small Sar1 GTPase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SGT1</term><def><p id="Par30">Suppressor of the G2 allele of Skp1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SIMCA</term><def><p id="Par31">Soft independent modelling of class analogy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>THIO</term><def><p id="Par32">Thioredoxin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UHPLC-Q-TOF/MS</term><def><p id="Par33">Ultra high performance liquid chromatography quadrupole time of flight mass spectrometry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VIP</term><def><p id="Par34">Variable importance in projection</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>XIC</term><def><p id="Par35">Extracted ion chromatogram</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12870-017-1157-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The South African National Research Foundation and the University of Johannesburg are acknowledged for fellowship support to ATD and ENN. NE Madala and MI Mhlongo are thanked for help with metabolite annotation, F Tugizimana for help with data analysis and L Piater for critical reading of the manuscript.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par74">This work was supported by the South African National Research Foundation through grant support to IAD (grant number 95818).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par75">The raw data files, together with the study description, have been deposited onto the online data repository, MetaboLights, an open-access general-purpose repository for metabolomics studies and associated meta-data, with accession number MTBLS559 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>].</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>IAD conceived and designed the overall study, supervised the research and assisted with data interpretation. ATD, ENN and PAS were responsible for acquisition, analysis and interpretation of data. ENN and PAS performed the metabolomics experimental work and data analysis and ATD performed the transcriptome studies and qRT-PCR analyses. All authors participated in drafting the manuscript and IAD revised it critically for intellectual content. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors&#8217; information</title><p id="Par76">Department of Biochemistry, University of Johannesburg APK Campus, Auckland Park, 2006, South Africa.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par77">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par78">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par79">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar7"><title>Publisher&#8217;s Note</title><p id="Par80">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>JDG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dangl</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant immune system</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2006</year><volume>444</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>329</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05286</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17108957?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17108957</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CMJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Leon-Reyes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Ent</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>van Wees</surname><given-names>SCM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Networking by small-molecule hormones in plant immunity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>316</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self/non-self-perception in plants in innate immunity and defense</article-title><source>Self/Non-Self Imm Recog Signal</source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>40</fpage><lpage>45</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spoel</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How do plants achieve immunity? Defence without specialized immune cells</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3141</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22273771?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22273771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choudhary</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Prakash</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johri</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induced systemic resistance (ISR) in plants: mechanism of action</article-title><source>Indian J Med Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>297</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12088-007-0054-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomic insights into the bioconversion of isonitrosoacetophenone in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> and its effects on defense-related pathways</article-title><source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source><year>2014</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>95</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plaphy.2014.08.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25240267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25240267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djami-Tchatchou</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Maake</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isonitrosoacetophenone drives transcriptional reprogramming in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells in support of innate immunity and defense</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>e0117377</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0117377</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25658943?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25658943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Balmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flors</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparing to fight back: generation and storage of priming compounds</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>295</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25009546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009546</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhlongo</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming agents of plant defence stimulate the accumulation of mono- and di-acylated chlorogenic acids in cultured tobacco cells</article-title><source>Physiol Mol Plant Path.</source><year>2014</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2014.09.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Medina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Flors</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Heil</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CMJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Recognizing plant defense priming</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>822</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2016.07.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27507609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27507609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N&#225;varov&#225;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernsdorff</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#246;ring</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pipecolic acid. An endogenous mediator of defense amplification and priming, is a critical regulator of inducible plant immunity</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>5123</fpage><lpage>5141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.103564</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23221596?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23221596</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Llorens</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#237;a-Agust&#237;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lape&#241;a</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advances in induced resistance by natural compounds: towards new options for woody crop protection</article-title><source>Sci Agric</source><year>2017</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/1678-992x-2016-0012</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Baccelli</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrella</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Flors</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defense priming: an adaptive part of induced resistance</article-title><source>Ann Rev Plant Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>16.1</fpage><lpage>16.28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-arplant-042916-041132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aranega-Bou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Finiti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#237;a-Agust&#237;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Bosch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming of plant resistance by natural compounds. Hexanoic acid as a model</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2014.00488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Long-distance communication and signal amplification in systemic acquired resistance</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>30</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2013.00030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23440336?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23440336</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandal</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanda</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gifford</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A feedback regulatory loop between G3P and lipid transfer proteins DIR1 and AZI1 mediates azelaic acid-induced systemic immunity</article-title><source>Cell Rep</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1266</fpage><lpage>1278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2013.03.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23602565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23602565</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tschaplinski</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Glazebrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming in systemic plant immunity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2009</year><volume>324</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1170025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19342588?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19342588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Flors</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Leyva</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Finiti</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kravchuk</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Real</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Hexanoic acid-induced resistance against <italic>Botrytis cinerea</italic> in tomato plants</article-title><source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-22-11-1455</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19810814?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19810814</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kravchuk</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicedo</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Flors</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Cama&#241;es</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Bosch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#237;a-Agust&#237;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming for JA-dependent defenses using hexanoic acid is an effective mechanism to protect Arabidopsis against <italic>B. cinerea</italic></article-title><source>J Plant Physiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>359</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2010.07.028</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20950893?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20950893</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hierarchical scheme for LC-MS<sup>n</sup> identification of chlorogenic acids</article-title><source>J Agric Food Chem</source><year>2003</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>2900</fpage><lpage>2911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf026187q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12720369?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12720369</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jaiswal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Halabi</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Karar</surname><given-names>MGE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterisation of the phenolics of <italic>Ilex glabra</italic> L. gray (Aquifoliaceae) leaves by liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>2014</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.phytochem.2014.07.018</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25086488?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25086488</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trygg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundstedt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemometrics in metabonomics</article-title><source>J Proteome Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/pr060594q</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17269704?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17269704</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiklund</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjoestroem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellerowicz</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Edlund</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Shockcor</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Visualization of GC/ TOF-MS-based metabolomics data for identification of biochemically interesting compounds using OPLS class models</article-title><source>Anal Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac0713510</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18027910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18027910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trygg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CV-ANOVA for significance testing of PLS and OPLS&#174; models</article-title><source>J Chemomet</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>600</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cem.1187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galindo-Prieto</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Eriksson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trygg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variable influence on projection (VIP) for orthogonal projections to latent structures (OPLS)</article-title><source>J Chemomet.</source><year>2014</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>623</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cem.2627</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saccenti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoefsloot</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smilde</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerhuis</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendriks</surname><given-names>MMWB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reflections on univariate and multivariate analysis of metabolomics data</article-title><source>Metabolomics</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11306-013-0598-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhlongo</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenylpropanoid defences in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells: overlapping metabolomes indicate common aspects to priming responses induced by lipopolysaccharides, chitosan and flagellin-22</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>e0151350</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0151350</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26978774?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26978774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhlongo</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Profiling of altered metabolomic states in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells induced by priming agents</article-title><source>Front Plant Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1527</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpls.2016.01527</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27803705?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27803705</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chlorogenic acids and other cinnamates - nature, occurrence, dietary burden, absorption and metabolism</article-title><source>J Sci Food Agr</source><year>2000</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>1033</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0010(20000515)80:7&lt;1033::AID-JSFA595&gt;3.0.CO;2-T</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhlongo</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madala</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomic fingerprinting of primed tobacco cells provide the first evidence for the biological origin of <italic>cis</italic>-chlorogenic acid</article-title><source>Biotechnol Lett</source><year>2015</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10529-014-1645-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25214217?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25214217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conrath</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming of induced plant defense responses</article-title><source>Adv Bot Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2296(09)51009-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balmer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pastor</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamir</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flors</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The &#8216;prime-ome&#8217;: towards a holistic approach to priming</article-title><source>Trends Plant Sci</source><year>2015</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2015.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25921921?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25921921</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Narasimhan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Swarup</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomics and its role in understanding cellular responses in plants</article-title><source>Plant Cell Rep</source><year>2005</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00299-005-0054-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16220342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16220342</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dettmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Aronov</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammock</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mass spectrometry-based metabolomics</article-title><source>Mass Spectrom Rev</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/mas.20108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16921475?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16921475</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tugizimana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant metabolomics: a new frontier in phytochemical analysis</article-title><source>S Afr J Sci</source><year>2013</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/sajs.2013/20120005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant metabolomics: from holistic hope, to hype, to hot topic</article-title><source>New Phytol</source><year>2006</year><volume>169</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2005.01632.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16411949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16411949</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allwood</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vos</surname><given-names>RCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Moing</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Deborde</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Erban</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Plant metabolomics and its potential for systems biology research: background concepts, technology, and methodology</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>2011</year><volume>500</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-385118-5.00016-5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21943904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21943904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayat</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Irfan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of exogenous salicylic acid under changing environment: a review</article-title><source>Env Exp Bot</source><year>2010</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envexpbot.2009.08.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tugizimana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multi-platform metabolomic analyses of ergosterol-induced dynamic changes in <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> cells</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e87846</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0087846</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24498209?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24498209</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finnegan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of phytoanticipin and phytoalexin pathways in <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> in response to LPS elicitation: a metabolomic study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2016</year><volume>11</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>e0163572</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0163572</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27656890?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27656890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tugizimana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomic analysis of methyl jasmonate-induced triterpenoid production in the medicinal herb <italic>Centella asiatica</italic> (L.) urban</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2013</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>4267</fpage><lpage>4281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules18044267</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23579994?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23579994</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allwood</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodacre</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolomic technologies and their application to the study of plants and plant&#8211;host interactions</article-title><source>Physiol Plant</source><year>2008</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>117</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18251855?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18251855</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenylpropanoid biosynthesis</article-title><source>Mol Plant</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/mp/ssp106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20035037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20035037</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horbowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiczkowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Koczkodaj</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Saniewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of methyl jasmonate on accumulation of flavonoids in seedlings of common buckwheat (<italic>Fagopyrum esculentum Moench</italic>)</article-title><source>Act Biol Hung</source><year>2011</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>278</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1556/ABiol.62.2011.3.6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#243;pez-Gresa</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Torres</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lis&#243;n</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell&#233;s</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of defence metabolites in tomato plants infected by the bacterial pathogen <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic></article-title><source>Environ Exp Bot</source><year>2011</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envexpbot.2011.06.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoefgen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernie</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of phenylpropanoid metabolism in the green lineage</article-title><source>Crit Rev Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/10409238.2012.758083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23350798?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23350798</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meurer-Grimes</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Strack</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxycinnamoyl-CoA: putrescine hydroxycinnamoyltransferase in tobacco cell cultures with high and low levels of caffeoylputrescine</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>488</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.89.2.488</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16666570?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16666570</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyss-benz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Streit</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Feruloylputrescine and caffeoylputrescine are not involved in growth and floral bud formation of stem explants from <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> L. var Xanthi nc</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>924</fpage><lpage>930</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.92.4.924</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16667407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16667407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clifford</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkpatrick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhnert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Roozendaal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Salgado</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LC-MS<sup>n</sup> analysis of the cis isomers of chlorogenic acids</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>379</fpage><lpage>385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2007.05.081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>J-Q</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenylalanine ammonia-lyase, a key component used for phenylpropanoids production by metabolic engineering</article-title><source>RSC Adv</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>62587</fpage><lpage>62603</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5RA08196C</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niggeweg</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Engineering plants with increased levels of the antioxidant chlorogenic acid. Nature</article-title><source>Biotechnol</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>746</fpage><lpage>754</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sonnante</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#8217;Amore</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierri</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>De Palma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Novel Hydroxycinnamoyl-coenzyme a quinate transferase genes from artichoke are involved in the synthesis of chlorogenic acid</article-title><source>Plant Physiol</source><year>2010</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>1224</fpage><lpage>1238</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.150144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20431089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20431089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hoffmann L, Besseau S, Geoffroy P, Ritzenthaler C , Meyer <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Meyer%20D%5Bauth%5D">D</ext-link>, Lapierre <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Lapierre%20C%5Bauth%5D">C</ext-link>, et al. Silencing of hydroxycinnamoyl-coenzyme a shikimate/quinate hydroxycinnamoyltransferase affects phenylpropanoid biosynthesis. Plant Cell 2004; 16:1446&#8211;1465.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanabria</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>van Heerden</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization and regulation of a <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic> S-domain receptor-like kinase gene induced during an early rapid response to lipopolysaccharides</article-title><source>Gene</source><year>2012</year><volume>501</volume><fpage>39</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gene.2012.03.073</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22507449?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22507449</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>New</surname><given-names>S-A</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>silico</italic> characterization and expression analysis of selected Arabidopsis receptor-like kinase genes responsive to different MAMP inducers</article-title><source>Biol Plant</source><year>2015</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>18</fpage><lpage>28</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10535-014-0478-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oosten</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Turlings</surname><given-names>TCJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pieterse</surname><given-names>CMJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Priming as a mechanism behind induced resistance against pathogens, insects and abiotic stress. Induced resistance in plants against insects and diseases</article-title><source>IOBC/wprs Bull</source><year>2009</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>13</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KLC</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethylene biosynthesis and signalling networks</article-title><source>Plant Cell</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.001768</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pei</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The HSP90-RAR1-SGT1 based protein interactome in barley and stripe rust</article-title><source>Physiol Mol Plant Path.</source><year>2015</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pmpp.2015.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The HSP90 complex of plants</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2012</year><volume>1823</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>697</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2011.09.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22001401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inducers of plant systemic acquired resistance regulate NPR1 function through redox changes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2003</year><volume>113</volume><fpage>935</fpage><lpage>944</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(03)00429-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12837250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NPR1, all things considered</article-title><source>Curr Opin Plant Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>552</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pbi.2004.07.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15337097?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15337097</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomma</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggermont</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Penninckx</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauch-Mani</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogelsang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cammue</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Broekaert</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separate jasmonate-dependent and salicylate-dependent defense response pathways in Arabidopsis are essential for resistance to distinct microbial pathogens</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>15107</fpage><lpage>15111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.25.15107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9844023?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9844023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berndt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lillig</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmgred</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioredoxins and glutaredoxins as facilitators of protein folding</article-title><source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source><year>2008</year><volume>1783</volume><fpage>641</fpage><lpage>650</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2008.02.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18331844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18331844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Strien</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The families of pathogenesis-related proteins, their activities, and comparative analysis of PR-1 type proteins</article-title><source>Physiol Mol Plant Path</source><year>1999</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/pmpp.1999.0213</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanayama</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kusano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hase</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikegami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Antagonistic interactions between the SA and JA signaling pathways in Arabidopsis modulated expression of defense genes and gene for gene resistance to cucumber mosaic virus</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pch085</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15215516?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tugizimana</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Steenkamp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Piater</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dubery</surname><given-names>IA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ergosterol-induced sesquiterpenoid synthesis in tobacco cells</article-title><source>Molecules</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1698</fpage><lpage>1715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules17021698</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22322447?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22322447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derveaux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandesompele</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellemans</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How to do successful gene expression analysis using real-time PCR</article-title><source>Methods</source><year>2010</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ymeth.2009.11.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19969088?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19969088</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Salek</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hastings</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>de Matos</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MetaboLights&#8211;an open-access general-purpose repository for metabolomics studies and associated meta-data</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2013</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>D781</fpage><lpage>D786</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gks1004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23109552?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23109552</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>