<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5552708</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2017.01515</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oyster RNA-seq Data Support the Development of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> Genomics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosani</surname><given-names>Umberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/431036/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venier</surname><given-names>Paola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn002"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/434570/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Department of Biology, University of Padua</institution>
<country>Padua, Italy</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Akio Adachi, Tokushima University, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Joaquin Martinez Martinez, Bigelow Laboratory for Ocean Sciences, United States; Timothy James Green, Macquarie University, Australia; Tristan Renault, French Research Institute for Exploitation of the Sea, France</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Umberto Rosani <email xlink:type="simple">umberto.rosani@unipd.it</email></corresp><corresp id="fn002">Paola Venier <email xlink:type="simple">paola.venier@unipd.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn003"><p>This article was submitted to Virology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>09</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>1515</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2017 Rosani and Venier.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Rosani and Venier</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The family of double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> includes viruses able to infect marine mollusks and detrimental for worldwide aquaculture production. Due to fast-occurring mortality and a lack of permissive cell lines, the available data on the few known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> provide only partial support for the study of molecular virus features, life cycle, and evolutionary history. Following thorough data mining of bivalve and gastropod RNA-seq experiments, we used more than five million <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads to improve the annotation of viral genomes and to characterize viral InDels, nucleotide stretches, and SNPs. Both genome and protein domain analyses confirmed the evolutionary diversification and gene uniqueness of known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>. However, the presence of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-like sequences integrated within genomes of phylogenetically distant invertebrates indicates broad diffusion of these viruses and indicates the need for confirmatory investigations. The manifest co-occurrence of OsHV-1 genotype variants in single RNA-seq samples of <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic> provide further support for the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> diversification. In addition to simple sequence motifs inter-punctuating viral ORFs, recombination-inducing sequences were found to be enriched in the OsHV-1 and AbHV1-AUS genomes. Finally, the highly correlated expression of most viral ORFs in multiple oyster samples is consistent with the burst of viral proteins during the lytic phase.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic></kwd><kwd>RNA-seq</kwd><kwd>viromes</kwd><kwd>bivalve</kwd><kwd>OsHV-1</kwd><kwd><italic>Herpesvirales</italic></kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Horizon 2020 Framework Programme<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/100010661</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">n&#176;678589</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="8"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="65"/><page-count count="15"/><word-count count="9647"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>The virus family of double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> refers to only those <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> which affect mollusks, with the Haliotid herpesvirus, and bivalve Ostreid herpesvirus-1 being highly similar virus variants and the only family members described so far (Davison et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Savin et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Based on phylogenetic analysis, <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> are distantly related to other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> families, namely <italic>alpha-, beta-, gamma</italic>-, and <italic>allo-herpesviridae</italic> (Davison et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Iranzo et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). In general, the considerable genome size of <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> (125&#8211;290 kb) supports complex transcriptional landscapes, including several coding (ORFs) and non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) such as microRNAs (miRNAs). Modulation of latent vs. lytic phases guarantees long-term survival and efficient propagation of <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>, although viral genomes are exposed to mutational pressure during their latency state into the cell nucleus (Brown, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). In <italic>alpha</italic>- and <italic>gamma</italic>-<italic>herpesvirales</italic>, different recombination-initiating motifs can activate host genome integrity pathways like homologous recombination-dependent DNA repair (HR), a virus-protective strategy proposed as being crucial for <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> biology (Brown, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Piekna-Przybylska et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>Speed, sensitivity, and resolution of current high-throughput sequencing (HTS) technologies have been successfully used to unlock the transcriptional landscape of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus, which is characterized by alternative splicing of viral introns, polycistronic mRNAs, alternative transcription starting sites, and a significant repertoire of ncRNAs (Arias et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Strahan et al., <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Although transcriptome complexity could be a general feature of <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> (Stern-Ginossar et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Ol&#225;h et al., <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Tomb&#225;cz et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), their marked host-adaptation and phylogenetic diversity discourage any oversimplification.</p><p>As reported in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>, the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes of Ostreid herpesvirus type-1 (OsHV-1), <italic>Chlamys</italic> acute necrobiotic virus (AVNV), and Haliotid herpesvirus 1 (AbHV-1-AUS) were sequenced in 2005, 2010, and 2013, respectively. A micro-variant genome called &#956;Var was described in 2010 by mapping its sequence differences on the OsHV-1 genome; a further variant of OsHV-1 (OsHV-1-SB) from diseased <italic>Scapharca broughtonii</italic> and a Taiwanese variant of AbHV-1-AUS (AbHV-1-TAI) were sequenced and recorded at NCBI in 2015 and 2016, respectively. So far, most published studies have focused on the variant &#956;Var, a genotype associated with severe and worldwide events of <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic> mortality (Segarra et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Arzul et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). The variant &#956;Var differs from the reference genome because of small and large deletions and due to some single nucleotide changes (Segarra et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Viruses most likely exist as a mixture of genotypes, and also a recent analysis of OsHV-1 DNA occurring in wild oyster stocks in Italy indicated the co-occurrence of slightly different OsHV-1 genotypes (Burioli et al., <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Expression profiles of both <italic>C. gigas</italic> and OsHV-1s have been investigated by suppression subtractive hybridization (Renault et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), qPCR (Segarra et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2014b</xref>; Green et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2015a</xref>) and by dual RNA-seq applied to oysters which were experimentally infected (He et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and naturally infected (Rosani et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Although OsHV-1 genotypes have been mainly reported in Pacific oysters, OsHV-1 was recently associated with mortality events of the Chinese bivalve <italic>S. broughtonii</italic> (Renault et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Bai et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Xia et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), whereas other bivalve spp. might act as simple virus carriers (Burge et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) or be not susceptible (Tan et al., <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In the same way, the closely related abalone herpesvirus represents an important pathogen for the gastropod family of <italic>Haliotis</italic> spp. (Chang et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Savin et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Corbeil et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Overall, the lack of stringent host-virus specificity indicates <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> as dangerous pathogens for the entire mollusk aquaculture sector.</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Malacoherpesviridae genomes.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Virus name and related host, NCBI ID of the reference genome, genome size, and percentage of annotated ORF are reported for bivalve and gastropod Malacoherpesviridae. Numbering in square brackets is a reference for Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref></italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>While the analysis of infected samples has greatly advanced the general understanding of antiviral pathways in bivalve mollusks (Renault et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Corporeau et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Segarra et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>; Green et al., <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2015b</xref>; Moreau et al., <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Martenot et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), the biology of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> is still obscure. The uniqueness of this viral family within the frame of poorly characterized marine mollusk viromes raises questions as to their evolutionary history, infection mechanisms in different hosts, and the functional roles of their proteins. In the absence of permissive cell lines, the development of &#8220;<italic>ad hoc</italic>&#8221; HTS approaches is today the most promising way to disclose the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> peculiarities.</p><p>In the present work, we used available mollusk RNA-seq data as a source of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads to perform a detailed genomic remapping. Also in comparison with the most recently sequenced virus genomes, we present and discuss the diversity and uniqueness of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, taking into consideration SNPs and sequence motifs and raising some annotation incongruities. In particular, we report the identification of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-like elements endogenously occurring in invertebrate genomes, and sequence motifs related to viral genome protection mechanisms and comprehensive OsHV-1 transcription data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Sequence data</title><p>We retrieved the whole genome sequences and classification of 2,665 dsDNA viruses, including 82 <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>, from the NCBI database. A total of 96 RNA-seq (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) and 8 miRNA-seq (Xu et al., <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) samples from <italic>C. gigas</italic> as well as 159 RNA-seq samples from different <italic>Haliotis</italic> spp. were retrieved from the SRA archive (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>). The <italic>C. gigas</italic> genome was obtained from <italic>Ensemble Metazoa v.3</italic> (Zhang et al., <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). <italic>MiRBase</italic> release 21 was downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mirbase.org/">http://www.mirbase.org/</ext-link> (Kozomara and Griffiths-Jones, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Additionally, scaffolds of genome drafts of Cephalochordates (<italic>Branchiostoma floridae, Branchiostoma belcheri</italic>, and <italic>Asymmetron lucayanum</italic>), <italic>Annelida (Capitella teleta, Hydroides elegans, and Helobdella robusta)</italic>, gastropods <italic>(Lottia gigantea, Aplysia californica, and Conus tribblei)</italic>, and bivalves <italic>(Mytilus galloprovincialis, C. virginica, Mizuhopecten yessoensis, Modiolus philippinarum, and Bathymodiolus platifrons)</italic> were retrieved from the NCBI archive and used to compose a genomic blast database (Camacho et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Identification and mapping of Malacoherpesviridae reads</title><p>If not differently indicated, all the analyses were performed using CLC Genomic Workbench v.10.0 (Qiagen, Germany). RNA reads were trimmed for quality, allowing a maximum of two ambiguous bases and a quality threshold of Q20. To reduce false positive viral hits, the mapping of <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq reads on the oyster genome was performed with the <italic>large gap read mapping</italic> (LGRM) tool. Sequence reads not mapping on the <italic>C. gigas</italic> genome were stringently mapped (0.9 and 0.9 for length and similarity fraction, respectively) on known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes and the resulting positive hits were labeled as &#8220;<italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads&#8221; and retained for subsequent analyses. Viral spliced reads were retrieved by mapping the reads on known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes with LGRM. In the absence of <italic>Haliotid</italic> spp. genomes, abalone RNA reads were directly mapped on known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes with stringent mapping parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis</title><p><italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes were aligned with the progressive Mauve algorithm included in the MAUVE tool (Darling et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> ORFs were compared with other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> ORFs extracted from the downloaded genomes. Predicted proteins were aligned with MUSCLE v.3.8 (Edgar, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>) and phylogenetic trees were generated using the Neighbor Joining algorithm and UPGMA algorithms, with Jukes-Cantor distance estimation and applying 1,000 bootstrap replicates with a significance cut-off set at 500. <italic>Blast</italic> searches were performed locally using BLAST+ (Camacho et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), whereas conserved domains as well as peptide and transmembrane regions were identified by using InterProScan v.60, SignalP, and THMM tools, respectively (Petersen et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Putative <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> endogenous viral elements (EVEs) were searched on 15 invertebrate genomes using <italic>tblastn</italic> with a cut-off <italic>E</italic>-value of 10<sup>&#8722;50</sup> with all the OsHV-1 ORFs as query. The resulting hits were extracted and further inspected.</p></sec><sec><title>Prediction of miRNA precursors and recombination-initiating motifs</title><p>Two <italic>ab-initio</italic> tools for the detection of miRNA precursors were tested on <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes, namely miRPara (Wu et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) and VMir (Grundhoff et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). Briefly, miRPAra is a Support Vector Machine tool that provides 76 parameters predictive of putative hairpin regions on the basis of experimentally verified animal, plant, and virus miRNA models. VMir slides a sequence window of adjustable size across the viral genomes and then employs the RNA fold algorithm to predict structures with minimal free energy folding. Pre-miRNA candidates were identified and scored by evaluating the structural features of known pre-miRNA hairpins. Results obtained with miRPAra and VMir were compared and only common predicted structures were retained as putative <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> miRNAs. To ascertain the presence of any viral miRNAs among <italic>C. gigas</italic> miRNA-seq reads, <italic>de-novo</italic> assembled consensus sequences generated from the 8 miRNA-seq samples were mapped on both <italic>C. gigas</italic> and <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes.</p><p>Nucleotidic motifs indicative of polyadenylation sites (PAS) or representative of conserved patterns were identified by simple textual searches along whole <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes or by applying the MEME tool (Bailey and Elkan, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>) in the 3&#8242; and 5&#8242;UTR ORF regions (the latter were defined as the 100 nt before the starting codon and after the stop codon, respectively). All viral dsDNA genomes were scanned for the presence of six recombination-initiating motifs possibly activating homologous recombination-dependent DNA repair (host HR), and enrichment ratios were calculated as reported in (Brown, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Briefly, sequence motifs were identified in both original sequences and randomized sequences obtained with <italic>shuffleseq</italic> (default parameters, EMBOSS Explorer, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cys.genomics.purdue.edu/emboss/">http://cys.genomics.purdue.edu/emboss/</ext-link>), and then counted. The amount of a given sequence motif in each viral genome was normalized by genome length before computing the motif enrichment (ratio higher than two between original and randomized sequences).</p></sec><sec><title>OsHV-1 expression analysis and SNP calling</title><p>To quantify the expression of viral ORFs, all <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads were stringently mapped on the OsHV-1 reference genome (GenBank ID: <ext-link ext-link-type="DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank" xlink:href="AY509253">AY509253</ext-link>) setting both length and similarity parameters to 0.9. Starting from the read counts, Transcripts Per Million (TPM) values were computed according to Wagner et al. (<xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) in order to evaluate viral expression patterns by Principal Component Analysis (PCA) and ORF clustering (Euclidean distance, single linkage).</p><p>Single Nucleotide Polymorphism (SNP) analysis was performed on mapping files. Nucleotide changes were called &#8220;SNP&#8221; if present in at least 5% of the locally aligned reads using the following parameters: minimum average quality of the five surrounding bases, 15; minimum quality of central base, 20; minimum required coverage, 100x. Subsequently, SNP analysis was repeated on read mappings joined by sample origin and SNPs were compared among groups. SNP calling parameters were maintained except for the coverage, which was lowered to 20x to account for a smaller number of aligned reads.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Tracing the phylogenetic history of divergent <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> (<italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>)</title><p><italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> display a genome size of 199&#8211;212 kb and a number of predicted ORFs ranging from 66 for AbHV-1-TAI to 136 for OsHV-1, always covering most of the genome sequence (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). As for other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>, 5&#8211;15% of the mollusk viral ORFs have a signal peptide region (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Multiple alignment of whole <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes highlighted conserved sequence blocks clearly discriminating two genome types, namely bivalve and gastropod viruses, with very few regions of high similarity between them (e.g., <italic>ribonucleoside-diphosphate reductase</italic>, light violet blocks) and other genomic regions shared between two only of the three bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes (red and light green boxes, Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2</xref>). These regions refer either to intergenic segments, like the variable microsatellite regions that differentiate OsHV-1 from the &#956;Var variant (Segarra et al., <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Martenot et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), or to deletions/insertions that modify the coding potential (e.g., the large deletion of ORF36-37 in the &#956;Var variant (Renault et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Among the latter discriminant features, we remarked a 2.7 kb insertion characterizing the AVNV and OsHV-1-SB genomes (position 60&#8211;63 kb) and encoding three ORFs with unknown function (OsHV-1-SB ORF125, a putative secreted protein; ORF126 and ORF127, a putative transmembrane protein). We later exploited these virus-specific regions to determine which type of virus variant was present in a given RNA sample.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Number of ORFs identified in <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> genomes. The black part of each bar indicates the ORFs fraction with a predicted signal peptide. <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes are highlighted by the red bars.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01515-g0001"/></fig><p>To obtain data useful for reconstructing the evolutionary history of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, we searched for EVEs in a number of invertebrate genomes, including nine bivalve and gastropod genome drafts. The analyzed invertebrate genomes did not include any putative <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> EVEs, the sole exception being ORFs denoting a <italic>Ribonucleotide reductase big subunit</italic>, found in the <italic>C. gigas, M. philippinarum, C. tribbei</italic>, and <italic>C. teleta</italic> genomes. As reported for <italic>B. floridae</italic> (Savin et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), we also identified a portion of a genome scaffold showing high similarity with Herpesvirales sequences in lancelet (Branchiostoma) spp. and in annelid Capitella teleta. These scaffolds matched several <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> ORFs, including viral DNA polymerase (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Phylogenetic trees based on the <italic>catalytic subunit of DNA polymerase</italic> and generated with two different algorithms always showed well-supported clades for the alpha-, beta-, and gamma-Herpesviridae, and for a clade containing <italic>Malacoherpesviridae, allo-Herpesvirales</italic>, and three DNA polymerase sequences retrieved from invertebrate genomes (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In detail, the annelid sequence clustered with bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, whereas the two lancelet sequences clustered as an out group that was more similar to abalone <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>. These results further emphasize the evolutionary divergence of known mollusk viruses from other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> as reported by Davison et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) and Iranzo et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Moreover, the presence of <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> EVEs very similar to <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> (<italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-like) is confirmed not only in <italic>B. floridae</italic> (Savin et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) but also in the <italic>B. belcheri</italic> and <italic>C. teleta</italic> genomes. Depending on the applied algorithm, allo-Herpesvirales clustered as an outgroup of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> or of other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> (data not shown).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Identification of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> endogenous viral elements <italic>(</italic>EVEs) in invertebrate genomes.</p></caption></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic tree of <italic>catalytic subunit of DNA polymerase</italic>. The blue lines represent <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> hits. Background colors highlight <italic>alpha-Herpesvirales</italic> in green, <italic>beta-Herpesvirales</italic> in blue, and <italic>gamma-Herpesvirales</italic> in yellow. The circular cladogram was computed with the Neighbor Joining algorithm and Jukes-Cantor distance estimation. Bootstrap values are reported for each node as percentages calculated over 1,000 performed replicates, with a significance cutoff set at 500.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01515-g0002"/></fig></sec><sec><title><italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-specific genes support the divergence from other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic></title><p>The uniqueness of most of the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genes hampers a comparative identification of conserved protein domains and homologous genes in public sequence databases. Moreover, <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> share amongst themselves, and with other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>, a small number of protein domains which mainly pertain to transcription-related proteins. As previously reported by Davison et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) for OsHV-1, the BIR domain (PF00653) was the only one exclusively found in all <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, whereas some other protein domains were identified as specific to bivalve or gastropod herpesviruses (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">3</xref>). Although some <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> possess proteins inhibiting the host apoptotic pathways, e.g., proteins with a partial BIR domain or a <italic>Bcl-2-like</italic> protein (Wang et al., <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Gallo et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), a highly-confident BIR domain was uniquely found in <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, whereas the FIC, Exo5, and zf-RING_5 domains were detected only in bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>. FIC (PF02661) characterizes proteins mediating post-translational modifications (Roy and Cherfils, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>) and Exo5 characterizes the same clan of other herpesvirus exonucleases (Herpes_UL24 and Herpes_alk_exo domains) including the gastropod <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> exonuclease (PDDEXK_1 domain). Through stable coordination of Zn cations, zf-RING_5 fingers acquire different binding specificities for DNA, RNA, proteins, and/or lipid targets, and therefore pleiotropic roles. For instance, the RING domain of the <italic>immediate-early protein</italic> (ICPO) of herpes simplex virus 1 (HSV-1) has ubiquitin ligase activity, enabling protein targeting for degradation, and inhibits interferon-stimulated host gene production (Taylor et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). As reported in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, the higher number of protein domains unique to gastropods and related to bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> (12 and 3, respectively) is mainly due to a couple of viral genes including six protein domains and encoding a <italic>DNA ligase</italic> (present on both AbHV-1-AUS and AbHV-1-TAI genomes) and a <italic>methyltransferase-like</italic> (present uniquely in AbHV-1-AUS).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Venn diagram of the protein domains detected in bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, gastropod <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, or other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>. Organization of protein domains (with PFAM IDs) of bivalve-exclusive <bold>(left)</bold> and gastropod-exclusive <bold>(right)</bold> viral proteins.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01515-g0003"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Viral ORFs with <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-specific protein domains.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>From left to right: putative ORF annotation and Malacoherpesviridae family members in which they are present (see numbering in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), domain description, total number of Malacoherpesviridae genes showing the specified domain (in parentheses, the number of unique genes), and occurrence of the same domain in other viral families as well as in mollusk genomes</italic>.</p><fn id="TN1"><label>*</label><p><italic>Partial or incomplete sequences are also present in bivalve Malacoherpesviridae</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Putative protein counterparts of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-specific domains</title><p>We further investigated the putative origin of viral genes including <italic>Malacoherpesviridae-exclusive</italic> (among <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>) protein domains by domain-based searches of similar genes in public databases (NCBI) and in available mollusk genomes. Accordingly, we were able to assign <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-specific domains to 17 viral genes, present in all or some of the known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>. Eleven of them matched mollusk counterparts with similar domain organization (<italic>blastp</italic> similarity value &lt; 10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>). Searches within the <italic>C. gigas</italic> gene models identified genes characterized by BIR, guanylate kinase, DNA ligase, FIC, and <italic>eukaryotic translation initiation factor</italic> domains. Other <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>-specific domains showed scarce similarity with host genes characterized by EXO5, PDDEXK_1, zf-RING_5 and Sprt-like domains, whereas the viral RNA-lig_T4_1 and methyltransferase domain did not find any similarity (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>).</p><p>BIR was detected in four bivalve herpesvirus genes and in two AbHV-1-AUS genes (absent in AbHV-1-TAI). Moreover, BIR was highly represented in the <italic>C. gigas</italic> genome, with the oyster protein EKC36433 (initial part of it) showing surprising similarity to one viral gene. Among the viral FICs, only those from dsDNA viruses (not from phages) showed strong conservation of the nine-residue signature of the FIC motif (HPFX(D/E)GNGR) (Roy and Cherfils, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>), whereas the other hits displayed less-conserved motifs, as observed for some bacterial proteins (Khater and Mohanty, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Some other domains of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>&#8211;specific genes are also present in other dsDNA viruses or in bacteria. The Exo5 exonuclease of bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> is unique among viruses, whereas the PDDEXK_1 exonuclease of gastropod <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> shows a wide distribution in the <italic>Caudovirales</italic> family and in other DNA viruses. Finally, the <italic>methyltransferase-like</italic> protein unique to AbHV-1-AUS showed similarity with bacterial and (a few) viral proteins (mainly from phages).</p></sec><sec><title>Only <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq samples include genuine <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads</title><p>We considered a total of 96 <italic>C. gigas</italic> and 159 <italic>Haliotis</italic> spp. RNA-seq samples, accounting for more than 5.5 billion reads, to identify reads generated by transcriptionally active <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>. Before mapping the mollusk RNA sequences on <italic>Malacoviridae</italic> genomes, we exploited the <italic>C. gigas</italic> genome to filter out all host reads from the <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq samples. Since a <italic>Haliotid</italic> genome draft was not available, we directly mapped abalone RNA-seq reads on <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes. Stringent mapping of oyster-genome-unmapped reads on known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes allowed for the selection of 5.483 M reads from the 2.27 billion starting dataset (0.24%), whereas stringent mapping of the <italic>Haliotis</italic> spp. reads produced only 0.01% of mapped reads, with very few reads correctly paired. Manual examination of the mapping files revealed the matching of the gastropod reads to viral oligo-nucleotidic stretches, a fact greatly impairing the mapping specificity. Conversely, the viral reads retrieved from <italic>C. gigas</italic> samples showed a pairing correctness of 94.2%, thus demonstrating that only the <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq samples contained genuine <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads. All analyzed oyster RNA samples (ten of them comprising 90% of the total reads) included at least a few bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> transcripts (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>). The RNA-seq sample richest in viral reads (3.5 % of the total reads) was from a naturally-occurring infection previously described (Rosani et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Viral transcripts were also abundant in samples from more susceptible life stages (larvae, spat, juveniles) and at 24 h post-infection with the variant &#956;Var (only two of the ten richest RNA-seq samples derived from infection trials) (He et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title><italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads are produced by slightly different viral variants</title><p>We further considered the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads mapping on the virus-specific regions previously identified by whole genome alignment (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">2</xref>). Stringent back-mapping of these reads on sequential combinations of bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes (0.9 of sequence similarity computed along the whole read length) supported the assignment of 4.903 M (out of 5.483 M reads) to <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes, with residual ~580 k reads failing the genome assignment step (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). Many of the latter (348 k reads) could be mapped anyway by gradually lowering the similarity mapping parameter to 0.5, a fact suggesting a certain degree of variability of viral RNA reads. Sequential genome mapping showed that 20,251 reads not matching an OsHV-1 sequence region could be re-assigned to a genomic region of AVNV, or OsHV-1-SB (60&#8211;63 kb) including a 2.7 kb insertion typical of these two genomes. <italic>De-novo</italic> assembling of these 20,251 reads confirmed the presence of ORF125 and ORF126, out of the three AVNV ORFs annotated in this region (ORF125-ORF127). A total of 4,461 other reads were attributed to a deletion on ORF103, typical of both OsHV-1 and OsHV-1-SB but absent in AVNV, suggesting the occurrence of a mixture of viral genotypes in the analyzed RNA-seq samples (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). To further endorse this hypothesis, we searched for viral spliced reads. Spliced reads normally result from the mapping of one mRNA read over an intron sequence, whereas in our analysis they were attributed to insertions or deletions occurring in the viral reference genome. Using ultra confident mapping parameters, like 0.95 and 0.95 for similarity and length fraction, we were able to re-assign a portion of the 11,947 spliced reads to the &#956;Var variant and AVNV genomes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>). All the AVNV-re-assigned reads mapped on a 9-nt deletion of ORF104, the one discriminating AVNV from other <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>.</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Identification of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads in <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq data.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>The spliced reads that were recovered with a large gap mapping tool were then re-assigned to Malacoherpesviridae genomes (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>)</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Detailed analysis of three RNA-seq samples rich in viral reads.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>From left to right: sample ID, total number of reads, percentage of C. gigas genomic unmapped reads and, for Malacoherpesviridae, the table illustrates the total number and fraction of reads mapped on unique regions of four viral genomes, with the assignment of percentages to each individual virus</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T6" position="float"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Re-assignment of spliced reads to <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Origin and number of spliced reads and the re-assignment percentages are reported</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Read mapping highlights few annotation inconsistencies in the OsHV-1 genome</title><p>Coverage graph analysis is a powerful tool for detect sequencing anomalies. If reads are unbiasedly produced, the coverage should appear quite homogenous along the entire sequence, even if a 5&#8242; peak may be due to the random fragmentation of multiple mRNA copies of any given transcript, as reported by Arias et al. (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Manual inspection of the coverage graph (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>) along the OsHV-1 genome highlighted a few anomalies. In the ORF104 graph (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>), two distinct peaks are indicative of a mismatch region impairing the read mapping and confirmative of above reported results. In the ORF107 graph (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>), highly uneven coverage (from 250x, along the first 1,000 nucleotides, to 4,800x) suggested the presence of two nested ORFs with completely different expression levels. In fact, we recognized two small ORFs, both of 152 AA length and one of them including three transmembrane regions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>).</p><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Coverage graph of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads <bold>(A)</bold>. Coverage graph of the whole OsHV-1 genome, as obtained by mapping 4.9 M viral reads with length and similarity mapping parameters set to 0.9. Yellow arrowheads indicate annotated ORFs along the virus genome. Maximum coverage was set to 10,000x. <bold>(B)</bold> Details of the ORF104 coverage graph, with the alignment including the 9-nt deletion causing coverage drop-off. <bold>(C)</bold> Details of ORF107 coverage graph, with two nested ORFs (arrows) that could explain the local coverage bias. One ORF encoded three transmembrane regions (highlighted in blue).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01515-g0004"/></fig><p>Moreover, the coverage graph showed that some reads mapped on the five large intergenic OsHV-1 regions. As previously reported, these regions contain non-coding, disrupted ORFs (Davison et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; He et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Following <italic>de-novo</italic> assembling of the reads corresponding to said genomic regions, we recovered few complete ORFs. Although the assembled reads were retrieved from different RNA samples, nearly all of them clustered in one consensus sequence (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T7">7</xref>). In detail, the consensus sequences generated for the 50k and 99k regions were similar to ORF88 (transmembrane OsHV-1 protein), whereas the consensus sequence for the 113k region showed similarity to a protein characterized by a domain found only in the crustacean <italic>White spot syndrome virus</italic> (<italic>Nimaviridae</italic>). Finally, for the three consensus sequences generated from the 72k and 94k regions, no similarities to any already annotated sequences were found.</p><table-wrap id="T7" position="float"><label>Table 7</label><caption><p><italic>De-novo</italic> assembly results of reads mapping on OsHV-1 putative coding regions.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Region name, number of extracted reads, and number of samples from which they originated are reported. Number of de novo assembled contigs, genomic region, and blastp annotation are also reported</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title><italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes include few recognizable sequence motifs</title><p>We searched known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes for nucleotidic motifs, oligo-nucleotidic stretches, and PAS. Simple motif searches revealed oligo-nucleotidic stretches (at least eight equal bases, mainly A or T) were preferentially located in intergenic regions (only 20/399 were found in ORFs). Mapping canonical PAS such as AAUAAA and AUUAAA (Arias et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), we retrieved completely conserved matches in 393 of 559 3&#8242;UTRs. Applying a more sophisticated tool (MEME) to the 5&#8242; and 3&#8242; UTR regions, we identified a longer PAS motif in 126 3&#8242;UTRs and a second 3&#8242;UTR motif. Unfortunately, the diffuse presence of T-stretches in intergenic regions hampered the mapping of reads containing 3&#8242; polyadenylated bases and, hence, an elegant identification of transcript ends, as described by Stern-Ginossar et al. (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). None of the MEME-proposed 5&#8242;-motifs were statistically convincing enough.</p></sec><sec><title>Two DNA recombination-initiating promoter motifs are enriched among <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic></title><p>We initially investigated the presence of six HR promoter motifs in two reference <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes (OsHV-1 and AbHV-1-AUS for bivalve and gastropod viruses, respectively) and then we analyzed the resulting data against 2,665 dsDNA viral genomes. Overall, we recognized 1,443,794, and 1,523,194 motifs in original and randomized viral sequences, respectively. As expected, shorter motifs were more present, whereas a classical meiotic recombination motif (CCTCCCCT) (Myers et al., <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) was found on 1,258 genomes and was labeled as &#8220;enriched&#8221; only in 88 of them. Complete data are reported in Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">4</xref>. Among the 104 invertebrate dsDNA viruses present in the dataset, only a truncated chi-motif (TGGTGG) (Chuzhanova et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>) was widely enriched (in around 50% of the viruses, including OsHV-1 but not AbHV-1-AUS). The CCTCCCCT motif was computed as being &#8220;enriched&#8221; only in four invertebrate viruses, namely the two <italic>Malacoherpesviridae, White spot syndrome virus</italic>, and <italic>Invertebrate iridescent virus 6</italic>, a virus for which the interaction with mammalian antiviral systems was recently reported (Ahlers et al., <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The distribution of CCTCCCCT motif in known <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes revealed its biased presence, with most them located in the second part genomes.</p></sec><sec><title>Do <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes encode genuine miRNAs?</title><p>To infer the presence of miRNAs in <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes, we exploited two <italic>ab-initio</italic> miRNA predictor tools. Compared with VMir, the miRPara algorithm predicted a higher number of putative structured RNAs, with a range of 11&#8211;25 predicted miRNAs per genome commonly identified (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T8">8</xref>). Although most of the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes are covered by ORFs, only 43&#8211;65% of the predicted miRNA structures were located in coding regions, thus indicating their preferential intergenic occurrence. None of the predicted structures found similarity in the miRBase database and, likewise, none of the miRBase hits found a decent match on <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes. Taking into account eight miRNA-seq samples (some of them rich in viral reads, all them belonging to the same oyster batches used to produce developmental RNA-seq libraries), we could not validate any of the predicted viral miRNA regions, nor the miRNA reads mapped to any other viral genome. These analyses do not indicate any genuine <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> miRNA; more focused experiments are needed to definitively clarify this point.</p><table-wrap id="T8" position="float"><label>Table 8</label><caption><p>miRNA prediction results. miRPara and vMir predictions are reported for the six <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes, with total number of predicted regions, common ones and percentage of those located in ORFs.</p></caption></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>OsHV-1 transcription levels are highly comparable among different RNA samples</title><p>We performed a detailed expression analysis by mapping the identified <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads only on the OsHV-1 reference genome and computing the related expression values in TPM. In addition to the already annotated ORFs, we considered the genomic regions for which we had previously observed a read coverage to be &#8220;putative coding regions.&#8221; The number of mapped reads as well as non-normalized (nn-TPM) and normalized (TPM) values calculated per ORF are reported in an interactive table offered as an easy tool for interested readers (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">5</xref>). Although all 96 <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq samples included viral reads, we classified 14 of them as &#8220;high&#8221; (i.e., more than 1,000 counted viral reads, Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">1</xref>). As stated above, this classification does not directly correlate to the number of identified <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads, since it relies only on the reads that stringently mapped on the OsHV-1 reference genome (and were subsequently counted). The RNA samples in which different viral types contributed to the final amount of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads were remarkable (e.g., SRR334249, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). Digital expression analysis highlighted few expression peaks, namely TPMs &gt; 2M for ORF76, ORF80, ORF29, ORF42, ORF88, and for a putative coding region (PUTA_72k). Principal component analysis (PCA) based on TPM-values clearly supported the &#8220;high-expression&#8221; grouping based on the counted reads (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">6.1</xref>). Few ORFs were expressed in almost all RNA-seq samples, such as ORF76, which represents 13% of the total TPMs and has an extremely high relative expression in every sample (although significantly expressed also in &#8220;high&#8221; samples, as showed by non-TPMs). On the contrary, several ORFs showed a preferential occurrence in selected samples, like ORF27, ORF45, ORF80, ORF82, ORF90, ORF104, ORF107, and ORF113, which grouped in a unique expression cluster (Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">6.2</xref>). Among the several ORFs with unknown function, ORF18 encoding for a 94-aa peptide was highly expressed in multiple RNA-seq samples. As clearly shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, almost all viral ORFs are simultaneously expressed in &#8220;high&#8221; samples, with very few line interruptions corresponding to ORF36, ORF37, and ORF48 previously reported as not functional (He et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In agreement with the results obtained from coverage graph analysis, detectable expression levels were evident for ORF50 (PUTA_72k), ORF62 and ORF63 (PUTA_94k), ORF65 (PUTA_99k), ORF73 (PUTA_113k), and (PUTA_110k).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Radar graph depicting the viral TPM values in 14 RNA-seq samples selected as &#8220;high&#8221;. Expression values are reported with a logarithmic scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01515-g0005"/></fig></sec><sec><title>SNPs analysis supports the presence of OsHV-1 variants within RNA samples</title><p>Using a conservative SNP-calling algorithm, we identified 664 variable positions consisting in changes of single nucleotides or small stretches (maximal 5 nt). Eighty-six percent of these SNPs mapped on annotated genes, with the majority of them (75%) involving amino acid substitutions (nsSNP). The total SNPs were distributed on 94 ORFs (40 ORFs are invariant) and non-synonymous (ns) SNP occurred in 87 ORFs (37 ORFs display only nsSNPs, seven only synonymous ones). ORF124 and ORF18 showed the maximal frequency of SNP (1.2%) and of nsSNP (1.1%), respectively (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). As reported above, the interactive Supplementary File <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">5</xref> also includes the SNP frequencies for each OsHV-1 ORF. In spite of their high expression levels, some ORFs showed very few SNPs or appeared invariable, as expected in the case of strict functional constraints. Further analysis of the viral SNPs in the RNA-seq samples grouped by geographical origin produced a core set of 78 common SNPs, with the main part of them supporting an effective difference between sample groups (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). Although most of the common SNPs concerned differences between the sampled viruses and the reference OsHV-1 (present at 100% frequency in all groups), 20 SNPs displayed a frequency lower than 95% in at least one group. Using the frequencies of those SNPs to &#8220;genotype&#8221; undefined OsHV-1-mixtures in eight selected RNA-seq samples, we were able to infer the variable presence of slightly different viruses in single stocks of virus-infected <italic>C. gigas</italic> (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6C</xref>), as previously suggested by read mapping on unique genomic regions (reported in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>).</p><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> SNPs occurrence in OsHV-1 ORFs. The graph depicts the ratio of nsSNP vs. total SNP for the ORFs presenting at least one variation. Globe size is proportional to the number of SNP for each ORF. <bold>(B)</bold> Common and exclusive SNPs indicated in the Venn diagram resulted from the comparison of oyster RNA-seq samples grouped by origin. <bold>(C)</bold> &#8220;Genotyping&#8221; graph based on 20 polymorphic common OsHV-1 SNPs in the eight samples richest in viral reads (indicated by IDs).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-08-01515-g0006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>HTS methodologies have extraordinarily contributed to the understanding of the viral world in the ocean (Brum et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Even though viruses are massively present in coastal waters (Suttle, <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), only a minimal number of them are represented in sequence databases. This bias allows for the discovery of new viruses in almost every virome study, as recently reported for six new bivalve-associated RNA viruses (Rosani and Gerdol, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and for RNA viruses associated with invertebrates (Shi et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Nevertheless, bivalve viromes essentially remain unknown, except for a few pathogenic viruses (Arzul et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>).</p><p>In the present work, we focused on the family of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, a case study considering their enigmatic evolutionary origin and limited transcriptional/genomic data. Moreover, <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> represent an urgent problem for mollusk aquaculture worldwide: their recurrent association with host mortality outbreaks may lead to a better understanding of their life cycles and dynamic host-pathogen interactions, ultimately for the development of effective prevention and mitigation strategies (Davison et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Corbeil et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Pernet et al., <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). The previously reported divergence of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> from other <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> suggests that long-lasting evolutionary processes may have given rise to the only <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> genomes known to infect invertebrates. Although TEM imaging of <italic>herpes-like</italic> particles supports the occurrence of <italic>Herpesvirales</italic> in corals, recent sequencing data are somewhat elusive (Correa et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Moreover, further studies are necessary to assess the presence of <italic>herpes-like</italic> viruses in crustaceans (Bang, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">1971</xref>; Ryazanova et al., <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Intriguingly, we reported Herpesvirales-like sequence elements in genomic scaffolds of <italic>C. teleta</italic> and <italic>Branciostoma</italic> spp. In agreement with Savin and colleagues (Savin et al., <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) demonstrated that <italic>B. floridae</italic> sequence is highly similar to Abalone <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>), we have shown that <italic>C. teleta</italic>-encoded DNA polymerase is more similar to bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, whereas both Branchiostoma-derived DNA polymerase clustered as an <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> outgroup. Taken together, these findings suggest a broader presence of invertebrate-infecting <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>, representing former or extant (still undisclosed) viruses. Although the integration of genetic elements of large DNA viruses in invertebrate host genomes has already been reported (Drezen et al., <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>), further experimental validation is needed to definitively prove the integration of these sequences in host genomes.</p><p>The few predictable protein domains of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> (most of the <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genes are unique) suggested complex evolutionary paths, including gene transfer events from other dsDNA viruses (in particular, invertebrate viruses), bacteria, and also from mollusk hosts. Among other protein domains, we focused on BIR-containing proteins (putative inhibitors of apoptosis), because apoptotic responses are reported as one of the main bivalve countermeasures to infections due to the &#956;Var variant (Segarra et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">2014b</xref>; He et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Martenot et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>) and BIR was found in several dsDNA and ssRNA viruses of invertebrates. Phylogenetic analysis of metazoan and viral BIRs did not indicate any robust evolutionary relationships, thus supporting the hypothesis of extensive gene transfer. We highlighted other common features of invertebrate dsDNA viruses by analyzing promoter sequence motifs involved in virus-protective DNA repair. Invertebrate dsDNA viruses analyzed in this work mainly encode one of the six searched HR promoter motifs, namely a truncated version of the chi-element, whereas almost only <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> are enriched in a classical meiotic recombination motif. These results support the interaction of <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> with host recombination machinery, although probably with promoter motifs that are partially different from the vertebrate ones (and unknown). Commonalities emerged between <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> and <italic>Whispovirus</italic> (<italic>White spot syndrome virus 1</italic>), namely shared domains and similar HR promoter enrichment patterns. An overlap between arthropod (in this case crustaceans) and bivalve viromes was recently reported for several RNA viral families (Shi et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) which might be a fascinating matter for future studies. Moreover, the reduced species-specificity for <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> somewhat recalls the lack of virus-host co-divergence observed in invertebrate RNA viruses (Shi et al., <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and calls for a broad, not species-specific mechanism of action.</p><p>Given the lack of permissive cell cultures, we used oyster RNA-seq samples as an effective (and unique) source of viral reads. In the so-called &#8220;RNA-seq dark matter&#8221; (Ponting and Belgard, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>), the accidental or deliberate sequencing of OsHV-1-infected oysters can make millions of viral reads available, revealing active viral transcription. Despite the analysis of numerous <italic>Haliotid</italic> RNA-seq samples, no similar results could be achieved for abalones. Read mapping on <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> unique genome regions as well as SNP analysis suggested the presence of more than one viral variant within and between RNA-seq samples. One virus type was preferentially present (i.e., more transcriptional active) in each host transcriptome sample, although a single virus encoding all the variants typical of different mollusk viruses might exist. Advanced ultra-deep RNA and DNA sequencing would be optimal to ascertain this point.</p><p>Although OsHV-1 was apparently suppressed in many of the analyzed samples (e.g., samples with less than a thousand viral reads), only proper controls could validate this hypothesis and assign the expressed viral ORFs to the persistent virus phase. Therefore, we only observed the broad expression of ORF76 in almost all samples with few viral reads. Interestingly, a limited structural similarity of ORF76 with the human nucleoporin (data not shown) postulates a role of this protein in the viral entry inside cell nucleus. Viral expression profiles were particularly informative in highly infected samples (supposed lithic virus phase), with most viral ORFs actively expressed and no predominant expression of single ORFs. Actually, the concordance between ORF expression ratios in these samples was a remarkable finding possibly revealing the functional importance of many viral proteins during virus replication, like in the case of the highly expressed dUTPase (ORF27, completely lacking nsSNPs) in agreement with (Segarra et al., <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>,<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). Functional validation based on <italic>in-situ</italic> hybridization, western blot and recombinant proteins is definitively needed to investigate the functional role of viral ORFs, as previously initiated (Martenot et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>; Segarra et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>Despite the lack of functional data for <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, conserved intergenic features might reveal hidden traits of virus-host co-existence mechanisms. The current expansion of mollusk genomics is expected to answer some of the open questions mentioned in this work. Our analyses demonstrated that viral transcriptomics may greatly contribute to the understanding of the molecular facets of new viral variants including ORFs and aminoacidic changes crucially related to the pathogenic nature of certain variants, and may be useful to improve diagnostic qPCR-based methods.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author contributions</title><p>UR and PV designed the analytical pipeline, UR performed the bioinformatic analysis, UR and PV prepared the manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research project was supported by the EU funded project VIVALDI (H2020 programme, n&#176;678589).</p></ack><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s6"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01515/full#supplementary-material">http://journal.frontiersin.org/article/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01515/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><label>Supplementary File 1</label><caption><p>Sequencing samples considered in the present work. Experiment description, SRA ID and sample description, number of millions reads, and number of identified <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> reads are reported. Underlined samples with more than 1,000 viral reads are indicated as &#8220;high&#8221; samples.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table1.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><label>Supplementary File 2</label><caption><p>Whole genome alignment of five <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic> genomes using progressive MAUVE. From top to bottom: OsHV-1, OsHV-1-SB, AVNV, AbHV-1-AUS, and AbHV-1-TAI. Conserved sequence blocks are reported in the same color whereas the available annotations are reported as empty boxes just below the colored blocks for each genome.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Image1.TIF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><label>Supplementary File 3</label><caption><p>PFAM domains encoded by <italic>Herpesvirales</italic>. Domain name, PFAM accession, domain description, and length are reported. Each domain is labeled (&#8220;yes&#8221;) if present in bivalve <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, gastropod <italic>Malacoherpesviridae</italic>, or other <italic>Herpesvirales. Malacoherpesviridae</italic>&#8211;exclusive domains are highlighted in yellow.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table3.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><label>Supplementary File 4</label><caption><p>Distribution of six HR promoters in 2,665 dsDNA viral genomes. From left to right: virus name, NCBI accession, genome length, number of predicted proteins, and main host and, for the six recombination-initiating motifs, the table illustrates their quantity, their genome-length normalized frequencies, and their enrichment ratios.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table4.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><label>Supplementary File 5</label><caption><p>Interactive visualization of the expression patterns of viral ORFs in <italic>C. gigas</italic> RNA-seq samples. Number of mapped reads per sample, non-normalized, and TPM expression values as well as total and non-synonymous SNPs are reported for any selected ORF.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table5.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6"><label>Supplementary File 6</label><caption><p>ORF expression analysis. Figure SF6_1. Correlation plot of Principal Component Analysis (PCA). Red and green dots indicate RNA-seq samples labeled as &#8220;high&#8221; or not labelled, respectively. Figure SF6_2. Clustering of viral ORFs. ORFs are clustered based on their TPM values using an Euclidean distance algorithm. &#8220;High&#8221; samples are framed in black. See the color legend at the bottom of the figure.</p></caption><media xlink:href="Table6.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahlers</surname><given-names>L. R. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastos</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiroyasu</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Invertebrate iridescent virus 6, a DNA virus, stimulates a mammalian innate immune response through RIG-I-Like receptors</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0166088</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0166088</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27824940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27824940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisburd</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stern-Ginossar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madrid</surname><given-names>A. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellare</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>KSHV 2.0: a comprehensive annotation of the Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus genome using next-generation sequencing reveals novel genomic and functional features</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e1003847</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1003847</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24453964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24453964</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arzul</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbeil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morga</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Viruses infecting marine molluscs</article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>147</volume>, <fpage>118</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2017.01.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28189502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28189502</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Emerging and endemic types of <italic>Ostreid herpesvirus</italic> 1 were detected in bivalves in China</article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>124</volume>, <fpage>98</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2014.11.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25483846?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25483846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Elkan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Fitting a mixture model by expectation maximization to discover motifs in biopolymers. <italic>Proc. Int. Conf. Intell. Syst. Mol</italic></article-title>. <source>Biol.</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>28</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bang</surname><given-names>F. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1971</year>). <article-title>Transmissible disease, probably viral in origin, affecting the amebocytes of the European shore crab, <italic>Carcinus maenas. Infect</italic></article-title>. <source>Immun.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>617</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>623</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The role of DNA repair in herpesvirus pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Genomics</source>
<volume>104</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>294</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygeno.2014.08.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25173572?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25173572</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Herpes simplex virus latency: the DNA repair-centered pathway</article-title>. <source>Adv. Virol.</source>
<volume>2017</volume>:<fpage>7028194</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2017/7028194</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28255301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28255301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brum</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ignacio-Espinoza</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roux</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doulcier</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Acinas</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alberti</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Ocean plankton. Patterns and ecological drivers of ocean viral communities</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>348</volume>:<fpage>1261498</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1261498</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25999515?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25999515</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strenge</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Friedman</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Detection of the oyster herpesvirus in commercial bivalve in northern California, USA: conventional and quantitative PCR</article-title>. <source>Dis. Aquat. Org.</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>116</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/dao02314</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21648239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21648239</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burioli</surname><given-names>E. A. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prearo</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riina</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bona</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fioravanti</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Ostreid herpesvirus type 1 genomic diversity in wild populations of <italic>Pacific oyster Crassostrea gigas</italic> from Italian coasts</article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>137</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2016.05.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27234424?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27234424</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulouris</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avagyan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bealer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>BLAST+: architecture and applications</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>421</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-10-421</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20003500?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20003500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ting</surname><given-names>Y. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Herpes-like virus infection causing mortality of cultured abalone <italic>Haliotis diversicolor</italic> supertexta in Taiwan</article-title>. <source>Dis. Aquat. Org.</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>23</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>27</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/dao065023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16042040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16042040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuzhanova</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacolla</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrinos</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#233;rec</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Gene conversion causing human inherited disease: evidence for involvement of non-B-DNA-forming sequences and recombination-promoting motifs in DNA breakage and repair</article-title>. <source>Hum. Mutat.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>1189</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1198</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/humu.21020</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19431182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19431182</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbeil</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>McColl</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>M. S. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Australian abalone (<italic>Haliotis laevigata, H. rubra and H. conicopora)</italic> are susceptible to infection by multiple abalone herpesvirus genotypes</article-title>. <source>Dis. Aquat. Organ.</source>
<volume>119</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>106</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/dao02989</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27137068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27137068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corporeau</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamayo</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pernet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu&#233;r&#233;</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Madec</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Proteomic signatures of the oyster metabolic response to herpesvirus OsHV-1 &#956;Var infection</article-title>. <source>J. Proteomics</source>
<volume>109</volume>, <fpage>176</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>187</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2014.06.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25009143?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25009143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>A. M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainsworth</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosales</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thurber</surname><given-names>A. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega Thurber</surname><given-names>R. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Viral outbreak in corals associated with an <italic>in situ</italic> bleaching event: atypical herpes-like viruses and a new megavirus infecting symbiodinium</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>127</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2016.00127</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26941712?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26941712</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>progressiveMauve: multiple genome alignment with gene gain, loss and rearrangement</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e11147</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0011147</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20593022?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Minson</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>The order Herpesvirales</article-title>. <source>Arch. Virol.</source>
<volume>154</volume>, <fpage>171</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>177</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00705-008-0278-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19066710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19066710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trus</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A novel class of herpesvirus with bivalve hosts</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>41</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>53</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/vir.0.80382-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15604430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15604430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drezen</surname><given-names>J.-M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gauthier</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Josse</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#233;zier</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herniou</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huguet</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Foreign DNA acquisition by invertebrate genomes</article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>147</volume>, <fpage>157</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>168</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2016.09.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27642089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27642089</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>MUSCLE: a multiple sequence alignment method with reduced time and space complexity</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>113</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-5-113</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15318951?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15318951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lampe</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#252;nther</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brune</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>The Viral Bcl-2 homologs of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated herpesvirus and rhesus rhadinovirus share an essential role for viral replication</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>e01875</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01875-16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28053098?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28053098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raftos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Speck</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagnani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015b</year>). <article-title>Antiviral immunity in marine molluscs</article-title>. <source>J. Gen. Virol.</source>
<volume>96</volume>, <fpage>2471</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2482</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jgv.0.000244</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26297577?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26297577</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>J.-L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergnes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raftos</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Montagnani</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015a</year>). <article-title>OsHV-1 countermeasures to the Pacific oyster's anti-viral response</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immunol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>, <fpage>435</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>443</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2015.09.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26384844?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26384844</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grundhoff</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganem</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>A combined computational and microarray-based approach identifies novel microRNAs encoded by human gamma-herpesviruses</article-title>. <source>RNA N. Y. N</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>750</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1261/rna.2326106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16540699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16540699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouaux</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lelong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sourdaine</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathieu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Transcriptome analysis reveals strong and complex antiviral response in a mollusc</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immunol.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>144</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2015.05.023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26004318?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26004318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iranzo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupovic</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koonin</surname><given-names>E. V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The Double-Stranded DNA virosphere as a modular hierarchical network of gene sharing</article-title>. <source>MBio</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e00978</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>16</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/mBio.00978-16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27486193?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27486193</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khater</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title><italic>In silico</italic> identification of AMPylating enzymes and study of their divergent evolution</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>10804</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep10804</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26039278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26039278</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozomara</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffiths-Jones</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>miRBase: annotating high confidence microRNAs using deep sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>D68</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>D73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1181</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24275495?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24275495</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martenot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gervais</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chollet</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houssin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Haemocytes collected from experimentally infected Pacific oysters, <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic>: detection of ostreid herpesvirus 1 DNA, RNA, and proteins in relation with inhibition of apoptosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>e0177448</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0177448</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28542284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28542284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martenot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houssin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title><italic>In situ</italic> localization and tissue distribution of ostreid herpesvirus 1 proteins in infected Pacific oyster, <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>136</volume>, <fpage>124</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>135</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2016.04.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27066775?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27066775</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martenot</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Travaill&#233;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lethuillier</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lelong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Houssin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Genome exploration of six variants of the Ostreid Herpesvirus 1 and characterization of large deletion in OsHV-1&#956;Var specimens</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source>
<volume>178</volume>, <fpage>462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>470</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2013.08.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24050996?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24050996</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourbiez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Travers</surname><given-names>M.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubinsztein</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Autophagy plays an important role in protecting Pacific oysters from OsHV-1 and <italic>Vibrio aestuarianus</italic> infections</article-title>. <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>516</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>526</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15548627.2015.1017188</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25714877?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25714877</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bottolo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>McVean</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Donnelly</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A fine-scale map of recombination rates and hotspots across the human genome</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>310</volume>, <fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>324</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1117196</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16224025?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16224025</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ol&#225;h</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomb&#225;cz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#243;ka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Csabai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prazs&#225;k</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boldogk&#337;i</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Characterization of pseudorabies virus transcriptome by Illumina sequencing</article-title>. <source>BMC Microbiol.</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12866-015-0470-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26129912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26129912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pernet</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lupo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacher</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Infectious diseases in oyster aquaculture require a new integrated approach</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>371</volume>:<fpage>20150213</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2015.0213</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26880845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26880845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>T. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>SignalP 4.0: discriminating signal peptides from transmembrane regions</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>785</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>786</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.1701</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21959131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21959131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piekna-Przybylska</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggirwar</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bambara</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Deficiency in DNA damage response, a new characteristic of cells infected with latent HIV-1</article-title>. <source>Cell Cycle</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>968</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>978</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15384101.2017.1312225</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28388353?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28388353</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ponting</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Belgard</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Transcribed dark matter: meaning or myth?</article-title>
<source>Hum. Mol. Genet.</source>
<volume>19</volume>, <fpage>R162</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>R168</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/ddq362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20798109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Complete genome sequence of acute viral necrosis virus associated with massive mortality outbreaks in the Chinese scallop, <italic>Chlamys farreri</italic></article-title>. <source>Virol. J.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-10-110</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23566284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23566284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbosa-Solomieu</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Suppression substractive hybridisation (SSH) and real time PCR reveal differential gene expression in the Pacific cupped oyster, <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic>, challenged with <italic>Ostreid herpesvirus</italic> 1</article-title>. <source>Dev. Comp. Immunol.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>725</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>735</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dci.2011.02.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21371503?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21371503</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pepin</surname><given-names>J.-F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Analysis of clinical ostreid herpesvirus 1 (Malacoherpesviridae) specimens by sequencing amplified fragments from three virus genome areas</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>86</volume>, <fpage>5942</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5947</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.06534-11</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22419803?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22419803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosani</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerdol</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>A bioinformatics approach reveals seven nearly-complete RNA-virus genomes in bivalve RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source> [Epub ahead of print]. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2016.10.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27769778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27769778</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosani</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Varotto</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Domeneghetti</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcangeli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallavicini</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venier</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Dual analysis of host and pathogen transcriptomes in ostreid herpesvirus 1-positive <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic></article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>4200</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4212</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.12706</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25384719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25384719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roy</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherfils</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Structure and function of Fic proteins</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>631</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>640</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3520</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26299785?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26299785</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryazanova</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliseikina</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalabekov</surname><given-names>I. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Odintsova</surname><given-names>N. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A herpes-like virus in king crabs: characterization and transmission under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>127</volume>, <fpage>21</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2015.02.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25712900?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25712900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savin</surname><given-names>K. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cocks</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawbridge</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cogan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savage</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A neurotropic herpesvirus infecting the gastropod, abalone, shares ancestry with oyster herpesvirus and a herpesvirus associated with the amphioxus genome</article-title>. <source>Virol. J.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>308</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1743-422X-7-308</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21062506?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21062506</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourbiez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Detection and distribution of ostreid herpesvirus 1 in experimentally infected Pacific oyster spat</article-title>. <source>J. Invertebr. Pathol.</source>
<volume>133</volume>, <fpage>59</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jip.2015.11.013</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26674009?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26674009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillon</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourbiez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benabdelmouna</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourgougnon</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014a</year>). <article-title>Ostreid herpesvirus type 1 replication and host response in adult Pacific oysters, <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic></article-title>. <source>Vet. Res.</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13567-014-0103-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25294338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25294338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauduit</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trancart</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#233;gremont</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tourbiez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014b</year>). <article-title>Dual transcriptomics of virus-host interactions: comparing two Pacific oyster families presenting contrasted susceptibility to ostreid herpesvirus 1</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>15</volume>:<fpage>580</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-580</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25012085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25012085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segarra</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#233;pin</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arzul</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morga</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Faury</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Detection and description of a particular Ostreid herpesvirus 1 genotype associated with massive mortality outbreaks of Pacific oysters, <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic>, in France in 2008</article-title>. <source>Virus Res.</source>
<volume>153</volume>, <fpage>92</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.virusres.2010.07.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20638433?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20638433</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>X.-D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>J.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L.-J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C.-X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Redefining the invertebrate RNA virosphere</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>540</volume>, <fpage>539</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>543</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature20167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern-Ginossar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisburd</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michalski</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>V. T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>M. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>S.-X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Decoding human cytomegalovirus</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>338</volume>, <fpage>1088</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1093</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1227919</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23180859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strahan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Uppal</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verma</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Next-Generation sequencing in the understanding of Kaposi's sarcoma-associated Herpesvirus (KSHV) biology</article-title>. <source>Viruses</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>92</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/v8040092</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27043613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27043613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suttle</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Marine viruses &#8212; major players in the global ecosystem</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>801</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>812</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1750</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17853907?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17853907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>T. L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul-Pont</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>O. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watterson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whittington</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Resistance of Black-lip learl oyster, <italic>Pinctada margaritifera</italic>, to infection by <italic>Ostreid herpes</italic> virus 1&#956;var under experimental challenge may be mediated by humoral antiviral activity</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immunol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>232</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>240</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2015.02.026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25712854?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25712854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chew</surname><given-names>M. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashkar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mossman</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Novel roles of cytoplasmic ICP0: proteasome-independent functions of the RING finger are required to block interferon-stimulated gene production but not to promote viral replication</article-title>. <source>J. Virol.</source>
<volume>88</volume>, <fpage>8091</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8101</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.00944-14</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24807717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomb&#225;cz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Csabai</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ol&#225;h</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bal&#225;zs</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lik&#243;</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zsigmond</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Full-length isoform sequencing reveals novel transcripts and substantial transcriptional overlaps in a Herpesvirus</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0162868</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0162868</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27685795?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27685795</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>A model based criterion for gene expression calls using RNA-seq data</article-title>. <source>Theory Biosci. Theor. Den Biowissenschaften</source>
<volume>132</volume>, <fpage>159</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>164</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12064-013-0178-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23615947?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23615947</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.-W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>T. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koumi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koentges</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boshoff</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Characterization of an anti-apoptotic glycoprotein encoded by <italic>Kaposi's sarcoma</italic>-associated herpesvirus which resembles a spliced variant of human survivin</article-title>. <source>EMBO J.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>2602</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2615</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/21.11.2602</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12032073?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12032073</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>MiRPara: a SVM-based software tool for prediction of most probable microRNA coding regions in genome scale sequences</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>107</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21504621?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21504621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Complete genome sequence of Ostreid herpesvirus-1 associated with mortalities of <italic>Scapharca broughtonii</italic> broodstocks</article-title>. <source>Virol. J.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>110</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12985-015-0334-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26209441?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26209441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Identification of conserved and novel microRNAs in the Pacific oyster <italic>Crassostrea gigas</italic> by deep sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e104371</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104371</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25137038?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25137038</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The oyster genome reveals stress adaptation and complexity of shell formation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>490</volume>, <fpage>49</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature11413</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22992520?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22992520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>