<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Cell Infect Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Cell. Infect. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2235-2988</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5241278</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2017.00001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>General Commentary</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Commentary: Systems Biology Approach to Model the Life Cycle of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carrea</surname><given-names>Alejandra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/393456/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Diambra</surname><given-names>Luis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/52751/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Laboratorio de Biolog&#237;a de Sistemas, Centro Regional de Estudios Gen&#243;micos, Facultad de Ciencias Exactas, Universidad Nacional de La Plata</institution><country>La Plata, Argentina</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#237;ficas y T&#233;cnicas</institution><country>Argentina</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Claudio Silva, Federal University of Uberlandia, Brazil</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Luciana Oliveira Andrade, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, Brazil; Jie Zheng, University of Pennsylvania, USA; Diana Bahia, Universidade Federal de Minas Gerais, Brazil</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Alejandra Carrea <email xlink:type="simple">carrea.alejandra@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>1</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2017 Carrea and Diambra.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Carrea and Diambra</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e126" related-article-type="commentary-article" xlink:href="26752404" ext-link-type="pubmed" journal-id="PLoS ONE" journal-id-type="nlm-ta" vol="11" page="e0146947">A commentary on <article-title>Systems Biology Approach to Model the Life Cycle of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></article-title> by Carrea, A., and Diambra, L. (2016). PLoS ONE 11:e0146947. doi: <object-id>10.1371/journal.pone.0146947</object-id></related-article><kwd-group><kwd>gene regulatory network</kwd><kwd><italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></kwd><kwd>metabolic enzymes</kwd><kwd>moonlighting proteins</kwd><kwd>computational approaches</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="28"/><page-count count="3"/><word-count count="2286"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>In a recent work we have identified, from a bigger gene regulatory network, a seven-node module involved in the control of the life cycle of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic> (<italic>T. cruzi</italic>) (Carrea and Diambra, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). To that end, we have analyzed microarray gene-expression data of the four different <italic>T. cruzi</italic>'s life cycle stages, by means of a systems biology approach. The found module is the smallest gene regulatory subnetwork able to emulate the dynamical properties of the parasite. This module is composed of nine genes: three of them coding for uncharacterized proteins, and the other six genes coding for characterized proteins. The latter code for: a hexokinase, a &#948;-1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate dehydrogenase, a quinone oxidoreductase, a glutamate dehydrogenase, a peptidyl-prolyl <italic>cis-trans</italic> isomerase, and a metaciclina II. Except for metaciclina II, these genes code for proteins involved in metabolic pathways. Thus, we were expecting gene-expression regulatory proteins instead of the striking information we obtained. Yet, it eventually became clear that these metabolic enzymes could have other regulatory functions beyond their known metabolic one. This type of multifunctional proteins are known as moonlighting proteins (Jeffery, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). They were first discovered in the late 1980s by Piatigorsky et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). They found that the lens structural protein &#948;-crystallin and the metabolic enzyme argininosuccinate lyase are both encoded by the same gene in ducks. Today, it is well-known that moonlighting proteins comprise diverse kinds of proteins, and that they are present in many different organisms including animals, plants, yeasts, prokaryotes, and protists (for reviews see Jeffery, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Huberts and van der Klei, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Jeffery, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><p>Moonlighting proteins characterized so far in unicellular parasites are mostly enzymes. Examples of these parasite's moonlighting enzymes include: a hexokinase in <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic>, which functions as a hemoglobin receptor within the parasite's flagellar pocket; the glycolytic enzyme aldolase in <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic> and <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic>, which has an additional (even if non-essential) function in host-cell invasion; various soluble metabolic enzymes in <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis</italic>, which moonlight as adhesins allowing parasite-host cell adhesion; the mitochondrial peroxiredoxin in <italic>Leishmania infantum</italic>, which not only functions as a peroxidase, but also as a chaperone essential for pathogenesis; the &#945;-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase E2 in bloodstream <italic>Trypanosoma brucei</italic>, which moonlights in the mitochondria ensuring a correct kinetoplast DNA inheritance (Collingridge et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Ginger, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Recently, Ferreira and colleagues have shown that the enzyme mevalonate kinase, originally involved in sterol isoprenoids biosynthesis in <italic>T. cruzi</italic>'s glycosomes, is also secreted and may modulate host cell signaling during parasite invasion (Ferreira et al., <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>).</p><p>A search carried out in two different moonlighting protein databases (MoonProt: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.moonlightingproteins.org">http://www.moonlightingproteins.org</ext-link> Mani et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>, and MultitaskProtDB: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wallace.uab.es/multitask">http://wallace.uab.es/multitask</ext-link> Hern&#225;ndez et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) showed that for the five metabolic enzymes that comprise the above mentioned module, there exist homologous enzymes in other organism/s with proven moonlighting function/s (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Another fact that came to light from this search is that, until now, there is no record of proteins moonlighting in <italic>T. cruzi</italic> in these two databases. Furthermore, there are several other examples in literature showing that some of these five enzymes actually moonlight, or have the potential to do so, in different organisms. We have previously mentioned hexokinase moonlighting as a hemoglobin receptor in <italic>Leishmania donovani</italic> (Collingridge et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Mantilla and colleagues have proposed that <italic>T. cruzi</italic>'s &#948;-1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate dehydrogenase has additional functions beyond the production of glutamate (Mantilla et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). They have suggested that this enzyme could be involved in the infection process, interacting with components of the mammalian host cells. They have based this hypothesis in enzyme structural data, in its mitochondrial membrane localization, and in its higher activity observed during the infective stages of the parasite. Another example is the peptidyl-prolyl <italic>cis-trans</italic> isomerase known as Mip, which moonlights as a host collagen IV biding protein in <italic>Legionella pneumophila</italic>. Rasch and colleagues have identified a 13-aminoacid-long peptide in collagen IV as the target of Mip, and have found that blocking this binding causes a decrease in bacterial transmigration <italic>in vitro</italic> (Rasch et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Moonlighting functions of the five enzymes that comprise the module controlling the <italic>T. cruzi</italic>'s life cycle in other organisms, according to MoonProt and MultitaskProtDB</bold>.</p></caption></table-wrap><p>Taking all of the above into consideration, it follows that not limiting the functions of a given protein to its canonical one, while keeping in mind that it could be a moonlighting protein, is of the uppermost importance. Moreover, in the search of new therapeutic targets, it would be interesting and useful to investigate these moonlighting functions in previously well characterized proteins. In doing so, it must be remembered that moonlighting proteins constitute a major challenge when it comes to predicting their functions based solely on sequence homology or on conserved domains. This analysis could lead to the loss of some proteins' functions or to the assignment of wrong functions to other proteins (Jeffery, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). To overcome this difficulty, computational approaches combining several types of data (available omics-scale data, functional annotations in public databases, bioinformatics predictions, computational simulations of pathways, molecular dynamics of biomolecules, and other biochemical data) have been developed (Khan and Kihara, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Khan et al., <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). These integrative computational strategies will allow us to deepen our knowledge of moonlighting proteins and, therefore improve the design of drugs that must affect only the desired function of the target protein (Khan and Kihara, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), and will also help us understand how and why these proteins can be essential during infection, virulence or immune responses (Jeffery, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>).</p><p>Finally, in relation to <italic>T. cruzi</italic>'s pathogenesis, all these progresses could increase our current knowledge of host-parasite interactions, and help accelerate the discovery of effective drugs against Chagas disease. In a systems biology context, moonlighting proteins can function as a link or switch between two different pathways, and aid the cell to respond to environmental changes (Jeffery, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Transitions between two different developmental stages in <italic>T. cruzi</italic> may be triggered by environmental changes such as the availability of nutrients or energy sources. To mention one representative example, it was demonstrated that L-proline amino acid plays an essential role during intracellular differentiation of <italic>T. cruzi</italic> in the mammalian host (Tonelli et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). This raises the possibility that enzymes participating in metabolic pathways could be, in addition, moonlighting proteins. Therefore, we suggest that the five metabolic enzymes resultant from our previous work (Carrea and Diambra, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) should be considered when studying <italic>T. cruzi</italic> and its implications in human health.</p><sec id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>AC and LD conceived and designed the work, and analyzed and interpreted the data. AC wrote the manuscript. LD critically revised the manuscript. AC and LD approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Funding</title><p>AC is a postdoctoral fellow of the CONICET (Argentina). LD is a research member of the CONICET (Argentina).</p><sec><title>Conflict of interest statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors wish to thank Prof. Rolando Rivera-Pomar for his valuable suggestions during the conception of this work.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Basak</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhattacharyya</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pathak</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kundu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>The secreted peptidyl prolyl cis, trans-isomerase hp0175 of helicobacter pylori induces apoptosis of gastric epithelial cells in a tlr4-and apoptosis signal-regulating kinase 1-dependent manner</article-title>. <source>J. Immunol.</source>
<volume>174</volume>, <fpage>5672</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5680</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.174.9.5672</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15843568?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15843568</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carrea</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diambra</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Systems biology approach to model the life cycle of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e0146947</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0146947</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26752404?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26752404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collingridge</surname><given-names>P. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginger</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Moonlighting enzymes in parasitic protozoa</article-title>. <source>Parasitology</source>
<volume>137</volume>, <fpage>1467</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1475</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182010000259</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20233494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20233494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Spicer</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Puta protein, a membrane-associated flavin dehydrogenase, acts as a redox-dependent transcriptional regulator</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>4295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4298</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.9.4295</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8483946?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8483946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Spicer</surname><given-names>P. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maloy</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>Regulation of proline utilization in salmonella typhimurium: a membrane-associated dehydrogenase binds dna <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>173</volume>, <fpage>211</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>219</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.173.1.211-219.1991</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1987118?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1987118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>&#201;. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horjales</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfim-Melo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortez</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>C. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Groote</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Unique behavior of trypanosoma cruzi mevalonate kinase: a conserved glycosomal enzyme involved in host cell invasion and signaling</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>24610</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep24610</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27113535?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27113535</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakai</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Taxon-specific &#950;-crystallin in japanese tree frog (hyla japonica) lens</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>276</volume>, <fpage>28134</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28139</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M102880200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11371565?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371565</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginger</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Protein moonlighting in parasitic protists</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1734</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1739</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST20140215</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25399598?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunka</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Newman</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Commichau</surname><given-names>F. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herzberg</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewitt</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Functional dissection of a trigger enzyme: mutations of the bacillus subtilis glutamate dehydrogenase rocg that affect differentially its catalytic activity and regulatory properties</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>400</volume>, <fpage>815</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>827</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2010.05.055</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20630473?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20630473</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferragut</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amela</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Pons</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pi&#241;ol</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mozo-Villarias</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Multitaskprotdb: a database of multitasking proteins</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>D517</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>D520</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkt1153</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24253302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24253302</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huberts</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Klei</surname><given-names>I. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Moonlighting proteins: an intriguing mode of multitasking</article-title>. <source>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta</source>
<volume>1803</volume>, <fpage>520</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>525</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2010.01.022</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20144902?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20144902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Moonlighting proteins</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem. Sci.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>8</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>11</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0968-0004(98)01335-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15605385?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10087914</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Moonlighting proteins&#8211;an update</article-title>. <source>Mol. BioSyst.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>345</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>350</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b900658n</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19396370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19396370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>An introduction to protein moonlighting</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1679</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1683</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST20140226</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25399589?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399589</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeffery</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Why study moonlighting proteins?</article-title>
<source>Front. Genet.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>211</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fgene.2015.00211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26150826?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26150826</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Z.-G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lungu</surname><given-names>A. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berk</surname><given-names>B. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Cyclophilin a is a proinflammatory cytokine that activates endothelial cells</article-title>. <source>Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>1186</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.ATV.0000130664.51010.28</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15130913?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15130913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Genome-scale identification and characterization of moonlighting proteins</article-title>. <source>Biol. Dir.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13062-014-0030-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25497125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25497125</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>I. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kihara</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Computational characterization of moonlighting proteins</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1780</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1785</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST20140214</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25399606?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amblee</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathur</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwicke</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Moonprot: a database for proteins that are known to moonlight</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>D277</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>D282</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku954</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25324305?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25324305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantilla</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paes</surname><given-names>L. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pral</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martil</surname><given-names>D. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiemann</surname><given-names>O. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#225;ndez-Silva</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Role of &#948;1-pyrroline-5-carboxylate dehydrogenase supports mitochondrial metabolism and host-cell invasion of trypanosoma cruzi</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>290</volume>, <fpage>7767</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7790</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M114.574525</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25623067?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25623067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolland</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>W.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.-X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Role of the Arabidopsis glucose sensor hxk1 in nutrient, light, and hormonal signaling</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>300</volume>, <fpage>332</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>336</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1080585</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12690200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12690200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>The hexokinase 2-dependent glucose signal transduction pathway of saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>83</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2002.tb00600.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12007644?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12007644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piatigorsky</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Norman</surname><given-names>B. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalumuck</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wistow</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borras</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Gene sharing by delta-crystallin and argininosuccinate lyase</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>85</volume>, <fpage>3479</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3483</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.85.10.3479</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3368457?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3368457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krishna</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zigler</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Identification and characterization of the enzymatic activity of zeta-crystallin from guinea pig lens. a novel nadph: quinone oxidoreductase</article-title>. <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>267</volume>, <fpage>96</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>102</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1370456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1370456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasch</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#220;nal</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinert</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Peptidylprolyl cis&#8211;trans isomerases of legionella pneumophila: virulence, moonlighting and novel therapeutic targets</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Soc. Trans.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1728</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1733</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BST20140202</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25399597?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399597</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sukumaran</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>N. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tin</surname><given-names>C. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>V. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>A soluble form of the pilus protein fima targets the VDAC-hexokinase complex at mitochondria to suppress host cell apoptosis</article-title>. <source>Mol. Cell</source>
<volume>37</volume>, <fpage>768</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>783</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2010.02.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20347420?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20347420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tonelli</surname><given-names>R. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silber</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida-de Faria</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirata</surname><given-names>I. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Colli</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>M. J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>l-proline is essential for the intracellular differentiation of trypanosoma cruzi</article-title>. <source>Cell. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, <fpage>733</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>741</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2004.00397.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15236640?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15236640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1981</year>). <article-title>Genetics of l-proline utilization in escherichia coli</article-title>. <source>J. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>146</volume>, <fpage>895</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>901</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 7016835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7016835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>