
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5511225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">4824</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-04824-0</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Emergence of ON1 genotype of human respiratory syncytial virus subgroup A in China between 2011 and 2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Jinhua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Huiling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Liwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xiaojie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zifeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Wenda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Hong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Pengbo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Zhengde</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Aili</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Teresa I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Wenbo</given-names></name><address><email>wenbo_xu1@aliyun.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8803 2373</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.198530.6</institution-id><institution>WHO WPRO Regional Reference Measles/Rubella Laboratory and Key Laboratory of Medical Virology Ministry of Health, National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention, </institution><institution>China Center for Disease Control and Prevention, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Lu Juan Community Health Center of Daxing Region, Beijing, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Jilin Children’s Medical Center Children’s Hospital of Changchun, Changchun, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.470124.4</institution-id><institution>State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Disease, National Clinical Research Center for Respiratory Disease, </institution><institution>First Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Guangzhou Guangdong, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Hunan Provincial Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Changsha, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Shaanxi Provincial Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Xian, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0369 153X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.24696.3f</institution-id><institution>Beijing Children’s Hospital, </institution><institution>Capital Medical University, </institution></institution-wrap>Beijing, People’s Republic of China </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0572 4227</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.431072.3</institution-id><institution/><institution>AbbVie, Inc., </institution></institution-wrap>North Chicago, IL USA </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0477 188X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.440648.a</institution-id><institution>Medical College, </institution><institution>Anhui University of Science &amp; Technology, </institution></institution-wrap>Huainan, People’s Republic of China </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>5501</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article’s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>A molecular epidemiological study of human respiratory syncytial virus (HRSV) was conducted to examine the distribution of its subgroups and genotypes, as well as to identify its transmission pattern in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>A total of 705 samples collected from 9 provinces in China between January 2008 and February 2015 were identified as HRSV-positive and were subsequently sequenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Of these, 336 samples were HRSV subgroup A (HRSVA), 368 samples were HRSV subgroup B (HRSVB), and 1 sample contained both HRSVA and HRSVB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>These 705 HRSV sequences, together with 766 HRSV sequences downloaded from GenBank, were analyzed to understand the recent circulation patterns of HRSV in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>HRSVB predominated in the 2008/2009 and 2009/2010 seasons, whereas HRSVA predominated in the 2010/2011 and 2011/2012 seasons; HRSVA and HRSVB co-circulated during 2012/2013 and 2014/2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis showed most of the HRSVA sequences clustered into 2 genotypes, namely, NA1 and ON1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The ON1 genotype was first detected in China in 2011, and it quickly replaced the NA1 genotype to become the most prevalent HRSVA genotype circulating in China between 2013 and 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Continuous epidemiological surveillance and molecular characterization of HRSV should be conducted to monitor the evolution of HRSV in China. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par2"><text><SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Human respiratory syncytial virus (HRSV) is one of the leading causes of acute respiratory tract infection in young children ( ≤ 5 years old), the elderly or immunocompromised patients1–5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In 2005, about 33.8 million new episodes of HRSV-associated acute lower respiratory infection (ALRI) occurred worldwide in children younger than 5 years of age. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Among these patients, approximately 66,000–199,000 died from the infection, with 99% of these deaths occurring in developing countries6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>In China, a study of 28,369 patients with ALRI from 81 (out of 108) sentinel hospitals in 22 provinces showed that the most frequently detected virus was HRSV (9.9%), and HRSV was the most common etiology (17.0%) in children younger than 2 years of age7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>In New York City, HRSV infection was a major cause for hospitalization due to respiratory infection for patients with age &lt; 4 or ≥ 75 years old; these patients may need additional control measures to mitigate the risk of infection during HRSV seasons8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Annual infection rate of HRSV in the USA ranged from 2% to 10% in community-dwelling older adults, and 5% to 10% in older adults living in congregate settings9. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Therefore, HRSV-associated lower respiratory tract infection is a big concern for public health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par3"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>HRSV is a member of the Pneumovirinae subfamily in the Paramyxoviridae family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>It consists of a non-segmented, single-strand negative RNA genome packaged in a lipid envelope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The genome of HRSV is about 15.2 kb in length and encodes 10 genes and 11 proteins: NS1, NS2, N, P, M, SH, G, F, M2-1, M2-2, and L10. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>The F protein and G protein are the major surface glycoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Both of them can stimulate the production of neutralizing antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>The sequence of the F protein is highly conserved, while that of the G protein is hypervariable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Due to the genetic diversity in the G gene, sequence encoding the second hypervariable region in the C-terminal (HVR2) of the G protein has been used for genotyping of HRSV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>According to the genetic characteristic and reactivity with monoclonal antibodies, HRSV is classified into 2 subgroups, A (HRSVA) and B (HRSVB)11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>To date, there are 15 genotypes of HRSVA (GA1-GA7, SAA1, CB-A, NA1-4 and ON1-2)12–15, and 24 genotypes of HRSVB (GB1-GB4, SAB1-SAB4, URU1-2, BA1-12, GB5/CB1 and CBB)16–20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The HRSVA genotype ON1 was first detected with a 72-nucleotide duplication in the HVR2 region encoded by the G gene in Canada in 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a lineage of the ON1 genotype was identified as a new genotype (ON2) in Italy in 201521, 22. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par4"><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>In this study, we collected and sequenced HRSV-positive samples collected from 9 sentinel hospitals in 9 provinces in China between 2008 and 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>In addition, HRSV sequences from 5 additional Chinese provinces were downloaded from Genbank on February 2016 and analyzed together with the sequences we generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The molecular epidemiology of HRSVA in 14 provinces in China was analyzed and the characteristics of these HRSVA sequences were examined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>HRSV samples </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par5"><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>In this study, 705 out of 4246 (16.60%) samples collected between January 2008 and February 2015 from 9 hospitals located in Beijing, Hebei, Jilin, Shandong, Shaanxi, Gansu, Shanghai, Guangdong, and Hunan provinces in China were tested positive for HRSV using double-channel real-time reverse transcription-polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR)23. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Of these, 336 (47.66%) samples were identified as HRSVA, 368 (52.20%) samples were identified as HRSVB and 1 (0.14%) sample identified as both HRSVA and HRSVB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Genetic sequences of all of the HRSVA samples were generated and used for genotyping and sequence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Additionally, 766 Chinese HRSV sequences with available sample collection information were downloaded from GenBank and included in the sequence analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Distribution of HRSV samples collected in China from 2008 to 2015 by year and geographical region is shown in Table 1.Table 1Distribution of HRSV samples collected in China from 2008 to 2015 by year and geographical region.Numbers shown are the sum of sequences collected in this study and those downloaded from GenBank; sequences collected in this study are shown within parentheses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Clinical characteristic of patients with HRSVA infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par6"><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>This study focused mainly on the analysis of data from the HRSVA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Of the 337 HRSVA patients from whom samples were collected and sequenced in this study, clinical information were available for 242 (71.81%) of them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Most of the 242 samples (228; 94.21%) were collected from inpatients, and the rest (14; 5.8%) were from outpatients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>The age of the patients ranged from 1 day to 75 years old, with median age being 2.28 years old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Most of the patients were less than 4 years old (92.15%) and the majority of the patients (53.11%) were less than 1 year old. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>The male to female ratio was 2.13:1 (68.05% vs 31.95%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Of the 242 patients, 172 (71.07%) were diagnosed with lower-respiratory tract infection, including 45 (26.16%) with pneumonia, 13 (7.56%) with asthmatic bronchitis with pneumonia, 114 (66.28%) with other lower-respiratory tract infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Moreover, 7 (2.90%) patients were diagnosed with upper-respiratory tract infection, while 63 (26.03%) patients were diagnosed with other diseases (3 cases of enteritis, 2 cases of mycoplasma pneumonia, 2 cases of laryngitis, 1 case of aplastic anemia, 1 case of asthma and 54 cases with unknown diagnosis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>There was no significant difference (χ2 = 7.736, P = 0.117) between the males and the females in the number of each of the 3 major HRSVA genotypes (NA1, ON1 and NA3) detected, but there was statistically significant difference (χ2 = 9.334, p = 0.009) between the two age groups (≤ 2 vs. &gt; 2 years old) in the number of each of these 3 genotypes detected: NA1 (77 vs. 19), ON1 (57 vs. 35), and NA3 (36 vs. 9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Therefore, more NA1, ON1 and NA3 samples were identified in patients who were younger than 2 years of age. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of HRSVA sequences </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par7"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>The HVR2 sequence of the G gene from 840 Chinese HRSVA sequences (337 sequences obtained in this study and 503 sequences downloaded from GenBank) were examined by molecular phylogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All HRSVA sequences clustered into 6 genotypes in the analysis, NA1 (539, 64.17%), ON1 (216, 25.71%), NA3 (59, 7.02%), NA4 (17, 2.02%), GA2 (5, 0.60%) and GA5 (4, 0.48%) (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The NA1 genotype constituted the majority of the HRSVA sequences and most of the samples of this genotype were collected between 2008 and 2013, while the ON1 genotype was the next in abundance and most of the patient samples of this genotype were collected from 2013 to 2015 (Fig. 2a and b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>A number of Chinese ON1 genotypes with lineage-specific substitutions as described below emerged as a potential new lineage from the ON1 genotype with 55% bootstrap value, and we have designated it as lineage 1 (Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>The average nucleotide pairwise distance between the sequences from lineage 1 and the other sequences of the ON1 genotype was 0.029 ± 0.009 (mean ± standard deviation). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree of all Chinese HRSVA sequences is shown in Fig. 1a and that of representative Chinese HRSVA sequences is shown in Fig. 1b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Representative Chinese sequences were chosen from sequences with pairwise distances &gt; 0.025.Figure 1(a) Phylogenetic tree of HRSVA sequences from 14 provinces in China between January 2008 and February 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The branch of the ON1 genotype is colored in red, lineage 1 is colored in light fluorescence blue, the NA3 genotype is colored in green, the NA4 genotype is colored in purple, and the NA1 genotype is colored in navy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>(b) Phylogenetic tree of representative HRSVA sequences obtained from January 2008 to February 2015 in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Representative sequences were chosen from those with the pairwise distances &gt; 0.025. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Years of sample collection are indicated by the colors of the sequence names, and the locations of sample collection are indicated by the symbols according to the legend. Figure 2(a) Monthly distribution of HRSV subgroups and HRSVA genotypes between January 2008 and February 2015 in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>HRSVB subgroup and different genotypes of the HRSVA subgroup are colored according to the legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>(b) Yearly and geographic distribution of HRSVA genotypes from 2008 to 2015 in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Different HRSVA genotypes are colored according to the legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>(c) Geographic distribution of HRSVA genotypes between January 2008 and February 2015 in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The pie map of China was generated using MapInfo professional software (version 11.0, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pitneybowes.com/us/location-intelligence/geographic-information-systems/mapinfo-pro.html">http://www.pitneybowes.com/us/location-intelligence/geographic-information-systems/mapinfo-pro.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>The number of the different genotypes is colored according to the legend. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The 14 provinces where sequences were obtained are shaded in grey. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Distribution of HRSV subgroups and HRSVA genotypes in China </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par8"><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The HRSV seasons are winter and spring in China, from October of one year to May of the next year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>For the surveillance of HRSV infection between 2008 to 2015 in China, we found that HRSVA and HRSVB occasionally co-circulated in the same HRSV season, but more often, one predominant subgroup was observed in each season (Fig. 2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>HRSVB was the predominant subgroup in the 2008/2009 and 2009/2010 seasons, while HRSVA was prevalent in the 2010/2011 and 2011/2012 seasons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>However, both HRSVA and HRSVB co-circulated in China from September 2012 to March 2014, whereas HRSVA subsequently became the predominant subgroup during the 2014/2015 season. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Moreover, of all the sequences included in the analysis, 216 of them were ON1 genotype, which had a 72-nucleotide duplication in the sequence encoding the C-terminal of the G protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>The first ON1 genotype sample identified in this study was isolated in Shanghai province in February 2011. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Following that, a total of 12 (5.56%) ON1 genotype sequences were identified from 2011 to 2013, and a total of 203 sequences (93.98%) of the ON1 genotype were detected in 2013/2014 and 2014/2015 (Fig. 2a,b and c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par9"><text><SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For the yearly and geographic distribution of HRSVA genotypes in China from 2008 to 2015, the NA1 genotype was the predominant genotype found in Beijing, Gansu, Shanghai, Chongqing, and the Hong Kong special administrative region (SAR) between 2008 and 2012, and circulated in Jilin, Hebei, Shaanxi, Guangdong, Sichuan, Hunan, Zhejiang, and Tibet provinces between 2009 and 2013 (Fig. 2b and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>The ON1 genotype became more and more prevalent from November 2013 to February 2015 in many regions of China, including Jilin, Shaanxi, Beijing, Hunan, Hebei and Shandong provinces (Fig. 2b and c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Amino acid analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par10"><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>The predicted lengths of the G protein HVR2 regions of the HRSVA sequences analyzed in this study were 87 (genotypes NA1 and NA5), 88 (genotypes A2, GA2, GA5 and NA4) and 111 (genotype ON1) amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>For the 6 genotypes identified in this study, residues at amino acid positions 216–218, 221, 228–230, 240, 246, 248, 252, 259, 267–268, 276–278, 281 and 287–288 were highly conserved (Fig. 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>The substitutions of S268T and P289S were found in the GA2, ON1, and all NA genotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>When the Chinese ON1 sequences were compared with the sequence of the first ON1 genotype detected in Canada in 2010, (GenBank number: JN257693), 2 lineage-specific substitutions were identified in some of the Chinese ON1 genotypes: T249I and E262K; HRSVA with these substitutions clustered into a potential new lineage (lineage 1) within the ON1 genotype (Figs 1a and 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The E262K substitution occurred in the sequence duplication region in the HVR2 of ON1 (Fig. 3b).Figure 3(a) Amino acid substitutions at the HVR2 region of the G protein in representative HRSVA sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Different background colors are used to facilitate visualization of different genotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Identical residues and stop codons are indicated by dots and asterisks, respectively; the lengths of the HVR2 region are shown next to the end of the sequences, followed by the genotype names. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The regions shaded in grey represent the conserved regions among genotypes A2, GA2, GA5, NA1, NA3, NA4 and ON1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>The box depicts the amino acid sequences corresponding to the 72-nucleotide duplication in the C-terminal of the G protein of the ON1 genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>(b) Amino acid substitutions at the HVR2 region of the G protein in representative ON1 sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Some sequences clustered into lineage 1 due to the 2 substitutions of T249I and E262K, shaded in grey. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>The boxes depict the amino acid sequences corresponding to the 72-nucleotide duplication in the C-terminal of the G protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par11"><text><SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In this study, the HVR2 regions of the G protein of 1471 Chinese HRSV samples (839 HRSVA, 631 HRSVB and 1 HRSVA/B) collected from 14 provinces between January 2008 and February 2015 were analyzed to determine the epidemiology of HRSV in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>All of the HRSVA sequences (337 sequences obtained in this study and 503 sequences downloaded from GenBank) were studied further for the distribution and sequence analysis of HRSVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Hence, this study examined the molecular epidemiology and sequence characteristics of HRSVA circulating in China in recent years. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par12"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The monthly distribution of HRSV subgroups showed the alternating prevalence of HRSVA and HRSVB during the past 8 HRSV seasons in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>HRSVB was the predominant subgroup from 2008 to the spring of 2010, whereas HRSVA was the predominant subgroup in the following seasons from 2010 to 2012. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, HRSVB became more and more prevalent again starting at the end of 2012 until the spring of 2014 when both HRSVA and HRSVB co-circulated in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The tendency of the replacement of the predominant subgroup indicated that alternating prevalence between HRSVA and HRSVB occurred every one or two years in China, which was also reported in other countries, such as Belgium and Finland24, 25. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par13"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Previous study showed GA2 was the predominant genotype of HRSVA circulating in some provinces in China from 2003/2004 to 2007/20085, 26–28. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>However, the GA2 genotype was replaced by the NA1 genotype from 2008 to 2013 in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>The NA1 genotype was first reported in Beijing of China from 2007 to 201329 and circulated in Chongqing between 2009 and 201330. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>In this study, the NA1 genotype was also detected in Beijing and Chongqing, as well as in Gansu, Shanghai, Hong Kong SAR from 2008 to 2012 and expanded to circulate in other provinces, such as Jilin, Hebei, Shaanxi, Guangdong, Sichuan, Hunan, Zhejiang, and Tibet between 2009 and 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>These data indicated that the NA1 genotype had circulated throughout mainland China from 2008 to 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>The circulation of the NA1 genotype was also widely reported during the same HRSV seasons in Canada, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, and other countries14, 18, 19, 31, 32. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par14"><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the ON1 genotype was first detected in Canada in 2010, and its detection has been reported in the USA, Latvia, Germany, Cyprus, Kenya, China, Korea, Japan, Malaysia, Western India, Thailand and other countries since then21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>In our study, the ON1 genotype was first detected in Shanghai in February 2011, which was earlier than its detection in Beijing in 2012 as reported previously15, 29. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>After that, the ON1 genotype became more and more prevalent, and replaced the NA1 genotype to become the predominant genotype in China between 2013 and 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Globally, the ON1 genotype has been reported in 21 countries and was evolving and disseminating quickly throughout the world with different ON1 lineages21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Based on the high prevalence and quick evolution of the ON1 genotype, it is expected that new lineages would emerge from the this genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>In our study, we detected a potential new lineage (lineage 1) of the ON1 genotype in samples collected from 2014 to 2015 in China. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par15"><text><SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>The sequence duplication in the ON1 genotype occurs in the HVR2 region of the G protein, an important antigenic region containing multiple epitopes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The structural flexibility of this region allows HRSV to generate variants with changes in key epitopes to overcome the pressure of antibodies raised after a natural infection33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>In additional, the 24-amino acid duplication found in the ON1 genotype increases the length and/or change the structure of the G protein, which may contribute to the antigenicity of the G protein or evade host immunity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, a similar sequence insertion was discovered in the HRSVB subgroup years before the discovery of the ON1 genotype: genotype BA with a 20-amino acid insertion in the HVR2 region of the G protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>More importantly, the BA genotype has circulated all over the world and evolved into 12 subgenotypes since its emergence in 199916, 34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>The spread of the BA genotype globally during the past decade suggested that the sequence repeat may provide some advantage to the virus35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Recent report showed that the BA genotype with the sequence duplication had a fitness advantage compared to the virus without the sequence duplication in vitro: the 20-amino acid insertion augmented virus attachment and fitness36. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The ON1 genotype has circulated in many countries during the past 5 years since its emergence in 2010. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>Continuous molecular epidemiology surveillance needs to be conducted to determine if the sequence insertion also influences the transmissibility of the ON1 genotype and if the ON1 genotype circulates widely and for a long period of time like the BA genotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par16"><text><SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>When compared with the first identified ON1 genotype sequence (Canada strain, ON67–1210, GenBank number: JN257693), a number of Chinese ON1 sequences identified in this study had 2 amino acid substitutions in the G protein: T249I and E262K. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Sequences with these 2 substitutions clustered into a new lineage, named lineage 1 in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Both substitutions were detected in Beijing, Shandong and Jilin provinces in 2014 and 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>The lineage 1 sequences from Beijing were classified as a new branch named ON1/NB previously37. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The 3 provinces with lineage 1 sequences were located in northern and eastern China, where winter and spring last longer than most of the other parts of China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>Studies had shown that for both HRSV subgroups, the geographical and temporal factors may play a role in the their genetic evolution18, 38. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Although the impact of these 2 substitutions to the biologic function of the G protein was not clear to date, these 2 amino acids are located close to the antigenic sites21. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Due to these substituions, the property of the amino acids changed from hydrophilic to hydrophobic for residue 249, and from acidic to alkaline for residue 262. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Both changes might affect the antigenicity of the protein and/or viral attachment to the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Residue 249 is close to the antigenic site at amino acids 250–25839, and this site has been suggested to be under positive selective pressure40. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Residue 262 had also been suggested to undergo adaptive evolution41. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Interesting, while substitution from Glu to Lys at residue 262 (E262K) was detected in samples from lineage 1 in the ON1 genoype, the same amino acid (Lys) is found at the same residue (262) in sequences of the GA2 and NA4 genotypes (i.e. K262). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>As shown in this study, the GA2 and NA4 genotypes had not circulated in China in recent years, while the NA1 genotype was found circulating widely in China from 2008 to 2013. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>The residue 262 of the G protein of the NA1 genotype was Glu, which was different from Met found at the same residue in the reference strain (Long). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>The biological significance of the substitution at residue 262 from Glu (e.g. NA1 and ON1 except lineage 1) to Lys (e.g. GA2, NA4 and lineage 1) or from Met (e.g. Long) to Glu (e.g. NA1 and ON1 except lineage 1) remains to be determined. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par17"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The genotype-specific substitutions identified in the NA3 genotype included S283P, as well as N255D and S280H which have been reported previously42. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Substitution S283P was found in all of our NA3 sequences, whereas substitutions N255D and S280H occurred in most of the genotype NA3 sequences with the exception that 2 sequences had no substitutions at residue 255, but had S280Y instead of S280H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the genotype NA4-specific substitutions N237H, T239S, I244G, and L274Q were found in all of the NA4 sequences in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Substitution N242I was identified as a genotype NA4-specific substitution from samples collected in Beijing previously42, but a mixure of 2 different substittuions were identified at residue 242 in NA4 sequences analyzed in this study: N242I (in a total of 3 sequences from Beijing, Guangzhou and Chongqing) and N242T (in 2 sequences from Shanghai). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The significance of the genotype-specific substitutions requires further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Among the 337 HRSVA sequences generated in this study, 52 of them were from clinical isolates and the rest of them were from clinical samples that have not been passaged in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>We have compared these 52 sequences with the sequence of a reference strain (Long strain) and sequences from clinical samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>No specific amino acid changes were detected in sequences from clinical isolates; the substitutions detected in the sequences from these 52 clinical isolates were also found in sequences from clinical samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>There were some limitations of our study due to the difference of sample collection in each year or geographic location that may impact the estimation of the prevalence of HRSVA genotypes in China: fewer samples were collected in 2008–2009, the number of samples from each province was different, and samples were not collected from some provinces every year. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Also, samples were collected from 14 representative provinces instead of from all provinces in China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Due to the large amount of data generated from the analysis of Chinese HRSVA and HRSVB sequences in this project, results of the analysis for HRSVA and HRSVB sequences are described in separate reports. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, this is an extensive study to investigate the yearly and geographic distribution of HRSV in 14 provinces in China from 2008 to 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>After 5 years of consecutive circulation in mainland China from 2008 to 2012, the NA1 genotype appeared to have been replaced by the ON1 genotype in recent years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>The ON1 genotype, detected as early as in 2011 in Shanghai, has become the predominant HRSVA genotype circulating in China between 2013 and 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Due to the widespread transmission and rapid evolution of HRSV, continuous and long-term epidemiological surveillance and molecular characterization need to be conducted to provide the scientific basis for the prevention and treatment of HRSV infection in the future. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Ethics statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In this study, there was no human experimentation; only nasopharyngeal aspirates or nasopharyngeal precipitates were collected from patients who were identified as potentially infected with HRSV infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Written informed consent for the use of clinical specimens was obtained from each patient involved in this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the second session of the Ethics Review Committee of the National Institute for Viral Disease Control and Prevention in the Chinese Center for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and the methods were conducted according to the guidelines. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Sample collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>4246 nasopharyngeal aspirates or nasopharyngeal precipitates were collected from patients who were hospitalized with acute respiratory illness or outpatients who had the symptoms of acute respiratory infections, such as fever, cough, dyspnea and other symptoms from 9 sentinel hospitals in 9 provinces in China, including Jilin, Beijing, Hebei, Gansu, Shaanxi, Shanghai, Hunan, Guangdong and Shandong provinces, respectively, from 2008 to 2015. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Some clinical samples were inoculated into Hep-2 cells for virus isolation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>The culture supernatants and the clinical samples were frozen and stored at −80 0C for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and subgroup screening </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Total RNA from clinical isolates or clinical samples were extracted using the QIAamp DNA/RNA mini kit (QIAGEN, Valencia, CA, USA, CAT: 52906 or 74106) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Double channel real-time RT-PCR was used for HRSV detection, as well as HRSVA and HRSVB subgroup identification23. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide amplification and sequence determination for HRSVA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The partial sequence of the G gene of HRSVA samples (634–897 nt) were amplified by RT-PCR using the One Step RT-PCR kit (TaKaRa Biotechnology Dalian, China, cat: DRR057A) with the primer pairs described previously26, 43. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Primer sets GPA-F1 were used to amplify and sequence the nucleotides encoding the HVR2 region located at the C-terminal region of the G protein of HRSVA samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The HRSVA PCR products were purified and sequenced using an ABI Prism 3710xl DNA Analyzer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>The sequences of HRSVA were edited and aligned using Sequencher software verion 5.0 (Gene Codes, Ann Arbor, MI, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>The sequences generated in this study were submitted to GenBank with the accession numbers from KX533544 to KX533879. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Other HRSV sequences used in this study </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>All (766) Chinese HRSV sequences from samples collected from 2008 to 2015 that were available from GenBank on February 2016, as well as the reference sequences of different HRSVA genotypes were downloaded from GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>The HVR2 regions of HRSVA G protein sequences were aligned using the software MEGA software (version 5.0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Information of the sequences downloaded from GenBank was showed in the Supplementary Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis and pairwise distance calculation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Alignment and phylogenetic analysis of the sequences were conducted using the software MEGA 5.044. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree was generated using the neighbor-joining method and the Kimura 2-parameter method was chosen for substitution model with pairwise deletion treatment for the missing and gaps data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of the reliability of phylogenetic inference was estimated using the bootstrap method with 1000 replicates with a cut-off of usually ≥ 75% in MEGA 5.0 program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Pairwise distance between different strains was also calculated by MEGA 5.0 as previously described45–47. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>Differences in clinical characteristic of HRSV infection between males and females, as well as between 2 different age groups were calculated using the SPSS17.0 software with Pearson Chi-Square test, and P-value &lt; 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec17"><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>supplementary Table 1 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Yan Zhang and Jinhua Song contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-04824-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Publisher's note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>We thank all the staffs of the 9 sentinel hospitals in Beijing, Shandong, Shanghai, Jilin, Guangdong, Shaanxi, Gansu, Hebei and Hunan provinces for providing the specimens, isolates and epidemiology information. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Key Technologies R&amp;D Program of National Ministry of Science (2013ZX10004-202, 2012ZX10004201-003) and non-clinical laboratory service agreement with AbbVie Pharmaceutical Trading (Shanghai) Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Ltd. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>W.B.X. and Y.Z. conceived and designed the study. Y.Z., J.H.S. performed sequences and data analysis. J.H.S., H.L.W., J.S., L.W.S., X.J.Z., Z.F.Y., G.W.D., H.Z., P.B.Y., Z.D.X and A.L.C. performed the experiments. Y.Z., J.H.S., T.I.N., W.B.X. wrote the main manuscript. Y.Z. and J.H.S. prepared Table 1 and Figs 1–3. All authors reviewed the manuscript.</p></notes></SecTag><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par29">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>1.WuAIncidence and Risk Factors for Respiratory Syncytial Virus and Human Metapneumovirus Infections among Children in the Remote Highlands of PeruPLoS One201510e013023310.1371/journal.pone.0130233<?supplied-pmid 26107630?>26107630 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>2.PretoriusMAThe role of influenza, RSV and other common respiratory viruses in severe acute respiratory infections and influenza-like illness in a population with a high HIV sero-prevalence, South Africa 2012–2015J Clin Virol20167521610.1016/j.jcv.2015.12.004<?supplied-pmid 26741826?>26741826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>3.TurnerTLRespiratory syncytial virus: current and emerging treatment optionsClinicoecon Outcomes Res201462172510.2147/CEOR.S60710<?supplied-pmid 24812523?>24812523 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>4.LiuTViral Etiology of acute respiratory tract infections in hospitalized children and adults in Shandong Province, ChinaVirol J20151216810.1186/s12985-015-0388-z<?supplied-pmid 26467854?>26467854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>5.ZhangRFHuman respiratory syncytial virus in children with acute respiratory tract infections in ChinaJ Clin Microbiol2010484193910.1128/JCM.00179-10<?supplied-pmid 20810776?>20810776 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>6.ReschBBurden of respiratory syncytial virus infection in young childrenWorld J Clin Pediatr2012181210.5409/wjcp.v1.i3.8<?supplied-pmid 25254161?>25254161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>7.FengLViral etiologies of hospitalized acute lower respiratory infection patients in China, 2009–2013PLoS One20149e9941910.1371/journal.pone.0099419<?supplied-pmid 24945280?>24945280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>8.GoldsteinEGreeneSKOlsonDRHanageWPLipsitchMEstimating the hospitalization burden associated with influenza and respiratory syncytial virus in New York City, 2003-2011Influenza Other Respir Viruses201592253310.1111/irv.12325<?supplied-pmid 25980600?>25980600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>9.BrancheARFalseyARRespiratory syncytial virus infection in older adults: an under-recognized problemDrugs Aging201532261910.1007/s40266-015-0258-9<?supplied-pmid 25851217?>25851217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>10.CanePAMolecular epidemiology of respiratory syncytial virusRev Med Virol2001111031610.1002/rmv.305<?supplied-pmid 11262529?>11262529 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>11.MufsonMAOrvellCRafnarBNorrbyETwo distinct subtypes of human respiratory syncytial virusJ Gen Virol198566Pt 1021112410.1099/0022-1317-66-10-2111<?supplied-pmid 2413163?>2413163 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>12.AvadhanulaVInfection with novel respiratory syncytial virus genotype Ontario (ON1) in adult hematopoietic cell transplant recipients, Texas, 2011-2013J Infect Dis2015211582910.1093/infdis/jiu473<?supplied-pmid 25156562?>25156562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>13.MartinelliMPhylogeny and population dynamics of respiratory syncytial virus (Rsv) A and BVirus Res201418929330210.1016/j.virusres.2014.06.006<?supplied-pmid 24954788?>24954788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>14.TsukagoshiHGenetic analysis of attachment glycoprotein (G) gene in new genotype ON1 of human respiratory syncytial virus detected in JapanMicrobiol Immunol2013576559<?supplied-pmid 23750702?>23750702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>15.LiuJGenetic variation of human respiratory syncytial virus among children with fever and respiratory symptoms in Shanghai, China, from 2009 to 2012Infect Genet Evol201427131610.1016/j.meegid.2014.07.011<?supplied-pmid 25046173?>25046173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>16.RenLXiaoQZhouLXiaQLiuEMolecular characterization of human respiratory syncytial virus subtype B: a novel genotype of subtype B circulating in ChinaJ Med Virol2015871910.1002/jmv.23960<?supplied-pmid 24910250?>24910250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>17.DapatICNew genotypes within respiratory syncytial virus group B genotype BA in Niigata, JapanJ Clin Microbiol2010483423710.1128/JCM.00646-10<?supplied-pmid 20610675?>20610675 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>18.EshaghiAGenetic variability of human respiratory syncytial virus A strains circulating in Ontario: a novel genotype with a 72 nucleotide G gene duplicationPLoS One20127e3280710.1371/journal.pone.0032807<?supplied-pmid 22470426?>22470426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>19.BaekYHPrevalence and genetic characterization of respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) in hospitalized children in KoreaArch Virol201215710395010.1007/s00705-012-1267-1<?supplied-pmid 22402914?>22402914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>20.BlancADelfraroAFrabasileSArbizaJGenotypes of respiratory syncytial virus group B identified in UruguayArch Virol2005150603910.1007/s00705-004-0412-x<?supplied-pmid 15480858?>15480858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>21.DuvvuriVRGenetic diversity and evolutionary insights of respiratory syncytial virus A ON1 genotype: global and local transmission dynamicsSci Rep201551426810.1038/srep14268<?supplied-pmid 26420660?>26420660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>22.HiranoEMolecular evolution of human respiratory syncytial virus attachment glycoprotein (G) gene of new genotype ON1 and ancestor NA1Infect Genet Evol2014281839110.1016/j.meegid.2014.09.030<?supplied-pmid 25283803?>25283803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>23.van EldenLJApplicability of a real-time quantitative PCR assay for diagnosis of respiratory syncytial virus infection in immunocompromised adultsJ Clin Microbiol20034143788110.1128/JCM.41.9.4378-4381.2003<?supplied-pmid 12958272?>12958272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>24.ZlatevaKTVijgenLDekeersmaekerNNaranjoCVan RanstMSubgroup prevalence and genotype circulation patterns of human respiratory syncytial virus in Belgium during ten successive epidemic seasonsJ Clin Microbiol20074530223010.1128/JCM.00339-07<?supplied-pmid 17609323?>17609323 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>25.WarisMPattern of respiratory syncytial virus epidemics in Finland: two-year cycles with alternating prevalence of groups A and BJ Infect Dis1991163464910.1093/infdis/163.3.464<?supplied-pmid 1995719?>1995719 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>26.ZhangYGenetic variability of group A and B human respiratory syncytial viruses isolated from 3 provinces in ChinaArch Virol200715214253410.1007/s00705-007-0984-3<?supplied-pmid 17510775?>17510775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>27.Mao, H., Lu,Y. &amp; Yan, J. Genetic Characteristics of the G Gene of RSV in Zhejiang Province. Virol Sin21, 111–115 (2006). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>28.Zhang, Y. et al. Study on Genetic Diversity of the G Protein of Subgroups A and B Human Respiratory Syncytial Viruses Isolated in Beijing, China. Chin J Virol21, 332–342 (2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>29.CuiGEmerging human respiratory syncytial virus genotype ON1 found in infants with pneumonia in Beijing, ChinaEmerg Microbes Infect20132e2210.1038/emi.2013.19<?supplied-pmid 26038462?>26038462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>30.RenLThe genetic variability of glycoproteins among respiratory syncytial virus subtype A in China between 2009 and 2013Infect Genet Evol2014273394710.1016/j.meegid.2014.07.030<?supplied-pmid 25109878?>25109878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>31.EtemadiMRSekawiZOthmanNLyeMSMoghaddamFYCirculation of human respiratory syncytial virus strains among hospitalized children with acute lower respiratory infection in malaysiaEvol Bioinform Online201391516110.4137/EBO.S10999<?supplied-pmid 23641140?>23641140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>32.KhorCSSamICHooiPSChanYFDisplacement of predominant respiratory syncytial virus genotypes in Malaysia between 1989 and 2011Infect Genet Evol2013143576010.1016/j.meegid.2012.12.017<?supplied-pmid 23305888?>23305888 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>33.MeleroJAGarcia-BarrenoBMartinezIPringleCRCanePAAntigenic structure, evolution and immunobiology of human respiratory syncytial virus attachment (G) proteinJ Gen Virol199778Pt 102411810.1099/0022-1317-78-10-2411<?supplied-pmid 9349459?>9349459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>34.TrentoAMajor changes in the G protein of human respiratory syncytial virus isolates introduced by a duplication of 60 nucleotidesJ Gen Virol20038431152010.1099/vir.0.19357-0<?supplied-pmid 14573817?>14573817 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>35.McLellanJSRayWCPeeplesMEStructure and function of respiratory syncytial virus surface glycoproteinsCurr Top Microbiol Immunol201337283104<?supplied-pmid 24362685?>24362685 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>36.HotardALLaikhterEBrooksKHartertTVMooreMLFunctional Analysis of the 60-Nucleotide Duplication in the Respiratory Syncytial Virus Buenos Aires Strain Attachment GlycoproteinJ Virol20158982586610.1128/JVI.01045-15<?supplied-pmid 26018171?>26018171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>37.Cui, G. et al. Rapid replacement of prevailing genotype of human respiratory syncytial virus by genotype ON1 in Beijing, 2012–2014. Infect Genet Evol33, 163–8 (2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>38.KuroiwaYA phylogenetic study of human respiratory syncytial viruses group A and B strains isolated in two cities in Japan from 1980–2002J Med Virol200576241710.1002/jmv.20348<?supplied-pmid 15834873?>15834873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>39.CanePAAnalysis of linear epitopes recognised by the primary human antibody response to a variable region of the attachment (G) protein of respiratory syncytial virusJ Med Virol19975129730410.1002/(SICI)1096-9071(199704)51:4&lt;297::AID-JMV7&gt;3.0.CO;2-0<?supplied-pmid 9093944?>9093944 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>40.BotossoVFPositive selection results in frequent reversible amino acid replacements in the G protein gene of human respiratory syncytial virusPLoS Pathog20095e100025410.1371/journal.ppat.1000254<?supplied-pmid 19119418?>19119418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>41.ZlatevaKTLemeyPVandammeAMVan RanstMMolecular Evolution and Circulation Patterns of Human Respiratory Syncytial Virus Subgroup A: Positively Selected Sites in the Attachment G GlycoproteinJournal of Virology2004784675468310.1128/JVI.78.9.4675-4683.2004<?supplied-pmid 15078950?>15078950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>42.CuiGGenetic variation in attachment glycoprotein genes of human respiratory syncytial virus subgroups a and B in children in recent five consecutive yearsPLoS One20138e7502010.1371/journal.pone.0075020<?supplied-pmid 24069376?>24069376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>43.PeretTCHallCBSchnabelKCGolubJAAndersonLJCirculation patterns of genetically distinct group A and B strains of human respiratory syncytial virus in a communityJ Gen Virol199879Pt 92221910.1099/0022-1317-79-9-2221<?supplied-pmid 9747732?>9747732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>44.TamuraKMEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methodsMol Biol Evol2011282731910.1093/molbev/msr121<?supplied-pmid 21546353?>21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>45.SaitouNNeiMThe neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic treesMol Biol Evol1987440625<?supplied-pmid 3447015?>3447015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>46.ZharkikhALiWHEstimation of confidence in phylogeny: the complete-and-partial bootstrap techniqueMol Phylogenet Evol19954446310.1006/mpev.1995.1005<?supplied-pmid 7620635?>7620635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>47.KimuraMA simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequencesJ Mol Evol1980161112010.1007/BF01731581<?supplied-pmid 7463489?>7463489 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
