<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5794978</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">20517</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-20517-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Molecular identification, transcript expression, and functional deorphanization of the adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide receptor in the disease vector, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wahedi</surname><given-names>Azizia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Paluzzi</surname><given-names>Jean-Paul</given-names></name><address><email>paluzzi@yorku.ca</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9430</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.21100.32</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology, </institution><institution>York University, </institution></institution-wrap>Toronto, M3J 1P3 Ontario Canada </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>2146</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2018</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">The recently discovered adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide (ACP) is an insect neuropeptide structurally intermediate between corazonin (CRZ) and adipokinetic (AKH) hormones, which all demonstrate homology to the vertebrate gonadotropin-releasing hormone (GnRH). To date, the function of the ACP signaling system remains unclear. In the present study, we molecularly identified the complete open reading frame encoding the <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> ACP receptor (ACPR), which spans nine exons and undergoes alternative splicing giving rise to three transcript variants. Only a single variant, <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I, yielding a deduced 577 residue protein, contains all seven transmembrane domains characteristic of rhodopsin-like G protein-coupled receptors. Functional deorphanization of <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I using a heterologous cell culture-based system revealed highly-selective and dose-dependent receptor activation by <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP (EC<sub>50</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;10.25&#8201;nM). Analysis of the <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I and <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP transcript levels in all post-embryonic developmental stages using quantitative RT-PCR identified enrichment of both transcripts after adult eclosion. Tissue-specific expression profiling in adult mosquitoes reveals expression of the <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I receptor transcript in the central nervous system, including significant enrichment within the abdominal ganglia. Further, the <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP transcript is prominently detected within the brain and thoracic ganglia. Collectively, these results indicate a neuromodulator or neurotransmitter role for ACP and suggest this neuropeptide may function in regulation of post-ecdysis activities.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; The Author(s) 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Neuropeptides are structurally and functionally the most diverse class of signaling molecules that function in intercellular communication in multicellular organisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. In insects, neuropeptides play a fundamental role in the regulation of various physiological processes including development, reproduction, osmoregulation, as well as behavior and feeding<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. One of the first neuropeptides to be isolated and purified from insects was the adipokinetic hormone (AKH), which is produced by neurosecretory cells of the corpora cardiaca (CC), and is one of the most extensively studied family of neuropeptides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Insect AKH neuropeptides have been functionally well characterized to stimulate the release of energy-rich compounds including diacylglycerols, trehalose, and in some cases proline, into the haemolymph to fuel the activity of the insect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. In addition to these catabolic actions, AKH peptides have been shown to stimulate heart beat and inhibit the synthesis of haemolymph and tissue proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. The AKH receptors (AKHR), first isolated from <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> and <italic>Bombyx mori</italic>, are G-protein coupled receptors (GPCR)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Both AKH and AKHR demonstrate homology with the vertebrate gonadotropin releasing hormone (GnRH) and its receptor (GnRHR), respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Another insect neuropeptide family that is structurally similar to the vertebrate GnRH signaling system are the corazonin peptides. Corazonin (CRZ) is an insect undeca-neuropeptide first discovered in the cockroach, <italic>Periplaneta americana</italic>, due to its significant cardioexcitatory activity on the isolated cockroach heart<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. A similar cardioexcitatory role has been established in other insects, including the kissing bug, <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>; however, this cardiostimulatory function is not universal since corazonin lacks cardiomyotropic activity in adult stage <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> mosquitoes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. Despite the CRZ sequence remaining largely conserved across insect species (primarily pQTFQYSRGWTNamide), to date no universal function has been described for this neuropeptide<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Nonetheless, multiple physiological roles have been described for CRZ, including the induction of melanization in swarming populations of <italic>Locusta migratoria</italic> and <italic>Schistocerca gregaria</italic>, initiation of ecdysis in <italic>Manduca sexta</italic>, the reduction in silk spinning rates in <italic>B. mori</italic>, and in social insects, CRZ has been proposed as a central regulator of behaviour and caste identity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Over the last decade, a third signaling system evolutionarily- and structurally-related to the AKHRs and CRZRs and their neuropeptides was identified and named adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide (ACP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. ACP and its receptor (ACPR), like AKH/AKHR and CRZ/CRZR, also demonstrate homology to the vertebrate GnRH/GnRHR system. Upon analysis of this structural intermediate it became evident that ACP and its receptor ACPR were in fact already described in a number of insects, however, were at the time characterized as AKHs and AKHRs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. Unlike AKH, but similar to CRZ, the ACP amino acid sequence beginning from the N-terminus (pQVTFSRDW) demonstrates conservation across most arthropods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Characterization of the ACP signaling system in <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic>, and <italic>A. gambiae</italic> revealed that the AKH, CRZ, and ACP receptors were only activated by their corresponding ligand, and thus are suggested to be independent signaling systems<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. However, <italic>in vitro</italic> studies characterizing <italic>B. mori</italic> AKHR and ACPR have shown that high concentrations of ACP can activate the AKH receptor, and vice versa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. In both <italic>R. prolixus</italic> and <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, it was also shown that CRZ cannot activate either ACPR or AKHR and furthermore, neither AKH nor ACP can activate CRZR, which indicates that the AKH/AKHR and ACP/ACPR signaling systems are more closely related to one another<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. To date, no functions have been assigned to the ACP signaling system, but expression profiles of ACP and ACPR in <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, and <italic>T. castaneum</italic>, show that both peptide and receptor are primarily expressed in the&#160;nervous system and, to a lesser extent, in the reproductive tissue of <italic>R. prolixus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Furthermore, ACP transcript was detected in the head and thorax of adult <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> with a similar transcript distribution observed in 4<sup>th</sup> instar larvae, pupae, and adult <italic>A. gambiae</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Developmental expression profiles have revealed high expression of both ACP and its receptor before and after hatching of eggs in <italic>T. castaneum</italic> and after ecdysis in <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, and thus a role in early larval development and post-ecdysis, respectively, has been proposed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Additionally, assays testing the potential for cardio-excitatory or lipid mobilization roles of ACP in <italic>R. prolixus</italic> yielded negative results, which indicates that ACP, AKH, and CRZ are indeed independent signaling systems with distinct functions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Further investigations are clearly necessary in order to assign a physiological role for the ACP/ACPR neuropeptide system in insects.</p><p id="Par5"><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> mosquitoes are principal vectors for a variety of pathogens including dengue fever, yellow fever, chikungunya, and Zika viruses, all of which have a significant impact on human morbidity and mortality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. A thorough understanding of mosquito biology is required to devise novel methods to reduce and prevent mosquito-borne diseases. In an attempt to advance our understanding of the ACP signaling system in <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, we have identified and functionally deorphanized the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR (<italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR). Furthermore, to begin identification of prospective target tissues and physiological roles, we have determined the post-embryonic developmental expression profile and the spatial expression pattern in the adult mosquito of the transcripts encoding the ACP precursor peptide as well as a functional ACP receptor in <italic>A. aegypti</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Animals</title><p id="Par6"><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> (Liverpool strain) eggs were hatched in plastic containers half-filled with deionized water at an initial density of approximately 100 larvae/litre of water. Larvae were fed a 2% brewers yeast, 2% liver powder solution daily, and adults were provided with a 10% sucrose solution through a microcentrifuge tube fitted with a cotton ball wick allowing feeding <italic>ad libitum</italic>. Larvae and pupae were maintained in an incubator at 26&#8201;&#176;C on a 12:12&#8201;hour light: dark cycle. Colony upkeep involved adult females being fed sheep&#8217;s blood in Alsever&#8217;s solution weekly (Cedarlane Laboratories Ltd., Burlington, ON) using an artificial feeding system described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. All experiments on adults were performed on either one or four-day old male and female mosquitoes that were sucrose-fed only and had been isolated during the pupal stage and transferred <italic>en masse</italic> into small glass microchambers.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Isolation and cloning of cDNA encoding A. aegypti ACPR</title><p id="Par7">Gene specific forward and reverse primers were designed using Primer 3 in Geneious Software (Biomatters Ltd, Auckland, New Zealand) based on a predicted incomplete <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR sequence (XM_001653870) described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> to amplify a 975&#8201;bp partial fragment using Q5 High Fidelity DNA Polymerase (New England Biolabs, Whitby, On) and whole adult female <italic>A. aegypti</italic> cDNA as template. The PCR product was purified, A-tailed, cloned into pGEM-T vector (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and nucleotide sequence was confirmed by Sanger sequencing (Center for Applied Genomics, Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON). After successful validation of the cloned partial sequence, primers were designed (as mentioned above) to perform 5&#8242; and 3&#8242; rapid amplification of cDNA ends (RACE)-PCR utilizing the Clontech SMARTer 5&#8242;/3&#8242; RACE Kit (Takara BIO USA Inc, CA, USA). To facilitate cloning of amplicons, the linker sequence GATTACGCCAAGCTT, which overlaps with the pRACE vector provided in the kit, was added to the 5&#8242; ends of the gene specific primers (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). First-strand cDNA synthesis was prepared using 1&#956;g total RNA from adult female head using the 3&#8242; CDS primer (provided in the kit) and a gene-specific reverse primer to generate template cDNA for 3&#8242; and 5&#8242; RACE, respectively. Initial attempts at 5&#8242;RACE using the 5&#8242;CDS primer (provided in the RACE kit) for first-strand cDNA synthesis and subsequent PCR with the SeqAmp DNA Polymerase (Takara BIO USA Inc, CA, USA) was not successful for this target. Thus, the protocol was modified to generate first-strand cDNA using a gene-specific reverse primer (<italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-R1, Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) and subsequent nested RACE-PCR reactions utilized Q5 High Fidelity DNA Polymerase <italic>in lieu</italic> of SeqAmp DNA Polymerase. Nested PCR reactions utilized gene specific forward (3&#8242; RACE) and reverse (5&#8242; RACE) primers and a universal primer mix (UPM) to amplify the complete cDNA encoding <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR. Optimal PCR cycling parameters for subsequent amplification of ACPR were determined empirically. Specifically, for 3&#8242; RACE this included an initial denaturation at 94&#8201;&#176;C for 1&#8201;min, followed by 40 cycles of 30&#8201;s at 94&#8201;&#176;C, 30&#8201;s at 68&#8201;&#176;C, and 3&#8201;min at 72&#8201;&#176;C to amplify PCR products using SeqAmp DNA Polymerase. For 5&#8242; RACE, the Q5 High Fidelity DNA Polymerase was utilized with the following cycling parameters, 30&#8201;s at 98&#8201;&#176;C, followed by 30 cycles of 5&#8201;s at 98&#8201;&#176;C, 15&#8201;s at 65&#8211;68&#8201;&#176;C, 1&#8201;min 10&#8201;s at 72&#8201;&#176;C, with a final extension step of 2&#8201;min at 72&#8201;&#176;C. Following two rounds of PCR using nested gene-specific primers, amplicons were gel extracted and cloned into the linearized pRACE vector and miniprep samples were then sent for sequencing. Finally, primers were designed at the 5&#8242; and 3&#8242; ends of the complete cDNA sequence (including UTRs) and at the start and stop codons of the sequence (region including only the open reading frame, excluding UTRs), and were used for subsequent PCR amplification of the receptor with Q5 High Fidelity DNA polymerase to confirm base pair accuracy.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Primer information for oligonucleotides used for initial amplification of partial cDNA, 5&#8242; and 3&#8242; RACE and RT-qPCR analysis to determine temporal and spatial transcript expression.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Primers based on partial ACPR mRNA sequence (Accession number: XM_001653870.2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>) identified through homology based <italic>in silico</italic> analysis of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Primers based on ACP mRNA sequence (Accession number: FM391984.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Gene Structure and Phylogenetic Analyses</title><p id="Par8">Mapping of exon-intron boundaries of <italic>A. aegypti ACPR</italic> gene was determined using the cloned complete cDNA sequence as a query against the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome scaffolds database available locally on a lab computer running Geneious Pro Bioinformatics Software (Biomatters Ltd, Auckland, New Zealand). Positions of introns and exons were further confirmed using the BDGP splice site prediction server using the standardized data set of <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> genes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Membrane topology of ACPR-I, II, and III were predicted using the Constrained Consensus TOPology prediction server (CCTOP)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. The deduced <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I, II and III protein sequences were aligned to the human gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptor 1 along with ACP, AKH, and CRZR receptors from other species (see Table&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>) using ClustalW in MEGA 6.06<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Relationships between the various receptor sequences were determined through neighbour-joining<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> and maximum-likelihood phylogenetic analysis methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. Bootstrap values are based on 1000 replicates.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Preparation of mammalian expression constructs</title><p id="Par9">Amplicons encoding just the open reading frame (start ATG to stop codon) were used as template for re-amplification using a modified forward primer possessing the consensus Kozak translation initiation sequence<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> at the 5&#8242; end of the start codon. The resulting product was cloned into pGEM-T Easy vector and then subcloned into the mammalian expression vector, pcDNA 3.1<sup>+</sup> (Life Technologies, Burlington, ON). Construct directionality was confirmed by Sanger sequencing and plasmid DNA was purified from overnight bacterial cultures using a PureLink MidiPrep Kit (Invitrogen, Burlington, ON) and subsequently used for transfection of mammalian cells for the receptor functional assay. Analysis of multiple independent sequences obtained from RACE-PCR revealed a number of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) that localized to various sites along the full cDNA sequence. Upon further analysis, it was determined that only a single SNP at nucleotide position 1924 within the open reading frame resulted in an amino acid change. To determine whether this difference in the resulting residue, in comparison to the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome database, confers any difference to the functional activity of the receptor, site directed mutagenesis was performed. Specifically, 5&#8242; phosphorylated primers were designed (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) with the forward primer possessing an adenine (position 1924) consistent with the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome sequence whereas our consensus sequence contained a thymine in this nucleotide position. Using these modified primers, asymmetric PCR was performed using a pGEM-T Easy plasmid construct as template to replace the Ile<sub>472</sub> in the cloned receptor with an Asn<sub>472</sub> matching the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome. Mutation of the coding sequence was verified by sequencing and sub-cloned into the mammalian expression plasmid, pcDNA3.1<sup>+</sup> (as described above).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cell culture, transfections, and bioluminescence assay</title><p id="Par10">Functional activation of <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I was assayed using a previously established cell culture system involving a recombinant Chinese hamster ovary (CHO)-K1 cell line stably expressing aequorin<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Cells were maintained in Dulbecco&#8217;s modified eagles medium: nutrient F12 (DMEM:F12; 1:1) media containing&#160;200ug/mL geneticin, 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS; Wisent, St. Bruno, QC) and grown&#160;to approximately 90% confluency, and were transiently transfected with pcDNA3.1<sup>+</sup> expression vector possessing <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I using Lipofectamine LTX and Plus Reagent transfection system (Invitrogen, Burlington, ON) following a 3:1:1 transfection reagent (&#956;L): Plus reagent (&#956;L): plasmid DNA (&#956;g) ratio. At 48&#8201;hours post-transfection, cells were detached from the culture flasks using Dulbecco&#8217;s phosphate buffered saline (DPBS;&#160;Wisent Corporation, St. Bruno, QC) containing 5&#8201;mM EDTA and resuspended in BSA medium (DMEM-F12 media containing 0.1% bovine serum albumin, 1X antimycotic-antibiotic) to a concentration of 10<sup>6</sup>&#8211;10<sup>7</sup> cells/mL. Coelenterazine h (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) was added to the cells to a final concentration of 5&#8201;&#956;M, and incubated for 3&#8201;hours in the dark at room temperature on a stirrer set at 200&#8201;rpm. The cell suspension was then diluted 10-fold and incubated at room temperature for an additional hour. Serial dilutions of peptide ligands (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were prepared in BSA medium (10<sup>&#8722;5</sup> to 10<sup>&#8722;12</sup>&#8201;M), and loaded in quadruplicates into 96-well luminescence plates (Greiner Bio-One, Germany). All peptides were commercially synthesized (Genscript, Piscataway, NJ) at a purity &gt;90% and were prepared in dimethyl sulfoxide at a stock concentration of 1&#8201;mM. Cells were loaded into each well with an automatic injector unit and luminescence was measured for 20&#8201;seconds using a Synergy 2 Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (BioTek, Winooski, VT, USA). BSA medium alone was utilized as a negative control and 5&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>&#8201;M ATP was used as a positive control, which acts on endogenously expressed purinoceptors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. EC<sub>50</sub> values were calculated in GraphPad Prism 7.02 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, USA) from dose-dependent curves from four independent transfections.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Tissue dissections, RNA extraction, and cDNA synthesis</title><p id="Par11">Lightly CO<sub>2</sub>-immobilized four-day old adult male (n&#8201;=&#8201;30) and female (n&#8201;=&#8201;20) <italic>A. aegypti</italic> were submerged in&#160;DPBS, and the following body segments and/or tissues were dissected and isolated: head, midgut, Malpighian tubules, hindgut, ovaries, testes, accessory reproductive tissues, and carcass (remaining fat body, musculature, and cuticle). Tissues were lysed in RNA lysis buffer containing 1% 2-mercaptoethanol. Whole adult RNA was obtained from submerging several males and females in RNA lysis buffer containing 1% 2-mercaptoethanol and using a sterile plastic pestle to disrupt the tissue. To measure the developmental expression profile for <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR, first to fourth instar larvae, pupae, as well as one- and four-day old adult mosquitoes were collected and submerged in RNA lysis buffer and flash frozen in liquid nitrogen. Total RNA was isolated from whole animal and individual adult tissues samples mentioned above using the PureLink<sup>TM</sup> RNA mini kit following manufacturer protocol with an on-column DNase treatment to remove genomic DNA (Invitrogen, Burlington, ON). Purified total RNA samples were quantified with a Take3 micro-volume plate and measured on a Synergy Multi-Mode Microplate Reader (BioTek, Winooski, VT, USA). To assess <italic>ACP</italic> and <italic>ACPR</italic> transcript levels, cDNA was synthesized from 20&#8201;ng total RNA using the iScript&#8482; Reverse Transcription Supermix for RT-qPCR (Bio-Rad, Mississauga, ON) following manufacturers protocol, including a ten-fold dilution of cDNA following synthesis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Quantitative PCR</title><p id="Par12">ACP and ACPR transcript abundance was quantified on a StepOnePlus&#8482; Real Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems, Carlsband, CA) using PowerUP&#8482; SYBR&#174; Green Master Mix (Applied Biosystems, Carlsband, CA). Cycling conditions were as follows: 1) UDG activation 50&#8201;&#176;C for 2&#8201;min, 2) 95&#8201;&#176;C for 2&#8201;min, and 3) 40 cycles of (i) 95&#8201;&#176;C for 15&#8201;seconds and (ii) 60&#8201;&#176;C for 1&#8201;minute. Gene-specific primers designed over different exons were used to amplify <italic>ACPR</italic>, with the forward primer designed over exon 5 (nucleotides 1458&#8211;1476) to ensure specificity for ACPR-I, and the reverse primer over exon 6 (nucleotides 1585&#8211;1603). Gene specific primers amplifying <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP were designed over multiple exons (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; forward: nucleotides 89&#8211;112, reverse: nucleotides 403&#8211;421) based on a previously published mRNA sequence (Genbank Accession Number: FN391984)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Relative expression levels were determined using the &#916;&#916;C<sub>T</sub> method and were normalized to the geometric mean of <italic>rp49</italic>, <italic>rpL8</italic>, and <italic>rps18</italic> reference genes, which were previously characterized and determined as optimal endogenous controls<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. The <italic>AedaeACPR</italic> spatial expression profile was determined using 7&#8211;9 biological replicates, all of which included three technical replicates per reaction and a no-template negative control. The <italic>AedaeACPR</italic> developmental expression is an average of 3&#8211;5 biological replicates that each included duplicate technical replicates for each target gene and a no-template negative control. The <italic>AedaeACP</italic> spatial expression profile consisted of 3&#8211;4 biological replicates and the developmental expression is an average of 3&#8211;5 biological replicates. Specificity of primers for target mRNA were assessed by conducting no reverse-transcriptase controls, analysis of dissociation curves, and Sanger sequencing of amplicons. Data were analyzed using a one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&#8217;s multiple comparisons test where p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 was considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Data availability</title><p id="Par13">The datasets generated and analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Results and Discussion</title><p id="Par14">We have identified the complete cDNA sequence encoding the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide (ACP) receptor (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Following initial cloning and sequence analysis, three transcript variants were identified, <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I, ACPR-II, and ACPR-III (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I is 2596&#8201;bp (GenBank Accession number: MF461644), which includes a 1734&#8201;bp open reading frame (ORF) encoding a 577 residue receptor (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). The cloned 5&#8242; untranslated region (UTR) is 509&#8201;bp in length and the 3&#8242;UTR is 346&#8201;bp and contains a predicted polyadenylation sequence (nucleotide position 2547&#8211;2552). <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPRs II and III are transcript variants of 2442&#8201;bp (GenBank: MF461645) and 2240&#8201;bp (GenBank: MF461646) in length, which yield deduced proteins comprised of 328 and 243 amino acids, respectively. Only <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I has the seven expected hydrophobic transmembrane (TM) domains characteristic of GPCRs, whereas <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-II has only five TM domains and <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-III has only three TM domains (see Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Similarly, previous studies in <italic>R. prolixus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and <italic>A. gambiae</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> revealed multiple receptor variants, whereas only a single variant was identified in <italic>T. castaneum</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Specifically, in <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, three ACPR variants have been identified, two of which contain the typical seven TM domains (<italic>Rhopr</italic>ACPR-B and <italic>Rhopr</italic>ACPR-C), and one which contains five TM domains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Additionally, two ACPR isoforms have been identified in <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, <italic>Anoga</italic>ACPR-A and <italic>Anoga</italic>ACPR-B, both of which result in receptors possessing seven TM domains<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide receptor variant I (ACPR-I) cDNA, amino acid sequence, and predicted gene structure. (<bold>a</bold>) Lower case letters denote cDNA, and uppercase letters represent amino acid residues with positions denoted by the numbers on the right of the sequences with bolded numbers indicating amino acid positions. Exon-exon boundaries within the cDNA are denoted by inverted red arrowheads. Underlined nucleotides indicate single nucleotide polymorphisms that differed from the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome. A putative polyadenylation signal is underlined in red in the 3&#8242;UTR. The predicted hydrophobic alpha-helices that form the transmembrane domains are outlined by black rectangular boxes. (<bold>b</bold>) The splicing pattern of the <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR gene based on BLAST analyses of cloned cDNA and splice site prediction analysis. Alternative splicing gives rise to three receptor mRNA variants where <italic>ACPR-I</italic> possesses all exons, <italic>ACPR-II</italic> lacks exon 5, and <italic>ACPR-III</italic> lacks both exons 4 and 5. Boxes representing exons are drawn to scale whereas intervening introns are not drawn to scale.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1051"/></fig></p><p id="Par15">The gene structure was modeled by comparing the cloned cDNA sequence to the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome database using Geneious Bioinformatics software (Biomatters Ltd., Auckland, New Zealand). Analysis of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR-I receptor shows that it maps over nine exons that are 810&#8201;bp, 191&#8201;bp, 228&#8201;bp, 202&#8201;bp, 154&#8201;bp, 197&#8201;bp, 177&#8201;bp, 83&#8201;bp, and 549&#8201;bp long, respectively. Alternative splicing of the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR gene results in the absence of either exon 5 only or absence of both exons 4 and 5, which yields <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-II and <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-III, respectively, both resulting in-frame translation shifts and premature stop codons, and consequently, truncated ORFs (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>).</p><p id="Par16">Alignment of <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR-I, with selected receptors from <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, <italic>T. castaneum</italic>, <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, and <italic>B. mori</italic>, reveals conservation of the ACP receptor across insect species (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Specifically, <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I shares 59.4% sequence identity with the <italic>A. gambiae</italic> ACP receptor, 42.4% identity with the <italic>R. prolixus</italic> ACPR-C, 41.5% identity with the <italic>T. castaneum</italic> ACPR and 33.8% identity with the <italic>B. mori</italic> ACP receptor. Overall, there is a high degree of conservation over the seven predicted TM domains, particularly over TM regions one, two, three, five and seven. Strong sequence identity is also observed in the first and second intracellular loops, as well as the first extracellular loop. All of the receptor sequences, except for <italic>Bommo</italic>ACPR, which harbors an Asp in place of Asn, possess the conserved NPXXY motif in the seventh TM domain characteristic of rhodopsin-like (family A) GPCRs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Another conserved motif found in rhodopsin-like GPCRs is the E/DRY motif adjacent to the second intracellular loop<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The Arg of the E/DRY motif and a negatively charged residue on TMVI of the GPCR undergo ionic interactions, known as the ionic lock, which stabilizes the inactive state of the receptor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. In particular, the ACP receptors possess a DRF motif in the silkworm <italic>B. mori</italic>, and DRC motifs are found in the mosquitoes <italic>A. gambiae</italic> and <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, in place of the characteristic DRY motif found in hemipteran <italic>R. prolixus</italic> and coleopteran <italic>T. castaneum</italic>, which have more conserved features of rhodopsin-like GPCRs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Sequence alignment of select insect adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide receptors (ACPR). Aligned amino acid sequences of ACPRs from <italic>A. aegypti</italic> (Variant I, GenBank: MF461644) <italic>R. prolixus</italic> (GenBank: AKO62858), <italic>B. mori</italic> (GenBank: NP_001127726), <italic>T. castaneum</italic> (GenBank: ABX52400), and <italic>A. gambiae</italic> (GenBank: ABX52399). Residues outlined in red indicate predicted transmembrane domains based on the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACPR sequence. Highlighting of residues indicates % identity with black denoting 100% sequence identity, dark grey denotes 80&#8211;100% identity, and light grey represents amino acid positions with 60&#8211;80% sequence identity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1178"/></fig></p><p id="Par17">Phylogenetic analysis using the neighbor-joining and maximum-likelihood methods (not shown) yielded trees with highly similar and well supported topologies (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). All the ACP receptors analyzed are positioned within a single clade that is a&#160;sister group to the clade comprised of the AKH receptors. Together, the AKH and ACP receptor clades form a monophyletic group which is a sister group to the clade comprised of CRZ receptors. The <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I identified herein clusters closely with the other insect ACPRs that have previously been identified and functionally characterized confirming that the receptor isolated in this study is an ortholog of other insect ACP receptors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Predicted ACPRs from other mosquito species including, <italic>Anopheles darlingi</italic>, <italic>Culex pipiens</italic>, and the Asian tiger mosquito <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> also cluster closely to the <italic>A. gambiae</italic> and <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACP receptors.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Phylogenetic relationship of adipokinetic hormone receptors (AKHR, <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e1224"/>), corazonin receptors (CRZR, <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Figb_HTML.gif" id="d29e1227"/>) and adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide receptors (ACPR, <inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Figc_HTML.gif" id="d29e1230"/>) from insects. Tree was constructed using the neighbour-joining analysis (with 1000 bootstrap replicates). Branch lengths indicate the number of amino acid substitutions per site and numbers adjacent to nodes denotes the percentage support for the clustering of the related sequences in that particular clade. Receptor protein sequences are labelled by species name and identified with their GenBank accession number. The <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I receptor cloned in this study is denoted in red text. The human gonadotropin releasing hormone receptor isoform 1 (GenBank: NP_000397) was included in the analysis and designated as the outgroup.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1236"/></fig></p><p id="Par18">A heterologous receptor functional assay involving CHO-K1 cells was used to validate the cloned receptor as a bona fide ACP receptor. Indeed, the <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I was dose-dependently activated by <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP (EC<sub>50</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.025&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;8</sup>&#8201;M) (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>), confirming the proposed identity of the receptor based on phylogenetic analysis. Kinetic analysis of receptor activation demonstrated maximal luminescence response was evident over the first five seconds following application of the ACP peptide, indicative of an immediate and transient elevation of intracellular calcium levels elicited through activation of the ACP receptor (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4b</xref>). Our results also confirm the specificity of the ACP receptor for the ACP peptide alone (see Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>), since no detectable luminescence indicative of receptor activation was observed in response to the closely related peptides, <italic>Aedae</italic>AKH and <italic>Aedae</italic>CRZ, or other tested peptides, specifically <italic>Aedae</italic>CAPA-1 and pyrokinin-1 (<italic>Aedae</italic>PK1), which share no structural similarity to <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP. Our findings in this study are consistent with past reports, since similar binding specificity of ACP receptors has been observed previously in <italic>T. castaneum</italic>, <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, and <italic>R. prolixus</italic> with EC<sub>50</sub> values reported in the low nanomolar range<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Additionally, previous research in the aforementioned insects have also observed that the AKH receptors are not activated by ACP or corazonin peptides, and similarly, the corazonin receptors are not activated by ACP or AKH peptides<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Thus, consistent with these previous observations, we determined that although these neuropeptide systems are structurally and evolutionarily related, they are indeed independent of one another and do not exhibit any cross talk in <italic>A. aegpyti</italic>. Notably, however, previous studies in <italic>B. mori</italic> have revealed that high concentrations of <italic>Bommo-</italic>ACP (previously referred to as AKH3) resulted in the activation of <italic>Bommo-</italic>AKHR whereas sensitivity to its natural AKH ligand was approximately 100-fold higher<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Similarly, high doses of the AKH peptides in <italic>B. mori</italic>, <italic>Bommo</italic>-AKH1 and <italic>Bommo</italic>-AKH2, were also found to activate putative <italic>B. mori</italic> ACPRs (A28 and A29), albeit at significantly higher concentrations than ACP<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Functional heterologous receptor assay of CHO-K1 aequorin cells transiently expressing the <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I. (<bold>a</bold>) Dose dependent effect on the bioluminescence response (mean 0&#8211;15&#8201;s) after the addition of between 10<sup>&#8722;12</sup>&#8211;10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>&#8201;M doses of <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACP, AKH and CRZ peptides. Luminescence is normalized to the BSA control and plotted relative to the maximal response (10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>&#8201;M). The EC<sub>50</sub> for <italic>Aedae</italic>ACP is 1.025&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;8</sup>&#8201;M. No receptor activation was detected when challenged with <italic>Aedae</italic>AKH and <italic>Aedae</italic>CRZ or <italic>Aedae</italic>CAPA1 and <italic>Aedae</italic>PK1 (not shown). (<bold>b</bold>) Kinetics of the bioluminescence response measured between 0&#8211;5&#8201;s, 6&#8211;10&#8201;s, and 11&#8211;20&#8201;s time intervals, following the addition of 1&#8201;&#215;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;6</sup>&#8201;M of the above peptides normalized to vehicle control (BSA media). Luminescence is normalized to the BSA control and plotted relative to the maximal response (10<sup>&#8722;5</sup>&#8201;M). Data represent the mean &#177; standard error (n&#8201;=&#8201;4).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1401"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Structure of peptides tested in the heterologous receptor functional assay and summary of activity in eliciting a luminescent response.</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>EC<sub>50</sub> values are the averages of multiple independent biological replicates involving CHOK1-aeq cells transiently expressing <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I.</p><p><sup>b</sup>No activity (NA) detected when tested with peptide titres up to a maximum of 10&#8201;&#181;M.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p id="Par19">In comparison to the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome, a number of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) were observed across the entire cDNA sequence. Of those occurring within the open reading frame, only one SNP (nucleotide 1924, found within the seventh exon, which corresponds to the C-terminus of the receptor) results in a different amino acid at residue Ile<sub>472</sub>, compared to the Asn<sub>472</sub> predicted by the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> genome. Modification of the isoleucine residue (Ile<sub>472</sub>) obtained in our cDNA to the genome consistent asparagine residue (Asn<sub>472</sub>) resulted in no change to receptor activation by its endogenous ACP ligand, as determined by equal luminescent response by both the cloned <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I and the mutated <italic>Aedae</italic>ACPR-I-N472I (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). No luminescence signals were obtained in response to any of the tested peptides in untransfected cells, or cells transfected with empty pcDNA 3.1<sup>+</sup> vector (data not shown).</p><p id="Par20">Next, utilizing RT-qPCR, we investigated the molecular expression of the ACP signaling system during development and in individual tissues of adult <italic>A. aegypti</italic>. Although we identified three transcript variants, only the <italic>ACPR-I</italic> transcript yields a complete receptor protein which we functionally deorphanized, and so expression profiles were determined only for this transcript variant (see methods). Developmental expression profiling revealed enrichment of both <italic>ACPR-I</italic> (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>) and <italic>ACP</italic> (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>) transcripts following the transition from pupal to adult stages. In particular, one-day and four-day old male <italic>A. aegypti</italic> had the highest levels of <italic>ACP</italic> and <italic>ACPR-I</italic> transcript abundance. Similar findings for the ACP receptor were observed in <italic>R. prolixus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>; however, in contrast, <italic>ACPR</italic> transcript levels in <italic>T. castaenum</italic> were highest in late embryonic and early larval stages and decreased thereafter as the beetle progressed in development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. In <italic>A. aegypti</italic>, the observed enrichment of the <italic>ACP</italic> and <italic>ACPR-I</italic> transcripts could be indicative of a post-eclosion function for the ACP system.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Transcript expression pattern of <italic>ACPR-I</italic> and <italic>ACP</italic> during post-embryonic development and in specific tissues of four-day old adult <italic>A. aegypti</italic>. Temporal expression of <italic>ACPR-I</italic> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic>ACP</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) transcript is analyzed across developmental stages of the mosquito with expression shown relative to transcript levels in pupa. Spatial expression is analyzed in various tissues from four-day old adult males, <italic>ACPR-I</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) and <italic>ACP</italic> (<bold>d</bold>), and females, <italic>ACPR-I</italic> (<bold>e</bold>) and <italic>ACP</italic> (<bold>f</bold>) with transcript abundance shown relative to levels in whole body adult mosquitoes. Abbreviations: thoracic ganglia (TG), abdominal ganglia (AG), midgut (MG), Malpighian tubules (MT), hindgut (HG), ovaries (OVA), testes (TE), accessory reproductive tissue (ART). Data represent mean&#8201;&#177;&#8201;standard error, *denotes significance (p&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) as determined by a one-way ANOVA, Dunnett&#8217;s multiple comparisons test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1665"/></fig></p><p id="Par21">Spatial transcript expression profiles of <italic>A. aegypti ACPR</italic> aimed to reveal potential functional roles for ACP and its receptor by determining prospective target tissues. The ACP receptor (<italic>ACPR-I</italic>) was found to be significantly enriched in the abdominal ganglia of both male (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>) and female (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>) <italic>A. aegypti</italic> when compared relative to expression in the whole adult (males, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.0025 and for females, p&#8201;=&#8201;0.0016). <italic>ACPR-I</italic> transcript was also observed in the carcass, accessory reproductive tissue, testes, head and thoracic ganglia of adult male mosquitoes, although not significantly enriched as was found in the abdominal ganglia (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). Similarly, <italic>ACPR-I</italic> transcript was also found in the head, thoracic ganglia, hindgut, and accessory reproductive tissues of adult female <italic>A. aegypti</italic> (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>). Enrichment of the ACP receptor transcript in the nervous system is not surprising, since expression of the transcripts encoding the ACP receptor and peptide have been described in the nervous system of other insects. Specifically, in fifth instar and adult <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, ACPR transcript was found to be enriched in the central nervous system and the corpus cardiacum /corpora allata (CC/CA) complex<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. <italic>ACPR</italic> expression in <italic>T. castaneum</italic> was revealed to be greatest in the brain in comparison to the torso (i.e. body minus the head)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. <italic>AedaeACP</italic> transcript was detected in the central nervous system, where it was enriched in the brain and thoracic ganglia of male (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>) and significantly enriched in the head (p&#8201;=&#8201;0.0127) and thoracic ganglia (p&#8201;=&#8201;0.004) of female mosquitoes (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5f</xref>). Consistent with our quantified ACP tissue-specific expression profile, ACP transcripts in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. gambiae</italic> were detected solely in head and thorax body segments of adult mosquitoes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par22">Expression of <italic>A. aegypti ACPR-I</italic> within the central nervous system suggests that ACP may be functioning as a neuromodulator and/or a neurotransmitter. This possibility is supported by the extensive varicose immunoreactive staining of ACP in the central nervous system of <italic>T. castaneum</italic> first instar larvae, where a neurosecretory role was suggested<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Specifically, immunoreactivity (IR) was observed in three to four neurons in the brain, the central brain neuropil with projections from the brain descending into the suboesophageal ganglion (SOG), thoracic ganglia, and abdominal ganglia, with no projections observed exiting the nervous system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Immunocytochemistry using an antiserum against <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> AKH, which recognizes both AKH and ACP in <italic>A. gambiae</italic> and <italic>A. aegypti</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, revealed immunoreactivity throughout the mosquito nervous system. In both <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, AKH-like immunoreactivity was observed in two pairs of lateral neurosecretory cells in the brain, but was explained by the authors of this study to represent ACP-producing neurons, since AKH synthesis and storage is restricted to the corpus cardiacum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Within the fused thoracic ganglia of adult <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. gambiae</italic>, AKH-like immunoreactivity was observed within at least one to a few cells within the ventral region of the pro- and mesothoracic ganglia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. Thoracic extracts were negative for ACP-like activity in <italic>A. gambiae</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, however, expression of the AKH transcript in adult male <italic>A. aegypti</italic> is absent in the head and thorax region<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>; thus, it is unclear if the cells detected previously within the thoracic ganglia are ACP- or AKH-producing neurons in mosquitoes although our data indicate that the <italic>A. aegypti</italic> ACP transcript is prominently expressed in both the brain and thoracic regions of the nervous system. In <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, ACP-like immunoreactivity is observed in two bilaterally paired cell bodies at the anterior portion of the protocerebrum near the optic lobes, and one bilateral pair of cell bodies medially positioned in the protocerebrum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Considering the extensive immunohistochemical distribution of ACP throughout the nervous system of insects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, the prominent expression of <italic>ACP</italic> transcript in the brain and thoracic ganglia along with the significant enrichment of <italic>ACPR-I</italic> within the abdominal ganglia of adult <italic>A. aegypti</italic> strongly supports that ACP may be functioning centrally within the nervous system. In <italic>L. migratoria</italic> ACP was identified in the storage lobe of the CC, in contrast to the glandular lobe where AKH is found, suggesting synthesis of this neuropeptide within neurosecretory cells of the brain<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Furthermore, it was previously suggested that given <italic>ACPR</italic> was found in the CC/CA complex in <italic>R. prolixus</italic>, ACP may be involved in the regulation of other hormones in a manner similar to its distant vertebrate homolog, GnRH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par23">We also determined <italic>A. aegypti ACPR-I</italic> expression is not restricted to nervous tissue since transcript expression was detected in other tissues/organs including the female hindgut (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>) and male carcass (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). ACPR expression in the hindgut, the primary site of reabsorption of ions and metabolites<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, was unexpected since neither AKH nor CRZ have been found to regulate hydromineral balance. Thus, this possible function for ACP on the hindgut will require further investigation. Detection of the ACPR transcript in the carcass, which includes the body wall musculature and fat body, suggests that ACP and AKH may share a lipid mobilizing function. However, this possibility is unlikely since ACP was shown to have no influence on lipid or carbohydrate metabolism in female <italic>A. gambiae</italic> nor did it influence energy stores in male insects of <italic>L. migratoria</italic> or <italic>P. americana</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Interestingly, contrary to our predictions, both spatial and temporal expression profiles reveal greater expression of <italic>ACP</italic> and <italic>ACPR</italic> in adult males compared to females, which is consistent with an earlier microarray analysis in <italic>A. gambiae</italic> that determined higher ACP expression in adult males, compared to adult female and last instar larvae<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. There is no clear explanation for such a sex-specific difference in <italic>AC</italic><italic>P</italic> and <italic>ACPR</italic> transcript expression, however similar to our findings, male <italic>D. melanogaster</italic> express greater levels of the AKH receptor than their female counterparts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. <italic>ACPR-I</italic> transcript expression was also observed in the accessory reproductive tissues of both male and female <italic>A. aegypti</italic>. Expression of ACPR in reproductive tissue has also been observed in <italic>R. prolixus</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Perhaps, in addition to structural homology between ACPR and GnRHR, there is a yet undiscovered functional conservation between these two signaling systems. Furthermore, in <italic>Gryllus bimaculatus</italic>, pharmacologically elevating AKH titre through injections resulted in a significantly lower egg production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. In <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>, knockdown of the AKH-GnRH peptide and GnRH receptor resulted in reduced progeny in early worms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. Also, in <italic>Glossina morsitans</italic>, knockdown of the AKHR transcript resulted in higher levels of whole body lipids and, in pregnant flies, the inability to utilize lipid reserves resulted in delayed larval development and thus reproductive disruption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Whether these effects on reproduction in these organisms are a direct result of signalling involving the AKH or GnRH receptor or AKH peptide remains unclear. Additionally, analysis of seminal fluid protein content of <italic>A. albopictus</italic> revealed the AKH peptide as one of the proteins transferred from males to female mosquitoes during mating<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Recently, CRZR transcript expression in <italic>R. prolixus</italic> was also observed in male and female reproductive tissues, which suggests some potentially overlapping reproductive target tissues in insects<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par24">Currently, no definitive function for ACP has been determined and functional studies in other insects have revealed that ACP does not influence energy mobilization and so does not duplicate the actions of AKH<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. Additionally, ACP failed to increase heart-beat frequency, suggesting that the physiological actions of ACP does not mirror the most established function of CRZ<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. Further studies are necessary to unravel the function of the ACP system, which could include methods aimed at knockdown of the ACP peptide or receptor.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec12"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2018_20517_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-018-20517-8.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Research conducted in this study was supported through new-investigator institutional start-up funds, an NSERC Discovery Grant and Petro Canada Young Innovator Award to J.P.P.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: A.W. and J.P.P. Performed the experiments and analyzed data: A.W. and J.P.P. Wrote the paper: A.W. and J.P.P.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par25">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klavdieva</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The history of neuropeptides I</article-title><source>Front Endocrinol</source><year>1995</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>293</fpage><lpage>321</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>N&#228;ssel</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neuropeptides in the insect brain: a review</article-title><source>Cell Tissue Res</source><year>1993</year><volume>273</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00304608</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8364953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8364953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diederen</surname><given-names>JHB</given-names></name><name><surname>Oudejans</surname><given-names>RCHM</given-names></name><name><surname>Harthoorn</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Horst</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell biology of the adipokinetic hormone-producing neurosecretory cells in the locust corpus cardiacum</article-title><source>Microsc Res Tech</source><year>2002</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>227</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jemt.10026</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11810724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11810724</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#228;de</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hormonal regulation of energy metabolism in insects as a driving force for performance</article-title><source>Integr Comp Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icb/icp019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21665828?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21665828</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#228;de</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Marco</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure, function and mode of action of select arthropod neuropeptides</article-title><source>Stud Nat Prod Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1572-5995(06)80026-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Staubli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular identification of the insect adipokinetic hormone receptors</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>3446</fpage><lpage>3451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.052556499</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11904407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11904407</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of G protein-coupled receptors for <italic>Drosophila</italic> PRXamide peptides, CCAP, corazonin, and AKH supports a theory of ligand-receptor coevolution</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>11423</fpage><lpage>11428</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.162276199</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12177421?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12177421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#248;ndergaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimmelikhuijzen</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular cloning, genomic organization and developmental regulation of a novel receptor from <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic> structurally related to gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptors for vertebrates</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>1998</year><volume>249</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>828</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.1998.9230</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9731220?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9731220</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veenstra</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and structure of corazonin, a cardioactive peptide from the American cockroach</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1989</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(89)80727-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2753132?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2753132</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Veenstra</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The distribution and physiological effects of three evolutionarily and sequence-related neuropeptides in <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic>: Adipokinetic hormone, corazonin and adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide</article-title><source>Gen Comp Endocrinol</source><year>2014</year><volume>203</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ygcen.2014.07.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25016049?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25016049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillyer</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Est&#233;vez-Lao</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Funkhouser</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aluoch</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> corazonin: Gene structure, expression and effect on mosquito heart physiology</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2583.2012.01140.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22404523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22404523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Predel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Neupert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheibner</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nachman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corazonin in insects</article-title><source>Peptides</source><year>2007</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2006.10.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17140699?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17140699</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tawfik</surname><given-names>aI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of the gregarization-associated dark-pigmentotropin in locusts through an albino mutant</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1999</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>7083</fpage><lpage>7087</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.96.12.7083</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10359842?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10359842</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Corazonin receptor signaling in ecdysis initiation</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2004</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>6704</fpage><lpage>6709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0305291101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15096620?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15096620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Roller</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Corazonin reduces the spinning rate in the silkworm, <italic>Bombyx mori</italic></article-title><source>J Insect Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-1910(02)00094-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12770065?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12770065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gospocic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The neuropeptide corazonin controls social behavior and caste identity in ants</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2017</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>748</fpage><lpage>759.e12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2017.07.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28802044?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28802044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Discovery of a novel insect neuropeptide signaling system closely related to the insect adipokinetic hormone and corazonin hormonal systems</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>10736</fpage><lpage>10747</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.045369</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20068045?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20068045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siegert</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Locust corpora cardiaca contain an inactive adipokinetic hormone</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1999</year><volume>447</volume><fpage>237</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(99)00299-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10214953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10214953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belmont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cazzamali</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Grimmelikhuijzen</surname><given-names>CJP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of four evolutionarily related G protein-coupled receptors from the malaria mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2006</year><volume>344</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>165</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.03.117</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16616003?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16616003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Merzendorfer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#228;de</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adipokinetic hormone system in Culicinae (Diptera: Culicidae): Molecular identification and characterization of two adipokinetic hormone (AKH) precursors from <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Culex pipiens</italic> and two putative AKH receptor variants from <italic>A. aegypti</italic></article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2009.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19748585?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19748585</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adipokinetic hormones in the African malaria mosquito, <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>: Identification and expression of genes for two peptides and a putative receptor</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>466</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2006.03.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16731343?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16731343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and functional characterization of two orphan G-protein-coupled receptors for adipokinetic hormones from silkworm <italic>Bombyx mori</italic></article-title><source>J Biol Chem.</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>42390</fpage><lpage>42402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.275602</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22009754?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22009754</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular and functional characterization of adipokinetic hormone receptor and its peptide ligands in <italic>Bombyx mori</italic></article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2009</year><volume>583</volume><fpage>1463</fpage><lpage>1468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2009.03.060</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19345219?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19345219</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li, B. <italic>et al</italic>. Genomics, transcriptomics, and peptidomics of neuropeptides and protein hormones in the red flour beetle <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic>. <italic>Genome Res</italic> 113&#8211;122 (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zandawala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haddad</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamoudi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of the adipokinetic hormone/corazonin-related peptide signaling system in <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic></article-title><source>FEBS J</source><year>2015</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>3603</fpage><lpage>3617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/febs.13366</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26138617?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26138617</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bar&#243;n</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ursic-Bedoya</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowenberger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ocampo</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential gene expression from midguts of refractory and susceptible lines of the mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, infected with Dengue-2 virus</article-title><source>J Insect Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>41</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1673/031.010.4101</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20572793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20572793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rocco</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Paluzzi</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunohistochemical mapping and transcript expression of the GPA2/GPB5 receptor in tissues of the adult mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title><source>Cell Tissue Res</source><year>2017</year><volume>369</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00441-017-2610-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Eeckman</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulp</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haussler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Improved splice site detection in Genie</article-title><source>J Comput Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.1997.4.311</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9278062?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9278062</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CCTOP: a Consensus Constrained TOPology prediction web server</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>W408</fpage><lpage>W412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkv451</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25943549?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25943549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stecher</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MEGA6: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis version 6.0</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2013</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2725</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/mst197</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24132122?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24132122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neighbor-joining method: a new method for reconstructing phylogenetic trees</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1987</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>406</fpage><lpage>425</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3447015?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3447015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The rapid generation of mutation data matrices from protein sequences</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>1992</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>275</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/8.3.275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Point mutations close to the AUG initiator codon affect the efficiency of translation of rat preproinsulin <italic>in vivo</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1984</year><volume>308</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/308241a0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6700727?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6700727</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kozak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Point mutations define a sequence flanking the AUG initiator codon that modulates translation by eukaryotic ribosomes</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1986</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(86)90762-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3943125?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3943125</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paluzzi</surname><given-names>J-PV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigation of the potential involvement of eicosanoid metabolites in anti-diuretic hormone signaling in <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic></article-title><source>Peptides</source><year>2012</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.peptides.2011.10.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22079222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22079222</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iredale</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increases in intracellular calcium via activation of an endogenous P2-purinoceptor in cultured CHO-K1 cells</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1993</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>1305</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1476-5381.1993.tb13960.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8306069?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8306069</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Michel</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chessell</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hibell</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphrey</surname><given-names>PPA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of an endogenous P2X7 (P2Z) receptor in CHO-K1 cells</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>1998</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>1194</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjp.0702205</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9863647?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9863647</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paluzzi</surname><given-names>J-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanderveken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#8217;Donnell</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The heterodimeric glycoprotein hormone, GPA2/GPB5, regulates ion transport across the hindgut of the adult mosquito, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0086386</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenbaum</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>SGF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobilka</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The structure and function of G-protein-coupled receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2014</year><volume>459</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>363</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mirzadegan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Benk&#246;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Filipek</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Palczewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequence analyses of G-protein-coupled receptors: similarities to rhodopsin</article-title><source>Biochemistry</source><year>2003</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>2759</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi027224+</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12627940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12627940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Audet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restructuring G-protein- coupled receptor activation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23021212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23021212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palczewski</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>G protein-coupled receptor rhodopsin</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>2006</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.75.103004.142743</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16756510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16756510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zandawala</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamoudi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adipokinetic hormone signalling system in the Chagas disease vector, <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic></article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>264</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imb.12157</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25545120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25545120</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamoudi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of the corazonin receptor and possible physiological roles of the corazonin-signaling pathway in <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic></article-title><source>Front Neurosci</source><year>2016</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnins.2016.00357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26858586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coast</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Orchard</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schooley</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insect diuretic and antidiuretic hormones</article-title><source>Adv Insect Physiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>409</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2806(02)29004-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaufmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of carbohydrate metabolism and flight performance by a hypertrehalosaemic hormone in the mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>J Insect Physiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jinsphys.2007.10.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18062987?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18062987</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marinotti</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>QK</given-names></name><name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>JMC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microarray analysis of genes showing variable expression following a blood meal in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2583.2005.00567.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16033430?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16033430</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adipokinetic hormone inhibits the formation of energy stores and egg production in the cricket <italic>Gryllus bimaculatus</italic></article-title><source>Comp Biochem and Physiol - B Bioch and Mol Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1096-4959(03)00227-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindemans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adipokinetic hormone signaling through the gonadotropin-releasing hormone receptor modulates egg-laying in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1642</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0809881106</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19164555?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19164555</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attardo</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of lipolysis underlying lactation in the tsetse fly</article-title><source>Glossina morsitans. Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.01.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22509523?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22509523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boes</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of seminal fluid proteins in the Asian tiger mosquito, <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic></article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e2946</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002946</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24945155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24945155</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>