<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5397871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep46163</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep46163</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Transcriptome Analysis of Mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.) Fruit Epidermal Peel to Identify Putative Cuticle-Associated Genes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tafolla-Arellano</surname><given-names>Julio C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Honghe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiao</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz-May</surname><given-names>Eliel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hern&#225;ndez-O&#241;ate</surname><given-names>Miguel A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Le&#243;n</surname><given-names>Alberto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>B&#225;ez-Sa&#241;udo</surname><given-names>Reginaldo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Zhangjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Domozych</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>Jocelyn K. C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tiznado-Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>Mart&#237;n E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Coordinaci&#243;n de Tecnolog&#237;a de Alimentos de Origen Vegetal, Centro de Investigaci&#243;n en Alimentaci&#243;n y Desarrollo, A. C. Hermosillo</institution>, Sonora, <country>M&#233;xico</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Plant Biology Section, School of Integrative Plant Science, Cornell University</institution>, Ithaca, NY, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Boyce Thompson Institute, Cornell University</institution>, Ithaca, NY, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label>4</label><institution>Red de Estudios Moleculares Avanzados, Instituto de Ecolog&#237;a A. C., Cluster Biomimic<sup>&#174;</sup>, C. Xalapa</institution>, Veracruz, <country>M&#233;xico</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label>5</label><institution>CONACYT-Coordinaci&#243;n de Tecnolog&#237;a de Alimentos de Origen Vegetal, Centro de Investigaci&#243;n en Alimentaci&#243;n y Desarrollo A.C. Hermosillo</institution>, Sonora, <country>M&#233;xico</country></aff><aff id="a6"><label>6</label><institution>US Department of Agriculture/Agriculture Research Service, Robert W. Holley Center for Agriculture and Health</institution>, Ithaca, NY, <country>USA</country></aff><aff id="a7"><label>7</label><institution>Department of Biology, Skidmore Microscopy Imaging Center, Skidmore College, Saratoga</institution>, Springs, NY, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>tiznado@ciad.mx</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>04</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>46163</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>03</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#169; 2017, The Author(s)</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><!--author-paid--><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#8217;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Mango fruit (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.) are highly perishable and have a limited shelf life, due to postharvest desiccation and senescence, which limits their global distribution. Recent studies of tomato fruit suggest that these traits are influenced by the expression of genes that are associated with cuticle metabolism. However, studies of these phenomena in mango fruit are limited by the lack of genome-scale data. In order to gain insight into the mango cuticle biogenesis and identify putative cuticle-associated genes, we analyzed the transcriptomes of peels from ripe and overripe mango fruit using RNA-Seq. Approximately 400 million reads were generated and <italic>de novo</italic> assembled into 107,744 unigenes, with a mean length of 1,717&#8201;bp and with this information an online Mango RNA-Seq Database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.bti.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/mango/index.cgi">http://bioinfo.bti.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/mango/index.cgi</ext-link>) which is a valuable genomic resource for molecular research into the biology of mango fruit was created. RNA-Seq analysis suggested that the pathway leading to biosynthesis of the cuticle component, cutin, is up-regulated during overripening. This data was supported by analysis of the expression of several putative cuticle-associated genes and by gravimetric and microscopic studies of cuticle deposition, revealing a complex continuous pattern of cuticle deposition during fruit development and involving substantial accumulation during ripening/overripening.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p>The fruit of the tropical species, mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.) belongs to the order sapindales in the family <italic>Anacardiaceae</italic>, also known as the &#8220;king of fruits&#8221;, is a climacteric, fleshy and large drupe that has considerable commercial value<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref>. The mango fruit varies in size, shape, color, fiber content, flavor, and taste. The exocarp region develops into a leathery protective skin that is smooth, green and waxy, including lenticels originated from stomata. When mango ripe, the skin changes to a pale green or yellow marked with red, according to cultivars<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3">3</xref>. After harvest and under native climatic conditions, mango fruit ripen within 6 to 7 days, but reach an overripe stage and spoil within 15 days<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4">4</xref>. As is typical of many fleshy fruit species, in addition to a loss of tissue integrity and microbial infection, postharvest desiccation and consequent oversoftening are important determinants of postharvest fruit quality<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>.</p><p>The exocarp influences the outward appearance of fruit, as reflected in characteristics such as color, glossiness, texture, and uniformity, and it also plays an important role in shelf life<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>. The exocarp is also referred to as the &#8220;peel&#8221;, and typically comprises the epidermal cell layer, together with layers of associated collenchyma, and even parenchyma cells, depending on how the peel was physically removed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>. An important constituent of the exocarp is the cuticle, a hydrophobic layer composed mostly of cutin and waxes, which is synthesized by epidermal cells and represents the outermost barrier between aerial plant organs and the environment<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. Cuticles have many functions, such as limiting water loss and gas diffusion, and providing protection against insects, pathogens, and ultraviolet radiation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>. Their composition and physical properties are also suggested to contribute to commercially important fruit traits and postharvest shelf life<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. In this regard, an improved understanding of the molecular processes involved in cuticle formation and modification has considerable potential value in designing strategies to improve fruit quality.</p><p>To date, most studies of cuticle related genes have been carried out using the vegetative organs of the model plant Arabidopsis (<italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic>). However, tomato fruit have become a model system for the study of the cuticle biology in fleshy fruits<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>, while additional important information has been gained from equivalent analyses of other fruits, such as apple (<italic>Malus domestica</italic> B.)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> and sweet cherry (<italic>Prunus avium</italic> L.)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>.</p><p>However, despite the agronomic and economic importance of mango fruit, little is known about the molecular mechanisms that underly the biosynthesis of its cuticle. Moreover, only a few studies have addressed the changes in mango fruit cuticle composition and morphology during development and storage<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, or in response to various treatments<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17">17</xref>. The major obstacle to further progress in mango genetic research is the limited availability of genomic data. However, next generation DNA sequencing methods and bioinformatic pipelines are facilitating the generation of genomic and transcriptomic analytical tools and resources. The application of such tools to study cuticle-associated genes will be of great value in elucidating many aspects of cuticle biology that currently are not well understood<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>.</p><p>The objective of this current study was to gain insight into cuticle biogenesis identifying putative cuticle-associated genes during mango fruit ontogeny. To this end, we used RNA Sequencing (RNA-Seq) to profile the transcriptomes of ripe and overripe fruit mango peels and further analyzed the expression profile of putative cuticle-associated genes by real time quantitative reverse transcription PCR (qRT-PCR). Patterns of gene expression were then correlated with the rate of cuticle accumulation during the fruit ontogeny. We discuss the putative roles of specific genes in the biosynthesis and transport of cutin and waxes during the cuticle formation.</p><sec disp-level="1"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Cuticle deposition during mango fruit ontogeny</title><p>The weight of the fruit cuticle was 889&#8201;&#956;g/cm<sup>2</sup> at 15 days after flowering (DAF), and continued increasing during subsequent fruit development (30&#8211;105&#8201;DAF), reaching a maximum value of 1,763&#8201;&#956;g/cm<sup>2</sup>, and then decreasing to 1,632&#8201;&#956;g/cm<sup>2</sup> at 120&#8201;DAF. After that, cuticular weight showed an increase of 1846 and 1920&#8201;&#956;g/cm<sup>2</sup> from 135 to 141&#8201;DAF, respectively. Unlike the foregoing pattern, a slight decrease to 1827&#8201;&#956;g/cm<sup>2</sup> was recorded at 147&#8201;DAF. Finally, the cuticle accumulation showed a large increase by the end of the storage time to reach 2100&#8201;&#956;g/cm<sup>2</sup> at 153 DAF, which is the maximum cuticular weight registered during mango fruit ontogeny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). This revealed a continuous pattern of cuticle deposition during fruit development and involving substantial accumulation during ripening/overripening. This is consistent with the cuticle accumulation pattern reported by Petit-Jim&#233;nez <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>, for the same mango cultivar. A similar result was reported for orange fruit (<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> Osbeck), where the weight of cuticle per unit increased by almost two-fold at 150&#8201;DAF compared with 120&#8201;DAF<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18">18</xref>. It has also been reported that apple fruit exhibit an increase in cuticular wax deposition during ripening, coincident with a burst in ethylene production<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>. Nonetheless, this pattern differs from that seen in many fruit species, where cuticle deposition ceases or decreases immediately after the phase of fruit expansion and before the initiation of the ripening<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. For example, grape berry was reported to undergo a decrease in the amount of cuticular material after harvest<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref>, and a similar phenomenon was seen in sweet cherry<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>. Moreover, in tomato, Yeats <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, reported that maximal cuticle accumulation occurred during the most rapid stage of fruit growth and thereafter, cuticle accumulation decreased until reaching the red ripe stage. However, to date nothing is known about its functional significance, or the factors that determine the various patterns of cuticular deposition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref>. The results of several studies suggest that cuticle biosynthesis depends on species and stage of development and it is influenced by genetics, physiological, environmental factors and postharvest handling<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9">9</xref>, which can explain the differences in the studies above mentioned.</p><p>There have been few studies of cuticles during fruit storage<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20">20</xref>. In this context, in order to identify potential changes in cuticle architecture during the ripe to overripe transition (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2A,B</xref>), we analyzed cuticle structural organization using light and SEM microscopy. Our results showed a slight increase in cuticle thickness and shape in overripe (16.64&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.31&#8201;&#956;m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2D</xref>) as compared with ripe stage fruits (14.39&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.37&#8201;&#956;m) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2C</xref>), moreover, a student&#8217;s t-test confirmed significant differences in the cuticle thickness between both fruit developmental stages (p-value&#8201;=&#8201;1.217E-05); which correlates with the differences in cuticle weight during the transition from ripe to overripe stages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Fig. 1</xref>). This finding agrees with previous reports showing that the cuticular wax density increased as the fruit develops, including during mature and overripe in mango cv. &#8216;Kensington Pride&#8217;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>, &#8216;Keitt&#8217;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref> and &#8216;Dashehari&#8217;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref>.</p><p>SEM imaging of the cuticles showed that the cuticular wax consisted of wax ridges, including a compact arrangement with few scales in ripe stage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2E</xref>). Meanwhile, in overripe fruits we observed a smooth wax layer with no scales, and small holes due to cracks between the wax ridges and lenticels (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Fig. 2F</xref>). Further, the development of cracks had been reported to occur as the fruit grew to maturity and ripened in mango<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15">15</xref>. Similar results were previously reported for ripe mango<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>, including loss of water and cell integrity.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><italic>De novo</italic> assembly, functional annotation and classification of mango unigenes</title><p>We sequenced six cDNA libraries (three ripe and three overripe) derived from mango (cv. &#8216;Keitt&#180;) peels using an Illumina HiSeq&#8482; 2500 operating in paired-end mode. This generated an average of approximately 74 million reads pairs from each ripe fruit peel library and 57 million read pairs from each overripe fruit peel library. After removing low-quality and adaptor sequences, a total of ~681 million reads (62.5&#8201;Gbp high-quality sequence) were used for <italic>de novo</italic> assembly. A total of 107,744 unigenes were assembled, with a total length of 184,977,733&#8201;bp, the robustness of this transcriptome data set is supported by the N50 value of 2,235&#8201;bp and mean length of 1,717&#8201;bp, which are among the highest values of previously mango transcriptomes reported (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). Unigenes were classified into four groups based on their length, 3,243 (3%) of the unigenes were &lt;300&#8201;bp, 69,214 (64.23%) were 300&#8211;2,000&#8201;bp, 33,426 (31.02%) were 2,000- 5,000&#8201;bp, while 2,235 (2.07%) unigenes were longer than 5,000&#8201;bp (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3A</xref>). Our transcriptome analysis summary and the comparison with the previously analysis is shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>.</p><p>The resulting sequence data were used to develop an online database called Mango RNA-Seq Database, which can be accessed at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.bti.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/mango/index.cgi">http://bioinfo.bti.cornell.edu/cgi-bin/mango/index.cgi</ext-link>. The annotation analysis using BLAST showed that the numbers of unigenes with significant hits (E-value&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;1E-5) to the Swiss-Prot, TrEMBL and Arabidopsis protein databases were 68,649 (63.7%), 91,736 (85.1%) and 88,242 (81.9%), respectively. A total of 15,984 unigenes had no significant matches in the Swiss-Prot and TrEMBL databases, and the remaining 91,760 unigenes were annotated using AHRD, among which 5,705 were annotated as unknown proteins (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Dataset S1</xref>).</p><p>A total of 79,208 (73.5%) unigenes were assigned into 9,945 Gene Ontology (GO) terms and, of these, 67,003, 68,347 and 67,160 were assigned at least one GO term in the &#8216;biological process&#8217;, &#8216;cellular component&#8217; and &#8216;molecular function&#8217; categories, respectively. The &#8216;biological process&#8217; includes &#8216;cellular protein modification process&#8217;, &#8216;response to stress&#8217;, &#8216;carbohydrate metabolic process&#8217;, &#8216;lipid metabolic process&#8217;, &#8216;secondary metabolic process&#8217;, among others. The molecular functions were related to hydrolase activity, catalytic activity, transferase activity, kinase activity, lipid binding. Additionally, we identified the putative biochemical pathways represented in the assembled mango transcriptome. Our analysis showed that a total of 7,740 unigenes were annotated in 461 pathways, including triacylglycerol biosynthesis, phenylpropanoid biosynthesis, phospholipid biosynthesis II, cutin monomer biosynthesis and flavonoid biosynthesis, among others. Finally, we identified unigenes encoding transcription factors (TFs) and protein kinases. A total of 5,342 TFs were classified into 55 different families, of which the largest were MYB, C3H, NAC, bHLH and HB. MYB transcription factor have been reported as regulators of various plant responses, including in cuticle biosynthesis under drought stress<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>.</p><p>A total of 3,662 protein kinases were classified into 76 different families. In addition, the families with the largest number of unigenes were Domain of Unknown Function 26 (DUF26) Kinase, Receptor Like Cytoplasmic Kinase VII, SNF1 Related Protein Kinase (SnRK), GmPK6/AtMRK1 Family and LAMMER Kinase Family (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Dataset S1</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Differential expression analysis</title><p>A comparative RNA-Seq analysis of peels from fruit at the overripe versus ripe developmental stages identified 1,616 and 3,733 unigenes that were up-regulated and down-regulated during overripening, respectively. An enrichment analyses of the up-regulated unigenes revealed that ~210 biological processes with associated GO terms, including those related to different &#8216;stress responses&#8217;, &#8216;lipid metabolic process&#8217;, &#8216;secondary metabolic process&#8217;, &#8216;cell wall metabolic process&#8217; and &#8216;fruit ripening&#8217;. In the &#8216;molecular functions&#8217; category (~125), the most represented GO terms assigned to unigenes were kynurenine-glyoxylate transaminase activity, cysteine-S-conjugate beta-lyase activity, long-chain-fatty-acyl-CoA reductase activity, fatty-acyl-CoA reductase (alcohol-forming) activity and acyl-[acyl-carrier-protein] desaturase activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Dataset S2</xref>).</p><p>For the down-regulated unigenes, the enrichment analysis identified ~550 significantly enriched biological processes, including those related to &#8216;cell wall polysaccharide metabolic process&#8217;, &#8216;homogalacturonan biosynthetic process&#8217;, &#8216;fruit development&#8217;, &#8216;response to ethylene&#8217; and &#8216;secondary metabolic process&#8217;. The molecular functions (~185) down-regulated included, angiotensin receptor activity, inositol-3-phosphate synthase activity, choline dehydrogenase activity, serine transmembrane transporter activity and shikimate kinase activity (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Dataset S2</xref>).</p><p>In addition, a clustering analysis of the 5,349 differentially expressed unigenes by expression levels identified 7 clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4A</xref>). Clusters I and II comprised 66 and 213 induced unigenes during overripening, respectively, and included genes related to glutathione-mediated detoxification II, homogalacturonan degradation, fatty acyl-CoA reductase and starch biosynthesis. Interestingly for the goal of this study, cluster III, which contained 1,318 induced unigenes, included those with annotated functions related to cutin monomer biosynthesis, flavonoid biosynthesis, oleate biosynthesis and homogalacturonan degradation. Cluster IV included 19 strongly induced unigenes with no clear functional annotation. The down-regulated unigenes during overripening were grouped into 3 clusters (V, VI and VII), and included genes associated with cytochrome P450 activity, carbohydrate degradation, glutathione transferase, chalcone synthase, chorismate biosynthesis and ethylene biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Dataset S3</xref>).</p><p>A metabolic pathway enrichment analysis showed that the up-regulated unigenes encoded enzymes in 106 metabolic pathways, included: 4-hydroxybenzoate biosynthesis V, phenylpropanoid biosynthesis, cutin monomers biosynthesis, flavonoid biosynthesis, and homogalacturonan degradation. The down-regulated unigenes encoded enzymes in 131 pathways such as glutathione-mediated detoxification II, chorismate biosynthesis I, chorismate biosynthesis from 3-dehydroquinate, lactose degradation III and 1,4-dihydroxi-2-naphthoate biosynthesis II (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4B</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Dataset S4</xref>).</p><p>We also identified the differentially expressed unigenes encoding TFs and protein kinases. A total of 92 TFs in 20 families were up-regulated during overripening, including: HSF, MYB and bHLH. Conversely, 342 TFs in 25 families were down-regulated during overripening, including NAC, C2C2-GATA and G2-like. We also observed that 54 protein kinases in 19 families were up-regulated during overripening, including Leucine Rich Repeat Kinase XI &amp; XII, Putative receptor like protein kinase and CRPK1 Like Kinase (Types 1 and 2). Conversely, 119 proteins kinases in 18 families were down-regulated during overripening, including SNF1 Related Protein Kinase (SnRK), CTR1/EDR1 Kinase and Ankyrin Repeat Domain Kinase (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Tables S3</xref>,<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">S4</xref>).</p><p>In order to corroborate the expression levels of the unigenes assembled by RNA-seq analysis, we performed a qRT-PCR expression analysis. For this, we selected several unigenes based on homology to genes associated with known roles in biosynthesis, regulation and transport of cuticle for other plants (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>). We used the same RNA samples from ripe and overripe mango peels used for RNA-Seq analysis to synthesize cDNA. We compared the log2fold change (overripe versus ripe) obtained by RNA-Seq and qRT-PCR analyses. Linear regression analysis showed a <italic>r</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup> value of 0.798 and a Pearson correlation coefficient of 0.893, with a p-value of 2.009E-5, indicating a close correlation between transcript abundance quantified by qRT-PCR and the transcription profile obtained by RNA-Seq data, thereby supporting the accuracy of the data (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Fig. 4C</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Cuticle biosynthesis</title><p>The biosynthesis of waxes, cutin, isoprenoids and phenylpropanoids involve four major metabolic pathways that are involved in tomato cuticle formation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>. Lipid metabolism is central to cuticle assembly as it supplies the precursors for the biosynthesis of wax and cutin. Indeed, Suh <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>, reported that over half of the fatty acids synthesized in the Arabidopsis stem epidermis are exported into the cuticle. In addition, Mintz-Oron <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref>, reported that the expression of 15% of the genes associated with fatty acid metabolism, wax and cutin was up-regulated in the tomato peel during cuticle formation, while secondary metabolites synthesized via the phenylpropanoid pathway are often constituents of cuticular waxes. In agreement with these data, our transcriptome analysis revealed a total of 136 and 45 unigenes, as associated with &#8216;lipid metabolism process&#8217; (GO:0006629) and &#8216;cutin biosynthetic process&#8217; (GO:0010143), respectively, whose expression was up-regulated during overripening. Additionally, the molecular functions most represented were &#8216;long-chain-fatty-acyl-CoA reductase activity (GO:0050062)&#8217; and &#8216;fatty-acyl-CoA reductase (alcohol-forming) activity (GO:0080019)&#8217;, with 45 unigenes each. We identified 53 and 4 unigenes, involved in the cutin biosynthesis pathway (PWY-321), that were up-regulated or down-regulated, respectively. In addition, we identified 123 and 110 unigenes whose expression was up-regulated involved in &#8216;secondary metabolic process&#8217; (GO:0019748) and &#8216;phenylpropanoid metabolic process&#8217; (GO:0009698), respectively, suggesting that the pathways related to the biosynthesis of cuticle components were very active in the peel during mango fruit overripening.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Gene expression during cuticle biosynthesis</title><p>In order to gain further insight into mango cuticle biogenesis, we analyzed the expression of fifteen putative cuticle-associated genes during fruit ontogeny (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Fig. 5</xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Regulation</title><p>The regulation of cuticle biosynthesis involves feedback from the cuticle components and with interacting metabolic pathways playing a role in responses to pathogen and environmental stress<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8">8</xref>. In Arabidopsis, the first cuticle-associated transcription factor, the AP2-domain super family member SHINE1/WAX INDUCER1 (AtSHN1/WIN1) induces the expression of a large numbers of gene encoding enzymes that are involved in fatty acid elongation and the formation of aliphatic compounds<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27">27</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtWIN1/SHN1, MiWIN1/SHN1</italic> (MIN047952), encoding a protein with 68% identity to AtWIN1/SHN1. The gene showed weak expression between 90 and 141&#8201;DAF, but this expression increased substantially during the storage period (147&#8211;153&#8201;DAF), coincident with cuticle accumulation. This is also consistent with the observation that overexpressing the tomato homolog, <italic>SlSHN1</italic>, induced a higher cuticular wax deposition compared with isogenic tomatoes lines<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>. Additionally, in sweet cherry (<italic>Prunus avium</italic>), the <italic>PaWIN/SHN1</italic> gene showed high expression levels at 21 days after full bloom, again during the major phase of cuticle accumulation<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>.</p><p>The transcription factor, <italic>SlCD2 (Solanum lycopersicum CUTIN DEFICIENT 2</italic>), a member of the HD-ZIP IV family, was identified as a regulator of cutin biosynthesis in tomato fruit<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10">10</xref>. Accordingly, fruit of the <italic>cd2</italic> mutant had an extremely thin cuticle and increased susceptibility to microbial infection. In addition, Matas <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11">11</xref>, reported that the <italic>CD2</italic> was the most differentially expressed transcription factor in the outer epidermis than in vascular tissues in tomato fruit. In this current study, we identified a mango homolog, <italic>MiCD2</italic> (MIN074277), encoding a protein with 86% identity to the tomato <italic>SlCD2</italic>. This gene showed low expression during the early and intermediate stages of development (15&#8211;141&#8201;DAF), but its transcript levels increased strongly during storage (147&#8211;153&#8201;DAF), coincident with cuticle accumulation, supporting its role in cuticle formation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Wax biosynthesis</title><p>The <italic>CER1</italic> gene encodes an aldehyde decarbonylase enzyme and catalyzes the conversion of long chain aldehydes to alkanes, a key step in wax biosynthesis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. Bourdenx <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref> demonstrated that the overexpression of <italic>CER1</italic> specifically increased the levels of odd-carbon-numbered alkanes; mainly C27, C29, C31, and C33 alkanes. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtCER1, MiCER1</italic> (MIN107433), encoding a protein with 64% sequence identity. This gene showed very low expression during early and intermediate stages of development (15&#8211;141 DAF), and a strong increase in expression during ripening and storage. Albert <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref> observed a correlation between the abundance of alkanes in apple fruit with the expression of <italic>MdCER1</italic> gene. Moreover, Broun <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref>, reported that <italic>AtCER1</italic> expression was induced by overexpression of <italic>AtWIN1/SHN1</italic>. We detected the presence of <italic>MiSHN1</italic> transcripts prior to the expression increase of <italic>MiCER1</italic>, which is consistent with an analogous regulatory system in mango, although this need to be tested experimentally.</p><p>The <italic>CER2</italic> gene encodes a putative BAHD acyltransferase involved in the elongation of alkanes beyond C28. In Arabidopsis, the <italic>cer2</italic> mutant lacks waxes longer than C28, suggest that <italic>CER2</italic> plays a role in very long chain fatty acid (VLCFA) synthesis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtCER2, MiCER2</italic> (MIN052433) with a low expression level during early and intermediate stages of fruit development (15&#8211;141&#8201;DAF) and increased expression during ripening and storage; thus <italic>MiCER2</italic> expression correlated with cuticle accumulation.</p><p><italic>CER3 (WAX2</italic>) was suggested to form an enzyme complex catalyzing the conversion of very long chain (VLC) acyl-CoAs to VLC alkanes<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref>. The total wax amount on <italic>Atcer3</italic> mutant leaves and stems was reported to be reduced by 78%, and a reduction in the amount of aldehydes, alkanes and secondary alcohols was observed<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtCER3, MiCER3</italic> (MIN064126) with low expression during early and intermediate stages of development (15&#8211;141&#8201;DAF), and high expression during ripening and storage.</p><p>The <italic>KCS2/Daysi</italic> gene encodes a 3-Ketoacyl-CoA synthase 2 and it is functionally redundant in cuticular wax and root suberin biosynthesis catalyzing the two-carbon elongation leading to C22 VLCFA<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtKCS2, MiKCS2</italic> (MIN101804) that was expressed at high levels during the early stages of fruit development (15&#8211;30&#8201;DAF). After that, expression was reduced during intermediate stages of development (75&#8211;141&#8201;DAF), but increased again during ripening and storage, although not reaching the levels observed during early stages. The expression of <italic>MiKCS2</italic> did not correlate with cuticle accumulation, and its function may be more related with changes in cuticle composition. This idea awaits to be experimentally tested.</p><p>The <italic>KCS6 (CER6</italic> or <italic>CUT1</italic>) gene encodes a 3-ketoacyl-CoA synthase 6<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref>. A loss-of-function tomato mutant showed a reduction in <italic>n</italic>-alkanes and aldehydes with chain lengths beyond C30 in waxes of leaf and fruit<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtKCS6, MiKCS6</italic> (MIN040156), with high expression during early fruit development stages (15&#8211;45&#8201;DAF), reaching the maximum expression at 60&#8201;DAF. After that, <italic>MiKCS6</italic> showed low expression during intermediate stages of development (75&#8211;141&#8201;DAF) and expression levels similar to the initial stages during ripening and storage. Thus, <italic>MiKCS6</italic> expression did not correlate with cuticle accumulation. A similar pattern was observed by Alkio <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>, in sweet cherry, where <italic>PaKCS6</italic> expression did not show an increase in expression during cuticle deposition. Conversely, Yeats <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, reported high expression of a tomato homolog, <italic>SlKCS6 (CER6</italic>) gene during the most rapid phase of fruit expansion, corresponding to a phase of substantial cuticle accumulation. The expression pattern of <italic>SlKCS6</italic> is therefore different developmentally compared with the expression of <italic>MiKCS6</italic>; however, both genes show high expression levels during the initial stages of fruit development.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Wax transport</title><p>Cuticle biosynthesis requires an extensive transport of lipids through the plasma membrane and cell wall of the epidermal cells. ATP binding cassette (ABC) transporters located in the plasma membrane of epidermal cells are required for both cutin and wax deposition<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39">39</xref>. In Arabidopsis, the ABC plasma membrane transporter, <italic>AtWBC11</italic>, is involved in the export of both cutin precursors and wax during cuticle development<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtWBC11, MiWBC11</italic> (MIN106958), with low expression during early and intermediate stages of fruit development (15&#8211;141&#8201;DAF), and high expression during ripening and storage, which correlated with cuticle deposition. Supporting these results, Bird <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref>, reported that alkane levels of mutant <italic>Atwbc11</italic> correlated with the levels of detectable <italic>AtWBC11</italic> transcript and Alkio <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>, reported a correlation in sweet cherry, between transcript levels of <italic>PaWBC11</italic> and the rate of cuticle deposition at earlier stages of fruit development.</p><p>The mechanism of structural lipid transport through the cell wall is not well understood, although lipid transfer proteins (LTPs), which are abundantly expressed in the epidermis and are secreted into the apoplast, have been proposed to be involved<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref>. Yeats <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, reported changes in the expression of LTPs during tomato fruit ontogeny coincident with cuticle biosynthesis. We identified three mango homologs of tomato LTP SGN-U579687: <italic>MiLTP1</italic> (MIN026365), <italic>MiLTP2</italic> (MIN018326) and <italic>MiLTP3</italic> (MIN107167). Our expression analysis showed that <italic>MiLTP1</italic> and <italic>MiLTP2</italic> were expressed at low levels during early (15&#8211;141) and intermediate stages (15&#8211;135&#8201;DAF) of fruit development. In contrast, <italic>MiLTP3</italic> showed moderate expression during early development (15&#8211;90&#8201;DAF) and low expression at the intermediate stage (105&#8211;141&#8201;DAF). However, all the three genes showed high expression during ripening and storage. These results suggest that these genes could be participating in the cuticle accumulation during the late stages. Mintz-Oron <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref> also reported high expression of SGN-U579687 in tomato fruit peels and we noted a higher expression of <italic>MiLTP1</italic> compared with all other genes analyzed.</p><p>In Arabidopsis, the export of some wax compounds appears to be facilitated by glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI)-anchored lipid-transfer (LTPG) proteins. LTPG1 protein was localized in the plasma membrane and an <italic>Atltpg1</italic> mutant with decreased expression showed a reduced wax load, mainly in C29 alkanes, and higher susceptibility to infection by <italic>Alternaria brassicicola</italic>, than the wild type<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43">43</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of <italic>AtLTPG1, MiLTPG1</italic> (MIN012243) that showed moderate expression during early stages of fruit development (15&#8211;60 DAF), low expression in intermediates stages (75&#8211;135&#8201;DAF) and maximal expression during ripening and storage which suggest a possible role for this gene in the export of cuticle wax components in mango fruit. In sweet cherry, Alkio <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14">14</xref>, reported positive correlations between <italic>PaLTPG1</italic> expression and cuticle accumulation during early fruit development but expression did not correlate in later development.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Cuticle assembly</title><p>The GDSL-motif lipase/hydrolase enzyme, <italic>SlCUS1</italic> (originally termed <italic>CD1</italic>), is a cutin synthase that catalyzes the polymerization of cutin monomers in the growing cuticle of tomato fruit<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44">44</xref>. We identify a mango homolog of <italic>SlCUS1, MiCUS1</italic> (MIN010966) that showed high expression during early fruit development (15&#8201;DAF), moderate expression during intermediate stages (45&#8211;141&#8201;DAF) and high expression during ripening and storage. Yeats <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19">19</xref>, reported that <italic>SlCUS1</italic> was maximally expressed during the most rapid phase of fruit expansion and cuticle accumulation, but not during ripening, which is consistent with the pattern of cuticle deposition late in mango fruit development, but not in tomato.</p><p>Another GDSL-motif lipase/hydrolase (SGN-U583101) gene was reported to show a high expression in the epidermis<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>. We identified a mango homolog of SGN-U583101, which we named <italic>MiCUS2</italic> (MIN031338). This gene showed a low gene expression during initial and intermediate stages, increasing expression at 147&#8201;DAF and maximum expression at 153&#8201;DAF. This data correlated with cuticle deposition during ripe and overripe stage. Conversely, Yeats <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref>, reported that SGN-U583101 was maximally expressed at 5&#8201;DPA which corresponds with a very early stage of fruit development.</p><p>As a control for ripening related gene expression, we also analyzed the expression of <italic>MiPEL1</italic> (AY987389), which encodes a pectate lyase in mango fruit. <italic>MiPEL1</italic> expression increased only at the ripe and overripe stage, in agreement with previous report where it had been associated with mango softening<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45">45</xref>.</p><p>Our transcriptome data derived from mango peel represents a valuable resource for future studies of mango fruit biology, but more specifically we have identified large numbers of unigenes, involved in several metabolic processes, related to mango fruit development, such as the synthesis or degradation of lipids, cutin, secondary metabolites and cell wall polysaccharides, among others.</p><p>Interestingly, the functional RNA-Seq analysis indicates that the cutin monomers biosynthesis pathway is enriched during overripening, which correlates with the microscopic and gravimetric analyses of cuticle accumulation. This revealed a complex continuous pattern of cuticle deposition during fruit development, involving substantial accumulation during ripening/overripening. The identification and analysis of the putative cuticle-associated genes expression provides the first insight to understand cuticle biosynthesis in mango fruit and indicate a close correlation with cuticle accumulation. However, further studies are required to confirm the role of these genes during fruit development. The cuticle-associated genes identified in this study will help in the elucidation of the molecular mechanism underlying cuticle biosynthesis and in the design of strategies to increase the postharvest shelf life of mango fruits.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Material and Methods</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Plant materials</title><p>Mango (<italic>Mangifera indica L</italic>., cultivar &#8216;Keitt&#8217;) fruit used for RNA-Seq profiling were obtained from a commercial store at Ithaca, New York, USA. The fruit were divided into two stages: ripe and overripe (storing them at room temperature approximately 20&#8201;&#176;C and 60&#8211;65% relative humidity for 12 days). Mango fruit of the same cultivar used for qRT-PCR analysis were hand harvested every 15 days after flowering (DAF) until ripening from trees in a commercial orchard and a packinghouse located at El Porvenir, Ahome, Sinaloa, Mexico (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.agricoladaniella.com.mx">www.agricoladaniella.com.mx</ext-link>). After ripening, the fruit were stored at 20&#8201;&#176;C and 60&#8211;65% relative humidity for 18 days, with sampling carried out every six days.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>RNA-Seq library construction and sequencing</title><p>Peel samples from three fruit were pooled to create a single biological replicate and three independent biological replicates of both ripe and overripe fruit were analyzed. Total RNA was extracted as previously described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46">46</xref>. Strand-specific RNA-Seq libraries were constructed using the protocol described in Zhong <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47">47</xref>. The resulting six RNA-Seq libraries were sequenced on an Illumina HiSeq 2500 system (Illumina Inc. San Diego, CA, USA) in paired-end mode with a read length of 100&#8201;bp in the Institute of Biotechnology at Cornell University (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biotech.cornell.edu/brc/genomics-facility">http://www.biotech.cornell.edu/brc/genomics-facility</ext-link>). The raw sequencing reads were deposited in the NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) under the accession number SRP043494.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>RNA-Seq data processing, <italic>de novo</italic> assembly and annotation</title><p>RNA-Seq reads were first processed to trim adapter and low quality sequences using Trimmomatic<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48">48</xref>. Reads shorter than 40&#8201;bp were discarded. The resulting high-quality cleaned reads were assembled <italic>de novo</italic> into contigs using Trinity, with &#8220;min_kmer_cov&#8221; set to 10<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49">49</xref>. Following assembly, the high-quality cleaned reads were aligned to assembled contigs using Bowtie<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>, allowing 3 mismatches. Following alignments, expression values (FPKM; fragments per kilobase of exon model per million mapped reads) were derived for each contig. Lowly expressed contigs (FPKM&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.002), and contigs with a low ratio number of sense to antisense reads (&lt;0.1) were discarded, as those sense reads may have been derived from incomplete digestion of the second strand during the strand-specific RNA-Seq library construction.</p><p>The resulting assembled contigs were then used to query the GenBank Nucleotide (nt) database (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genbank/</ext-link>) using the Basic Local Alignment Search Tool (BLAST)<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51">51</xref> function, and those having hits only to sequences from viruses, bacteria, and archaea were discarded. Next, rRNA, low-complexity, and polyA/T sequences were removed or trimmed from the contigs using SeqClean (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/seqclean/">https://sourceforge.net/projects/seqclean/</ext-link>). To remove redundancies in the contigs, the remaining contigs were further <italic>de novo</italic> assembled using iAssembler<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52">52</xref> with 97% minimum percent identify.</p><p>The final assembled mango unigenes were used to query the UniProt (Swiss-Prot and TrEMBL; <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uniprot.org/">http://www.uniprot.org/</ext-link>) and Arabidopsis protein databases (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.arabidopsis.org/">https://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link>) using BLAST, with a cutoff E-value of 1E-5. Based on the BLAST results, functional descriptions were assigned to each mango transcript using automated assignment of human readable descriptions (AHRD: <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/groupschoof/AHRD">https://github.com/groupschoof/AHRD</ext-link>). Gene ontology (GO) terms were assigned to the mango assembled transcripts based on the GO terms annotated to their corresponding homologs in the UniProt database<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53">53</xref>. Biochemical pathways were predicted from the mango transcripts using the Pathway Tools program<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54">54</xref>. Transcription factors and protein kinases were identified and classified into different families using the iTAK pipeline (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.bti.cornell.edu/tool/itak">http://bioinfo.bti.cornell.edu/tool/itak</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Gene expression quantification and differential expression analysis</title><p>The high-quality cleaned RNA-Seq reads were aligned to the assembled mango transcripts using Bowtie<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50">50</xref>, allowing 3 mismatches and only keeping the best alignments. Following alignments, raw counts for each mango transcript, and in each sample, were derived and normalized to FPKM. Genes that were differentially expressed (fold changes &#8805;2.0 and adjusted p-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) between overripe and ripe fruits were identified with the DESeq package<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55">55</xref>. GO terms enriched in the set of differentially expressed genes (adjusted p value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) and altered pathways were identified using Plant MetGenMAP<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b56">56</xref>.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>cDNA synthesis and real-time quantitative reverse transcription PCR for the developmental time course</title><p>DNA sequences of the mango homologs of tomato and Arabidopsis genes associated with cuticle biosynthesis, transport and regulation were obtained from our mango database using BLASTX (E-value&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;1E-5). The Coding DNA Sequence (CDS) and deduced amino acid sequence were obtained using Open Reading Frame Finder (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/gorf.html">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gorf/gorf.html</ext-link>). Signal-3L was used to identify signal peptides<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57">57</xref> and PredGPI predictor to identify glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) domains<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58">58</xref>. Oligonucleotide primers were designed according to Thornton and Basu<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59">59</xref> and are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table S1</xref>.</p><p>Peels were pooled to generate replicates and RNA extracted as above. A total of 2&#8201;&#956;g of total DNase-treated RNA was used for first strand cDNA synthesis using SuperScript II reverse transcriptase and oligo(dT) primers (Invitrogen), according to the manufacturer&#8217;s instructions.</p><p>Quantitative PCR analyses were performed using a StepOne&#8482; Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). The cDNA samples were diluted 5-fold with water and 1&#8201;&#956;l was used as a template for each 20&#8201;&#956;l quantitative PCR, prepared using HotStart-IT SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix (2X) (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA, USA) in biological triplicates. The thermal cycling conditions consisted of 2&#8201;min at 95&#8201;&#176;C, followed by 40 cycles at 95&#8201;&#176;C for 15&#8201;s and 60&#8201;&#176;C for 1&#8201;min. The specificity of the PCR products was determined by high-resolution melt curve analysis, gel electrophoresis and by sequencing, carried out at Macrogen (Macrogen Inc., Seoul, South Korea).</p><p>Statistical analysis of the relative expression results was carried out using the relative expression method<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60">60</xref>, with MiActin1 (GenBank accession No. JF737036) as a reference gene<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61">61</xref>, assuming a PCR efficiency of 1.0 for all genes. For each gene, expression was linearly normalized, with a value of 0.0 assigned to the stage with the lowest expression and 1.0 to the stage with the highest expression. Normalized gene expression profile data were used to create a heat map using heatmap.2 in the gplots package in R library (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/gplots/index.html">http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/gplots/index.html</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Microscopy</title><p>Peels from both ripe and overripe fruits was harvested, fixed, cryoprotected, and embedded as in Buda <italic>et al</italic>.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62">62</xref>. Cryosections of each sample were transferred at room temperature onto VistaVision HistoBond slides (VWR Radnor, PA, USA), dried and stained with Oil Red O saturated in 60% isopropanol (Alfa Aesar, Ward Hill, MA, USA). Sections were imaged with a Zeiss AxioImager A1 microscope equipped with a Zeiss EC-Plan NeoFluar 3100/1.3 oil immersion objective, a Zeiss AxioCam MRc color video camera, and Zeiss AXIOVs40 4.6.3.0 software. Images were obtained using DIC optics on an AxioImager A1 microscope equipped with an EC-Plan NeoFluar 40x/0.75 objective and an AxioCam Mrc color video camera (Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany). Cuticle thickness measurements were made on digitized micrograph images using ImageJ software (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://imagej.nih.gov/ij/">https://imagej.nih.gov/ij/</ext-link>). Ten replicates from several fruits were used for ripe and overripe stage, respectively. Each replicate consisted of 5 measurements made on five sections from the same sample. For SEM, the preparation technique is described next: 2&#8201;cm&#8201;&#215;&#8201;2&#8201;cm squares of surface tissue were quickly excised with a razor blade and adhered to small drop of low temperature glue on a 3&#8201;cm by 3&#8201;cm nitrocellulose sheet. The platform was rapidly plunged into liquid nitrogen and cooled for 30&#8201;sec. The platform was then secured to a liquid nitrogen-cooled JEOL cryostage (JEOL; www. jeolusa.com) and then placed into a JEOL 6480 Variable Pressure Scanning Electron Microscope. Specimens were imaged at 20&#8201;kV, 30&#8201;Pa (Pascal) pressure and spot size of 60.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Isolation and quantification of the fruit cuticle</title><p>Three replicate samples, each consisting of 10 exocarp discs, were collected for each developmental stage. The cuticles and gravimetric analysis during mango ontogeny were carried out as previously described<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref>. Data was analyzed by using variance analysis based in a complete randomized design with a significance level of 5%. Tukey test was run when significant differences were found.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1"><title>Additional Information</title><p><bold>How to cite this article</bold>: Tafolla-Arellano, J. C. <italic>et al</italic>. Transcriptome Analysis of Mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.) Fruit Epidermal Peel to Identify Putative Cuticle-Associated Genes. <italic>Sci. Rep.</italic>
<bold>7</bold>, 46163; doi: 10.1038/srep46163 (2017).</p><p><bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="d32e24" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Dataset S1</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-s1.xls"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e27" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Dataset S2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-s2.xls"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e30" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Dataset S3</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-s3.xls"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e33" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Dataset S4</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-s4.xls"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e36" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S1-S2</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-s5.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d32e39" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary Table S3-S4</title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-s6.xls"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>The author Julio C&#233;sar Tafolla Arellano thanks Mexican Council of Science and Technology (CONACyT) for the PhD scholarship assigned. This work was supported by Project 20120 (P0045001): Aseguramiento de Calidad de Frutas y Hortalizas from Research Center for Food and Development A.C. Also, the financial support of the National Council of Science and Technology (CONACYT) of Mexico with the grant number 579 is gratefully appreciated. The authors gratefully acknowledge M.Sc. Javier Ojeda for the help during mango sampling and storage. We also thank Agricola Daniella (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.agricoladaniella.com.mx">www.agricoladaniella.com.mx</ext-link>) for providing facilities and mango fruits for this study. Eric Fich and Laetitia Martin for advice in light microscopy. Dra. Iben S&#248;rensen for helpful in SEMs microscopy images. Dra. Silvia Moya and Dr. Jesus Hern&#225;ndez for access to qRT-PCR equipment facilities. Dr. Marisela Montalvo and Monica Resendiz for helpful advice during the qRT-PCR analysis.</p></ack><ref-list><ref id="b1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Litz</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>&#8220;Introduction: botany and importance&#8221;</article-title>. In <source>The mango, 2<sup>nd</sup> edition: Botany, production and uses</source> (Ed. <name><surname>Litz</surname><given-names>R. E.</given-names></name>CAB international 23) <fpage>1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>18</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/9781845934897.0001</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tharanathan</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yashoda</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Prabha</surname><given-names>T. N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.),&#8220;The king of fruits&#8221;&#8212;An overview</article-title>. <source>Food Rev. Int.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>95</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>123</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/87559120600574493</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Du Plooy</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van der Merwe</surname><given-names>C. F.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Korsten</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Lenticel discolouration in mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.) fruit&#8211;a cytological study of mesophyll cells from affected tissue</article-title>. <source>J. Hortic. Sci. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>81</volume>, <fpage>869</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>873</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/14620316.2006.11512152</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vazquez&#8208;Salinas</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Lakshminarayana</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Compositional changes in mango fruit during ripening at different storage temperatures</article-title>. <source>J. Food Sci.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>1646</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1648</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2621.1985.tb10555.x</pub-id> (<year>1985</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>L. B. B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>J. K. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>There&#8217;s more than one way to skin a fruit: formation and functions of fruit cuticles</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>65</volume>, <fpage>4639</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4651</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/eru301</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25028557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><name><surname>Mandel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>The ins and outs of tomato fruit peel metabolome. ISHS Acta Horticulturae 814: XII EUCARPIA Symposium on Fruit Breeding and Genetics</article-title>. <fpage>465</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>474</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.17660/ActaHortic.2009.814.79</pub-id> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mintz-Oron</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Gene expression and metabolism in tomato fruit surface tissues</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>147</volume>, <fpage>823</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>851</lpage>. 10. 1104/pp.108.116004 (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18441227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeats</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>J. K. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The formation and function of plant cuticles</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>163</volume>, <fpage>5</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.113.222737</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23893170</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tafolla-Arellano</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Le&#243;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tiznado-Hern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zacar&#237;as Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>B&#225;ez-Sa&#241;udo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Composici&#243;n, fisiolog&#237;a y bios&#237;ntesis de la cut&#237;cula en plantas</article-title>. <source>Rev. Fitotec. Mex.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Cutin deficiency in the tomato fruit cuticle consistently affects resistance to microbial infection and biomechanical properties, but not transpirational water loss</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>363</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>377</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03969.x</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19594708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matas</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Tissue- and cell-type specific transcriptome profiling of expanding tomato fruit provides insights into metabolic and regulatory specialization and cuticle formation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>3893</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3910</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.111.091173</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22045915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeats</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>The identification of cutin synthase: formation of the plant polyester cutin</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem. Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>611</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.960</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Candidate genes of cuticle formation show characteristic expression in the fruit skin of apple</article-title>. <source>Plant Growth Regul.</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>71</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>78</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10725-012-9779-y</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Alkio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jonas</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sprink</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Nocker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Knoche</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Identification of putative candidate genes involved in cuticle formation in <italic>Prunus avium</italic> (sweet cherry) fruit</article-title>. <source>Ann. Bot.</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>112</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aob/mcs087</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bally</surname><given-names>I. S. E.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Changes in the cuticular surface during the development of mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L.) cv. Kensington Pride</article-title>. <source>Sci. Hortic</source>. <volume>79</volume>, <fpage>13</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-4238(98)00159-9</pub-id> (<year>1999</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petit-Jim&#233;nez</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Le&#243;n</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonz&#225;lez-Aguilar</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sotelo-Mundo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>B&#225;ez-Sa&#241;udo</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cambios de la cut&#237;cula durante la ontogenia del fruto de <italic>Mangifera indica</italic> L</article-title>. <source>Rev. Fitotec. Mex.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>60</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jacobi</surname><given-names>K. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Gowanlock</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ultrastructural Studies of &#8216;Kensington&#8217; Mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> Linn.) Heat Injuries</article-title>. <source>HortScience</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>103</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/>. <article-title>Regulation of cuticle formation during fruit development and ripening in &#8216;Newhall&#8217; navel orange (<italic>Citrus sinensis</italic> Osbeck) revealed by transcriptomic and metabolomic profiling</article-title>. <source>Plant Sci.</source>
<volume>243</volume>, <fpage>131</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>144</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.plantsci.2015.12.010</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26795158</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Bramlage</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Developmental changes of cuticular constituents and their association with ethylene during fruit ripening in &#8216;Delicious&#8217; apples</article-title>. <source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>257</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>263</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0925-5214(00)00156-3</pub-id> (<year>2001</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lara</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Belge</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Goulao</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The fruit cuticle as a modulator of postharvest quality</article-title>. <source>Postharvest Biol. Technol.</source>
<volume>87</volume>, <fpage>103</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>112</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.postharvbio.2013.08.012</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Commenil</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunet</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Audran</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The development of the grape berry cuticle in relation to susceptibility to bunch rot disease</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>1599</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>607</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/48.8.1599</pub-id> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeats</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Mining the surface proteome of tomato (<italic>Solanum lycopersicum</italic>) fruit for proteins associated with cuticle biogenesis</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>61</volume>, <fpage>3759</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3771</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erq194</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20571035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khader</surname><given-names>S. E. S. A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tandon</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kalra</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Epicuticular wax and lenticel changes during development of mango fruit cv. dashehari</article-title>. <source>Indian J. Hortic.</source>
<volume>49</volume>, <fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>168</lpage> (<year>1992</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>Z. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Response of physiologic metabolism and cell structures in mango fruit to exogenous methyl salicylate under low-temperature stress</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Plant.</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>133</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2006.00731.x</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H. U.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>MYB94 and MYB96 additively activate cuticular wax biosynthesis in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell Physiol. pcw147</source>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcw147</pub-id> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Suh</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Cuticular lipid composition, surface structure, and gene expression in Arabidopsis stem epidermis</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>139</volume>, <fpage>1649</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1665</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.105.070805</pub-id> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16299169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aharoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>The SHINE clade of AP2 domain transcription factors activates wax biosynthesis, alters cuticle properties, and confers drought tolerance when overexpressed in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>2463</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2480</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.</pub-id>104. 022897 (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Broun</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poindexter</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>C. Z.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Riechmann</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title><italic>WIN1</italic>, a transcriptional activator of epidermal wax accumulation in Arabidopsis</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>4706</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4711</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0305574101</pub-id> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15070782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Al-Abdallat</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al-Debei</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ayad</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Hasan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Over-expression of <italic>SlSHN1</italic> gene improves drought tolerance by increasing cuticular wax accumulation in tomato</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mol. Sci</source>. <volume>15</volume>, <fpage>19499</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>19515</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms151119499</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25350113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aarts</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keijzer</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stiekema</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular characterization of the <italic>CER1</italic> gene of arabidopsis involved in epicuticular wax biosynthesis and pollen fertility</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>2115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2127</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.7.12.2115</pub-id> (<year>1995</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8718622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Reconstitution of plant alkane biosynthesis in yeast demonstrates that Arabidopsis <italic>ECERIFERUM1</italic> and <italic>ECERIFERUM3</italic> are core components of a very-long-chain alkane synthesis complex</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>3106</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3118</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.112.099796</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22773744</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bourdenx</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Overexpression of Arabidopsis <italic>ECERIFERUM1</italic> promotes wax very-long-chain alkane biosynthesis and influences plant response to biotic and abiotic stresses</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>156</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.111.172320</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21386033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nikolau</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Schnable</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cloning and characterization of <italic>CER2</italic>, an Arabidopsis gene that affects cuticular wax accumulation</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1291</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1304</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.8.8.1291</pub-id> (<year>1996</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8776898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haslam</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ma&#241;as-Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kunst</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Arabidopsis <italic>ECERIFERUM2</italic> is a component of the fatty acid elongation machinery required for fatty acid extension to exceptional lengths</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>, <fpage>1164</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1174</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.112.201640</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22930748</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodwin</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boroff</surname><given-names>V. L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Jenks</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Cloning and characterization of the <italic>WAX2</italic> gene of Arabidopsis involved in cuticle membrane and wax production</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>15</volume>, <fpage>1170</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1185</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.010926</pub-id> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12724542</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Two Arabidopsis 3-ketoacyl CoA synthase genes, <italic>KCS20</italic> and <italic>KCS2/DAISY</italic>, are functionally redundant in cuticular wax and root suberin biosynthesis, but differentially controlled by osmotic stress</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>60</volume>, <fpage>462</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>475</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03973.x</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19619160</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title><italic>CUT1</italic>, an Arabidopsis gene required for cuticular wax biosynthesis and pollen fertility, encodes a very-long-chain fatty acid condensing enzyme</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>825</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>838</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.11.5.825</pub-id> (<year>1999</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10330468</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vogg</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Tomato fruit cuticular waxes and their effects on transpiration barrier properties: functional characterization of a mutant deficient in a very&#8208;long&#8208;chain fatty acid &#946;&#8208;ketoacyl&#8208;CoA synthase</article-title>. <source>J. Exp. Bot.</source>
<volume>55</volume>, <fpage>1401</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1410</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erh149</pub-id> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15133057</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pighin</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Plant cuticular lipid export requires an ABC Transporter</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>306</volume>, <fpage>702</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>704</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1102331</pub-id> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15499022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bird</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Characterization of Arabidopsis <italic>ABCG11/WBC11</italic>, an ATP binding cassette (ABC) transporter that is required for cuticular lipid secretion</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>52</volume>, <fpage>485</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>498</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2007.03252.x</pub-id> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17727615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeats</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>J. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The biochemistry and biology of extracellular plant lipid&#8208;transfer proteins (LTPs)</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci.</source>
<volume>17</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>198</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1110/ps.073300108</pub-id> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18096636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>DeBono</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Arabidopsis LTPG is a glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored lipid transfer protein required for export of lipids to the plant surface</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>1230</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1238</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.108.064451</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19366900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Disruption of glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored lipid transfer protein gene altered cuticular lipid composition, increased plastoglobules, and enhanced susceptibility to infection by the fungal pathogen <italic>alternaria brassicicola</italic></article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>150</volume>, <fpage>42</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.137745</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19321705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yeats</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>The identification of cutin synthase: formation of the plant polyester cutin</article-title>. <source>Nat. Chem.Biol.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>611</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nchembio.960</pub-id> (<year>2012</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22610035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chourasia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sane</surname><given-names>V. A.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Nath</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Differential expression of pectate lyase during ethylene-induced postharvest softening of mango (<italic>Mangifera indica</italic> var. Dashehari)</article-title>. <source>Physiol. Plant.</source>
<volume>128</volume>, <fpage>546</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>55</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1399-3054.2006.00752.x</pub-id> (<year>2006</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Wilkins</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A modified hot borate method significantly enhances the yield of high-quality RNA from cotton (<italic>Gossypium hirsutum</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Anal. Biochem.</source>
<volume>223</volume>, <fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/abio.1994.1538</pub-id> (<year>1994</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7535022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>High-throughput Illumina strand-specific RNA sequencing library preparation</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb. Protoc.</source>
<volume>2011</volume>, <fpage>940</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>949</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/pdb.prot5652</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21807852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>2114</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2120</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title>. <source>Nat. biotechnol.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>644</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.1883</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Ultrafast and memory-efficient alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>R25</fpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2009-10-3-r25</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19261174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>S. F.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>3389</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>402</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id> (<year>1997</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<article-title>iAssembler: a package for <italic>de novo assembly</italic> of Roche-454/Sanger transcriptome sequences</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>453</fpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-453</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22111509</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">The Gene Ontology Consortium. <article-title>Gene Ontology Consortium: going forward</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>D1049</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>D1056</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1179</pub-id> (<year>2015</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25428369</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>P. D.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paley</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Pathway Tools software</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>S225</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>S232</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/18.suppl_1.S225</pub-id> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12169551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Differential expression analysis for sequence count data</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>R106</fpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2010-11-10-r106</pub-id> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20979621</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Joung</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>
<etal/>. <article-title>Plant MetGenMAP: an integrative analysis system for plant systems biology</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>151</volume>, <fpage>1758</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1768</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.109.145169</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19819981</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hong-Bin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Kuo-Chen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Signal-3L: a 3-layer approach for predicting signal peptides</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun.</source>
<volume>363</volume>, <fpage>297</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>303</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2007.08.140</pub-id> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17880924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pierleoni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Casadio</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>PredGPI: a GPI anchor predictor</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>392</fpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-9-392</pub-id> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18811934</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Real-time PCR (qPCR) primer design using free online software</article-title>. <source>Biochem. Mol. Biol. Educ.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>54</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bmb.20461</pub-id> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21445907</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#8722;&#916;&#916;CT</sup> Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>402</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>408</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.2001.1262</pub-id> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X. H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Ou</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Molecular cloning and expression analysis of four actin genes (<italic>MiACT)</italic> from mango</article-title>. <source>Biol. Plant.</source>
<volume>57</volume>, <fpage>238</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>244</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10535-012-0278-9</pub-id> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Buda</surname><given-names>G. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isaacson</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matas</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paolillo</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name> &amp; <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>J. K. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Three-dimensional imaging of plant cuticle architecture using confocal scanning laser microscopy</article-title>. <source>Plant J.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>378</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>385</lpage>, doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2009.03960.x</pub-id> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19563439</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Author Contributions</bold> J.T., J.R., R.B., A.G., Z.F. and M.T. designed and supervised the research. J.T. performed the experiments and data analysis. E.R. carried out the RNA-Seq library construction. M.H. performed the data analysis. J.T., M.T. and J.R. wrote the paper. DD did the SEM microscopy images. Y.Z., H.S., C.J. and Z.F. analyzed the transcriptome data and developed the Mango RNA-Seq database. All authors contributed to improving the paper, critically reviewed and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Cuticle accumulation.</title><p>Cuticle deposition during mango fruit ontogeny. The X axis shows the stage of mango fruit development in days after flowering (DAF) and the Y axis shows the amount of cuticle. The error bars correspond to the standard error, as determined using three replicates samples, each consisting of 10 exocarp discs. Sampling points with different letters are significantly different based in variance analysis and Tukey test with 5% of significance. Ovr stands for overripe.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-f1"/></fig><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Fruit cuticle structural diversity.</title><p>Mango fruit at the stages used for RNA-Seq analysis: ripe (<bold>A</bold>) and overripe (<bold>B</bold>). Cuticles stained with Oil Red from ripe (<bold>C</bold>) and overripe (<bold>D</bold>) mango fruit SEM images of cuticles from ripe (<bold>E</bold>;14.39&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.37&#8201;&#181;m) and overripe (F;16.64&#8201;&#177;&#8201;0.31 &#181;m) stages. Arrows indicates scales (<bold>E</bold>) and holes (<bold>F</bold>), respectively.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-f2"/></fig><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Mango RNA-Seq assembly annotation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Length distribution of mango unigenes. (<bold>B</bold>) Summary of mango unigene annotation. (<bold>C</bold>) Top 25 GO terms in biological process category. The X axis indicates the number of unigenes for each biological process. The numbers indicate the annotated unigenes.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-f3"/></fig><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Differential expression analysis.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Heat-map of 5,349 differentially expressed unigenes. The Roman numeral in the right side and the left column colors indicate independent clusters and the color key indicates the log2 fold change of overripe versus ripe samples. (<bold>B</bold>) Graph showing the pathways enriched in the overripe versus ripe fruit peel comparison. Right and left side indicates the metabolic pathways enriched in the up-regulated and down-regulated unigenes during overripening, respectively. Asterisks indicate the statistical significance level, corrected p-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.001 (***), corrected p-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.01 (**), corrected p-value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05 (*). (<bold>C</bold>) Graphing shows the Pearson Correlation Coefficient value between the gene expression ratios obtained from RNA-Seq and qRT-PCR analysis.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-f4"/></fig><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Heat map of expression profile of putative cuticle-associated genes and cuticle accumulation during mango fruit ontogeny.</title><p>Time course of the expression of selected genes during fruit growth and ripening. The genes were classified into five groups according the role in cuticle biosynthesis. I: Regulation; II: Wax biosynthesis; III: Wax transport; IV: Cuticle assembly and V: Control for ripening. The cuticle deposition is indicated above the fruit development stages. Ovr stands for overripe.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep46163-f5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="t1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characterization of cuticle-associated genes in mango.</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t1-fn1"><p>Mango genes analyzed in this study were named after the most similar Tomato and Arabidopsis genes and including a prefix &#8220;Mi&#8221; for <italic>Mangifera indica</italic>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></floats-group></article>