<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Int Med Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Int. Med. Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">IMR</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spimr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of International Medical Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0300-0605</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1473-2300</issn><publisher><publisher-name>SAGE Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage UK: London, England</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5536669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300060517700322</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_0300060517700322</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Reports</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Efficacy and safety of topical diclofenac/menthol gel for ankle sprain: A randomized, double-blind, placebo- and active-controlled trial</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Pamela M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0300060517700322">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-0300060517700322"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Collaku</surname><given-names>Agron</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2-0300060517700322">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-0300060517700322">&#8224;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>Kenneth</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-0300060517700322">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-0300060517700322"><label>1</label>Clinical Development and Medical Affairs, GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare, Warren, NJ, USA</aff><aff id="aff2-0300060517700322"><label>2</label>Biostatistics Department, GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare, Warren, NJ, USA</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn1-0300060517700322"><label>&#8224;</label><p>Current address: Biostatistics Department, Perrigo Company plc, 8 Campus Drive, Parsippany, NJ, USA</p></fn><corresp id="corresp1-0300060517700322">Pamela M. Lai, Principal Clinical Scientist, GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare, 184 Liberty Corner Road, Warren, NJ 07059, USA. Email: <email>pamela.m.lai@gsk.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>45</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>661</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><copyright-holder content-type="sage">SAGE Publications</copyright-holder><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://www.creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access page(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage">https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Purpose</title><p>This study was performed to evaluate topical 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel in treating ankle sprain.</p></sec><sec><title>Design</title><p>In this randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial, adolescents and adults with acute ankle sprain (N&#8201;=&#8201;385) applied 4&#8201;g of gel containing 1% diclofenac/3% menthol (n&#8201;=&#8201;117), 1% diclofenac (n&#8201;=&#8201;112), 3% menthol (n&#8201;=&#8201;77), or placebo (n&#8201;=&#8201;75) four times daily. The primary outcome was the area under the curve of pain intensity (PI) on movement [0 (no pain) to 10 (extreme pain)] from 24 to 72 hours post-application (AUC<sub>1&#8211;3 days</sub>). Secondary outcomes included pain relief (PR); PI; time to onset of PR, meaningful PR, cooling, and complete recovery; PI difference; sum of PI difference; total PR; reduction in ankle swelling; and the patient&#8217;s global assessment of response to treatment.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>There were no statistically significant differences in AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> between 1% diclofenac/3% menthol and placebo, diclofenac, or menthol gels and no meaningful advantages of 1% diclofenac/3% menthol for any secondary outcome. There was a higher incidence of skin and application-site events with 1% diclofenac/3% menthol than with placebo or 1% diclofenac.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>No significant improvement was observed with topical 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel compared with placebo, 1% diclofenac, or 3% menthol gel in treating pain from ankle sprain.</p><p>ClinicalTrials.Gov Identifier: NCT02100670</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Ankle sprain</kwd><kwd>pain</kwd><kwd>diclofenac</kwd><kwd>menthol</kwd><kwd>topical administration</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-0300060517700322"><title>Introduction</title><p>Ankle sprain is a common musculoskeletal injury, particularly among physically active individuals.<sup><xref rid="bibr1-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">1</xref><xref rid="bibr2-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr"/>&#8211;<xref rid="bibr3-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The most common form of ankle sprain involves plantar flexion and inversion, which results in damage to the lateral stabilizing ankle ligaments, including the anterior talofibular ligament, calcaneofibular ligament, and posterior talofibular ligament.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Depending on the severity of the sprain, these ligaments may be stretched, partially torn, or completely ruptured.<sup><xref rid="bibr4-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> In severe sprains, additional structures, including tendons, nerves, muscles, and other ligaments, may also be injured.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> These injuries can lead to pain, swelling, loss of function, and reduced range of motion.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup></p><p>Standard care for ankle sprain includes rest, ice, compression, and elevation (known as the RICE protocol); early weight bearing with support (depending on severity); manual therapy; and functional rehabilitation.<sup><xref rid="bibr3-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="bibr4-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Oral and topical nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) can be used as supportive therapy to reduce pain, swelling, and disability and improve function in patients with ankle sprain.<sup><xref rid="bibr5-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="bibr6-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup></p><p>Topical NSAIDs work locally to provide short-term pain relief (PR) while potentially reducing systemic side effects (e.g., gastrointestinal effects) that may occur with orally administered NSAIDs.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr8-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> Topical diclofenac gel is used to treat pain associated with osteoarthritis and other musculoskeletal disorders, including ligament, tendon, muscle, and joint conditions characterized by pain and inflammation.<sup><xref rid="bibr7-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup></p><p>Topical menthol stimulates thermoreceptors, resulting in sensations of either cooling or warmth, and has an anesthetic effect.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr10-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> Menthol, which is lipophilic and causes local vasodilation, has been shown to enhance skin penetration when added to topical analgesics such as tetracaine or diclofenac; menthol may also enhance the analgesic effects of these agents, as previously demonstrated with tetracaine.<sup><xref rid="bibr9-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bibr11-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">11</xref><xref rid="bibr12-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr"/>&#8211;<xref rid="bibr13-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p>Whether combining a topical NSAID with topical menthol will improve PR remains unknown. This study was conducted to evaluate the efficacy and safety of a combination 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel in treating ankle sprain in adolescents and adults.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2-0300060517700322"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3-0300060517700322"><title>Study design and procedures</title><p>This randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial involved patients with ankle sprain at 16 centers in Germany from 13 November 2013 to 22 March 2015 (ClinicalTrials.gov Identifier: NCT02100670). Eligible patients were randomly assigned to receive 4&#8201;g of topical 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel, 1% diclofenac/0.09% menthol gel, 3% menthol gel, or placebo gel with 0.09% menthol four times daily at 4- to 6-hour intervals either until complete resolution of pain and swelling or for 10 days, whichever occurred first. The diclofenac in the 1% diclofenac/0.09% menthol gel represented the active control; the amount of menthol was subtherapeutic and added for its fragrance to maintain investigator and patient blinding to the treatment assignments. The patients received training in correct application of the gel and a marked applicator strip to facilitate correct dosing, and application of the first dose was supervised. The marked applicator strip contained two circles with an X marked in the center of each; the patients were instructed to squeeze the tube to dispense the gel into the center of each circle until the gel filled the circle completely, which provided a dose of approximately 4&#8201;g.</p><p>Randomization numbers were assigned to eligible patients in ascending numerical order, with both patients and key staff blinded to the treatment allocation. The randomization schedule was provided by the Biostatistics Department of GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare using their internal randomization process, which ensures concealment of the treatment code identifier. A block randomization method was used to randomize the patients into the four treatment groups in a 3:3:2:2 ratio. The randomization was stratified by site and age group (Stratum 1: 16- to 17-year-old patients; Stratum 2: 18- to 65-year-old patients).</p><p>The patients remained at the clinic site for 1 hour after the first dose. They completed and recorded subsequent treatment applications and assessments using a paper diary card at home. The patients then returned to the clinic on days 3 and 7 for follow-up and on day 10 for the final evaluation. They recorded pain intensity (PI) at baseline and then recorded PI and PR at 10 and 30 minutes; at 1, 4, 6, 12, 18, and 24 hours after the first dose; and then twice daily on days 2 through 10. PI was recorded at rest and on movement (walking 5 steps on a flat surface) using an 11-point numerical rating scale (NRS) with scores of 0 (no pain) to 10 (extreme pain). The PR score (PRS) was recorded using a 5-point categorical scale of 0&#8201;=&#8201;no PR, 1&#8201;=&#8201;a little or perceptible PR, 2&#8201;=&#8201;meaningful PR, 3&#8201;=&#8201;a lot of PR, and 4&#8201;=&#8201;complete PR. The patients also rated (yes/no) whether they had a cooling sensation at 10 and 30 minutes after each dose application and at 1, 4, and 6 hours.</p><p>The investigator (or designee) assessed ankle swelling by measuring the perimeter using the &#8220;figure-of-eight&#8221; method<sup><xref rid="bibr14-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup> at baseline and on days 3, 7, and 10. At the end of treatment, the investigator assessed patients&#8217; ankle function, and the patients completed a questionnaire regarding their global assessment of the response to treatment on a 5-point categorical scale (0&#8201;=&#8201;poor, 1&#8201;=&#8201;fair, 2&#8201;=&#8201;good, 3&#8201;=&#8201;very good, and 4&#8201;=&#8201;excellent). The patients were contacted via telephone 6 (&#177;1) days post-treatment to collect additional safety data.</p><p>Paracetamol was dispensed for use as a rescue medication (1000&#8201;mg every 6 hours as needed based on the patient&#8217;s opinion, not to exceed 4&#8201;g/day; patients were encouraged to wait at least 2 hours after applying the topical study medication before using the rescue medication). Use of other analgesics was prohibited during the study, with the exception of aspirin (81&#8201;mg/day or 325&#8201;mg/day) for cardiac prophylaxis.</p><p>This study was approved by independent central and local institutional review boards and conducted in accordance with the requirements specified in the Declaration of Helsinki. All patients provided written informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-0300060517700322"><title>Study population</title><p>The patients were aged 16 to 65 years and had a unilateral grade I or II acute sprain of the lateral or medial ankle that had occurred within 24 hours of presentation to one of the clinic sites based on the patient&#8217;s self-report. Enrollment was limited to those whose injury occurred within 24 hours of presentation because PI from ankle sprain largely decreases after 1 or 2 days. Thus, the greatest potential for a treatment benefit and an opportunity to observe a treatment effect would be anticipated within the first 24 hours after injury. The patients were recruited by placing advertisements in pharmacies close to the study center and in sports facilities/clubs, as well as by providing information about the study directly to trainers to encourage referral. In addition, some of the investigators were present during evening or weekend sports events (e.g., soccer), where they directly recruited players who experienced ankle sprain.</p><p>The inclusion criteria were an ankle PI score of &#8805;5 on an 11-point NRS, at rest or during movement, and perimalleolar edema (submalleolar perimeter difference of &#8805;20&#8201;mm between the injured and uninjured ankles as assessed using the &#8220;figure-of-eight&#8221; method). All patients were required to be in good physical and mental health and able and willing to comply with the study procedures and restrictions, and female patients of child-bearing potential were required to be using a reliable method of contraception. Fractures were ruled out based on the Ottawa ankle rules.<sup><xref rid="bibr15-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup> Patients subsequently noted to have grade III sprain or fracture were excluded from the study and referred for immediate care.</p><p>The exclusion criteria included pregnancy or breast-feeding, acute or chronic pain disorders, and current injury to both ankles or to both medial and lateral ligaments of the same ankle. Screened individuals were considered ineligible if they had any of the following in the sprained ankle: previous injury or surgery within the past 30 days, pain or instability due to a previous sprain or trauma, or ligament hyperlaxity due to connective tissue disease. Patients were also excluded if they had already used pain medications, massage, or physical therapy to treat the current ankle sprain (icing was permitted) or had current or past conditions or medication use that would preclude safe use of the study treatment or interfere with the validity of the study assessments.</p></sec><sec id="sec5-0300060517700322"><title>Study outcomes</title><p>The primary outcome was the area under the curve (AUC) of PI on movement as measured on an 11-point NRS (described above) from 24 to 72 hours after the initial treatment application [i.e., days 1&#8211;3 (AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub>)]. The AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> was calculated based on the trapezoidal method as the sum of the AUCs of PI for the time intervals 24&#8211;36, 36&#8211;48, 48&#8211;60, and 60&#8211;72 hours. The secondary outcomes were the patient-reported PRS, time to onset of PR, time to meaningful PR, time to onset of a cooling sensation, time to complete recovery, PI difference (PID) on movement and at rest, sum of PI differences (SPID), total PR (TOTPAR), reduction in ankle swelling, and the patient&#8217;s global assessment of their response to treatment.</p><p>The time to onset of PR was recorded as the time point at which the patients first reported a PRS of &#8805;1, representing &#8220;a little&#8221; or &#8220;perceptible&#8221; PR, confirmed by subsequent achievement of &#8220;meaningful&#8221; PR. The time to meaningful PR was defined as the first recording of a PRS of &#8805;2. The time to onset of cooling was defined as the time point at which the patients first endorsed experiencing a &#8220;cooling effect as an enhancement of PR&#8221; on the diary questionnaire. The time to complete recovery was the first day on which the patient reported complete relief of ankle pain and swelling. The PID on movement was calculated as PID<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;PI<sub>baseline</sub> &#8722; PI<sub>time t</sub>, where PI is PI on movement as measured using the NRS ratings at baseline and time t. PID at rest was calculated similarly using the NRS scores at rest. The SPID was calculated as SPID<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;&#931;(PID<sub>t</sub>&#8201;&#215;&#8201;[time<sub>t</sub> &#8211; time<sub>t&#8211;1</sub>]), where PID<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;PID at time t, time<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;time t in hours, and time<sub>t&#8211;1</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;time at previous time point t; the SPID was reported for hours 24&#8211;72 (1&#8211;3 days) and 0&#8211;168 (0&#8211;7 days). The TOTPAR was calculated as the sum of the products of the PRS with a time interval from one time point to another: TOTPAR<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=&#931;(PRS<sub>t</sub>&#8201;&#215;&#8201;[time<sub>t</sub>&#8201;&#8722;&#8201;time<sub>t&#8211;1</sub>]), where PRS<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=PRS at time t, time<sub>t</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;time t in hours, and time<sub>t&#8211;1</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;time at previous time point. The TOTPAR was reported for hours 24&#8211;72 (1&#8211;3 days) and 0&#8211;168 (0&#8211;7 days). Treatment differences were calculated for reduction in ankle swelling, measured as the change in the ankle perimeter from baseline to days 3 and 7, based on the investigator&#8217;s &#8220;figure-of-eight&#8221; measurement. (Because not all patients were expected to require 10 days of treatment, the final measurement on day 10 was performed only to provide reassurance that the patient did not need further treatment or follow-up.)</p><p>Safety outcomes included frequency, severity, and the relationship between treatment and adverse events (AEs) and serious AEs. Safety was evaluated from the first visit through 6 (&#177;1) days after treatment completion.</p></sec><sec id="sec6-0300060517700322"><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Safety was analyzed in all patients who were randomized and received any study medication. Efficacy was evaluated in the intent-to-treat (ITT) population, which comprised patients who were randomized, received treatment, and provided at least one post-baseline efficacy assessment. A sensitivity analysis for the primary and some secondary outcomes was performed in a per-protocol (PP) population that comprised patients who fully complied with all study procedures without major protocol violations.</p><p>The sample size was estimated based on the SPID<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> data because the AUC of PI on movement and the SPID are similar measures. Based on the clinical estimation of the performance of diclofenac from previous data,<sup><xref rid="bibr16-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> the effect of the diclofenac/menthol gel was assumed to be 27.5% greater than that of placebo and to show a difference of about 1.7 (8.0 for the diclofenac/menthol formulation vs. 6.3 for placebo). A sample size of 360 patients in a ratio of 3:3:2:2 (n&#8201;=&#8201;108 in the diclofenac/menthol group, n&#8201;=&#8201;108 in the 1% diclofenac group, n&#8201;=&#8201;72 in the menthol group, and n&#8201;=&#8201;72 in the placebo group) was determined to have 80% power to detect a significant difference between diclofenac/menthol compared with placebo at the 0.05% alpha level. Accounting for a dropout rate of 10%, enrollment of 400 patients was planned.</p><p>The AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub>, PRS, PID, SPID, TOTPAR, reduction in ankle swelling, and global assessment were analyzed using a mixed model analysis of covariance using SAS Proc Mixed (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA), with treatment and site as fixed effects and baseline PI as a covariate. As a sensitivity analysis, the mixed model analysis of covariance was repeated for the primary efficacy endpoint (AUC) with the site-by-treatment interaction effect added into the model. Differences among treatment least squares means for pairwise comparisons were performed at a 5% significance level (<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&#8804;&#8201;0.05). The time to onset of PR, time to meaningful PR, time to a cooling sensation, and time to complete recovery were analyzed using a Cox proportional hazards model (PROC PHREG in SAS) with factors for treatments and baseline assessment of PI (NRS) and site as covariates. Summary statistics were calculated for all other endpoints.</p><p>For the AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> and PRS, missing ratings during the first 3 days were imputed as the mean of the two adjacent values, if available. If all pain ratings or PR ratings were missing after a certain time point with no explanation, the patient was considered to have dropped out due to lack of efficacy, and subsequent pain rating scores were imputed using the last recorded score or the baseline score, whichever was more severe, and a score of 0 was assigned for the missing PRS. If a patient dropped out of the study because of an AE or reasons unrelated to the study medication, then the last recorded PI score and PRS were carried forward through day 3. For patients who used the rescue medication, all pain assessments within a 6-hour period after the rescue medication was taken were imputed as the last reported pain score before rescue medication use or the baseline pain score, whichever was worse; all PRSs during this time were set to 0. The procedure was repeated as many times as the patient used the rescue medication.</p><p>Compliance was calculated for each patient as a percentage (number of gel applications recorded in the diary card divided by the number of planned applications). The number of planned applications was calculated as the number of days the patient remained in the study multiplied by 4. Overall compliance was calculated as the mean of the individual patients&#8217; compliance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec7-0300060517700322"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec8-0300060517700322"><title>Study population</title><p>In total, 385 patients met the enrollment criteria and were randomly assigned to treatment. The safety and ITT populations both comprised 381 patients, and 360 completed the trial (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1-0300060517700322">Figure 1</xref>). The ITT population included 117 patients in the diclofenac/menthol group, 112 in the 1% diclofenac group, 77 in the 3% menthol group, and 75 in the placebo treatment group. There were 341 patients with no major protocol violations who were included in the PP population. A total of 40 patients had protocol violations, including 16 with acute, chronic, or recurrent pain (in violation of the exclusion criteria), 14 with poor compliance, 4 who had taken medications likely to interfere with subjective assessments (again in violation of the exclusion criteria), 4 who dropped out of the study, 1 who used rescue medication for most of the study, 1 with medial distortion of the ankle, 1 who was misallocated to treatment, and 1 for whom drug screening was not performed. Although aspirin doses of 81 or 325&#8201;mg/day were permitted for cardiac prophylaxis based on the study protocol, none of the enrolled patients used aspirin for this indication during the study.
<fig id="fig1-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Patient flow. <sup>a</sup>All patients who received at least one dose of medication also provided at least one post-baseline assessment; therefore, the safety and intent-to-treat populations were identical.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-fig1"/></fig></p><p>The baseline demographic characteristics and PI were similar across the treatment groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-0300060517700322">Table 1</xref>). Mean compliance was 94% to 96% across all treatment arms. Rescue medication was used on one or more occasions by 20 (17.1%) patients in the 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel group, 17 (15.2%) in the 1% diclofenac gel group, 19 (24.7%) in the 3% menthol gel group, and 18 (24.0%) in the placebo group.
<table-wrap id="table1-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Baseline demographics and pain intensity in the safety and intent-to-treat populations</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table1-0300060517700322" xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-table1"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-0300060517700322"><label>a</label><p>Patients rated their pain intensity on movement (walking 5 steps on a flat surface) on a scale ranging from 0&#8201;=&#8201;no pain to 10&#8201;=&#8201;extreme pain.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn2-0300060517700322"><p>SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec9-0300060517700322"><title>Efficacy</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-0300060517700322">Table 2</xref> shows results for the primary efficacy endpoint, AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> for PI on movement. There was no statistically significant difference in pain reduction as measured by the adjusted mean AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> between 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel (261.43) and placebo (270.66), nor was there a statistically significant difference in this endpoint between 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel and either of the active controls (1% diclofenac gel, 259.85; 3% menthol gel, 258.82). Furthermore, neither active control significantly differed from placebo on this endpoint. The results were similar for the sensitivity analysis that included the site-by-treatment interaction in the model.
<table-wrap id="table2-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub> for pain intensity on movement with 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel compared with 1% diclofenac gel, 3% menthol gel, and placebo gel in the intent-to-treat population</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table2-0300060517700322" xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-table2"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn3-0300060517700322"><label>a</label><p>Least squares treatment means from mixed model analysis of covariance, with treatment and site as fixed effects and pain intensity at baseline as a covariate. Lower values indicate a better response because of lower pain intensity over time.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn4-0300060517700322"><label>b</label><p>Difference in least squares means for the treatment named in each row minus the 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn5-0300060517700322"><p>AUC<sub>1&#8211;3</sub>, area under the curve of pain intensity on movement as measured on an 11-point numerical rating scale from 1 to 3 days after the initial treatment application; CI, confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>There were no statistically significant differences in the PRS between 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel and placebo or either active control at any time point from 10 minutes to 72 hours after the first treatment application (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0300060517700322">Figure 2</xref>). Mean PR was similar across all four treatment groups (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2-0300060517700322">Figure 2</xref>), and the active controls did not significantly improve the PRS compared with placebo at any time point. The other secondary efficacy outcomes (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-0300060517700322">Tables 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="table4-0300060517700322">4</xref>) did not reveal any meaningful advantages for 1% diclofenac/3% menthol over placebo or either active control.
<fig id="fig2-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Adjusted mean pain relief ratings with 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel compared with 1% diclofenac gel, 3% menthol gel, and placebo in the intent-to-treat population. Pain relief was assessed using a 5-point scale: 0&#8201;=&#8201;no pain relief, 1&#8201;=&#8201;a little or perceptible pain relief, 2&#8201;=&#8201;meaningful pain relief, 3&#8201;=&#8201;a lot of pain relief, and 4&#8201;=&#8201;complete pain relief. The adjusted mean pain relief rating score is the least squares mean from the mixed model analysis of covariance, with treatment and site as fixed effects and pain intensity at baseline as a covariate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-fig2"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="table3-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>Time-to-event outcomes in the intent-to-treat population</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table3-0300060517700322" xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-table3"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn6-0300060517700322"><label>a</label><p>Cox proportional hazard ratio and 95% confidence intervals of survival time (i.e., time to event).</p></fn><fn id="table-fn7-0300060517700322"><label>b</label><p>There were also no significant differences between 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel and either active treatment (data not shown).</p></fn><fn id="table-fn8-0300060517700322"><p>CI, confidence interval; HR, hazard ratio.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
<table-wrap id="table4-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 4.</label><caption><p>Assessments of pain, global response, and ankle swelling in the intent-to-treat population<sup><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-fn9-0300060517700322">a</xref></sup></p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table4-0300060517700322" xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-table4"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn9-0300060517700322"><label>a</label><p>n values shown in the column headings represent the full intent-to-treat population; sample sizes for the individual endpoints varied due to missing data at some time points for some outcomes.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn10-0300060517700322"><label>b</label><p>Difference in least squares means and 95% confidence intervals for each active treatment minus placebo.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn11-0300060517700322"><label>c</label><p><italic>P</italic>-value for active treatments vs. placebo from multiple comparisons using <italic>t</italic>-test in Proc Mixed (SAS Institute); other between-group comparisons were not statistically significant unless otherwise noted.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn12-0300060517700322"><label>d</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;0.0300 for diclofenac/menthol vs. diclofenac.</p></fn><fn id="table-fn13-0300060517700322"><p>SD, standard deviation; CI, confidence interval; PID, pain intensity difference: TOTPAR, total pain relief; SPID, sum of pain intensity differences.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="sec10-0300060517700322"><title>Safety</title><p>The 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel was associated with a greater number of treatment-emergent AEs (TEAEs) and treatment-related TEAEs compared with the other treatments; these TEAEs largely consisted of skin and application-site events (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table5-0300060517700322">Table 5</xref>). Two patients, both in the 1% diclofenac/3% menthol arm, experienced severe TEAEs. One patient developed application-site vesicles and necrosis, and the other had a hypersensitivity reaction; these events were considered treatment-related. All other TEAEs were mild or moderate. No serious AEs were reported.
<table-wrap id="table5-0300060517700322" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 5.</label><caption><p>Treatment-emergent adverse events in the safety population</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table5-0300060517700322" xlink:href="10.1177_0300060517700322-table5"/></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn14-0300060517700322"><p>TEAE, treatment-emergent adverse event.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec11-0300060517700322"><title>Discussion</title><p>The primary and secondary efficacy endpoints were not met in this trial. There were no significant improvements in the primary and secondary endpoints for 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel relative to placebo, 1% diclofenac gel, or 3% menthol gel. Treatment of acute ankle sprain with 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel was associated with a greater likelihood of application site and skin TEAEs. To our knowledge, this is the only published study to have evaluated the efficacy and safety of a combination topical diclofenac and menthol analgesic.</p><p>In this study, the active control gel containing 1% diclofenac alone showed no significant PR compared with placebo. Other randomized controlled studies have demonstrated efficacy with topical diclofenac or other NSAIDs compared with placebo. In fact, a Cochrane meta-analysis of randomized double-blind active- or placebo-controlled trials in acute musculoskeletal pain concluded that there is moderate- to high-quality evidence that topical diclofenac, ibuprofen, ketoprofen, piroxicam, and indomethacin all produce superior PR compared with topical placebo in acute conditions including strains, sprains, and other types of sports or overuse-related injuries, with diclofenac and ketoprofen being the most effective.<sup><xref rid="bibr17-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p><p>Individual studies have demonstrated efficacy specifically of diclofenac gel in the treatment of acute ankle sprain.<sup><xref rid="bibr18-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bibr19-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> In a phase III multicenter study conducted in Germany (NCT01272934), topical 1% diclofenac sodium gel applied four times daily was associated with less pain on movement at 72 hours compared with placebo (mean, 25.6 vs. 61.2&#8201;mm for placebo on a 100-mm visual analog scale [VAS]) and provided more rapid onset of PR (median, 4 hours vs. not achieved with placebo) in adult patients with acute grade I or II ankle sprain that had occurred within 12 hours of enrollment (N&#8201;=&#8201;205).<sup><xref rid="bibr18-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> Another randomized, double-blind study conducted at six centers in Germany evaluated a higher concentration diclofenac gel (2.32%) applied as 2&#8201;g rubbed into the ankle for about 1 minute, two or three times daily for 7 days in adults with acute grade I or II ankle sprain that had occurred within 12 hours of randomization (N&#8201;=&#8201;242).<sup><xref rid="bibr19-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> On day 5, the mean changes in the 100-mm VAS pain ratings were &#8722;49.1 and &#8722;49.7&#8201;mm with the diclofenac regimens, respectively, vs. &#8722;25.4&#8201;mm with placebo (both <italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.0001).<sup><xref rid="bibr19-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup></p><p>A 1.3% diclofenac epolamine topical patch<sup><xref rid="bibr20-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup> and a 4% diclofenac spray gel<sup><xref rid="bibr21-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup> have also shown efficacy over placebo in the treatment of acute ankle sprain. Effective relief of pain associated with acute ankle sprain has also been demonstrated with a variety of other topical NSAIDs, including 5% ibuprofen cream,<sup><xref rid="bibr22-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">22</xref></sup> 2% ketorolac gel,<sup><xref rid="bibr23-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">23</xref></sup> a 100-mg/day ketoprofen patch,<sup><xref rid="bibr24-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup> 2.5% niflumic acid gel,<sup><xref rid="bibr25-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup> and 0.2% mucopolysaccharide polysulphate/2% salicylic acid cream.<sup><xref rid="bibr26-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">26</xref></sup> Topical 1% (or 1.16%) diclofenac gel also has shown efficacy over placebo in relieving pain associated with osteoarthritis,<sup><xref rid="bibr7-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="bibr27-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">27</xref><xref rid="bibr28-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr"/>&#8211;<xref rid="bibr29-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup> as well as acute neck pain,<sup><xref rid="bibr30-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup> in randomized, double-blind trials.</p><p>Our results differ from the body of literature documenting the efficacy of topically applied NSAIDs in an ankle sprain model of pain. Possible explanations may include differences in the pain scales used (11-point NRS vs. 100-mm VAS), the longer interval between injury and treatment in our study (up to 24 hours vs. 12 in the two above-mentioned German studies<sup><xref rid="bibr18-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="bibr19-0300060517700322" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup>), no stratification by time since injury, and possible differences in dosing frequency, dose volume, and time spent rubbing the product into the skin. Patients did not always comply with self-assessment time schedules or avoid prohibited medications, such that the ITT analysis included 40 patients with protocol violations. Nonetheless, the results in the PP population also failed to show a significant treatment effect for diclofenac/menthol gel vs. placebo. Because there is no objective measurement for pain, studies of analgesics must rely on subjective pain rating scales. The amount of rescue medication used, particularly in the menthol and placebo groups, may also have influenced the results. Finally, this study was conducted in patients with acute ankle sprain who tend to be physically active individuals; therefore, the results may not be generalizable to other populations with other types of musculoskeletal pain.</p><p>The combination of diclofenac and menthol resulted in increased reported local AEs compared with placebo or with diclofenac alone.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec12-0300060517700322"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study failed to show a statistically significant difference in the efficacy of topical 1% diclofenac/3% menthol gel self-administered four times daily compared with placebo, 1% diclofenac gel, or 3% menthol gel in the treatment of pain related to ankle sprain. Although the product was generally well tolerated, combining topical 1% diclofenac with 3% menthol increased the incidence of mostly mild to moderate skin and application-site conditions compared with placebo or topical 1% diclofenac alone.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The Authors thank all of the investigators and participants of this trial. They also thank Jo&#235;lle Monnet in the GlaxoSmithKline Biostatistics Department for her statistical review of the manuscript.</p></ack><sec id="sec18-0300060517700322"><title>Declaration of conflicting interest</title><p>Pamela Lai and Kenneth Reed are employees of GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare. Agron Collaku was an employee of GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare at the time of the study conduct and analysis.</p></sec><sec id="sec17-0300060517700322"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was sponsored by GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare, Parsippany, NJ, USA. Medical writing assistance was provided by Peloton Advantage, Parsippany, NJ and was funded by GlaxoSmithKline Consumer Healthcare.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-0300060517700322"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerkhoffs</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Bekerom</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Elders</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosis, treatment and prevention of ankle sprains: an evidence-based clinical guideline</article-title>. <source>Br J Sports Med</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>854</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>860</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22522586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-0300060517700322"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doherty</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Delahunt</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Caulfield</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>The incidence and prevalence of ankle sprain injury: a systematic review and meta-analysis of prospective epidemiological studies</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24105612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-0300060517700322"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulseth</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Ankle stability and movement coordination impairments: ankle ligament sprains</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>A1</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>A40</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-0300060517700322"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhl</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattacola</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Management of ankle sprains</article-title>. <source>Am Fam Physician</source>
<year>2001</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>104</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11195774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-0300060517700322"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bleakley</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>MacAuley</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Some conservative strategies are effective when added to controlled mobilisation with external support after acute ankle sprain: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Aust J Physiother</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>54</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18298355</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-0300060517700322"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van den Bekerom</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sjer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Somford</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) for treating acute ankle sprains in adults: benefits outweigh adverse events</article-title>. <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>2390</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2399</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24474583</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-0300060517700322"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niethard</surname><given-names>FU</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy of topical diclofenac diethylamine gel in osteoarthritis of the knee</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>2384</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>2392</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16331769</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-0300060517700322"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Argoff</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Topical analgesics in the management of acute and chronic pain</article-title>. <source>Mayo Clin Proc</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>195</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>205</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23374622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-0300060517700322"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Menthol and related cooling compounds</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>46</volume>: <fpage>618</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>630</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7529306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-0300060517700322"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galeotti</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Cesare Mannelli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazzanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Menthol: a natural analgesic compound</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>322</volume>: <fpage>145</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>148</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11897159</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-0300060517700322"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Synergistically enhanced transdermal permeation and topical analgesia of tetracaine gel containing menthol and ethanol in experimental and clinical studies</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharm Biopharm</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>68</volume>: <fpage>735</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>740</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17398083</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-0300060517700322"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Menthol facilitates the skin analgesic effect of tetracaine gel</article-title>. <source>Int J Pharm</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>36</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16219435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-0300060517700322"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effect of O-acylmenthol and salt formation on the skin permeation of diclofenac acid</article-title>. <source>Drug Dev Ind Pharm</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>814</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>826</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19466898</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-0300060517700322"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esterson</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Measurement of ankle joint swelling using a figure of 8*</article-title>. <source>J Orthop Sports Phys Ther</source>
<year>1979</year>; <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>52</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18810189</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-0300060517700322"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stiell</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>McKnight</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Implementation of the Ottawa ankle rules</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>271</volume>: <fpage>827</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>832</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8114236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-0300060517700322"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopacka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gugliotta</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and tolerability of DHEP-heparin plaster in reducing pain in mild-to-moderate muscle contusions: a double-blind, randomized trial</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Res Opin</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1313</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1321</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22762346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-0300060517700322"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Derry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaskell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Topical NSAIDs for acute musculoskeletal pain in adults</article-title>. <source>Cochrane Database Syst Rev</source>
<year>2015</year>; <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>CD007402</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>CD007402</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-0300060517700322"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Efficacy and safety of diclofenac sodium topical gel 1% applied four times daily in subjects with acute ankle sprain (NCT01272934). ClinicalTrials.gov, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01272934">https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01272934</ext-link> (accessed September 20, 2016)</comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-0300060517700322"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Predel</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamelsky</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of diclofenac diethylamine 2.32% gel in acute ankle sprain</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>44</volume>: <fpage>1629</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1636</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22525762</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-0300060517700322"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lionberger</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Joussellin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanchick</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Pooled analysis of clinical trial data evaluating the safety and effectiveness of diclofenac epolamine topical patch 1.3% for the treatment of acute ankle sprain</article-title>. <source>Open Access J Sports Med</source>
<year>2011</year>; <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>75</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>84</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24198574</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-0300060517700322"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Predel</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Seigfried</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled multicentre study to evaluate the efficacy and safety of diclofenac 4% spray gel in the treatment of acute uncomplicated ankle sprain</article-title>. <source>J Int Med Res</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>1187</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23908551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-0300060517700322"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunn</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evaluation of topical ibuprofen cream in the treatment of acute ankle sprains</article-title>. <source>J Accid Emerg Med</source>
<year>1994</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>182</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7804585</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-0300060517700322"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diebschlag</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Nocker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullingham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A double-blind study of the efficacy of topical ketorolac tromethamine gel in the treatment of ankle sprain, in comparison to placebo and etofenamate</article-title>. <source>J Clin Pharmacol</source>
<year>1990</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>89</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2105985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-0300060517700322"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazi&#232;res</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouanet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Velicy</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Topical ketoprofen patch (100 mg) for the treatment of ankle sprain: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>33</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>523</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15722295</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-0300060517700322"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dreiser</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlot</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Clinical evaluation of niflumic acid gel in the treatment of uncomplicated ankle sprains</article-title>. <source>Curr Med Res Opin</source>
<year>1990</year>; <volume>12</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>99</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2202553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-0300060517700322"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frahm</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsasser</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#228;mmereit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Topical treatment of acute sprains</article-title>. <source>Br J Clin Pract</source>
<year>1993</year>; <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>321</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>322</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8117556</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-0300060517700322"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreiser</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Diclofenac sodium gel in patients with primary hand osteoarthritis: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled trial</article-title>. <source>J Rheumatol</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1991</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1999</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19648310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-0300060517700322"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baraf</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Safety and efficacy of topical diclofenac sodium 1% gel in knee osteoarthritis: a randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>Phys Sportsmed</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>28</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-0300060517700322"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barthel</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Haselwood</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Longley</surname><given-names>S</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Randomized controlled trial of diclofenac sodium gel in knee osteoarthritis</article-title>. <source>Semin Arthritis Rheum</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>39</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>212</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19932833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-0300060517700322"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Predel</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Giannetti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pabst</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Efficacy and safety of diclofenac diethylamine 1.16% gel in acute neck pain: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study</article-title>. <source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>250</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>250</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23964752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>