<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Oncotarget</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ImpactJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Oncotarget</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1949-2553</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Impact Journals LLC</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5085214</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27147566</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9046</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.9046</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>JNK2 downregulation promotes tumorigenesis and chemoresistance by decreasing p53 stability in bladder cancer</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Chun-Wu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Hailong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>Chenchen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Liguo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Jun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><sup>1</sup> Department of Urology, Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine, Huangpu, Shanghai 200092, China</aff><aff id="A2"><sup>2</sup> Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Mayo Clinic College of Medicine, Rochester, MN 55905, US</aff><aff id="A3"><sup>3</sup> Department of Gastroenterology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-Sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong 510080, China</aff><aff id="A4"><sup>4</sup> Division of Biomedical Statistics and Informatics, Mayo Clinic College of Medicine, Rochester, MN 55905, US</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold><italic>Correspondence to:</italic></bold><italic>Jun Qi,</italic><email>jasonqi@sh163.net</email></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><italic>Chun-Wu Pan,</italic><email>pancwu@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>23</issue><fpage>35119</fpage><lpage>35131</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#169; 2016 Pan et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Bladder cancer is one of the most common malignancies of the urinary system, and the 5-year survival rate remains low. A comprehensive understanding of the carcinogenesis and progression of bladder cancer is urgently needed to advance treatment. c-Jun N-terminal kinase-2 (JNK2) exhibits both tumor promoter and tumor suppressor actions, depending on tumor type. Here, we analyzed the JNK2 function in bladder cancer. Using gene expression microarrays, we demonstrated that JNK2 mRNA is downregulated in an orthotopic rat model of bladder cancer. JNK2 protein levels were lower in rat and human bladder cancer tissues than in normal tissues, and the levels correlated with those of p53. Moreover, JNK2 phosphorylated p53 at Thr-81, thus protecting p53 from MDM2-induced proteasome degradation. Decreased expression of JNK2 in T24 cells conferred resistance to cell death induced by mitomycin C. Furthermore, lower JNK2 expression was associated with poorer overall survival among patients who underwent radical cystectomy. These results indicate that JNK2 acts as a tumor suppressor in bladder cancer, and that decreased JNK2 expression promotes bladder cancer tumorigenesis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>JNK2</kwd><kwd>p53</kwd><kwd>bladder cancer</kwd><kwd>tumorigenesis</kwd><kwd>chemoresistance</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>Bladder cancer is one of the most common malignant tumors of the urinary system [<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Non-muscle invasive bladder cancer (NMIBC) accounts for nearly 70% of these cases, which can be easily resected through transurethral resection of bladder tumor (TURBT), but recur frequently (50-70%). Ten percent to 5% of NMIBCs progress to muscle invasive bladder cancer (MIBC), which has a 5-year survival rate of less than 50%, even if treated with radical cystectomy (RC) combined chemotherapy [<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Bladder cancer treatment has not improved for decades, and new approaches are needed [<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. A comprehensive understanding of the carcinogenesis and progression of bladder cancer is urgently needed to advance treatment.</p><p>The c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) family, a subfamily of the MAPKs, participates in a variety of cell responses, including proliferation, differentiation, and cell death and survival. As a result, abnormal JNK function leads to diverse diseases, including cancer [<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The JNK family contains three proteins, of which JNK1 and JNK2 are widely expressed in most tissues, while JNK3 is found only in brain, heart and testes [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The role of JNK1 and JNK2 in cancer is complicated and controversial. JNK1 is thought to function as a tumor promoter in lung cancer and primary hepatocellular carcinoma [<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and JNK2 promotes carcinogenesis in skin cancer and myeloma [<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. However, several studies suggested that JNK1 and JNK2 might also inhibit tumor progression. For example, JNK1-deficient mice are highly susceptible to intestinal cancer [<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Moreover, JNK2 inhibits breast cancer progression via regulation of cell cycle and DNA repair [<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. It is thus important to define the specific roles played by JNKs in particular cancer types.</p><p>P53, a classic tumor-suppressor protein, inhibits the development of cancer by promoting apoptotic cell death or blocking cell cycle progression [<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. In addition, p53 is an important regulator of metabolic changes and homoeostasis, making it perhaps the most commonly mutated protein in cancer [<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Given the high mutation rate of p53 and its various functions, it is still unclear whether p53 mutation may serve as a prognostic marker for bladder cancer patients [<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Here, we report that JNK2 mRNA is downregulated in an orthotopic rat model of bladder cancer, and that JNK2 protein levels are decreased in rat and human bladder cancer tissues, and correlate with p53 levels. Our findings indicate that JNK2 phosphorylates p53 at Thr81, which prevents its MDM2-induced proteasome degradation, and that lower expression of JNK2 is associated with worse overall survival among patients undergoing radical cystectomy.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>RESULTS</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>JNK2 expression is decreased in bladder cancer</title><p>The pathologic type of the tumors was identified as bladder transitional cell carcinoma (BTCC) by H&amp;E staining (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a</xref>). Using Affymetrix gene expression microarrays (GEM), we compared mRNA expression in tumors and normal bladder tissues. The data obtained from GEM have been deposited in the GEO database (GEO accession number GSE76702). The results of pathway analysis and Gene Ontology (GO) analysis are shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S2</xref>. Based on the GEM data, we found that the expression patterns of genes involved in MAPK signaling exhibited prominent changes (tumor vs. normal, p=0.009, Enrichment test). For example, mRNA expression of <italic>MAPK9</italic>, which is the gene encoding JNK2 kinase, was significantly lower in tumors than that in normal tissues (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1b</xref>). We then examined the JNK2 protein levels in rat tissues using immunohistochemistry (IHC). The JNK2 protein levels were significantly lower in tumors than in normal tissues, which was consistent with the mRNA results (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1a</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Both mRNA and protein levels of JNK2 decrease in bladder cancer</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Representative images of macrography, H&amp;E staining and IHC of anti-JNK2 antibody on tissues of orthotopic rat bladder cancer model. Scale bar represents 100&#956;m. <bold>b.</bold> Left panel shows changed genes in rat bladder cancer tissues (n=3) compared with normal rat bladder tissues (n=3) analyzed by gene expression microarray (GEM). Right panel shows details of <italic>MAPK9</italic> gene and genes around. <bold>c.</bold> Heat map shows IHC staining index of JNK2 of human bladder tissues. See a detailed scoring method in Material and Methods section. Left panel comes from tissue microarray (TMA) of 44 patients underwent RC (Radical cystectomy). Right panel comes from 16 patients underwent TURBT (Transurethral resection of bladder tumor). ANT: adjacent normal tissue. <bold>d.</bold> Representative images of H&amp;E staining and IHC of anti-JNK2 antibody on TMA of 44 RC patients. Areas indicated by arrows are blood vessels and connective tissues, not tumor area. Scale bar represents 100&#956;m. <bold>e.</bold> Box-plot shows IHC staining index of JNK2 on tissues from 44 RC patients and 16 TURBT patients respectively. <bold>f.</bold> Western blotting analysis of protein from bladder tissues of 7 MIBC patients. Histogram shows ratios of relative quantity of indicated proteins from ANT to tumor tissues. T: tumor tissues. A: adjacent normal tissues.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-35119-g001"/></fig><p>In tissues obtained from RC and TURBT patients, JNK2 expression was evaluated by tissue microarrays (TMA) and IHC. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1c</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1d</xref>, the staining index (SI) of JNK2 in tumors was significantly lower than that in the paired ANTs of both RC patients (p=0.000, t test) and TURBT patients (p=0.005, t test). Box plot showed that there was a further decrease tendency of JNK2 levels in RC patients compared to TURBT patients (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1e</xref>). Using western blotting, we further evaluated the JNK2 protein levels in tissues of 28 MIBC patients. 21 out of 28 MIBC patients exhibited lower JNK2 protein levels in tumor tissues compared with paired ANTs (p=0.000, chi-square); 7 representative cases are shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1f</xref>. These data indicate that bladder tumorigenesis and tumor progression are associated with decreased mRNA and protein levels of JNK2.</p></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>JNK2 promotes stability and pro-apoptotic activity of p53 through p53 phosphorylation at Thr81</title><p>As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2a</xref>, p53 primary sequence contains a JNK-binding consensus motif [<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. To determine whether p53 binds to JNK2 in T24 cells, we performed a co-immunoprecipitation (co-IP) assay (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2b</xref>). We learned from the GEM data that there was no difference in <italic>TP53</italic> mRNA levels between normal bladder tissues and tumor tissues, which was further confirmed by real time qPCR of tissues from 3 MIBC patients (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2c</xref>). However, western blotting demonstrated that the p53 protein levels were significantly lower in tumors compared to paired ANTs in 25 out of 28 MIBC patients (p=0.000,chi-square); Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1f</xref> shows 7 representative cases. Scatter plot of the grayscale values of JNK2 and p53 was utilized to reveal the regression relationship between p53 and JNK2 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2d</xref>). Linear regression analysis demonstrates that there is positive correlation between JNK2 and p53 in both tumors (R<sup>2</sup>=0.163, p=0.033, ANOVA) and normal tissues (R<sup>2</sup>=0.412, p=0.000, ANOVA).</p><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>JNK2 promotes p53 stability and apoptosis activity through phosphorylation of p53 at Thr81</title><p><bold>a.</bold> The p53 has consensus binding motif with JNK in different species. <bold>b.</bold> Western blotting detection of co-immunoprecipitated endogenous JNK2 and p53 proteins in T24 cells. <bold>c.</bold> Histogram shows changes of p53 mRNA between normal and tumor tissues, which are from human and rat bladder tissues respectively. <bold>d.</bold> Scatter plot of relative grayscale values of JNK2 and p53. Western blotting detected JNK2 and p53 proteins of tumor and paired adjacent normal tissues (ANTs) from 28 MIBC patients, then the grayscale values were measured. R<sup>2</sup> in tumors and ANTs are 0.163 (p=0.033, ANOVA) and 0.412 (p=0.000, ANOVA) respectively. <bold>e.</bold> Western Blotting shows JNK2, p53, phosphor-p53 and related apoptotic proteins in T24 cells. Cells were infected with lentivirus expressing indicated shRNAs for 48h, then transfected with indicated plasmids for 24h before harvest. <bold>f.</bold> Western blot analysis of indicated proteins in T24 cells 24 h after treated with or without 10 &#956;M SP600125.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-35119-g002"/></fig><p>Based on these results, we hypothesized that JNK2 may promote p53 stability and biological activity in bladder cancer. To test this hypothesis, we over-expressed JNK2 in T24 cells. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2e</xref>, western blotting revealed that p53 and phospho-p53-Thr81 were increased in JNK2-overexpressing cells (lane 4). The Bcl-2/Bax proteins play an important role in regulating cell apoptosis, and caspase-3, a major regulator of apoptosis, is activated by cleavage of procaspase-3 during apoptosis [<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2e</xref>, in JNK2 overexpressing cells, Bcl-2 protein levels decreased, while Bax increased. In consequence, cleaved caspase-3 was elevated (lane 4). On the other hand, when JNK2 was knocked down in T24 cells, total p53 and phospho-p53-Thr81 protein levels decreased, and the apoptosis pathway was inhibited (lanes 2 and 3). Moreover, the effect of JNK2 knockdown could be offset by overexpression of JNK2 (lanes 5 and 6). It is noteworthy that we detected only a very low signal of phospho-p53-Ser6 in these experiments. When phospho-JNK was inhibited by treating T24 cells with JNK inhibitor SP600125, total p53 and phospho-p53-Thr81 protein levels decreased, but phospho-p53-Ser6 was not detected (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2f</xref>). Our findings suggest that in bladder cancer, JNK2 promotes p53 stability and downstream apoptosis signaling through phosphorylation of p53 at Thr81 site rather than at Ser6 site.</p></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>JNK2 prevents p53 from MDM2-mediated degradation</title><p>MDM2-mediated ubiquitination of p53 is one of the most common mechanisms of p53 inactivation. MDM2 binding to p53 and subsequent proteasome-dependent p53 degradation are important steps in inducing p53 loss in cancer cells [<xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In our study, JNK2-overexpressing T24 cells exhibited lower levels of the immunoprecipitated MDM2-p53 complex than control cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3a</xref>). On the contrary, when T24 cells were treated with SP600125, a JNK inhibitor, p-JNK level decreased and MDM2-p53 complex increased (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3b</xref>). These results indicate that p-JNK2 can prevent MDM2 from binding to p53 to form complex.</p><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>JNK2 prevents p53 from mdm2 mediated degradation</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Western blot analysis of whole cell lysate (WCL) and co-IP samples of IgG or anti-MDM2 antibody obtained from T24 cells 24 h after transfected with indicated plasmids. <bold>b.</bold> Western blot analysis of WCL and co-IP samples of IgG or anti-MDM2 antibody obtained from T24 cells 24 h after treated with or without 10 &#956;M SP600125. <bold>c.</bold> Western blotting analysis of ubiquitin co-IP samples of anti-p53 antibody in T24 cells 24h after transfected with indicated plasmids. <bold>d.</bold> Western blotting analysis of ubiquitin co-IP samples of anti-p53 antibody in T24 cells 48h after transfected with indicated siRNAs. <bold>e.</bold> Western blotting analysis of ubiquitin co-IP samples of anti-p53 antibody in T24 cells 24h after treated with or without 10 &#956;M SP600125. <bold>f.</bold> Western blot analysis of WCL and co-IP samples of IgG or anti-Flag antibody obtained from T24 cells 24 h after transfected with indicated plasmids. The cells were treated with 20&#956;M MG132 for 6 hours before they were harvested. <bold>g.</bold> Western blotting analysis of ubiquitin co-IP samples of anti-Flag antibody in T24 cells 24h after transfected with indicated plasmids. The cells were treated with 20&#956;M MG132 for 6 hours before they were harvested.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-35119-g003"/></fig><p>As MDM2-p53 complex is a prerequisite for p53 proteasome-dependent degradation, we measured the levels of ubiquitin binding to p53 under different JNK2 conditions. The amount of ubiquitin binding to p53 was significantly decreased in JNK2-overexpressing T24 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3c</xref>). Furthermore, ubiquitin binding to p53 increased when JNK2 was suppressed by siJNK2 or SP600125 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3d</xref> and Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3e</xref>). These results indicate that JNK2 prevents p53 from MDM2-dependent ubiquitination by blocking the MDM2-p53 complex formation.</p><p>Since our results indicate that JNK2 promotes p53 stability through phosphorylation of p53 at Thr81 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2e, 2f</xref>), and that phosphatase treatment increases the MDM2-p53 interaction (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1">Supplementary Figure S3</xref>), we constructed a p53 Thr81Ala mutant to determine whether p53 phosphorylation at Thr81 is important for blocking the MDM2-p53 interaction. As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3f</xref>, p53 T81A mutant pulled more MDM2 comparing with p53 wild type (wt) control. Moreover, the amount of ubiquitin binding to p53 T81A was increased compared to p53 wt in T24 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3g</xref>). These results indicate that p53 phosphorylation at Thr81 is essential for blocking the p53-MDM2 interaction.</p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>Decreased expression of JNK2 confers resistance to cell death induced by mitomycin C</title><p>To determine the role of JNK2 in regulating resistance to mitomycin C (MMC)-induced cell death, we measured apoptosis in T24 cells with suppressed and over-expressed JNK2. Flow cytometry analysis demonstrated that the percentage of apoptotic and necrotic cells was significantly lower in control cells than in JNK2-overexpressed cells (p=0.000, chi-square). Furthermore, the combination of overexpression of JNK2 with mitomycin C synergistically induced cell death and resulted in higher percentage of apoptotic cells than control (p=0.000, chi-square) or MMC group (p=0.000, chi-square) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4a</xref>). On the contrary, JNK2 knockdown decreased apoptosis and necrosis compared to control (p=0.000, chi-square), and siJNK2 combined with mitomycin C resulted in even lower percentage of apoptotic cells than MMC alone (p=0.000, chi-square) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4b</xref>). Consistent with these results, cell proliferation MTS assay further demonstrated that combination of mitomycin C with JNK2 overexpression resulted in greater inhibitory effect on cell viability compared to mitomycin C alone (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4c</xref>). Moreover, JNK2-knockdown cells showed significantly higher viability than cells treated with mitomycin C (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4d</xref>). Collectively, these data suggest that decreased expression of JNK2 confers resistance to cell death induced by mitomycin C. To determine whether the JNK2 function in regulating mitomycin C resistance is p53-dependent, we knocked down p53 and measured cell viability. MTS assay demonstrated that the synergistic effect of JNK2 and mitomycin C was reversed by p53 suppression in 5637 cells (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4e</xref>). These data indicate that the resistance induced by JNK2 suppression is p53 dependent.</p><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Decreased expression of JNK2 confers resistance to cell death induced by MMC</title><p>(<bold>a.</bold> and <bold>b</bold>.) Flow cytometry (FCM) analysis of apoptotic and necrotic T24 cells. Cells were transfected with indicated plasmids (24h) or siRNAs (48h), then treated with or without 100ug/ml mitomycin C (MMC) for 12h before dual-stained by Annexin V-Alexa Fluor 488 and PI solution. Stained cell suspension was analyzed by FCM. *: p&lt;0.001 vs. control group; #: p&lt;0.001 vs. EV+MMC group. (<bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold>) MTS assay analysis of T24 cells proliferation. Cells were transfected with indicated plasmids (24h) or siRNAs (48h) before treated with or without 100ug/ml MMC for 12h followed by MTS assay. *: p&lt;0.05 vs. Group 1; #: p&lt;0.05 vs. Group 2; &amp;: p&lt;0.05 vs. Group 3. <bold>e.</bold> MTS assay analysis of 5637 cells proliferation. Cells were transfected with indicated plasmids (24h) or siRNAs (48h) before treated with 100ug/ml MMC for 12h followed by MTS assay. *: p&lt;0.05 vs. JNK2+si-P53+MMC group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-35119-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>Lower JNK2 expression is associated with worse clinical outcome in radical cystectomy patients</title><p>The characteristics of patients who underwent operations are shown in Tables <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. In patients who underwent radical cystectomy (RC), the mean overall survival time of lower JNK2 expression group was 42.7&#177;4.2months, which was markedly lower compared to the higher JNK2 expression group (58.6&#177;2.9months) (p=0.041, Log-rank test) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>). In patients who underwent transurethral resection of bladder tumor (TURBT), the mean recurrence-free survival time of the lower JNK2 expression group was 37.2&#177;4.2 months, which was lower than the higher JNK2 expression group (41.7&#177;2.6months); however, there was no statistical significance (p=0.182, Log-rank test) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>). Cox hazard regression analysis showed that the Hazard Ratio (HR) is 0.516 (95%CI: 0.303-0.930). These data indicate that lower expression of JNK2 is associated with worse clinical outcome in RC patients.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of patients who underwent RC</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><p>All patients who needed adjuvant chemotherapy or radiotherapy according to AUA guidelines completed these therapies.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Characteristics of patients who underwent TURBT</title></caption><table-wrap-foot><p>All patients completed intravesical instillation chemotherapy according to AUA guidelines.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Survival analysis for patients with different expression levels of JNK2</title><p><bold>a.</bold> Kaplan-Meier analysis of overall survival of patients underwent RC (Radical cystectomy) in different JNK2 conditions. <bold>b.</bold> Kaplan-Meier analysis of recurrence-free survival of patients underwent TURBT (Transurethral resection of bladder tumor) in different JNK2 conditions. HR=0.516 (95%CI: 0.303-0.930). <bold>c.</bold> A hypothetical model depicts that JNK2 serves as a tumor suppressor in bladder cancer, and that decreased JNK2 expression promotes bladder tumorigenesis.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="oncotarget-07-35119-g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>Our findings suggest that JNK2 serves as a tumor suppressor in bladder cancer, and that decreased JNK2 expression promotes bladder tumorigenesis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5c</xref>). JNK2 protects p53 from MDM2 mediated degradation through phosphorylation at Thr81. Cell death induced by MMC can be attenuated by downregulation of JNK2 in T24 cells. Additionally, we found that lower expression of JNK2 is associated with poorer overall survival among patients who underwent RC.</p><p>The role of JNK2 in tumors is still controversial. Studies suggest that the actions of JNK2 is pro-tumorigenic multiple myeloma, glioblastoma, epidermal neoplasia, lung cancer, and breast cancer [<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. However, in some lung and breast cancers, JNK2 appears to function as a tumor suppressor [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Our study demonstrates that JNK2 also serves as tumor suppressor in bladder cancer. The GEM data from our rat bladder cancer model suggest that <italic>MAPK9</italic> gene is down-regulated in rat bladder tumors as compared with normal bladder tissues, which is consistent with results from other human gene expression data sets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>, GSE13507; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.oncomine.org/">https://www.oncomine.org/</ext-link>, TCGA bladder, reporter: 05-179622439). How can JNK2 exert opposing effects, sometimes even within the same cancer type? Tumor stage-specific actions and different splice variants of JNK2 provide a partial explanation to this apparent paradox [<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. JNKs are frequently activated by stress stimuli, such as cytokines, ultraviolet irradiation, heat shock, and osmotic shock [<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Our orthotopic rat model of bladder cancer was induced by transurethral instillation of MNU, a carcinogenic stimulus, and the presence of carcinogenic chemicals in the urine is an important risk factor for human bladder cancer [<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. We therefore envision that bladder epithelial cells under stress require higher expression of JNK2 to stabilize p53, which can repair or remove impaired cells. As a result, JNK2 downregulation leads to bladder tumorigenesis.</p><p>P53 is maintained at low levels through ubiquitination and proteasomal degradation mediated mainly by the RING-finger type E3 ligase MDM2. MDM2 and p53 interact sequentially at several points of contact. A p53-binding domain in the N-terminus of MDM2 serves as a docking site for three residues in the N-terminus of p53: Phe19, Trp23 and Leu26 [<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. This high-affinity interaction leads to a conformational shift that permits the acidic domain of MDM2 to associate with the Box IV/V region of p53. This brings p53 into contact with RING domain of MDM2, leading to its ubiquitination [<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Our findings suggest that JNK2 phosphorylation of p53 at Thr81 blocks MDM2 binding, thus reducing p53 binding to ubiquitin and, ultimately, its degradation. Buschmann et al. identified Thr81 of p53 as a JNK phosphorylation site in 293T cells [<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. However, Oleinik et al. found that p53 is directly phosphorylated by JNK2 at Ser6 in lung cancer cells [<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], which is consistent with the idea that JNK2 plays different roles in different tumor types. The Thr81 phosphorylation site is not one of the N-terminus sites (Phe19, Trp23 and Leu26) or in the Box IV/V region (Ser261-Phe270) of p53. We therefore hypothesize that p53 phosphorylation at Thr81 by JNK2 produces a conformational shift that prevents p53 from binding to MDM2.</p><p>An important reason of poor clinical outcome in bladder cancer is that tumor cells become resistant to chemotherapy. In our experiments, downregulation of JNK2 inhibited p53-induced apoptotic signaling and conferred resistance to MMC-induced cell death in T24 cells. Moreover, in RC patients, overall survival time in the lower JNK2 group was significantly worse than that in the higher JNK2 group (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5a</xref>). In TURBT patients, recurrence-free survival time in the lower JNK2 group also tended to be lower than in the higher JNK2 group, though the difference was not statistically significant (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5b</xref>). Cox hazard regression analysis showed the HR to be 0.516 (95%CI: 0.303-0.930), implying a lower recurrence hazard in the higher JNK2 group. We should also note that in this set of TURBT patients, the overall JNK2 level was relatively high (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1e</xref>), which may lead to an indistinguishable difference in recurrence rates in small samples. To show the outstanding impact on clinical outcomes of decreasing JNK2, more cases and longer follow-up will be needed in our future studies.</p><p>In sum, our data demonstrate that JNK2 is a tumor suppressor in bladder cancer, and that JNK2 downregulation promotes bladder tumorigenesis (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5c</xref>). JNK2 protects p53 from MDM2-mediated degradation through phosphorylation at Thr81. Downregulation of JNK2 confers resistance to cell death induced by MMC in vitro, and lower expression of JNK2 is associated with poorer overall survival among patients who underwent RC. Collectively, our results suggest the JNK2 pathway could serve as an attractive target for therapeutic management of bladder cancer.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s4"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec id="s4_1"><title>Plasmids and reagents</title><p>The mammalian expression vectors for Flag-JNK2, Flag-p53-wt and HA-Ubiquitin were purchased from Addgene. Flag-p53-T81A was generated by site-specific mutagenesis (Stratagene). Antibodies used were anti-JNK2 (Abcam), anti-phospho-JNK (Abcam), anti-p53 (Abcam), anti-phospho-p53-Thr81 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-phospho-p53-Ser6 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-MDM2 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology), anti-Bcl2 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-Bcl2 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-Cleaved Caspase-3 (Cell Signaling Technology), anti-&#946;-actin (Sigma-Aldrich), anti-Flag (Sigma-Aldrich) and anti-HA (Covance). SP600125 and MG132 were purchased from Selleck Chemicals, and mitomycin C was purchased from Calbiochem.</p></sec><sec id="s4_2"><title>Cell lines, cell culture, and transfection</title><p>T24 and 5637 cells were purchased from the Shanghai Cellular Institute, Chinese Academy of Science, and incubated in RPMI-1640 (HyClone) medium containing 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) (Gibco) in a humidified chamber with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> at 37&#176;C. Transfections were performed by using Lipofectamine2000 (Invitrogen). Approximately 75&#8211;90% transfection efficiencies were routinely achieved.</p></sec><sec id="s4_3"><title>RNA interference</title><p>Non-specific control siRNA and siRNA for human JNK2 were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology. Cell transfection was performed following the manufacturer's instruction. Lentivirus-based control and gene-specific shRNAs were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Lois, MO).</p></sec><sec id="s4_4"><title>Immunoprecipitation (IP) and western blotting</title><p>For IP, cells were harvested and lysed in cell lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 1% Nonidet P-40, 0.5% sodium deoxycholate and 1% protease inhibitor cocktails, Sigma-Aldrich) using glass dounce homogenizer. Cell lysates were centrifuged and the supernatant was incubated with indicated antibodies and protein-G beads (Invitrogen) at 4&#176;C overnight. The beads were washed five times with cell lysis buffer and the precipitated proteins were subjected to further analysis. For western blotting, protein samples were prepared in modified RIPA buffer (1&#215;PBS, 1% NP-40, 0.1% SDS and 1% protease inhibitor cocktail). Equal amounts of protein (50 ~ 100 &#956;g) from cell lysates were denatured in sample buffer (Invitrogen), subjected to SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis, and transferred to nitrocellulose membranes (Bio-Rad). The membranes were immunoblotted with specific primary antibodies, horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibodies, and visualized by Super Signal West Pico Stable Peroxide Solution (Thermo Scientific).</p></sec><sec id="s4_5"><title>Ubiquitination assays</title><p>HA-ubiquitin was co-transfected with Flag-JNK2 or siJNK2 in T24 cells. The cells were treated with 20 &#956;M MG132 (Selleck) for 6 hours before they were harvested. Cell extracts were immunoprecipitated with anti-p53 antibody. The HA-ubiquitin-p53 complex was detected by immunoblotting with the anti-HA antibody.</p></sec><sec id="s4_6"><title>Cell proliferation assay (MTS)</title><p>Cell growth was monitored by absorbance using the MTS assay according to manufacturer's instructions (Promega). Briefly, cells were plated in 96-well plates at a density of 1,000 cells per well. At the indicated times, 20 &#956;l of CellTiter 96AQueous One Solution Reagent (Promega) was added to cells, and after 60-min incubation at 37&#176;C, cell growth was measured in a microplate reader at 490 nm.</p></sec><sec id="s4_7"><title>Apoptosis analysis</title><p>A Vybrant Apoptosis Kit (Invitrogen) was used to measure cell apoptosis as described previously [<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Briefly, 5 &#956;L of Alexa Fluor 488 Annexin V and 1 &#956;L of PI solution (100&#956;g/mL) were added to 100 &#956;L of cell suspension (10<sup>6</sup>cells/mL) and incubated for 15 min at room temperature. The stained cell suspension was analyzed by flow cytometry using FACSCalibur System (BD).</p></sec><sec id="s4_8"><title>Orthotopic rat model of bladder cancer</title><p>An orthotopic rat model of bladder cancer was established as described previously [<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Briefly, SD rats were intravesically instilled with 20 mg/ml MNU once per week for 10 weeks. The tumor growth in bladders was monitored by CT scanning, and the pathologic type was confirmed as bladder transitional cell carcinoma (BTCC) by H&amp;E staining.</p></sec><sec id="s4_9"><title>Gene expression microarray (GEM)</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using TRIZOL Reagent (Life technologies, Carlsbad, CA) from 3 normal and 3 tumor tissues from orthotopic rat bladder cancer model. RNA integrity was checked by an Agilent Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent technologies, Santa Clara, CA). Total RNA was amplified, labeled and purified by using GeneChip 3&#8242;IVT Express Kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA) to obtain biotin-labeled cRNA. Array hybridization and washings were performed using GeneChip Hybridization, Wash and Stain Kit (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA) in Hybridization Oven 645 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA) and Fluidics Station 450 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA). Slides were scanned by GeneChip Scanner 3000 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA) and Command Console Software 3.1 (Affymetrix, Santa Clara, CA) with default settings. Raw data were normalized by MAS 5.0 algorithm, Gene Spring Software 11.0 (Agilent technologies, Santa Clara, CA). Data obtained from these gene expression studies are deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/</ext-link>) with the GEO accession number GSE76702.</p></sec><sec id="s4_10"><title>Real time quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR)</title><p>Total RNA was isolated from tissues and cDNA was synthesized using the Super-Script kit from Invitrogen. Two-step real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) was performed using the SYBR Green Mix (BioRad) and iCycleriQTM detection system (Bio-Rad). Forward and reverse primers were used at a final concentration of 200 nM. The expression of <italic>GAPDH</italic> gene in each sample was used as an internal control. The primers for p53 were: Forward, 5&#8242;-ATG GAG GAG CCG CAG TCA GAT-3&#8242;; reverse, 5&#8242;-GCA GCG CCT CAC AAC CTC CGT C-3&#8242;.</p></sec><sec id="s4_11"><title>Human bladder tissue specimen and tissue microarray (TMA)</title><p>Forty-four BTCC patients who underwent radical cystectomy (RC) and 60 patients who underwent TURBT in Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine from January 2010 to December 2012 were enrolled in study. Patients with other malignant tumors or TURBT patients without following intravesical chemotherapy were excluded from the study. The tumor tissues and paired adjacent normal tissues (ANTs, 2 cm from tumor) from total of 44 RC patients were analyzed by tissue microarray (TMA) by Outdo biotechnology, Shanghai, China.</p><p>In addition, tumor tissues and paired ANTs were obtained from 28 patients who underwent RC from November 2014 to September 2015 in the same hospital. All 28 patients were diagnosed as MIBC by pathology. The tissues were stored in&#8722;80&#176;C for later analyses by western blotting and real time qRT-PCR.</p><p>The protocols were approved by the Ethics Committee of Xinhua Hospital, Shanghai Jiao Tong University School of Medicine.</p></sec><sec id="s4_12"><title>Immunohistochemistry (IHC) and staining scoring</title><p>Tissue slides were deparaffinized through xylene and hydrated by graded alcohols after incubation at 60&#176;C for 1 hour. Antigen retrieval by heat mediation was performed with Antigen Unmasking Solution (Vector Labs). The slides were incubated with JNK2 rabbit monoclonal antibody diluted 1:200 (Abcam) at 4&#176;C overnight, followed by incubation with a peroxidase-conjugated goat anti-rabbit IgG (Alexa Fluor, Life technologies). The slides were visualized with Vectastain ABC kit (Vector Labs) and counterstained with hematoxylin. Control sections were incubated without the primary antibody. Staining intensity was graded/scored in a blinded fashion: 0 = no staining at 100&#215; magnification; 1 = weak staining at 100&#215; magnification, but little or no staining at 40&#215;magnification; 2 = medium staining at 40&#215;magnification; 3 = strong staining at 40&#215;magnification. Staining percentage was also graded/scored in a blinded fashion: 1 = positive area less than 25% of the whole tissue; 2 = positive area less than 50% of the whole tissue but more than 25%; 3 = positive area less than 75% of the whole tissue but more than 50%; 4 = positive area more than 75% of the whole tissue. Staining index (SI) was obtained by multiplying values of staining percentage and intensity.</p></sec><sec id="s4_13"><title>Patients and survival analysis</title><p>Forty-four RC patients and 60 TURBT patients mentioned above were followed up from January 2010 to April 2015. Overall survival times and recurrence-free survival times were obtained. The patients were divided into 2 groups according to SI of JNK2 IHC. The SI of lower JNK2 expression group is from 0 to 5, and higher group is from 6 to 12. Log-rank test was applied and 95% confidence intervals were determined. Data were analyzed using GraphPad Prism 5.</p></sec><sec id="s4_14"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All experiments were done in triplicates. The chi-square test was used to compare the rates among groups. Descriptive results of continuous variables were expressed as mean &#177; standard deviation and assessed by Student's t test or 1-way ANOVA. The Kaplan-Meier method was used to calculate time dependent outcomes and differences were reassessed with the log rank statistic. Statistical significance was set as p&lt;0.05. Analyses were performed with SPSS19.0.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>SUPPLEMENTARY FIGURES</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="oncotarget-07-35119-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e1026" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This work was supported in part by grants from the National Natural Science Foundation of China (81101931 to C.W.P.) and Project of Science and Technology Commission of Shanghai Municipality (12140901202 to J.Q).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>CONFLICTS OF INTEREST</bold></p><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p>Pan and Qi had full access to all the data in the study and take responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis.</p><p>Study concept and design: Pan.</p><p>Acquisition of data: Pan, Liu, Zhao and Qian.</p><p>Analysis and interpretation of data: Pan, Liu and Zhao.</p><p>Drafting of the manuscript: Pan and Liu.</p><p>Critical revision of the manuscript: Pan and Qian.</p><p>Statistical analysis: Liu and Wang.</p><p>Supervision: Pan and Qi.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torre</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bray</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferlay</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lortet-Tieulent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jemal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global cancer statistics, 2012</article-title><source>CA Cancer J Clin</source><year>2015</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>87</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25651787</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knowles</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hurst</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular biology of bladder cancer: new insights into pathogenesis and clinical diversity</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2015</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25533674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soloway</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bladder cancer: Lack of progress in bladder cancer--what are the obstacles?</article-title><source>Nat Rev Urol</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23165404</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bubici</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JNK signalling in cancer: in need of new, smarter therapeutic targets</article-title><source>Br J Pharmacol</source><year>2014</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24117156</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bogoyevitch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uses for JNK: the many and varied substrates of the c-Jun N-terminal kinases</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>2006</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1095</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17158707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogata</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishigaki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Broide</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tobacco smoke promotes lung tumorigenesis by triggering IKKbeta- and JNK1-dependent inflammation</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2010</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20129250</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Beezhold</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Castranova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JNK1 activation predicts the prognostic outcome of the human hepatocellular carcinoma</article-title><source>Mol Cancer</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>64</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19686584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>She</surname><given-names>QB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name><name><surname>Bode</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of skin tumorigenesis in c-Jun NH(2)-terminal kinase-2-deficient mice</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>3908</fpage><lpage>3912</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11358804</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barbarulo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Iansante</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaidos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Naresh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahemtulla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Franzoso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Karadimitris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haskard</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bubici</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase family member 14 (PARP14) is a novel effector of the JNK2-dependent pro-survival signal in multiple myeloma</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>4231</fpage><lpage>4242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23045269</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Dockendorff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariadason</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Augenlicht</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase 1 plays a critical role in intestinal homeostasis and tumor suppression</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2007</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17591974</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Neal</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebelt</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nasrazadani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandenbroek</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Heasley</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Berg</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Jnk2 effects on tumor development, genetic instability and replicative stress in an oncogene-driven mouse mammary tumor model</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e10443</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20454618</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p53 Research: the past thirty years and the next thirty years</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>a000893</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20463001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vousden</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Prives</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Blinded by the Light: The Growing Complexity of p53</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2009</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>431</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19410540</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malats</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bustos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Puente</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kogevinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Real</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>P53 as a prognostic marker for bladder cancer: a meta-analysis and review</article-title><source>Lancet Oncol</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>678</fpage><lpage>686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16129368</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell adhesion to fibronectin induces mitomycin C resistance in bladder cancer cells</article-title><source>BJU Int</source><year>2009</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1774</fpage><lpage>1779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19624598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>ZJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishment and CT diagnosis of orthotopic rat model of bladder cancer</article-title><source>Acta Laboratorium Animalis Scientia Sinica</source><year>2010</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>ZG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Um</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear and cytoplasmic p53 suppress cell invasion by inhibiting respiratory complex-I activity via Bcl-2 family proteins</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2014</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>8452</fpage><lpage>8465</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.2320</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meek</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of the p53 response and its relationship to cancer</article-title><source>Biochem J</source><year>2015</year><volume>469</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26205489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Harshyne</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Holgado-Madruga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>c-Jun NH(2)-terminal kinase 2alpha2 promotes the tumorigenicity of human glioblastoma cells</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>10024</fpage><lpage>10031</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17047065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Coloff</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Leshin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Miliani de Marval</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathmell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase 2 plays a dominant role in human epidermal neoplasia</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>3080</fpage><lpage>3088</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20354187</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nitta</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Vecchio</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Godwin</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the c-Jun N-terminal kinase 2-alpha-isoform in non-small cell lung carcinoma tumorigenesis</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2011</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20871632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cantrell</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebelt</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfefferle</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perou</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Den Berg</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>c-Jun N-terminal kinase 2 prevents luminal cell commitment in normal mammary glands and tumors by inhibiting p53/Notch1 and breast cancer gene 1 expression</article-title><source>Oncotarget</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>11863</fpage><lpage>11881</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.3787</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25970777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oleinik</surname><given-names>NV</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupenko</surname><given-names>NI</given-names></name><name><surname>Krupenko</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cooperation between JNK1 and JNK2 in activation of p53 apoptotic pathway</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2007</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>7222</fpage><lpage>7230</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17525747</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cellurale</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weston</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Reilly</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garlick</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerry</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluss</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of JNK in a Trp53-dependent mouse model of breast cancer</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2010</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>e12469</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20814571</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stress-activated protein kinases-tumor suppressors or tumor initiators?</article-title><source>Semin Cancer Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15219620</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Heasley</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential gene regulation by specific gain-of-function JNK1 proteins expressed in Swiss 3T3 fibroblasts</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2002</year><volume>277</volume><fpage>47167</fpage><lpage>47174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354774</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raciti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotti</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Valia</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulcinelli</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Renzo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>JNK2 is activated during ER stress and promotes cell survival</article-title><source>Cell Death Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e429</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23171849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Catto</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalbagni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Herr</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakiewicz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kassouf</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiemeney</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>La Vecchia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shariat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epidemiology and risk factors of urothelial bladder cancer</article-title><source>Eur Urol</source><year>2013</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22877502</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kussie</surname><given-names>PH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorina</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marechal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Elenbaas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Levine</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavletich</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Structure of the MDM2 oncoprotein bound to the p53 tumor suppressor transactivation domain</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>948</fpage><lpage>953</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8875929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Worrall</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pettersson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hupp</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dual-site regulation of MDM2 E3-ubiquitin ligase activity</article-title><source>Mol Cell</source><year>2006</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>251</fpage><lpage>263</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16857591</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buschmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Potapova</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Shira</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Fried</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Minamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Alarcon-Vargas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pincus</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaarde</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holbrook</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiloh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Jun NH2-terminal kinase phosphorylation of p53 on Thr-81 is important for p53 stabilization and transcriptional activities in response to stress</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>2743</fpage><lpage>2754</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283254</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>