<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virus Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Virus Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">vevolu</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">vevolu</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Virus Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2057-1577</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6167919</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ve/vew017</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">vew017</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Islands of linkage in an ocean of pervasive recombination reveals two-speed
evolution of human cytomegalovirus genomes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lassalle</surname><given-names>Florent</given-names></name><author-comment><title>#</title><p>The authors are joint authors and contributed equally to this contribution</p></author-comment><author-comment><title>&#8224;</title><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8957-2520">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8957-2520</ext-link>
</p></author-comment><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="vew017-cor1">*</xref><!--<email>florent.lassalle@ucl.ac.uk</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Depledge</surname><given-names>Daniel P.</given-names></name><author-comment><title>#</title><p>The authors are joint authors and contributed equally to this contribution</p></author-comment><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="vew017-cor1">*</xref><!--<email>florent.lassalle@ucl.ac.uk</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>Matthew B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Amanda C.</given-names></name><author-comment><title>&#167;</title><p>Current address: Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Cornell University,
Ithaca, NY 14853, USA</p></author-comment><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>Mette T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tutill</surname><given-names>Helena J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Rachel J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Einer-Jensen</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Holdstock</surname><given-names>Jolyon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>Claire</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>Julianne R.</given-names></name><author-comment><title>&#8225;</title><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4681-9586">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4681-9586</ext-link>
</p></author-comment><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Loenen</surname><given-names>Freek B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Duncan A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Griffiths</surname><given-names>Paul D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Verjans</surname><given-names>Georges M.G.M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schutten</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>Richard S.B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Balloux</surname><given-names>Francois</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Breuer</surname><given-names>Judith</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="vew017-aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="vew017-aff1">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>UCL Genetics Institute, University College London, London, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="vew017-aff2">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>Division of Infection and Immunity, University College London, London, United
Kingdom</aff><aff id="vew017-aff3">
<label><sup>3</sup></label>Oxford Gene Technology, Begbroke, Oxfordshire, UK</aff><aff id="vew017-aff4">
<label><sup>4</sup></label>QIAGEN-AAR, Aarhus, Denmark</aff><aff id="vew017-aff5">
<label><sup>5</sup></label>Department of Virology, Royal Free Hospital, London, United Kingdom</aff><aff id="vew017-aff6">
<label><sup>6</sup></label>Microbiology, Virology and Infection Prevention and Control, Camelia Botnar
Laboratories, Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children NHS Foundation Trust, London, United
Kingdom</aff><aff id="vew017-aff7">
<label><sup>7</sup></label>Department of Viroscience, Erasmus, MC Rotterdam, the Netherlands</aff><aff id="vew017-aff8">
<label><sup>8</sup></label>Department of Virology, Barts Health NHS Trust, London, United Kingdom</aff><author-notes><fn id="vew017-FM1"><label>&#167;</label><p>Current address: Department of Microbiology and Immunology, Cornell University, Ithaca,
NY 14853, USA</p></fn><fn id="vew017-FM2"><label>#</label><p>The authors are joint authors and contributed equally to this contribution</p></fn><corresp id="vew017-cor1">*Corresponding author: E-mail:
<email>florent.lassalle@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="vew017-FM3"><label>&#8224;</label><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8957-2520">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8957-2520</ext-link>
</p></fn><fn id="vew017-FM4"><label>&#8225;</label><p>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4681-9586">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-4681-9586</ext-link>
</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2016-06-15"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>2</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>vew017</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University
Press.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative
Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted
reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="vew017.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) infects most of the population worldwide, persisting
throughout the host's life in a latent state with periodic episodes of reactivation. While
typically asymptomatic, HCMV can cause fatal disease among congenitally infected infants
and immunocompromised patients. These clinical issues are compounded by the emergence of
antiviral resistance and the absence of an effective vaccine, the development of which is
likely complicated by the numerous immune evasins encoded by HCMV to counter the host's
adaptive immune responses, a feature that facilitates frequent super-infections.
Understanding the evolutionary dynamics of HCMV is essential for the development of
effective new drugs and vaccines. By comparing viral genomes from uncultivated or
low-passaged clinical samples of diverse origins, we observe evidence of frequent
homologous recombination events, both recent and ancient, and no structure of HCMV genetic
diversity at the whole-genome scale. Analysis of individual gene-scale loci reveals a
striking dichotomy: while most of the genome is highly conserved, recombines essentially
freely and has evolved under purifying selection, 21 genes display extreme diversity,
structured into distinct genotypes that do not recombine with each other. Most of these
hyper-variable genes encode glycoproteins involved in cell entry or escape of host
immunity. Evidence that half of them have diverged through episodes of intense positive
selection suggests that rapid evolution of hyper-variable loci is likely driven by
interactions with host immunity. It appears that this process is enabled by recombination
unlinking hyper-variable loci from strongly constrained neighboring sites. It is
conceivable that viral mechanisms facilitating super-infection have evolved to promote
recombination between diverged genotypes, allowing the virus to continuously diversify at
key loci to escape immune detection, while maintaining a genome optimally adapted to its
asymptomatic infectious lifecycle.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>CMV</kwd><kwd>recombination</kwd><kwd>immune evasion</kwd><kwd>viral evolution</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>1. Introduction</title><p>Cytomegalovirus (CMV) species are widespread among mammals, establishing life-long
infections in their specific host. Human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) has a linear dsDNA genome of
approximately 235 kb encoding at least 165 canonical ORFs (<xref rid="vew017-B16" ref-type="bibr">Dolan et al. 2004</xref>), plus many alternative transcripts and
pervasive translation outside these annotated ORFs revealed by recent expression analyses
(<xref rid="vew017-B40" ref-type="bibr">Murphy et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B68" ref-type="bibr">Stern-Ginossar et al. 2012</xref>). The genome of HCMV consists of two
domains (L and S), each comprising a unique region (U<sub>L</sub> and U<sub>S</sub>) flanked
by an inverted repeat sequence (TR<sub>L</sub> and IR<sub>L</sub>, TR<sub>S</sub> and
IR<sub>S</sub>), yielding the genome configuration
TR<sub>L</sub>&#8211;U<sub>L</sub>&#8211;IR<sub>L</sub>&#8211;IR<sub>S</sub>&#8211;U<sub>S</sub>&#8211;TR<sub>S</sub>.
While primary infection of healthy individuals is common but usually asymptomatic, HCMV
infections of severely immune-suppressed individuals (e.g. HIV-infected and transplant
patients) cause significant morbidity and mortality (<xref rid="vew017-B56" ref-type="bibr">Rubin 1989</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B64" ref-type="bibr">Snydman 1990</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B34" ref-type="bibr">Krause et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B38" ref-type="bibr">Manicklal et al. 2013</xref>). Additionally, trans-placental
transmissions of HCMV are the commonest viral cause of severe birth defects in infants
(<xref rid="vew017-B55" ref-type="bibr">Ross et al. 2006</xref>). These problems are
compounded by growing antiviral resistance and the lack of an effective vaccine (<xref rid="vew017-B34" ref-type="bibr">Krause et al. 2013</xref>) and there remains an unmet
need for data on viral diversity and HCMV evolution to facilitate the development of new
intervention strategies to prevent and/or counteract HCMV pathology. Very recently, the high
frequency of recombination at the genome-wide level has been observed (<xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. 2015</xref>). This sheds new light on the understanding of
HCMV evolution, in particular regarding recent studies where rapid fixation of novel point
mutations was thought to be the main mechanism for intra-host diversification (<xref rid="vew017-B51" ref-type="bibr">Renzette et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B52" ref-type="bibr">Renzette et al. 2013</xref>). However, estimation of the local
recombination intensity along the genome is subject to biases when other evolutionary
factors vary, and methodological issues may account for some patterns reported by <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. (2015)</xref>.</p><p>Here, we explored the landscape of recombination across HCMV genomes and its relation to
selective constraints. We used a diverse dataset of genomes recovered from unrelated
clinical samples collected in the UK, the Netherlands, Germany, Belgium, Italy, the USA and
South Korea for which whole genome sequences were previously published (<xref rid="vew017-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B9" ref-type="bibr">Cunningham et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B11" ref-type="bibr">Dargan et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B29" ref-type="bibr">Jung et al.
2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B59" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. 2015</xref>), in addition to 16 new HCMV
genomes sequences obtained directly from clinical samples. Our results confirm that
extensive recombination affects HCMV genomes to the extent that the majority of sites in the
genome are unlinked. In addition, we show that there are exceptions to this pattern of free
recombination within several loci that are deeply divergent between strains and in high
linkage disequilibrium (LD). The largest of these linked hypervariable loci spans the RL11
region, which encodes glycoproteins with multiple functions related to immunity and tropism.
The rapid evolution of this locus, both within HCMV and between primate CMV species,
suggests an important role for these genes in CMV genome adaptation to their host. Taken
together, these patterns support the idea of homologous recombination being a major force in
the evolution of HCMV.</p></sec><sec><title>2. Materials and methods</title><sec><title>2.1. Sample collection and sequencing</title><p>Twenty-five samples were collected from various hospitals in London, UK (detailed in
<xref rid="vew017-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) from a population reflecting the
highly heterogeneous ethnic and geographical origin of London's population. Samples were
collected from a mixture of congenitally infected infants as well as children and adults
with either competent or suppressed immune statuses with varying HCMV loads. The sample
collection included two sets of paired samples (whole blood and bile/whole blood and a
solid tissue biopsy) from different body compartments and three sets of longitudinally
collected samples from either whole blood or plasma (<xref rid="vew017-T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). DNA was extracted using the QIAamp DNA Mini Kit
(QIAGEN) according to the instructions of the manufacturer and quality assured using the
Qubit and Tapestation systems. Viral loads were determined for each sample using a
diagnostic qPCR assay as follows. A 15 &#181;L mastermix (12.5 &#181;L of QuantiFast Multiplex
PCR&#8201;+R and 2.5 &#181;L of Primer/Probe mix) was combined with 10 &#181;L of extracted DNA. Initial
denaturation was at 95 &#176;C for 5&#8201;min followed by 45 cycles of denaturation (95 &#176;C for 30 s)
and annealing/extension (60 &#176;C for 30 s). Forward (GCATGCGC&#160;GAGTGTCAAGAC) and reverse
(GTTACTTT&#160;GAGCGCCATCTGT&#160;TCCT) primers were used at a final reaction concentration of
0.6&#8201;pmol/&#181;L while the probe (TGCGCCGTATGCTGCTCGACA, reporter&#8201;=&#8201;JOE, quencher&#8201;=&#8201;BHQ1) was
used at a final concentration of 0.4&#8201;pmol/&#181;L. All reactions were run in triplicate on an
Applied Biosystems 7500 Fast Real-Time PCR System using six standards ranging from 500
copies/mL to 20,000,000 copies/mL. </p><table-wrap id="vew017-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p> List of genomes sequences used in the present study and associated metadata</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="vew017-TF1"><p>pass, passage.</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF2"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Longitudinal sampling (3 timepoints).</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF3"><p>
<sup>b</sup>Simultaneous sampling of two bodycompartments.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The 120-mer RNA baits spanning the length of the positive strand of 15 whole and 44
partial HCMV genome sequences (as obtained from GenBank in July 2013) were designed by
tiling (at 12&#215;) along each genome and subsequently filtering to ensure even representation
of distinct bait sequences across any given genome. Both actions were performed using
in-house PERL scripts developed by the PATHSEEK consortium. The specificity of the baits
was verified by BLASTn searches against the Human Genomic&#8201;+&#8201;Transcript database. The
custom designed HCMV bait library was uploaded to SureDesign and synthesized by Agilent
Technologies (San Diego, USA). Following library preparation and enrichment for HCMV DNA
by hybridization using the SureSelect XT v1.5 protocol (200 ng starting material),
modified only to increase the post-hybridization PCR yield where viral loads were low,
deep sequencing using an Illumina MiSeq (500&#8201;bp v2 kits) was performed yielding millions
of 2&#215;250 bp paired-end reads. Paired-end reads were trimmed and mapped by local assembly
against a database of all full or partially sequenced HCMV genomes available in GenBank.
Several isolates of HCMV have been previously sequenced for their whole genome and the
presence of hypervariable regions within the HCMV genome are well documented (<xref rid="vew017-B37" ref-type="bibr">Lurain et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B50" ref-type="bibr">Rasmussen et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B23" ref-type="bibr">Garrigue et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al.
2009</xref>), which led us to use a <italic>de novo</italic> approach to read assembly
(<xref rid="vew017-B9" ref-type="bibr">Cunningham et al. 2010</xref>). Thus, all HCMV
mapping read pairs were extracted and assembled into two <italic>de novo</italic> contigs
forming the U<sub>L</sub> and U<sub>S</sub> sequences. Accurate assembly of the repeated
regions (TR<sub>L</sub>, IR<sub>L</sub>, IR<sub>S</sub>, and TR<sub>S</sub>) could not be
performed with short read data while insufficient material was available to obtain this
sequence by other methods. A positive correlation was observed between the input viral
load and the percentage of HCMV mapping reads (On Target Reads percent (OTR percent)),
which was maintained until saturation i.e. the point at which the number of unique RNA
baits is less than the total number of HCMV genome copies present in the hybridization
reactions.</p></sec><sec><title>2.2. Consensus sequence analyses</title><p>Consensus sequences comprising the U<sub>L</sub> and U<sub>S</sub> regions for each
sample were generated using a minimum read depth of 35 reads per base with low coverage
regions coded as ambiguities (Ns). All consensus sequences were aligned against all
available low/un-passaged (&#8804;&#8201;3 passages) HCMV genome sequences in GenBank using the
program Mafft, v7 (<xref rid="vew017-B30" ref-type="bibr">Katoh and Standley 2013</xref>).
The alignment was subsequently inspected by hand to correct sequence alignments in the
hypervariable regions. Nucleotide diversity estimates were obtained with in-house R
scripts using the 'ape' package (<xref rid="vew017-B46" ref-type="bibr">Paradis et al.
2004</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B49" ref-type="bibr">Popescu et al. 2012</xref>).
Phylogenetic network analysis were performed using SplitsTree4 (<xref rid="vew017-B27" ref-type="bibr">Huson and Bryant 2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.3. Gene phylogenies</title><p>Newly sequenced genomes were annotated with RATT (Rapid Annotation Transfer Tool, version
18) (<xref rid="vew017-B45" ref-type="bibr">Otto et al. 2011</xref>) in reference to the
annotation of reference strain Merlin (GenBank AY446894.2) with a 'Species' transfer
setting, and were cross-checked with an analogous annotation using strain AD169 (GenBank
FJ527563) as a reference, allowing the recovery of genes missing from the Merlin reference
sequence, notably UL128. Coding sequence (CDS) alignments were obtained by first aligning
the encoded protein sequences with ClustalOmega (<xref rid="vew017-B58" ref-type="bibr">Sievers et al. 2011</xref>) (version 1.2.1, default parameters) and then
reverse-translated to CDSs with pal2nal (<xref rid="vew017-B69" ref-type="bibr">Suyama et
al. 2006</xref>) (version 14), using Python scripts though the interface provided by
BioPython modules (version 1.63) (<xref rid="vew017-B8" ref-type="bibr">Cock et al.
2009</xref>) and finally hand-corrected for incongruent alignments in repetitive regions
using the SEAVIEW program (<xref rid="vew017-B24" ref-type="bibr">Gouy et al.
2010</xref>). Alignments of genes <italic>RL12</italic>, <italic>UL50</italic>,
<italic>UL146</italic>, and <italic>IRS1</italic> were discarded because most sites in
gene sequences were not homologous. Alignments were subsequently scanned for within-gene
recombination breakpoints using the GARD algorithm from the HyPhy package (<xref rid="vew017-B32" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky Pond et al. 2006a</xref>, <xref rid="vew017-B33" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>), and the alignment was split according to
significant breakpoints. Contrary to LD analysis, GARD screen does not have a site-scale
resolution since it relies on regional signals to detect significant disagreement of the
phylogenetic signals found on each side of the breakpoints (phylogeny reconstructed under
the HKY85 substitution model, rejection of common history based on a Kishino&#8211;Hasegawa
test, <italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05) (<xref rid="vew017-B32" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky
Pond et al. 2006</xref>). However, it permitted us to ascertain that, in each (part of
a) gene, any phylogenetic signal that is found with strong support is stemming from a
unique vertical history. The 202 alignments obtained for each gene or gene part resulting
from GARD analysis (hereafter simply called genes) were used for a Bayesian phylogenetic
analysis using MrBayes (version 3.2.2) (<xref rid="vew017-B54" ref-type="bibr">Ronquist
and Huelsenbeck 2003</xref>) under a GTR&#8201;+&#8201;I&#8201;+&#8201;4&#915; nucleotide substitution model and
default parameters (notably two independent runs of four chains over 1,000,000
generations, including 250,000 discarded as burn-in and then sampling of trees every 500
generations).</p><p>We took advantage of the recent study by <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons
et al. (2015</xref>) and the resource of gene alignments they provided to extend our
dataset by merging Sijmons et al.'s gene alignments with those produced in the present
study (split at the same recombination breakpoints as determined previously), using
MAFFT--merge option (<xref rid="vew017-B30" ref-type="bibr">Katoh and Standley
2013</xref>). This resulted in a set of 181 alignments with at most 142 sequences (some
genes being missing in certain strains) which we used to replicate all downstream
analysis, exception made of the BranchSiteREL positive selection scan (see below). In that
case, the smaller dataset is sufficiently representative of the species' diversity to
cover all major deep splits, whereas the larger number of branches per tree in the
extended dataset (ca. 300) would have unnecessarily lowered the power of the branch-wise
test. For both datasets, lists of covered loci, their alignments and gene trees are
available on TreeBASE server at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S18391">http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S18391</ext-link>.</p><p>To compare phylogenetic histories of different gene loci, the diversity of phylogenetic
signals recorded in HCMV genomes was explored by building a matrix of posterior
probability (PP) supports of tree bipartitions observed in each gene's MCMC sample of
trees (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).
Linkage between neighboring genes was identified as tracks of genes with shared high PP
for the same bipartition(s). This method enables the recognition of similar clusters of
strains along the genome, signing their recent history of common descent. In particular
this approach does not require that all sequences share the history of descent across loci
(i.e. that gene tree topologies are completely matching) and hence allows identification
of haplotypes shared by a group of strains where other strains are recombining. A similar
matrix can be obtained for the compatibility score of bipartitions with the gene
alignment, defined as one minus the maximal PP support observed for any bipartition that
is topologically exclusive (incompatible) with the bipartition of interest (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>). The latter
approach allows a more sensitive scan for shared histories among genes as it detects
non-exclusive signals from non-fully resolved parts of trees, and, at the same time, it
can reveal gene alignments in which no signal is contained as they will not reject many or
all possible bipartitions (vertical blue smears in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>).</p><sec><title>2.3.1. Recombination and LD analyses</title><p>To perform an LD scan at the genomic scale, a 238,390-bp alignment of the 42 genomes
dataset (excluding the TR<sub>L</sub>, IR<sub>L</sub>, IR<sub>S</sub>, and
TR<sub>S</sub> regions) was restricted to its 22,159 bi-allelic positions having at
most one missing sequence. LD scans were performed using in-house R scripts making use
of the 'ape' package (<xref rid="vew017-B46" ref-type="bibr">Paradis et al. 2004</xref>;
<xref rid="vew017-B49" ref-type="bibr">Popescu et al. 2012</xref>). Significance of LD
was tested using Fisher's exact test on the 2&#215;2 contingency table of counts of possible
allele pairs. First, we searched the all-versus-all biallelic site matrix for
significant associations at <italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05, using the Bonferroni
correction for multiple testing. Then, to detect short domains resilient to
recombination, a sliding window scan was conducted to detect local peaks of LD (windows
of 20 bi-allelic sites with a sliding step of 5 sites). The &#8722;log10 transform of Fisher's
test <italic>P</italic> values [&#8722;log10(<italic>P</italic><sub>LDFisher</sub>)] from a
window were compared to the distribution of
&#8722;log10(<italic>P</italic><sub>LDFisher</sub>) for the genome-wide set of comparisons
made in this range (i.e. within the diagonal ribbon of the square matrix of
all-versus-all sites LD tests, sampled with a quantile function to get a representative
sample of the same size than the window's) using a Mann&#8211;Whitney&#8211;Wilcoxon U test
(single-tailed test with alternative hypothesis of local LD greater than the
background). The reported local LD index is defined as &#8722;log
10(<italic>P</italic><sub>Wilcox</sub>), with <italic>P</italic><sub>Wilcox</sub> the
<italic>P</italic> value of the Mann&#8211;Whitney&#8211;Wilcoxon U test. Using windows of 20
successive bi-allelic sites spreading over variable physical distances (window sizes
ranged from 24 bp to 3,376 bp), we observed that the density of bi-allelic SNPs was
strongly correlated to the power of the test (Pearson's correlation,
<italic>r&#8201;</italic>=<italic>&#8201;</italic>0.56,
<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>16</sup>). Because the physical spacing of
sites impacts directly the expected linkage between them, we modified the scan so that
bi-allelic SNP density is constant and cannot bias our measure of LD: we used windows of
fixed physical size in which a constant number of 20 bi-allelic sites were sub-sampled
so that their spacing is the closest possible to uniformity. We chose a window size of
700 bp as a trade-off between resolution and coverage of the genome (95 percent of
windows encompassed at least 20 sites) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.3.2. Simulation studies</title><p>To validate the properties of the local LD index, and notably to investigate its
dependence on nucleotidic diversity, we performed simulations of genome evolution using
the software ALF (<xref rid="vew017-B10" ref-type="bibr">Dalquen et al. 2012</xref>). We
generated synthetic genomes where nucleotidic diversity is homogeneous, but population
structure and recombination rate varies among loci. On one hand, 21 background loci of
&#8764;500 bp were simulated following trees that have no strong clonal structure and
underwent homologous recombination during evolution, with different histories of
orthologous replacement events in each of their five &#8764;100-bp partitions; this yielded a
background of mosaic phylogenetic history marked by recombination (expected to induce
strong homoplasy signatures). On the other hand, three interspersed foreground loci of
size &#8764;500 bp were simulated following trees that show strong clonal structure (i.e.
tight clusters of strains at the tip of long internal branches, expected to induce
strong LD patterns) and did not undergo recombination during evolution. The resulting
simulated genomes of size &#8764;12,000 bp thus meet the conditions for local LD test to be
applied &#8211; searching for relatively rare local hotspots of high LD in a background of
little or no LD &#8211; without the confounding effect of covarying nucleotidic diversity. To
ensure that the simulation conditions were the closest to the real conditions of our
HCMV dataset, gene trees from the 42-genome HCMV dataset were used as guides to the
simulation, yielding alignments reflecting population structure that vary in a way
comparable to the HCMV dataset. All loci evolved under the same evolution model
(CodonPAM) with trees of similar sizes, producing a homogeneously distributed range of
nucleotidic diversity values (ranging 0.07&#8211;0.23), allowing us to see the potential
covariation of factors under a range of parameter combinations (low/strong diversity
with low/strong population structure). Parameter files and guides trees are available in
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File S1</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>2.3.3. Population structure</title><p>The 42-strain genome-wide alignment of bi-alleic SNPs described above was used to
perform a PCA on the covariance matrix of bi-allelic genotypes. The latter analyses was
repeated after further restricting the dataset to the 5,669 bi-allelic positions having
at most one missing sequence and a minimum of 3 counts for the minor allele, to focus on
the variation of ancient polymorphisms. To remove the effect of the strong linkage in
the RL10&#8211;UL13 region in structuring the signal from the whole genome, we recomputed both
phylogenetic networks and PCA separately for the whole-genome alignment restricted to
the RL10&#8211;UL13 region (positions 8,600&#8211;21,100 in Merlin coordinates, 2,347 bi-allelic
sites and 812 bi-allelic sites with a minimum of 3 counts for the minor allele,
respectively) and for the remainder of the genome. The R code used for these analyses is
available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/flass/genomescans/">https://github.com/flass/genomescans/</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>2.4. Genotype classification</title><p>To characterize the extent of intergenic linkage when considering all strains together,
we categorized strains into genotypes for each gene locus, using an iterative approach
based on the variance of branch lengths for recognizing the relatively long branches in a
gene tree. Clades in midpoint-rooted Bayesian gene trees were systematically evaluated
from the smallest (skipping those made of less than five tips) to the most inclusive ones:
the variance <italic>Vc</italic> of all branch lengths in the clade's subtree were
computed, and then compared to the variance <italic>Vp</italic> computed when adding the
parent branch; if <italic>V</italic>p&#8201;&gt;&#8201;2 &#183; <italic>V</italic>c and the parent's branch
length was greater than the mean branch length in the subtree and the parent branch had a
minimum PP support of 0.8, the parent branch was pruned from the gene tree. Similarly,
each branch within the clade was systematically singled out to test if it increased the
variance of the subtree's branch lengths, and if so was pruned accordingly. This step was
repeated after pruning until no evaluated branch was to prune in the evaluated clade, then
higher clades were explored, until reaching the root of the gene tree. This procedure
yielded for each gene tree a forest of subtrees, which defined clusters of strains, or
genotypes. To avoid later statistical biases when comparing gene trees with heterogeneous
numbers of genotypes, the number of genotypes to obtain was fixed to 8 (median of
unrestricted genotype counts over all genes), meaning that the iterative pruning procedure
was stopped when reaching this number. Alternatively, if not enough significant genotypes
were found on the first pass, the procedure was repeated on all branches, including new
branches resulting from the previous pruning steps, with a sensitivity increased by
halving the thresholds of the test described above. The final set of genotypes is
indicated in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table
S1</xref>. This approach and the parameters used here were designed to produce clusters
of significantly diverged strains independently of the variable evolutionary rate of each
gene. Profiles of genotypes were then compared between all gene loci using the RV matrix
correlation statistics (<xref rid="vew017-B53" ref-type="bibr">Robert and Escoufier
1976</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B28" ref-type="bibr">Josse et al. 2008</xref>).
Correlation <italic>P</italic> values were scaled using the Bonferroni correction,
accounting for the <italic>N &#183;</italic> (<italic>N</italic> &#8211; 1)/2 multiple tests. All
phylogenetic tree manipulations were implemented using the 'tree2' Python package
(github.com/flass/tree2/) and all statistical analyses were performed with R statistical
software, with notable use of 'ade4' and 'ape' packages (<xref rid="vew017-B18" ref-type="bibr">Dufour and Dray 2007</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B49" ref-type="bibr">Popescu et al. 2012</xref>).</p><sec><title>2.4.1. Positive selection</title><p>Positive selection scans were performed for each gene locus using the adaptive
BranchSiteREL (aBSREL) algorithm provided in the HyPhy package (<xref rid="vew017-B31" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky Pond et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B63" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2015</xref>). This program allows searching for branches
in a gene tree where the <italic>dN</italic>/<italic>dS</italic> ratio is greater than
one for a significant proportion of the sites in the alignment, without <italic>a
priori</italic> on the branches to test, thus highlighting every episode of positive
selection that may have affected any set of sites in the gene sequence. aBSREL was run
on the topology of the Bayesian gene tree; the alpha parameter was fixed per branch and
0.05 was set as threshold of corrected <italic>P</italic> value for significance. An
algorithm of the same family but with greater statistical power, BUSTED, was recently
published as a more appropriate tool to detect the occurrence of any episode of positive
selection in at least one of the positions of the alignment (<xref rid="vew017-B41" ref-type="bibr">Murrell et al. 2015</xref>). We, therefore, applied this test to the
same dataset and to the extended (142 strains) dataset. Both tests yielded comparable
results, as 29 genes were found to carry signals of past positive selection episodes
using BUSTED out of the 33 that had been detected by aBSREL (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>). We
conservatively considered a gene under positive selection when positive for both the
aBSREL test and the BUSTED test on at least one of the datasets (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). aBSREL
result reports were then analyzed to identify which branch in the gene tree were
identified as episodes of positive selection (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>) and to compute the branch-weighted average
<italic>dN</italic>/<italic>dS</italic> per gene (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S2</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>2.4.2. Inter-specific genome comparisons</title><p>Translated proteomes from representative genomes from six other species of
primate-infecting cytomegaloviruses (CCMV &#8211; Chimpanzee CMV, NC_003521; RhCMV &#8211; Rhesus
macaque CMV, NC_006150; GMCMV &#8211; Green Monkey CMV, NC_012783; CyCMV &#8211; Cynomolgus macaque
CMV, NC_016154; OMCMV &#8211; Owl Monkey CMV, NC_016447; SMCMV &#8211; Squirrel Monkey CMV,
NC_01644), as well as MCMV (Murine CMV, NC_004065) were searched for homology to HCMV
(NC_006273) proteome using BLASTP. A multiple genome alignment of the eight genomes was
obtained using progressiveMauve (version 2.3.1) (<xref rid="vew017-B12" ref-type="bibr">Darling et al. 2010</xref>) under the default parameters plus the collinear flag, and
the core parts of the alignment were used to build a species phylogeny with RAxML
(version 7.7.2) under a GTR&#8201;+&#8201;I&#8201;+&#8201;4&#915; nucleotide substitution model (<xref rid="vew017-B65" ref-type="bibr">Stamatakis 2006</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>3. Results</title><sec><title>3.1. Origin and characteristics of the genomic dataset</title><p>To enable analyses of recombination amongst circulating HCMV genomes, 26 whole genome
sequences were retrieved from GenBank, comprising 17 low-passage and nine uncultured
strains (<xref rid="vew017-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B9" ref-type="bibr">Cunningham et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B11" ref-type="bibr">Dargan et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B29" ref-type="bibr">Jung
et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B59" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. 2014</xref>).
To increase the heterogeneity of the dataset relative to the worldwide HCMV diversity, 16
new sequences (nine uncultured and seven single-passage clinical samples) were generated
through the PATHSEEK pipeline (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ucl.ac.uk/pathseek">http://www.ucl.ac.uk/pathseek</ext-link>), which uses a target enrichment method to
enable deep sequencing of HCMV DNA directly from the clinical material (<xref rid="vew017-B15" ref-type="bibr">Depledge et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="vew017-B14" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). The samples collected were primarily from congenitally
infected (immune-competent) neonates and immune-deficient adolescents/adults (full sample
details are shown in the 16 first rows of <xref rid="vew017-T1" ref-type="table">Table
1</xref>). While the complete dataset is dominated by HCMV strains isolated from Western
Europe, individual sequences from the USA and South Korea were also included.</p><p>The repeat regions flanking the unique long (U<sub>L</sub>) and unique short
(U<sub>S</sub>) were excluded from all downstream analyses, as accurate sequences could
not be generated from next-generation sequencing data alone for the 16 additional samples.
Nucleotide diversity between consensus sequences of individual strains were in the
interval 0.46&#8211;3.26 percent (average, 2.49 percent) for the whole dataset and no
significant difference was observed between low-passage strains (0.46&#8211;3.26 percent,
average 2.49 percent) and uncultured samples (1.40&#8211;3.04 percent, average 2.45 percent,
<italic>t</italic>-test, <italic>df&#8201;</italic>=<italic>&#8201;</italic>427,
<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;0.17). By remapping the read data for each sample against its
consensus sequence, estimates of nucleotide diversity for within-host populations (i.e.
the diversity within a single patient sample) could be derived. Prior studies initially
reported the nucleotide diversity of within-host HCMV populations to be 0.210&#8211;0.640
percent, comparable with that of the&#8201;+ssRNA Dengue virus (<xref rid="vew017-B51" ref-type="bibr">Renzette et al. 2011</xref>). While this estimate was subsequently
reduced to 0.080&#8211;0.200 percent (<xref rid="vew017-B52" ref-type="bibr">Renzette et al.
2013</xref>), here our estimates are lower again (0.016&#8211;0.059 percent, mean 0.0306
percent), with the greatest diversity observed in samples obtained from whole blood (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>3.2. Variety of phylogenetic signals demonstrates homologous recombination
extensively shapes HCMV genomes</title><p>Given the diversity of origins and clinical characteristics of samples in our dataset, we
investigated whether there were genetic properties shared by subsets of our HCMV genome
sample that might indicate epidemiological structure and/or adaptation of sub-populations
to specific niches. A multiple sequence alignment comprising the 42 HCMV genome sequences
was generated to study the genome-wide population structure. Principal component analysis
(PCA) of polymorphism at bi-allelic sites did not show any obvious population structure
and samples did not cluster by any of the available epidemiological factors like
geographic origin, body compartment and host immune status (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S5A and B</xref> and
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File S2</xref>). These
findings were confirmed by the reconstruction of a phylogenetic network based on the
whole-genome alignment, where no clade showed a clear separation from the rest of the
population (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig.
S6A</xref>). The absence of structure appears to be due to extensive homologous
recombination, as evidenced by the numerous central reticulations of the network involving
virtually all combinations of lineages as recombination partners. The role of
recombination in mixing the genetic pool of HCMV at the whole genome level is confirmed by
a highly significant rejection of the pairwise homoplasy index (PHI) test (<xref rid="vew017-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bruen et al. 2006</xref>;
<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>8</sup>).</p><p>To understand how recombination shapes the diversity of HCMV genomes across loci, we
reconstructed the phylogenetic history of each gene locus in the HCMV genome and looked
for consistency of strain relationships across the genome. These phylogenetic inferences
require prior definition of non-recombining loci in the genome. To identify these regions,
we used GARD (<xref rid="vew017-B33" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky Pond et al. 2006</xref>)
to screen the alignment of each annotated gene for the presence of segments of sequence
showing incongruent phylogenetic signals due to recombination; in the presence of
recombination breakpoints, the gene alignment was split into sub-alignments carrying
statistically uniform phylogenetic signal. The resulting collection of alignments was used
to build Bayesian phylogenetic trees. The phylogenetic signal at each locus was then
dissected into every tree bipartition recorded in the sample of gene trees, to quantify
the support for any cluster of strains (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File S3</xref>). By comparing their occurrence between neighbouring loci,
we could reveal haplotypes shared by groups of strains of various sizes. The majority of
loci showed no consistent phylogenetic patterns with their neighbors, proving that
recombination was recurrent through HCMV history, yielding conflicting patterns of strain
relationships between loci. The signature of the most recent shared ancestry of strains
(by either clonal descent or recombination), i.e. the pairing of strains as closest
relatives in the gene trees, formed haplotypes no longer than two genes on average (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S7</xref>). This shows
that recombination occurs frequently enough to yield genomes that behave as gene-scale
mosaics of sequences of different origin.</p><p>Nonetheless, rare haplotypes spanning long stretches of the genome were shared by pairs
of strains, marking recent recombination events (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S8</xref>). In addition, several long haplotypes involving
larger groups of strains could be recovered: one 22 gene-long haplotype ranging from gene
<italic>US1</italic> to gene <italic>US24</italic>, shared by strains 3,157, BE/10/2010
and NL/Rot1/Urine/2012 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary
Fig. S1A</xref>, black arrow), and a few haplotypes at the left hand end of the
prototypic genome orientation (genes <italic>RL10</italic> to <italic>UL13</italic>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1A and B</xref>, top
left of each panel), indicating that some level of population structure occurs locally in
the genome. This was confirmed by repeating the PCA and phylogenetic network analysis on
the segment of the whole-genome alignment covering the RL10-UL13 genomic region, revealing
three major clusters of diversity in this region (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figs. S5C and D and S3B</xref>), while diversity in the
remainder of the genome appear even less structured when considered separately (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figs. S5E and F and
S3C</xref>).</p><p>We reran the gene-scale phylogenetic analysis after inclusion of the dataset of gene
alignments recently published by <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al.
(2015)</xref> which leads to a total of 142 strains. The inclusion of these additional
sequences allowed for a better resolution of gene tree topologies, with an average ratio
of bipartitions posterior probability support over compatibility of 0.056 in the 42-genome
dataset vs. 0.169 in the 142-genome dataset (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figs. S1D vs. S1B</xref>), thus increasing the method's
specificity when identifying common haplotype structures across loci. In this more
conservative setting, we could nonetheless detect many long haplotypes up to the size of
the genome shared by several sets of strains, e.g. by BE/1/2011, BE/8/2010, and BE/9/2012.
This indicates clonal relatedness of these strains, as could be expected from the
clustering in time and space of the samples from <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. (2015)</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>3.3. Linkage disequilibrium shows heterogeneous intensity of recombination at
genome-wide and sub-genic scales</title><p>While it is beyond doubt that HCMV genomes undergo frequent and extensive recombination,
we next asked whether this process is equally frequent throughout the genome. We thus used
linkage disequilibrium (LD) approaches to study the intensity of recombination between
loci. LD reflects the non-random association of alleles at two loci, with a high LD value
indicating co-inheritance of loci (<xref rid="vew017-B61" ref-type="bibr">Slatkin
2008</xref>) and hence lower incidence of recombination between them. LD is usually
characterized based on the distribution of biallelic single nucleotide polymorphisms
(SNPs), but can also be inferred using a categorization of DNA sequences into alleles or
haplotypes. We thus conducted two sets of LD scans to evaluate the impact of recombination
on population structure at different scales in the HCMV genomes.</p><p>First we sought potential linkage between genes across the genome. Gene sequences were
classified into genotypes using an algorithm for dynamic pruning of gene trees from the
142-genome dataset (see Material and methods section), and these categories were used to
identify genome-wide correlation of genotype distribution among strains, yielding a metric
analogous to LD. The majority of genes showed no significant association with genes other
than their immediate neighbor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). The
most striking exception to his trend is the cluster of 13 genes (<italic>RL10</italic> to
<italic>UL11</italic>, included in the structured RL10&#8211;UL13 region reported above) in
substantially higher LD, consistent with locally reduced recombination (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). The average linkage between direct
neighbour genes in this region is <italic>r</italic><sup>2&#8201;</sup>=<sup>&#8201;</sup>0.45, and
the most distal genes in the locus, RL10 and UL11, are 9 kb apart and yet are in tighter
linkage (<italic>r</italic><sup>2&#8201;</sup>=<sup>&#8201;</sup>0.34) than the average for pairs of
direct neighbor genes elsewhere in the genome
(<italic>r</italic><sup>2&#8201;</sup>=<sup>&#8201;</sup>0.18). This region includes multiple genes
from the RL11 family and is hereafter referred to as the RL11 region. A comparative
similarity analysis of the HCMV proteomes demonstrates substantial variation in this
region (across the protein-coding loci in the region, the most divergent pairwise strain
comparisons range from 30 percent to 70 percent protein identity) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Moreover, when extending this comparison to include all
primate CMV and murine CMV species, this region consistently retains the highest genetic
variability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). A second gene cluster
of 11 genes (<italic>UL87</italic>&#8211;<italic>UL97</italic>) also shows a significant degree
of LD (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F1">Fig. 1C</xref>), although to a lesser extent
(average linkage between direct neighbours,
<italic>r</italic><sup>2&#8201;</sup>=<sup>&#8201;</sup>0.23). To verify that these results do not
only stem from the clonal relationships between a few related strains in the dataset, we
split the dataset into two subsets, the first comprising the 42 worldwide genomes and the
second the 100 genomes from <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al.
(2015)</xref>, which were collected on a more restricted geographic and temporal scale
(<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S9</xref>). In
both cases, we robustly recovered the high linkage of RL11 region. However, the linkage
within the <italic>UL87</italic>&#8211;<italic>UL97</italic> cluster is only evident within the
larger dataset from Sijmons et al., in which it may reflect the clonality of a few strain
clusters. This hypothesis is supported by a group of 13 strains sharing a large haplotype
that covers this region, among which twelve were sampled in Belgium and ten in the same
year (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File S3</xref>,
bipartition #2484). </p><fig id="vew017-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p> Heat map of correlation significance between the distribution of sequence genotypes
in the 142 strains along (A) the whole genome or (B) in a close-up of the first 19
genes (25 non-recombining loci) in the prototypic HCMV genome organization.
<italic>P</italic> values are indicated by coloring of the matrix cells (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary methods</xref> for
attribution of genotypes). Each individual gene alignment was first scanned using GARD
to identify recombination breakpoints and the alignments subsequently split either
side of the breakpoint and considered as separate entities.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="vew017f1p"/></fig><fig id="vew017-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p> Conservation of protein sequences in cytomegalovirus. Syntenic circular genome maps
showing protein sequence conservation (percent identity) against HCMV strain Merlin
for (A) all 42 HCMV strains used in this study and (B) the non-human CMVs, from outer
to inner track: CCMV, GMCMV, CyCMV, RhCMV, OMCMV, SMCMV, and MCMV. The percentage
sequence identity is illustrated by the color legend for both A and B. (C)
Maximum-likelihood tree of eight cytomegalovirus species (as in (B)) based on a whole
genome alignment of conserved syntenic blocks. All bootstrap support values (based on
100 samples) were 100 percent.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="vew017f2p"/></fig><p>To characterize the recombination landscape at a finer scale, we performed a genome-wide
LD scan, based on the polymorphism at bi-allelic sites, i.e. sites where exactly two
different nucleotides are present in the sample. In order to characterize the genomic
properties common to the whole viral species and to exclude the potential effect of clonal
population structure, we restricted our analyses to the dataset of 42 diverse genomes. A
total of 22,159 bi-allelic sites were identified within the 238-kb whole-genome alignment.
Using Fisher's exact tests for all pairwise site comparisons, we identified 19,084
significantly linked site pairs (Bonferroni-corrected <italic>P</italic>
values&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.05). The maximal distance between linked sites was 16.35 kb, with 99 percent
of the distances falling below 3 kb and 87 percent below 1 kb. The latter analysis points
to the absence of long-range linkage among most sites of HCMV genomes and supports
widespread intra- and inter-genic recombination.</p><p>Given the near-absence of long-range linkage in the HCMV genomes, we next searched for
short-scale patterns of excessive LD using a local LD index (see Methods section) in
sliding windows of 700 bp over the whole genome alignment (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File S4</xref>). We
identified hotspots of linkage in 31 genes out of the 169 annotated in the Merlin
reference genome, as those harboring the top 5 percent windows in higher LD than the
genomic average (corresponding to local LD index&#8201;&gt;&#8201;5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F3">Fig. 3A</xref>, blue track 4). Interestingly, there is an apparent
association between these hotspots of LD and peaks of nucleotide diversity, a measure of
average similarity between strains in our sample (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F3">Fig. 3A</xref>, red track 5; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S4</xref>). Indeed, out of the 26 hyper-variable genes (those
harbouring the top 5 percent windows of higher nucleotide diversity), 21 were also found
to be LD hotspots (<xref rid="vew017-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). This
association is confirmed by a significant correlation between nucleotide diversity and the
<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> metric of LD (Pearson's correlation,
<italic>r</italic><sup>2&#8201;</sup>=<sup>&#8201;</sup>0.214,
<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>16</sup>) or the local LD index
(<italic>r</italic><sup>2&#8201;</sup>=<sup>&#8201;</sup>0.307,
<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>16</sup>). </p><fig id="vew017-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p> Circular genome map showing linkage disequilibrium and nucleotidic diversity. (A)
The purple backbone represents the classical HCMV genome arrangement
TR<sub>L</sub>&#8211;U<sub>L</sub>&#8211;IR<sub>L</sub>&#8211;IR<sub>S</sub>&#8211;U<sub>S</sub>&#8211;TR<sub>S</sub>
where repeat sequences are shown in a lighter shade, the origin of lytic replication
highlighted in pink, and the RL11 gene family indicated by the red shading. Tracks are
numbered inwards: (1) Map of the protein-coding genes; (2) Presence of epitopes for
CD4+&#8201;(blue), CD8+&#8201;(red) or both (purple)T-cells (<xref rid="vew017-B70" ref-type="bibr">Sylwester et al. 2005</xref>); (3) location of genes that have
undergone positive selection episodes; (4) Local LD index, computed in 700-bp windows,
the hotspots of LD (top 5 percent values) are highlighted in dark blue, with
corresponding gene names shown outside of the plot; (5) HCMV nucleotide diversity,
computed in adjacent windows of 100&#8201;bp, the hypervariable loci (top 5 percent values)
are highlighted in dark red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="vew017f3p"/></fig><table-wrap id="vew017-T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>
<bold/> List of genes with the strongest hotspots of linkage disequilibrium (high-LD
genes)</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><fn id="vew017-TF4"><p>#, RL11 family; *, UL/b&#8217;, region.</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF5"><p>
<sup>a</sup>Gene name in Merlin reference sequence annotation (NCBI RefSeq
NC_006273/AY446894), genes are ranked by decreasing LD score.</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF6"><p>
<sup>b</sup>Functional annotation summarized from Merlin reference sequence
annotation in NCBI RefSeq record (NC_006273/AY446894) and from the extensive review
provided by <xref rid="vew017-B202" ref-type="bibr">van Damme and van Looke
(2014)</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF7"><p>
<sup>c</sup>Antigenic status derived from <xref rid="vew017-B70" ref-type="bibr">Sylwester et al. (2005)</xref>. &#8201;&#8201;++, the gene was among the top 30, when ranked
by total memory-corrected response, over 33 seropositive subjects; &#8201;+, the gene was
eliciting a positive response in at least 4 of the 33 tested seropositive
subjects.</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF8"><p>
<sup>d</sup>The highest local LD index among all windows included in the gene
boudaries; local LD index is the &#8722;log10 transform of the <italic>P</italic> values
of Mann&#8211;Whitney&#8211;Wilcoxon tests for each 700-pb windows located in the gene, under
the null hypothesis that there is no higher LD in the window than in average in the
genome. Genes presented in this table include the 5 percent top-scoring windows
(high-LD genes); bold values are in the top 2 percent.</p></fn><fn id="vew017-TF9"><p>
<sup>e</sup>Nucleotidic diversity, highest value recorded in 100-bp windows within
the gene; bold values are in the top 5 percent (hyper-variable genes).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>To exclude the possibility that this correlation resulted from a systematic bias in our
method leading to measure higher LD in more diverse regions, we performed simulations of
genome evolution using ALF (<xref rid="vew017-B10" ref-type="bibr">Dalquen et al.
2012</xref>) under a model where phylogenetic structure and recombination rate vary
independently of diversity (see Methods section). Analysis of these simulated genomes
showed that the local LD index accurately reports local domains of clonal structure
(accuracy statistics over 20 independent simulations, given a detection threshold of local
LD index&#8201;&#8805;&#8201;5): per-window sensitivity SN<sub>w</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.63&#8211;0.85 (median 0.85) and
specificity SP<sub>w</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.98&#8211;1.0 (median 1.0); average per-locus sensitivity
SN<sub>L</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;1.0 and specificity SP<sub>L</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.95 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S5</xref>). In
addition, we verified that this metric is not positively misled by local peaks of
nucleotidic diversity, with only a non-specific correlation to local nucleotidic diversity
(Pearson correlation, <italic>r</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;&#8722;0.15&#8211;0.17, median 0.04, significant
associations at <italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;10<sup>&#8722;</sup><sup>2</sup>: 2/20 negative and 2/20
positive). In comparison, other metrics used as proxy for homoplasy were not able to
report as accurately the clonally evolving loci and were strongly impacted by the local
diversity levels (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig.
S10</xref> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ve.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/ve/vew017/-/DC1">Table
S5</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec><title>3.4. Hyper-variable loci are under diversifying selective pressure leading to
divergence between haplotypes</title><p>Homologous recombination is likely to be restricted between highly differentiated
genotypes due to the inability of homologous strands to anneal, favoring further
divergence. Their primary divergence may, however, have been driven by positive selective
pressure, i.e. selection for changes in the resultant protein. To test this hypothesis, we
scanned all HCMV gene trees using the aBSREL algorithm (<xref rid="vew017-B31" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky Pond et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B63" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2015</xref>) and show that the genomes evolved mostly
under purifying selection, with an average d<italic>N</italic>/d<italic>S</italic> of 0.18
over their complete evolutionary history (branch length-weighted average of mean
d<italic>N</italic>/d<italic>S</italic> values for all branches pooled across all
genes). This constraint on the diversification of encoded proteins is also seen within
hyper-variable genes (average d<italic>N</italic>/d<italic>S</italic> of 0.22) but to a
lesser extent than in other genes (average d<italic>N</italic>/d<italic>S</italic> of
0.17, <italic>t</italic>-test <italic>P</italic> value&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.003) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). However,
this analysis also pointed to evidence for episodes of positive selection (branches with
significantly non-null proportion of sites with
d<italic>N</italic>/d<italic>S</italic>&#8201;&gt;&#8201;1) in 29 genes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F3">Fig. 3</xref>, track 4 and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S2</xref>), nine of which have also been identified as
hyper-variable (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table
S4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File
S5</xref>) and hotspots of LD (<xref rid="vew017-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>).
There is a significant enrichment of positively selected genes in hyper-variable
non-recombining genes (Chi-squared test, d<italic>f</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;1,
<italic>P</italic>&#8201;&lt;&#8201;0.003). It should be noted that this test is conservative given
the greater possibility of spurious inference of episodes of positive selection in
recombining genes by the phylogenetic selection scan. Indeed, when using an alternative
method based on pairwise sequence comparisons that does not make assumptions about the
phylogenetic history of samples (<xref rid="vew017-B77" ref-type="bibr">Yang and Nielsen
2000</xref>), we generally fail to detect positive selection in recombining genes (data
not shown). Closer examination of the nine positively selected hyper-variable genes
identified episodes of positive selection in the deep branches separating the diverged
genotypes as well as on terminal branches (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary File S5</xref>), in contrast with purifying selection occurring
in the rest of branches (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary
Table S2</xref>). This supports a scenario of recurrent episodes of positive selection
throughout the evolution of these genes rapidly generating sequence diversity, driving
these loci to gradually diverge into almost non-homologous genotypes.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>4. Discussion</title><sec><title>4.1. Recombination is widespread in HCMV genomes but linkage occurs locally in
association with peaks of diversity</title><p>Using a series of phylogenetic and population genetics analyses, we characterized
recombination in HCMV genomes at increasing resolution and show recombination to be so
pervasive across most of the genome that virtually every variable site segregates
independently. In this respect, this viral species can be considered to behave as a single
freely recombining worldwide population. This observation is in line with the absence of
any apparent geographical or epidemiological structure in the HCMV population at the
genome-wide level (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figs.
S5 and S6</xref>), as has previously been reported for individual gene markers (<xref rid="vew017-B25" ref-type="bibr">Haberland et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B48" ref-type="bibr">Pignatelli et al. 2004</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al. 2008</xref>). Recombination of sub-genomic fragments has previously been
observed for Epstein&#8211;Barr virus and also genome-wide for herpes simplex virus 1&amp;2,
VZV, and murine CMV (<xref rid="vew017-B71" ref-type="bibr">Walling et al. 1994</xref>;
<xref rid="vew017-B36" ref-type="bibr">Lingen et al. 1997</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B42" ref-type="bibr">Norberg et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B43" ref-type="bibr">Norberg et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B44" ref-type="bibr">Norberg et al
2015</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B62" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2013</xref>), and thus
appears to be a hallmark of many herpesviruses. Recombination is indeed known to be a
crucial step of the replication process in HSV-1 (<xref rid="vew017-B76" ref-type="bibr">Wilkinson and Weller 2003</xref>) and has been postulated to occur between
superinfecting as well as reactivating genomes in HCMV (<xref rid="vew017-B6" ref-type="bibr">Chou 1989</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B25" ref-type="bibr">Haberland et
al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B67" ref-type="bibr">Steininger et al. 2005</xref>;
<xref rid="vew017-B23" ref-type="bibr">Garrigue et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B66" ref-type="bibr">Steininger 2007</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B20" ref-type="bibr">Faure-Della Corte et al. 2010</xref>). The topology of long haplotypes
observed between pairs of strains is suggestive of recombination occurring through large
replacement events, for example, by crossing-over or joining replicated genome segments
(<xref rid="vew017-B76" ref-type="bibr">Wilkinson and Weller 2003</xref>) rather than by
localized gene conversion events. The recent study from <xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. (2015)</xref> also reported the occurrence of intense,
genome-wide homologous recombination in HCMV genomes and similarly stressed the
heterogeneity of the recombination intensity across the genome. However, the map of the
recombination landscape resulting from their analysis differs markedly from ours. Using
recombination breakpoint detection methods, they showed a globally higher prevalence of
recombination in genes with higher diversity (<xref rid="vew017-B60" ref-type="bibr">Sijmons et al. 2015</xref>). These breakpoint methods are appropriate to identify
partitions of sequence alignments with different phylogenetic history (<xref rid="vew017-B32" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky Pond et al. 2006</xref>) in order to treat
them separately in downstream analyses &#8211; as we did ourselves for our gene-scale analyses.
However, recombination breakpoints are generically identified from the conflicting
phylogenetic signals estimated over their flanking segments of sequence. Breakpoint
detection methods thus can only report a finite number of recombination events per locus,
which are biased towards the most obvious, i.e. recent events. This limited account of
recombination history thus leads to a biased estimate of recombination intensities. In
addition, methods like GARD (<xref rid="vew017-B32" ref-type="bibr">Kosakovsky Pond et al.
2006</xref>), which involve the reconstruction and comparison of phylogenetic trees, can
be afflicted by high rates of false positives in the face of strong evolutionary rate
variation across a gene sequence; a situation often met in genes with hyper-variable
domains but highly conserved otherwise (e.g. in UL55/gB). Finally, these methods, like all
polymorphism-based analyses, are highly biased towards the detection of more recombination
breakpoints in more variable genomic regions. Conversely, LD can be quantified at every
variable site and naturally integrates the effect of recombination over long evolutionary
times. For all these reasons, we feel that the analysis of variation of recombination
intensities within HCMV genomes is better addressed by the approach we deployed, which is
based on LD and was specially designed to control for heterogeneity in polymorphism
density.</p><p>In contrast to Sijmons et al.'s findings, we find the majority of hyper-variable loci to
be in high linkage. Specifically, within these high-LD loci, recombination between
divergent genotypes is prevented, although recombination is still expected to occur
between strains sharing the same genotype. Whereas occurrences of LD have previously been
identified between genes of the RL11 region (<xref rid="vew017-B57" ref-type="bibr">Sekulin et al. 2007</xref>), which harbors exceptionally large haplotypes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S1</xref>), we here
report several other loci where occurrence of LD is only evident at a scale smaller than a
gene and when contrasted with the genome-wide background of essentially free
recombination. Paradoxically, many of these hotspots of LD occur in genes that were
associated with previous reports of absence of linkage between genes, as they are mostly
hyper-variable and can be used as highly discriminant epidemiological markers (<xref rid="vew017-B25" ref-type="bibr">Haberland et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B48" ref-type="bibr">Pignatelli et al. 2004</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B3" ref-type="bibr">Bradley et al. 2008</xref>), but the presence of linkage within them has been
overlooked so far.</p></sec><sec><title>4.2. Islands of linkage arise by fast evolution under diversifying selection or slow
evolution under putative epistatic constraints</title><p>Within this genome-wide pattern of essentially free recombination and strong genome
conservation, some 31 loci do not recombine freely (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Two-thirds of these genes have evolved multiple genotypes that are
sufficiently divergent to prevent recombination between each other (<xref rid="vew017-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Considering the functional annotation of these genes,
most (24/31) of the high-LD genes are annotated as membrane glycoproteins that are either
known or predicted to be involved in virus entry or immune evasion (<xref rid="vew017-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). In addition, 10/31 harbor T-cell epitopes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F3">Fig. 3A</xref>, track 2; <xref rid="vew017-T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), as previously determined by a systematic experimental
scan (<xref rid="vew017-B70" ref-type="bibr">Sylwester et al. 2005</xref>). Functions
implying protein&#8211;&#160;protein interaction with host factors and/or having antigenic status are
suggestive of co-evolutionary dynamics driving the diversification of these proteins. In
nine of these genes, phylogenetic analysis revealed evidence of past and present positive
selections, which likely accounts for this extreme divergence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Tables S2 and S4</xref>). For
these nine positively selected hyper-variable genes, which include antigenic viral
proteins like UL55/gB, this pattern is highly suggestive of selective pressure for escape
of the host immune system driving sequence diversification. Causes of diversification of
other hyper-variable proteins are less obvious, and may involve more complex scenarios.
For instance RL11 gene family members encode putative glycoproteins (both membrane and
cytosolic, <xref rid="vew017-B22" ref-type="bibr">Gabaev et al. 2011</xref>) that can
impact virus growth in a cell type-specific manner, manipulate leukocyte adhesion and
cytokine production (via interaction with CD229) or bind to immunoglobulin-Fc receptors
postulated to contribute to epithelial cell tropism <italic>in vivo</italic> (<xref rid="vew017-B35" ref-type="bibr">Lilley et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B1" ref-type="bibr">Atalay et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B19" ref-type="bibr">Engel
et al. 2011</xref>). As these proteins bind host receptors that are themselves
polymorphic, negative frequency-dependent selection for a tighter interaction with the
variety of ligands available in the host population could be driving their
diversification. Another known cause of the emergence of LD is the competition for
resources such as cellular receptors among co-infecting strains, promoting a stably
diverse population of pathogens (<xref rid="vew017-B72" ref-type="bibr">Watkins et al.,
2014</xref>); this mechanism promoting population structure is, however, expected to
lead to long-range linkage among loci, which is not observed here (apart for the RL11
locus, see below).</p><p>LD hotspots were also present within ten genes (including UL75/gH, UL86/MCP, UL100/gM,
UL104, and UL123/IE1) that are more conserved among HCMV strains, with an average
nucleotide diversity only marginally higher than the genomic average (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S11</xref>). For these,
lack of recombination cannot be explained by between-genotype nucleotide divergence, and
we speculate that in these genes linkage may preserve key protein functions that rely on
crucial intra-genic epistasis. In the case of UL86 and UL104, both capsid proteins, it
seems plausible that strong conformational constraints in these proteins &#8211; for which
stability is essential for virion formation and transmissibility &#8211; may lead to such strong
selection for co-evolution of interacting residues that linkage between them could be
maintained even in face of the high recombination rate. In principle, such haplotypes
maintained in LD by natural selection alone for sufficient periods of time might evolve
into hypervariable regions through the independent accumulation of mutations.</p><p>The identification of a set of genes with function that drove (and is likely still
driving) their constant divergence may be valuable for research into new therapeutic
strategies. Glycoproteins gB (UL55) and gH (UL75), both of which are prime targets for
neutralizing antibodies and vaccine development, are encoded by high-LD genes. This raises
the possibility that other proteins in this group may also be suitable targets for the
development of new drugs or vaccines, for example glycoprotein gM. It is interesting to
note that none of these hotspots overlapped with more recent revisions of the HCMV coding
content (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig.
S12</xref>), and thus these inferences are unlikely to come from selection on cryptic
functions of the loci.</p></sec><sec><title>4.3. RL11 region diversification is coherent and uncoupled from the rest of the
genome</title><p>The most striking of the linked hotspots is the RL11 region (comprising genes
<italic>RL11</italic>&#8211;<italic>UL11</italic>), where strong linkage is found between
thirteen genes. Although the high degree of linkage in this region has previously been
noted (<xref rid="vew017-B16" ref-type="bibr">Dolan et al. 2004</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B57" ref-type="bibr">Sekulin et al. 2007</xref>), our whole genome analyses
reveal this is the only region of the HCMV genome showing any evidence of a consistent
evolutionary history (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F1">Fig. 1</xref>). These uniquely
large haplotypes in the HCMV genome could reflect immune pressure for co-segregation of
antigenic alleles at multiple loci into non-overlapping combinations of antigens to avoid
cross-immunity, a phenomenon which has been shown to occur in some bacterial pathogens
(<xref rid="vew017-B72" ref-type="bibr">Watkins et al. 2014</xref>). However, the fact
that these co-segregating genes sit contiguously in a globally hyper-variable region
prevent us from distinguishing whether recombination in this region is counter-selected or
neutrally prevented because homologous recombination cannot be initiated due to the
excessive divergence of sequences throughout this region.</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis of core genes of genomes of CMV isolated from eight host species,
including all sequenced primate CMVs and using murine CMV as an outgroup (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig. 2C</xref>), generated a topology congruent with the
accepted evolutionary relationships of the primate host species (<xref rid="vew017-B47" ref-type="bibr">Perelman et al. 2011</xref>). This supports a history of repeated
co-speciation of virus and hosts, during which the <italic>RL11</italic> gene family
expanded and evolved rapidly in a continuous process of diversification since the early
CMV ancestor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). This rapid evolution
of the RL11 region continued within HCMV species, with high levels of diversification
within and between species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig. 2A</xref>).</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis within HCMV indicates that several members of the RL11 family
(RL13, UL9, and UL11) originally diverged under positive selective pressures (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Table S3</xref>). This
suggests that these genes have an important functional role in HCMV biology, even though a
number of genes encoded in the RL11 region are non-essential for viral replication
<italic>in vitro</italic> (<xref rid="vew017-B1" ref-type="bibr">Atalay et al.
2002</xref>). The common feature of this gene family is the RL11 core domain (RL11D),
which shares homology with the adenovirus E3 family of proteins (<xref rid="vew017-B13" ref-type="bibr">Davison et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B22" ref-type="bibr">Gabaev et al. 2011</xref>) which are important for evasion of T-cell responses and
inhibition of cell death. This putative function, in addition to the characterized roles
of individual proteins in cell tropism, would further implicate the RL11 region as a
crucial region for HCMV replication <italic>in vivo</italic>, notably through specific
interactions with human receptors. Therefore, we hypothesize that the
<italic>RL11</italic> gene family diversification has been an important driver of
adaptive co-evolution of HCMV genomes within their hosts. From this perspective, the
presence of divergent genotypes at this locus having lost the ability to recombine with
each other, while free recombination is still occurring in the rest of the genome, is
indicative of population differentiation occurring within HCMV species. More genomic and
epidemiological data are needed to link this cryptic differentiation to demographic or
selective processes.</p></sec><sec><title>4.5. Recombination enables selection to operate with varying dynamics across HCMV
genomes</title><p>Apart from the few hyper-variable loci, the majority of the HCMV genome harbors only
limited genetic diversity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F3">Fig. 3</xref>),
translating into very homogeneous proteomes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig.
2A</xref>). This high degree of conservation at the protein level is likely due to the
strong purifying selection experienced by all protein-coding genes in the genome over most
of their phylogenetic history (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Fig. S3</xref>). Genome-wide purifying selection is common in viral
pathogens (<xref rid="vew017-B74" ref-type="bibr">Wertheim and Kosakovsky Pond
2011</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B73" ref-type="bibr">Wertheim et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B7" ref-type="bibr">Cloete et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B17" ref-type="bibr">Duch&#234;ne et al. 2014</xref>), indicating strong and long-standing
evolutionary constraint on the encoded proteome. In HCMV, such constraint might be
explained by the long co-evolution with its host: herpesviruses have co-evolved over long
periods of time with their specific host (<xref rid="vew017-B201" ref-type="bibr">McGeoch
et al. 1995</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B75" ref-type="bibr">Wertheim et al. 2014</xref>)
&#8211; in the case of CMVs with no evidence of further introductions since the last primate
ancestor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="vew017-F2">Fig. 2C</xref>). With such extended time
periods under constant ecological conditions, the HCMV genome is likely close to encode an
optimal phenotype, characterized by a life cycle of asymptomatic reactivation and
transmission. This lifestyle necessitates a large apparatus of regulators and immune
escape factors that constitute as many mutation targets. Intense homologous recombination
is known to increase the efficiency of natural selection by unlinking selected sites from
the genomic background, and may thus provide the means to achieve the levels of purifying
selection required for maintaining HCMV's genome functionality.</p><p>Moreover, we observe two sets of sites in HCMV genomes with conflicting evolutionary
dynamics: those under strong pressure for long-term conservation, and those under episodic
pressure for rapid diversification. In the presence of genetic linkage, selective
pressures operating at independent loci interfere with each other and prevent fixation of
the fittest genotypes, notably through the accumulation of deleterious mutations in the
genomic backgrounds that carry positively selected mutations &#8211; the so-called
Hill-Robertson effect, a counter-adaptive phenomenon avoided when recombination occurs
between loci (<xref rid="vew017-B21" ref-type="bibr">Felsenstein 1974</xref>). This common
evolutionary trade-off is emphasized in HCMV by the extreme dichotomy of evolutionary
rates observed in the genome, with the few loci under strong positive selection for
frequent change being at risk of recurrently hitch-hiking deleterious mutations in the
large remainder of the genome under purifying selection. The maintenance of such
contrasting evolutionary dynamics in a same genome prompts an even greater need for HCMV
genomes to recombine frequently.</p><p>Population-level selection could thus have operated to favor intense genetic mixing. For
instance, inter-strain homologous recombination is likely to occur during infection with
multiple CMV strains, either simultaneously (co-infection) or over time (super-infection),
phenomena which are frequently observed in both humans (HCMV) and mice (MCMV) (<xref rid="vew017-B2" ref-type="bibr">Booth et al. 1993</xref>; <xref rid="vew017-B39" ref-type="bibr">Meyer-K&#246;nig et al. 1998</xref>). Interestingly, evasion of pre-existing
adaptive immunity, mainly CD8 T-cells, orchestrated by the <italic>CMV US2-11</italic>
gene products, which down-regulate MHC class I and II antigen presentation pathways, has
been shown to be critical for super-infection in the rhesus CMV primate model (<xref rid="vew017-B26" ref-type="bibr">Hansen et al. 2010</xref>). However, these genes are
dispensable for primary infection of CMV-naive animals, and thus appear to specifically
promote immune evasion during super-infection. Under the hypothesis of the crucial role of
recombination in HCMV evolution, it would seem plausible that acquisitions of genes
promoting super-infection and, as a consequence, frequent recombination of viral strains,
were positively selected.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>5. Conclusion</title><p>In summary, we conclude that HCMV recombines essentially freely, except at hotspots of LD
found in 31 genes, among which a majority of hyper-variable genes that originally diverged
under positive selection and code for proteins associated with adaptive or innate immune
evasion. Immune evasion is postulated to favor the high levels of HCMV superinfection
observed in humans, and this in turn promotes recombination. This mechanism would allow HCMV
genomes to satisfy an evolutionary trade-off between short term pressures to evade host
immune recognition and a long-standing evolutionary constraint on a complex genome optimally
tuned towards silent parasitism.</p></sec><sec><title>Data availability</title><p>New HCMV genome sequences were deposited in GenBank under the accessions KT726940-KT726955.
Data used for and resulting from phylogenetic inferences are available on TreeBASE at:
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S18391">http://purl.org/phylo/treebase/phylows/study/TB2:S18391</ext-link>. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary material</xref> is accessible
on Figshare under Project no. 13369: <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Tables S1&#8211;S5</xref>, DOI: 10.6084/m9.figshare.3219184; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Figures S1&#8211;S12</xref>, DOI:
10.6084/m9.figshare.3219214; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Files S1&#8211;S5</xref>, DOI: 10.6084/m9.figshare.3219223.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary data</title><p> Supplementary data are available <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">here</xref>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Data</label><media xlink:href="vew017_Supplementary_Data.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors acknowledge the infrastructure support provided the MRC Centre for Molecular
Medical Virology Grant G0900950, the NIHR UCL/UCLH Biomedical Research Centre, and the use
of the UCL Legion High Performance Computing Facility, and associated support services, in
the completion of this work. We acknowledge all partners within the PATHSEEK consortium
(involving University College London, Erasmus MC, QIAGEN AAR, and Oxford Gene Technology),
which received funding from the European Union&#8217;s Seventh Programme for research,
technological development and demonstration under Grant agreement no, 304875. F.L. and F.B.
are supported by ERC Grant BIG_IDEA 260801 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://erc.europa.eu">http://erc.europa.eu</ext-link>) and, together with
J.B., the National Institute for Health Research University College London Hospitals
Biomedical Research Centre. M.B.R. is supported by an MRC Fellowship (G:0900466). D.P.D. is
supported by an MRF New Investigator award. J.R.B. is supported by the National Institute
for Health Research Biomedical Research Centre at Great Ormond Street Hospital for Children
NHS Foundation Trust and University College London.</p><p>Conflict of interest. None declared.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="vew017-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atalay</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Identification and
Expression of Human Cytomegalovirus Transcription Units Coding for Two Distinct Fcgamma
Receptor Homologs&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Virology</source>,
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>8596</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12163579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Booth</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Molecular and Biological
Characterization of New Strains of Murine Cytomegalovirus Isolated From Wild
Mice&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Archive Virology</source><volume>132</volume>:
<fpage>209</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Genotypic Analysis of Two
Hypervariable Human Cytomegalovirus Genes&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Medical
Virology</source>, <volume>80</volume>:
<fpage>1615</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18649324</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>&#8216;High-Throughput Sequence
Analysis of Variants of Human Cytomegalovirus Strains Towne and AD169&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of General Virology</source>, <volume>90</volume>:
<fpage>2375</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19553388</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruen</surname><given-names>T. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Philippe</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;A Simple and Robust Statistical Test
for Detecting the Presence of Recombination&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Genetics</source>,
<volume>172</volume>: <fpage>2665</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16489234</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>S. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Reactivation and Recombination of
Multiple Cytomegalovirus Strains From Individual Organ Donors&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of Infectious Diseases</source>, <volume>160</volume>:
<fpage>11</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2543706</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cloete</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Influence of Secondary
Structure, Selection and Recombination on Rubella Virus Nucleotide Substitution Rate
Estimates&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Virology Journal</source>, <volume>11</volume>:
<fpage>166</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25224517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>P. J. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Biopython: Freely Available
Python Tools for Computational Molecular Biology and Bioinformatics.
Bioinforma&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Oxford</source>, <volume>25</volume>:
<fpage>1422</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Sequences of Complete Human
Cytomegalovirus Genomes From Infected Cell Cultures and Clinical
Specimens&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of General Virology</source>,
<volume>91</volume>: <fpage>605</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19906940</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dalquen</surname><given-names>D. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>&#8216;ALF&#8211;A Simulation Framework
for Genome Evolution&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>,
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1115</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22160766</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dargan</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Sequential Mutations
Associated With Adaptation of Human Cytomegalovirus to Growth in Cell
Culture&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of General Virology</source>,
<volume>91</volume>: <fpage>1535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20479471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darling</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mau</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perna</surname><given-names>N. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#8216;ProgressiveMauve: Multiple Genome
Alignment With Gene Gain, Loss and Rearrangement&#8217;</article-title>, <source>PloS
One</source>, <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e11147</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20593022</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Homology Between the Human
Cytomegalovirus RL11 Gene Family and Human Adenovirus E3 Genes&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of General Virology</source>, <volume>84</volume>:
<fpage>657</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12604818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Depledge</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Deep Sequencing of Viral
Genomes Provides Insight into the Evolution and Pathogenesis of Varicella Zoster Virus
and Its Vaccine in Humans&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and
Evolution</source>, <volume>31</volume>:
<fpage>397</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>409</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24162921</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Depledge</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Specific Capture and
Whole-Genome Sequencing of Viruses from Clinical Samples&#8217;</article-title>, <source>PLoS
One</source>, <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e27805</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22125625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Genetic Content of Wild-Type
Human Cytomegalovirus&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of General Virology</source>,
<volume>85</volume>: <fpage>1301</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duch&#234;ne</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ho</surname><given-names>S. Y. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Analyses of Evolutionary Dynamics in
Viruses Are Hindered by a Time-Dependent Bias in Rate Estimates&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological
Sciences</source>, <volume>281</volume>: <fpage>20140732</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24850916</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dufour</surname><given-names>A. -B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dray</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The ade4 Package: Implementing the
Duality Diagram for Ecologists&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Statistical
Software</source>, <volume>22</volume>: <fpage>i04</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Human Cytomegalovirus UL7, a
Homologue of the SLAM-Family Receptor CD229, Impairs Cytokine
Production&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Immunology &amp; Cell Biology</source>,
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>753</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21670740</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faure-Della Corte</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Variability and
Recombination of Clinical Human Cytomegalovirus Strains From Transplantation
Recipients&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Clinical Virology: The Official
Publication of the Pan American Society for Clinical Virology</source>,
<volume>47</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20022297</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1974</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Evolutionary Advantage of
Recombination&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Genetics</source>, <volume>78</volume>:
<fpage>737</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4448362</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gabaev</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Human Cytomegalovirus
UL11 Protein Interacts With the Receptor Tyrosine Phosphatase CD45, Resulting in
Functional Paralysis of T Cells&#8217;</article-title>, <source>PLoS Pathogens</source>,
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1002432</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22174689</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrigue</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Variability of UL18, UL40,
UL111a and US3 Immunomodulatory Genes Among Human Cytomegalovirus Clinical Isolates From
Renal Transplant Recipients&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Clinical Virology: The
Official publicAtion of the Pan American Society for Clinical Virology</source>,
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>120</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17827058</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gouy</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guindon</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascuel</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#8216;SeaView Version 4: A Multiplatform
Graphical User Interface for Sequence Alignment and Phylogenetic Tree
Building&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>,
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>221</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19854763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haberland</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer-K&#246;nig</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hufert</surname><given-names>F. T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Variation Within the Glycoprotein B
Gene of Human Cytomegalovirus Is Due to Homologous Recombination&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of General Virology</source>, <volume>80</volume>/<issue>Pt 6</issue>:
<fpage>1495</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>500</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10374968</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Evasion of CD8+ T Cells Is
Critical for Superinfection by Cytomegalovirus&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Science</source>, <volume>328</volume>:
<fpage>102</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20360110</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huson</surname><given-names>D. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryant</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Application of Phylogenetic Networks
in Evolutionary Studies&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and
Evolution</source>, <volume>23</volume>:
<fpage>254</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16221896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Josse</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pag&#232;s</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Husson</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Testing the Significance of the RV
Coefficient&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Computational Statistics &amp; Data
Analysis</source>, <volume>53</volume>:
<fpage>82</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>91</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>G. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Full Genome Sequencing and
Analysis of Human Cytomegalovirus Strain JHC Isolated From a Korean
Patient&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Virus Research</source>, <volume>156</volume>:
<fpage>113</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21255625</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>&#8216;MAFFT Multiple Sequence Alignment
Software Version 7: Improvements in Performance and Usability&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>, <volume>30</volume>:
<fpage>772</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;A Random Effects Branch-Site
Model for Detecting Episodic Diversifying Selection&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular
Biology and Evolution</source>, <volume>28</volume>:
<fpage>3033</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21670087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Automated Phylogenetic
Detection of Recombination Using a Genetic Algorithm&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular
Biology and Evolution</source>, <volume>23</volume>:
<fpage>1891</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>901</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16818476</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;GARD: A Genetic Algorithm
for Recombination Detection&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Bioinformatics</source>,
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>3096</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17110367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Priorities for CMV Vaccine
Development&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Vaccine</source>, <volume>32</volume>:
<fpage>4</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24129123</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lilley</surname><given-names>B. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ploegh</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tirabassi</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Human Cytomegalovirus Open Reading
Frame TRL11/IRL11 Encodes an Immunoglobulin G Fc-Binding Protein&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of Virology</source>, <volume>75</volume>:
<fpage>11218</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11602761</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lingen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hengerer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Falke</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Mixed Vaginal Infections of Balb/c
mice With Low Virulent Herpes Simplex Type 1 Strains Result in Restoration of Virulence
Properties: Vaginitis/Vulvitis and Neuroinvasiveness&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Medical
Microbiology and Immunology (Berlin)</source>, <volume>185</volume>:
<fpage>217</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>22</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lurain</surname><given-names>N. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Human Cytomegalovirus UL144
Open Reading Frame: Sequence Hypervariability in Low-Passage Clinical
Isolates&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Virology</source>, <volume>73</volume>:
<fpage>10040</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10559318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manicklal</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Silent&#8221; Global Burden of
Congenital Cytomegalovirus&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Clinical Microbiology
Reviews</source>, <volume>26</volume>:
<fpage>86</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23297260</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B201"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Molecular Phylogeny and
Evolutionary Timescale for the Family of Mammalian Herpesviruses&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of Molecular Biology</source>, <volume>247</volume>:
<fpage>443</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7714900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer-K&#246;nig</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Simultaneous Infection of
Healthy People With Multiple Human Cytomegalovirus Strains&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Lancet</source>, <volume>352</volume>:
<fpage>1280</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Coding Potential of
Laboratory and Clinical Strains of Human Cytomegalovirus&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source>, <volume>100</volume>:
<fpage>14976</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>81</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Gene-Wide Identification of
Episodic Selection&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>,
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>1365</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25701167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Divergence and Recombination
of Clinical Herpes Simplex Virus Type 2 Isolates&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of
Virology</source>, <volume>81</volume>:
<fpage>13158</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>67</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17881457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;A Genome-Wide Comparative
Evolutionary Analysis of HERPES SIMPLEX VIRUS TYPE 1 and Varicella Zoster
Virus&#8217;</article-title>, <source>PLoS One</source>, <volume>6</volume>:
<fpage>e22527</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21799886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norberg</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Recombination of Globally
Circulating Varicella-Zoster Virus&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of
Virology</source>, <volume>89</volume>:
<fpage>7133</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25926648</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;RATT: Rapid Annotation
Transfer Tool&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Nucleic Acids
Research</source><volume>39</volume>: <fpage>e57</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21306991</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Claude</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strimmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>&#8216;APE: Analyses of Phylogenetics and
Evolution in R Language&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Bioinformatics</source>.,
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14734327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perelman</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;A Molecular Phylogeny of
Living Primates&#8217;</article-title>, <source>PLoS Genetics</source>, <volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>e1001342</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21436896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pignatelli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Genetic Polymorphisms Among
Human Cytomegalovirus (HCMV) Wild-Type Strains&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Reviews in
Medical Virology</source>, <volume>14</volume>:
<fpage>383</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15386592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popescu</surname><given-names>A. -A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>K. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paradis</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>&#8216;ape 3.0: New Tools for Distance-Based
Phylogenetics and Evolutionary Analysis in R&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Bioinformatic</source>, <volume>28</volume>:
<fpage>1536</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmussen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Genes Encoding the gCIII
Complex of Human Cytomegalovirus Exist in Highly Diverse Combinations in Clinical
Isolates&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Virology</source>, <volume>76</volume>:
<fpage>10841</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renzette</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Extensive Genome-Wide
Variability of Human Cytomegalovirus in Congenitally Infected Infants&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>PLoS Pathogens</source>, <volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>e1001344</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21625576</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renzette</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Rapid Intrahost Evolution of
Human Cytomegalovirus Is Shaped by Demography and Positive Selection&#8217;</article-title>
Worobey M, editor., <source>PLoS Genetics</source>, <volume>9</volume>:
<fpage>e1003735</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24086142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Escoufier</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1976</year>) <article-title>&#8216;A Unifying Tool for Linear
Multivariate Statistical Methods: The RV-Coefficient&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal
of Applied Statistics</source>, <volume>25</volume>: <fpage>257</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ronquist</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huelsenbeck</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>&#8216;MrBayes 3: Bayesian Phylogenetic
Inference Under Mixed Models&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Bioinformatics. Oxford,
England</source>, <volume>19</volume>:
<fpage>1572</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>4</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Epidemiology and
Prevention of Congenital Cytomegalovirus Infection and Disease: Activities of the
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention Workgroup&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal
of Womens Health</source> 2002, <volume>15</volume>:
<fpage>224</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubin</surname><given-names>R. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Indirect Effects of
Cytomegalovirus Infection on the Outcome of Organ Transplantation&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Journal of the American Medical Association</source>, <volume>261</volume>:
<fpage>3607</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2542634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sekulin</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Analysis of the Variability
of CMV Strains in the RL11D Domain of the RL11 Multigene Family&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Virus and Genes</source>, <volume>35</volume>:
<fpage>577</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>83</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Fast, Scalable Generation of
High&#8208;Quality Protein Multiple Sequence Alignments Using Clustal Omega&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Molecular Systems Biology</source>, <volume>7</volume>:
<fpage>539</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21988835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sijmons</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Ranst</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Genomic and Functional Characteristics
of Human Cytomegalovirus Revealed by Next-Generation Sequencing&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Viruses</source>, <volume>6</volume>:
<fpage>1049</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24603756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sijmons</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>&#8216;High-Throughput Analysis of
Human Cytomegalovirus Genome Diversity Highlights the Widespread Occurrence of
Gene-Disrupting Mutations and Pervasive Recombination&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal
of Virology</source>, <volume>89</volume>:
<fpage>7673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>95</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Linkage Disequilibrium &#8211; Understanding
the Evolutionary Past and Mapping the Medical Future&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Nature
Reviews Genetics</source>, <volume>9</volume>:
<fpage>477</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>L. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Genome of Murine
Cytomegalovirus Is Shaped by Purifying Selection and Extensive
Recombination&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Virology</source>, <volume>435</volume>:
<fpage>258</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23107009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2015</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Less Is More: An Adaptive
Branch-Site Random Effects Model for Efficient Detection of Episodic Diversifying
Selection&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and
Evolution</source>,:&#160;<fpage>msv022</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snydman</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Cytomegalovirus Immunoglobulins in the
Prevention and Treatment of Cytomegalovirus Disease&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Reviews of
Infectious Diseases</source>, <volume>12 Suppl 7</volume>:
<fpage>S839</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2173113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;RAxML-VI-HPC: Maximum Likelihood-Based
Phylogenetic Analyses With Thousands of Taxa and Mixed Models&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Bioinformatics</source>, <volume>22</volume>:
<fpage>2688</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>90</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16928733</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steininger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Clinical Relevance of Cytomegalovirus
Infection in Patients With Disorders of the Immune System</article-title>.&#8217;,
<source>Clinical Microbiology &amp; Infectious Diseases: Official Publication of the
European Society of Clinical Microbiology</source>, <volume>13</volume>:
<fpage>953</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>63</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steininger</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Cytomegalovirus Genotypes
Present in Cerebrospinal Fluid of HIV-Infected Patients&#8217;</article-title>, <source>AIDS
(London, England)</source>, <volume>19</volume>:
<fpage>273</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern-Ginossar</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Decoding Human
Cytomegalovirus&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Science</source>, <volume>338</volume>:
<fpage>1088</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23180859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suyama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Torrents</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>&#8216;PAL2NAL: Robust Conversion of Protein
Sequence Alignments Into the Corresponding Codon Alignments&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Nucleic Acids Research</source>, <volume>34</volume>:
<fpage>W609</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16845082</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sylwester</surname><given-names>A. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Broadly Targeted Human
Cytomegalovirus-Specific CD4+ and CD8+ T Cells Dominate The Memory Compartments Of
Exposed Subjects&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Experimental Medicine</source>,
<volume>202</volume>: <fpage>673</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16147978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B202"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Damme</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Loock</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Functional annotation of human
cytomegalovirus gene products: an update&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Frontiers in
Microbiology</source>, <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>218</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24904534</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walling</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Epstein&#8211;Barr virus
EBNA-2 Gene in Oral Hairy Leukoplakia: Strain Variation, Genetic Recombination, and
Transcriptional Expression&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Virology</source>,
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>7918</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7966582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watkins</surname><given-names>E. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Contrasting Within- and
Between-Host Immune Selection Shapes Neisseria Opa Repertoires&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Science Report</source>, [Internet] 4. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nature.com/srep/2014/141009/srep06554/full/srep06554.html">http://www.nature.com/srep/2014/141009/srep06554/full/srep06554.html</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>&#8216;A Case for the Ancient
Origin of Coronaviruses&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Journal of Virology</source>,
<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>7039</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23596293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosakovsky Pond</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Purifying Selection Can Obscure the
Ancient Age of Viral Lineages&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and
Evolution</source>, <volume>28</volume>:
<fpage>3355</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21705379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wertheim</surname><given-names>J. O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal/> (<year>2014</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Evolutionary Origins of
Human Herpes Simplex Viruses 1 and 2&#8217;</article-title>, <source>Molecular Biology and
Evolution</source>, <volume>31</volume>:
<fpage>2356</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24916030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weller</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>&#8216;The Role of DNA Recombination in
Herpes Simplex Virus DNA replication&#8217;</article-title>, <source>IUBMB Life</source>,
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14609200</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="vew017-B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>&#8216;Estimating Synonymous and
Nonsynonymous Substitution Rates Under Realistic Evolutionary Models&#8217;</article-title>,
<source>Molecular Biology and Evolution</source>, <volume>17</volume>:
<fpage>32</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10666704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>