<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?all-math-mml yes?><?use-mml?><?properties open_access?><?properties manuscript?><?origin nihpa?><?iso-abbr Stem Cell Res?><?submitter-system nihms?><?submitter-canonical-name Elsevier?><?submitter-canonical-id ELSEVIERAM?><?submitter-userid 8068823?><?submitter-authority myNCBI?><?submitter-login elsevieram?><?submitter-name Author support, Elsevier?><?domain nihpa?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-journal-id">101316957</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pubmed-jr-id">35616</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Stem Cell Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Stem Cell Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Stem cell research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1873-5061</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1876-7753</issn></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6317900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30312871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scr.2018.10.003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="manuscript">nihpa1516406</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Generation of an induced pluripotent stem cell line from an individual with a heterozygous RECQL4 mutation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>Brittany E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Mo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Linchao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Ruoji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Dandan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>Zijun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>An</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Donghui</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A6">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mata</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Weidong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>Weiya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>Pulivarthi H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Ruiying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hung</surname><given-names>Mien-Chie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A7">g</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A8">h</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Lisa L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">c</xref><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Dung-Fang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">b</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A9">i</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A10">j</xref><xref rid="CR2" ref-type="corresp">**</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>a</label>Department of Integrative Biology and Pharmacology, McGovern Medical School, The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, Houston, TX 77030, USA</aff><aff id="A2"><label>b</label>The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center UTHealth Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences, Houston, TX 77030, USA</aff><aff id="A3"><label>c</label>Department of Pediatrics, Baylor College of Medicine, Texas Children's Cancer and Hematology Centers, Houston, TX 77030, USA</aff><aff id="A4"><label>d</label>Department of Musculoskeletal Oncology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou 510080, PR China</aff><aff id="A5"><label>e</label>Department of Endocrinology, The First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou 510080, PR China</aff><aff id="A6"><label>f</label>Department of Pathophysiology, Zhongshan School of Medicine, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou 510080, PR China</aff><aff id="A7"><label>g</label>Department of Molecular and Cellular Oncology, The University of Texas M.D. Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX 77030, USA</aff><aff id="A8"><label>h</label>Graduate Institute of Biomedical Sciences and Center for Molecular Medicine, China Medical University, Taichung 404, Taiwan</aff><aff id="A9"><label>i</label>Center for Stem Cell and Regenerative Medicine, The Brown Foundation Institute of Molecular Medicine for the Prevention of Human Diseases, The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, Houston, TX 77030, USA</aff><aff id="A10"><label>j</label>Center for Precision Health, School of Biomedical Informatics and School of Public Health, The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, Houston, TX 77030, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. <email>llwang@txch.org</email> (L.L. Wang)</corresp><corresp id="CR2"><label>**</label>Correspondence to: Dung-Fang Lee, Department of Integrative Biology and Pharmacology, McGovern Medical School, The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston, Houston, TX 77030, USA. <email>dung-fang.lee@uth.tmc.edu</email> (D.-F. Lee).</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="nihms-submitted"><day>13</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>03</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>33</volume><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><!--elocation-id from pubmed: 10.1016/j.scr.2018.10.003--><permissions><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/BY-NC-ND/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/BY-NC-ND/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P1">The DNA helicase RECQL4 is known for its roles in DNA replication and repair. <italic>RECQL4</italic> mutations cause several genetic disorders including Rothmund-Thomson syndrome (RTS), characterized by developmental defects and predisposition to osteosarcoma. Here we reprogrammed fibroblasts with a heterozygous <italic>RECQL4</italic> mutation (c.1878 + 32_1878 + 55del24) to induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs). These iPSCs are pluripotent and are able to be differentiated into all three germ layers, providing a novel tool to further interrogate the role of RECQL4 DNA helicase <italic>in vitro</italic>.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><table-wrap id="T1" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><sec id="S1"><title>Resource utility</title><p id="P2">We have generated an iPSC line with a heterozygous <italic>RECQL4</italic> (c.1878 + 32_1878 + 55del24) mutation. This iPSC line will be useful to study the effects of aberrant RECQL4 protein on genomic stability.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Resource details</title><p id="P3">RECQL4, one of five human RecQ DNA helicases, is known as a guardian of the genome due to its function in multiple DNA metabolic processes, including DNA replication, recombination and repair (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Van Maldergem et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2017</xref>). Compound heterozygous or homozygous mutations in the <italic>RECQL4</italic> gene are responsible for the majority of cases of Rothmund-Thomson syndrome (RTS), an autosomal recessive disorder characterized by multiple clinical features including a poikilodermatous skin rash, small stature, skeletal dysplasias, and a striking risk for developing osteosarcoma (<xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">Van Maldergem et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">Lin et al., 2017</xref>). Here we have reprogrammed fibroblasts from an RTS heterozygous carrier of <italic>RECQL4</italic> mutation c.1878 + 32_1878 + 55del24, a 24 base pair deletion in intron 11 of the <italic>RECQL4</italic> gene (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1A</xref>). This mutation results in a shortened intron and has been shown to cause aberrant splicing leading to exon skipping (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">Wang et al., 2002</xref>; <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">Colombo et al., 2018</xref>). The resource we describe here will be useful in characterizing the role of RECQL4 in DNA damage repair and replication and provides a valuable tool for investigating the pathogenesis of osteosarcoma.</p><p id="P4">Fibroblasts were isolated from a punch biopsy taken from the arm of an individual with a heterozygous <italic>RECQL4</italic> (c.1878 + 32_1878 + 55del24) mutation. Primary fibroblasts were reprogrammed by Yamanaka four factors OCT4, SOX2, KLF4 and MYC using CytoTune-iPS Sendai Reprogramming kit. The emerged iPS clones were picked and cultured for approximately 15 passages. The iPS clone FCP351G exhibits hESC morphology which is evident by cell clusters with a dense, domed center and well-defined borders (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>, left panel, Scale bar, 250 &#956;m). PCR detection of exogenous <italic>OCT4, SOX2, KLF4</italic> and <italic>MYC</italic> in FCP351G iPSC line verified loss of Sendai virus and transgenes (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1C</xref>). PCR-based mycoplasma detection assay further validates FCP351G iPSCs are free of mycoplasma (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1D</xref>). The short tandem repeat (STR) profile of FCP351G iPSCs were identical to that of parental FCP351 fibroblasts (data available upon request). Immunofluorescence staining of FCP351G iPSCs demonstrated ubiquitous expression of pluripotency transcription factor NANOG, hESC surface markers SSEA-4 and TRA-1-81 (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1E</xref>, Scale bar, 75 &#956;m) and alkaline phosphatase (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1B</xref>, right panel, Scale bar, 100 &#956;:m). Examination of pluripotent gene expression by qRT-PCR showed that FCP351G iPSCs express pluripotency gene <italic>NANOG, OCT4, SOX2, DPPA4, REX1</italic> and <italic>TERT</italic> at a level equal to or greater than H1 hESCs, whereas FCP351 fibroblasts do not express these genes (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1F</xref>) Higher <italic>SOX2</italic> and <italic>TERT</italic> mRNAs in FCP351G iPSCs may reult from RECQL4 mutation-induced gene up-regulation. G-band karyotype analysis confirmed the normal karyotype of the FCP351G iPSCs (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1G</xref>). Teratoma assay indicates that FCP351 iPSCs are capable of differentiation to three germ layers including epithelium (endoderm), cartilage (mesoderm), and melanin (ectoderm) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1H</xref>), confirming their pluripotency. The characterization of the FCP351G iPSC line is summarized in <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p id="P5">In summary, FCP351G iPSCs are pluripotent and demonstrate a normal karyotype. FCP351G iPSCs provide a valuable cell resource to study RECQL4 function.</p></sec><sec id="S3"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="S4"><title>Cell culture</title><p id="P6">Fibroblasts were cultured in DMEM/F12 (Corning) supplemented with Glutamax (Thermo Fisher) and 10% FBS (GenDEPOT) at 37 &#176;C with 5% CO<sub>2</sub> after thawing until the cells were confluent. Cells were then passaged to six well plates, where they were grown to approximately 90% confluence. Cells were then reprogrammed with OCT4, SOX2, KLF4, and MYC using the CytoTune iPS 2.0 Sendai reprogramming kit (Life Technologies) according to manufacturer's instructions. Clones were picked and seeded in 96-well plates coated with Matrigel (Corning) using hESC medium supplemented with ROCK inhibitor Thiazovivin (Millipore). After one day of culture, the medium was replaced with StemMACS iPS-Brew XF media (Miltenyi Biotech). Following growth, these clones were passaged to a six well plate and cultured in the same manner for approximately 15 passages to ensure the removal of Sendai viruses.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>PCR, sequencing, and STR</title><p id="P7">Genomic DNA was isolated from one 10 cm dish of 80% confluent iPSCs according to protocol using the PureLink DNA Isolation kit (Invitrogen). PCR was performed using primers listed in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> and OneTaq polymerase (New England Biolabs). PCR reaction was performed according to the following protocol: 94 &#176;C for 1 min; 35 cycles of reaction: 94 &#176;C for 30 s, 56 &#176;C for 45 s and 68 &#176;C for 1 min; and 68 &#176;C for 5 min on a Biometra TRIO Thermal Cycler (Analytik Jena). Sanger sequencing was done by Eton Bioscience (San Diego, California). STR DNA fingerprinting was done by the CCSG-funded Characterized Cell Line Core Facility at the University of Texas M.D. Anderson Cancer Center. The STRs at 14 loci (AMEL, CSF1PO, D13S317, D16S539, D18S51, D21S11, D3S1358, D5S818, D7S820, D8S1179, FGA, TH01, TPOX and vWA) were assessed in the FCP351G iPSC line and original FCP351 fibroblast.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>qRT-PCR</title><p id="P8">RNA was isolated from cells grown to 85% confluency in 6 well culture dish using Trizol (Life Technologies) according to manufacturer's instructions. 4 &#956;g of RNA was used to make cDNA according to the reverse transcriptase protocol using iScript Reverse Transcription Supermix (BioRad). qPCR was then performed using primers described in <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> according to the protocol using iQ SYBR Green Supermix (Biorad) on a CFX96 machine (Bio-Rad). The reaction was performed according to the following parameters: 50 &#176;C for 10 min, 95 &#176;C for 5 min, 40 cycle of 95 &#176;C for 10 s and 60 &#176;C for 30 s, and 95 &#176;C for 10 min. Results were calculated using the &#916;&#916;CT method and were normalized to GAPDH expression and are displayed relative to hESC H1.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Mycoplasma testing</title><p id="P9">Mycoplasma detection was performed using PCR Mycoplasma Detection Kit (Applied Biological Materials Inc) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>Karyotyping</title><p id="P10">The cultures were harvested and G-banded using standard protocols. Clonal chromosomal changes identified by G-banding were described according to an International System for Human Cytogenetic Nomenclature ISCN (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">McGowan-Jordan &amp; An, n.d</xref>.). Twenty metaphase chromosome spreads at 400 band resolution were analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Immunofluorescent staining</title><p id="P11">iPSCs were grown to 70% confluence in 12 well plates, then fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde (Affymatrix) for 10 min. Cells were then washed 2 &#215; 500 &#956;L in wash buffer (PBS with 1% BSA (Fisher Scientific), followed by blocking with PBS with 10% donkey serum (Jackson ImmunoResearch Labs), 1% BSA, 0.3% Triton X-100 (Sigma) for 45 min. Cells were then incubated with primary antibody diluted in dilution buffer (PBS with 1%BSA, 1% donkey serum, 0.3% Triton X-100, and 0.01% sodium azide (Sigma) at 4 &#176;C overnight gently rocking. Cells were then washed twice. Where appropriate, secondary antibody was diluted in dilution buffer, then added to cells and incubated for 1 h at room temperature protected from light. This was followed by 2 more washes, then counterstain with DAPI diluted in dilution buffer. Cells were finally washed 2 times, then stored in PBS for visualization.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Alkaline phosphatase staining</title><p id="P12">iPSCs were grown to 70% confluence in 12 well plates, then fixed and stained using the Alkaline Phosphatase Staining Kit II (Stemgent) according to manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec id="S11"><title>Teratoma assay</title><p id="P13">Cells were grown in 10 cm dishes to 80% confluence. Cells were dissociated from the dish, then resuspended in phenol red-free Matrigel (Corning cat#354262). Immunodeficient NOD SCID mice (Charles River Laboratories) were injected subcutaneously with 2 &#215; 10<sup>7</sup> cells in each flank and observed for palpable teratoma formation. After approximately 6 weeks, teratomas were excised then fixed in 10% formalin (Sigma). Histology was performed by Histowiz (Brooklyn, New York).</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack id="S12"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="P14">B.E.J. is supported by Tzu Chi scholarship award for excellence (The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center UTHealth Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences). R.Z. is supported by UTHealth Innovation for Cancer Prevention Research Training Program Pre-doctoral Fellowship (Cancer Prevention and Research Institute of Texas grant RP160015) and Wei Yu Family Endowed Scholarship (The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center UTHealth Graduate School of Biomedical Sciences). J.T. and Z.H. are supported by the Ke Lin Program of the First Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-sen University. D.W. is supported by State-sponsored Joint Ph.D. Program from China Scholarship Council (201606380093). M.-C.H. is supported by NIHR01 CA211615. L.L.W. was supported by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Clinical Scientist Development Award, NIH-NICHD K08HD42136 and HD083092. D.-F.L. is the CPRIT scholar in Cancer Research and supported by NIH Pathway to Independence Award R00 CA181496 and CPRIT Award RR160019.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN1"><p id="P15">Conflict of interest</p><p id="P16">The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Colombo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cubells Sanchez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Elcioglu</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maystadt</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Esteve Martinez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sironi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finelli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gervasini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pecile</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larizza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <year>2018</year>
<article-title>Rothmund-Thomson syndrome: insights from new patients on the genetic variability underpinning clinical presentation and cancer outcome</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Mol. Sci</source>
<volume>19</volume> (<issue>4</issue>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms19041103</pub-id><comment>.</comment> Epub 2018/04/13. (PubMed PMID: 29642415; PMCID: PMC5979380).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jewell</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gingold</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <year>2017</year>
<article-title>Osteosarcoma: Molecular pathogenesis and iPSC modeling</article-title>. <source>Trends Mol. Med</source>
<volume>23</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>737</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>755</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molmed.2017.06.004</pub-id><comment>.</comment> (PubMed PMID: 28735817; PMCID: PMC5558609).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28735817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McGowan-Jordan</surname><given-names>JSA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>An</surname><given-names>Schmid M.</given-names></name>, <year>2016</year>
<source>International System for Human Cytogenetic Nomenclature (ISCN)</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Van Maldergem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larizza</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <year>2016</year>
<chapter-title>RECQL4-related recessive conditions</chapter-title> In: <source>Epstein's Inborn Errors of Development</source>. 3. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Oxford, England</publisher-loc>, pp. <fpage>1137</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1144</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Worley</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gannavarapu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chintagumpala</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plon</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Intron-size constraint as a mutational mechanism in Rothmund-Thomson syndrome</article-title>. <source>Am. J. Hum. Genet</source>
<volume>71</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>165</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>167</lpage>. Epub 2002/05/23. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/341234</pub-id> (PubMed PMID: 12016592; PMCID: PMC384974).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12016592</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p id="P17">Generation and characterization of FCP351G iPSCs. (A) Sanger sequence of RECQL4 Exons 11-12 depicting the deletion found in FCP351 fibroblasts and verified by Sanger sequencing (see chromatogram) in FCP351G iPSCs. (B) Cell morphology (left panel) and alkaline phosphatase staining (right panel) of the FCP351G line. Scale bar, 250 &#956;m (left) and 100 &#956;m (right). (C) PCR detection of exogenous OCT4, SOX2, KLF4 and c-MYC in FCP351G iPSCs. (D) Mycoplasma PCR assay in FCP351G iPSCs.(E) Immunofluorescence staining of pluripotency factor NANOG and hESC surface markers (SSEA4 and TRA-1-81) in the FCP351G line. Scale bar, 75 &#956;m. (F) qRT-PCR assay for the expression of endogenous pluripotency genes (NANOG, SOX2, OCT4, DPPA4, REX1, and TERT) in the FCP351G iPSCs. (G) A representative G-banded karyotype from iPSCs (FCP351G) showing 46, XX. (H) In vivo teratoma assay of the FCP351G iPSCs. Scale bar, 50 &#956;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihms-1516406-f0001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T2" position="float" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p id="P18">Characterization and validation.</p></caption></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T3" position="float" orientation="landscape"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p id="P19">Reagents details.</p></caption></table-wrap></floats-group></article>