<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6498646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5677</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-019-5677-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>New insights into the genome of <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Guevara</surname><given-names>Govinda</given-names></name><address><email>fguevara@ucm.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Castillo Lopez</surname><given-names>Maria</given-names></name><address><email>mariac01@ucm.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>Sergio</given-names></name><address><email>salonsou@igtp.cat</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>Juli&#225;n</given-names></name><address><email>jpererag@bio.ucm.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8181-3147</contrib-id><name><surname>Navarro-Llorens</surname><given-names>Juana Mar&#237;a</given-names></name><address><email>joana@bio.ucm.es</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2157 7667</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4795.f</institution-id><institution>Departamento de Bioqu&#237;mica y Biolog&#237;a Molecular, Facultad de Ciencias Biol&#243;gicas, </institution><institution>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, </institution></institution-wrap>Madrid, Spain </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Program of Predictive and Personalized Medicine of Cancer (PMPPC), Germans Trias i Pujol Research Institute (IGTP), Carretera de Can Ruti S/N 08916 Badalona, Barcelona, Spain </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>20</volume><elocation-id>332</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>14</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; The Author(s). 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1"><italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4, a strain isolated from a sewage sludge sample, is able to grow in minimal medium supplemented with several compounds, showing a broad catabolic capacity. We have previously determined its genome sequence but a more comprehensive study of their metabolic capacities was necessary to fully unravel its potential for biotechnological applications.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par2">In this work, the genome of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 has been re-sequenced, revised, annotated and compared to other bacterial genomes in order to investigate the metabolic capabilities of this microorganism. The analysis of the data suggests that <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 contains several putative metabolic clusters of biotechnological interest, particularly those involved on steroid and aromatic compounds catabolism.</p><p id="Par3">To demonstrate some of its putative metabolic abilities, <italic>R. ruber</italic> has been cultured in minimal media containing compounds belonging to several of the predicted metabolic pathways. Moreover, mutants were built to test the naphtalen and protocatechuate predicted catabolic gene clusters.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The genomic analysis and experimental data presented in this work confirm the metabolic potential of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4. This strain is an interesting model bacterium due to its biodegradation capabilities. The results obtained in this work will facilitate the application of this strain as a biotechnological tool.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s12864-019-5677-2) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd><italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic></kwd><kwd>Catabolism</kwd><kwd>Biodegradation</kwd><kwd>Genome analysis</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100010198</institution-id><institution>Ministerio de Econom&#237;a, Industria y Competitividad, Gobierno de Espa&#241;a</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>RTC-2014-2249-1</award-id><award-id>BIO2012-39695-CO2-01</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>Juli&#225;n</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#169; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par13"><italic>Rhodococci</italic> belong to the taxon of nocardioform actinomycetes. These aerobic Gram-positive bacteria are found in diverse environmental niches and are world-widely distributed being abundant in soil, water and marine environments [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. They differ from other Actinomycetes and are called the Mycolata because their distinctive cell envelope contains large branched chain lipids known as mycolic acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The genome size of these non-sporulating mycolic-acid-containing bacteria varied for different strains from 4.3&#8201;Mb (e.g. <italic>R. rhodnii</italic> strain LMG5362, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]) to 10.0&#8201;Mb (e.g. <italic>R. wratislaviensis</italic>, GCA_000583735.1).</p><p id="Par14"><italic>Rhodococci</italic> are known for displaying a wide metabolic versatility and for their ability to transform a varied range of pollutants such as aliphatic and aromatic hydrocarbons, oxygenated and halogenated compounds, nitroaromatics, heterocyclic compounds, nitriles, and various pesticides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The analysis of their genomes has revealed a multiplicity of genes, a high genetic redundancy of metabolic pathways, and a complex regulatory network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Moreover, some <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains harbor circular and linear plasmids that contain genes encoding additional catabolic enzymes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Even the extracellular polysaccharides of the outer membrane of rhodococci contribute to the catabolism of aromatic compounds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. This versatile metabolic capacity and also their environmental persistence and tolerance to stress conditions make <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains good candidates for biotechnological processes such as bioremediation, biotransformations or biocatalysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. On the other hand, <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains are able to synthesize compounds of industrial interest including biosurfactants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and steroid precursors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. For all these reasons, the characterization of different <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> metabolic capabilities is necessary to fully exploit their biotechnological potential.</p><p id="Par15"><italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4, isolated from a sewage sludge sample, is classified as a Gram-positive bacteria belonging to the actinobacteria taxon with a high guanine-cytosine content [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. This strain is able to grow in minimal medium supplemented with several aromatic compounds, showing a broad catabolic capacity. We have recently published the draft genome sequence of this bacterium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The analysis of the genomic sequence of different bacterial species, i.e. the presence of specific genes or gene families, allows inferring their particular metabolic capabilities. In this work we present novel and more comprehensive results, both computational and experimental, that support the versatile metabolic potential of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Bacterial strains and culture conditions</title><p id="Par16">The bacterial strains and plasmids used in this work are listed in Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par17"><italic>E. coli DH5&#945;</italic> was purchased to Thermo Fisher Scientific<italic>. E. coli GM48</italic> was obtained from the <italic>E. coli</italic> Genetic Resources Collection (CGSC5127 number) and <italic>E. coli S17.1</italic> was obtained from the ATCC Bacteriology Collection (ATCC 47055 number). <italic>Rhodococcus ruber strain Chol-4,</italic> a strain isolated from a sewage sludge sample [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], and their derived mutants have been obtained in our laboratory.</p><p id="Par18"><italic>Escherichia coli</italic> cells were grown at 37&#8201;&#176;C in Luria Bertani (LB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> and its derived mutant strains were routinely grown in LB or minimal medium (Medium 457 of the DSMZ, Braunschweig, Germany) containing the desired carbon and energy source under aerobic conditions at 30&#8201;&#176;C in a rotary shaker (250&#8201;rpm) for 1&#8211;3&#8201;days. Where appropriate, antibiotic were added at the following concentrations: ampicillin (100&#8201;&#956;g/mL), nalidixic acid (15&#8201;&#956;g/mL) or kanamycin (25&#8211;50&#8201;&#956;g/mL for <italic>E. coli</italic> or 200&#8201;&#956;g/mL for <italic>Rhodococcus</italic>). For the growth experiments, a LB pre-grown culture was washed two times with minimal medium prior to inoculation of 10&#8201;mL of fresh minimal medium (initial DO<sub>600nm</sub>&#8201;=&#8201;0.05) supplemented with an organic compound as only source of energy and carbon. Volatile compounds such as indane, tetralin, isopropanol, 1,3-butanediol, 2,3-butanediol, xylene, benzene, ethylbenzene, toluene, phenylacetic acid or styrene were provided supplied in gas phase via saturated atmosphere (Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>). Aromatic compounds were used at 1&#8201;mg/mL of naphthalene in powder, 10&#8201;mM sodium benzoate, 2&#8201;mM phenol, 5&#8201;mM&#8201;L-tryptophan, 4&#8201;mM vanillic acid, 4&#8201;mM gentisate, 5&#8201;mM homogentisate, 2&#8201;mM catechol, 2.2&#8201;mM cholic acid, 2&#8201;mM DHEA and 10&#8201;mM protocathecuate, 15&#8201;mM biphenyl, 20&#8201;mM phthalate, 5&#8201;mM 2-aminobenzoate, from 2 to 4&#8201;mM salicylic acid, 0.5&#8201;mM hydroxyquinol or 2&#8201;mM&#8201;L-tyrosine. DHEA (dehydroepiandrosterone) and cholic acid were previously dissolved in 16.5&#8201;mM methyl-&#946;-cyclodextrin to form inclusion complexes following a modification of a previously reported method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and prepared as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]<italic>.</italic> Although it is not necessary to add methyl-&#946;-cyclodextrin to dissolve cholic acid at the concentrations employed in our experiments, we have used them in the cholic acid growth experiments to homogenize the experimental conditions for compounds with similar structures (e.g. steroids). Biological replicas (2 to 5 replicates) were performed for all growth experiments.</p><p id="Par19">Competent and electrocompetent cells of <italic>E. coli</italic> were prepared and transformed as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Selection of transformed cells was carried out in LB agar plates supplemented with appropriate antibiotics.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>DNA manipulation and sequencing</title><p id="Par20">Chromosomal DNA extraction from <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 was performed using the Cetyl Trimethyl Ammonium Bromide procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Briefly, bacterial cells were collected from a LB plate, resuspended in 400&#8201;&#956;L Tris-EDTA buffer (10&#8201;mM Tris/HCl, pH&#8201;8, 1&#8201;mM EDTA) and incubated at 80&#8201;&#176;C for 20&#8201;min. Then, 50&#8201;&#956;L of lysozyme (100&#8201;mg/mL) was added and incubated at 37&#8201;&#176;C for 12&#8201;h. Afterwards, 70&#8201;&#956;L of 10% SDS and 5&#8201;&#956;L of proteinase K (10&#8201;mg/mL) were added and the sample was incubated for 10&#8201;min at 65&#8201;&#176;C. Proteins were precipitated with 100&#8201;&#956;l of 5&#8201;M NaOH and 100&#8201;&#956;l CTAB (0.1&#8201;g/ml resuspended in 0.7&#8201;M NaOH) for 10&#8201;min at 65&#8201;&#176;C. DNA was purified by extraction with chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (24:1) and phenol-chloroform-isoamyl alcohol (25:24:1) and precipitated with 0.6 vol of isopropanol at room temperature for 30&#8201;min. After centrifugation, DNA was washed with 70% ethanol and resuspended in sterile water.</p><p id="Par21">Manipulation of genomic DNA was carried out according to standard protocols [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and the extracted DNA was purified three times to achieve highest purity and quality for subsequent sequencing of the complete genome.</p><p id="Par22">Two independent NGS experiments were combined to generate this new version of the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 de novo genomic assembly. One was previously performed using Roche 454 technology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A new one based on massively parallel pyrosequencing of the genomic DNA was done by Biejing Genomics Institute, BGI - Hong Kong Laboratory (Hong Kong, China), using Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform. A 500&#8201;bp short-insert library was constructed and a 91 PE sequencing was used as strategy. Before data delivery, Incoming Quality Control and three levels of Quality Control processes (e.g. GC content and depth correlative analysis) were performed by BGI.</p><p id="Par23">The program SPAdes v3.1.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] was employed to assemble the reads. This assembler accepts different formats for the input sequences (Fasta, FastaQ, single-end, pair-end, etc.), thus allowing the combination of sequences generated by different sequencing platforms. Four large sequences previously generated in our lab by conventional cloning and Sanger sequencing (JQ083440.1, JQ083439.1, EU878550.1 and FJ842098.2) were entered as trusted contigs (&#8722;-trusted-contigs flag), Illumina reads as paired-reads and Roche reads as unpaired. To reduce the number of mismatches and short indels, mismatch corrector was run after the initial assembly by specifying the flag --careful in the SPAdes command. The quality assessment of the genome assembly was done using QUAST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Manual curation of the assembly was subsequently carried out in order to reduce the number of contigs, based on their length, the G&#8201;+&#8201;C content and sequence similarity of the generated contigs with other known species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Mutagenesis of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</title><p id="Par24">Unmarked gene deletions were carried out as described previously in <italic>R. erythropolis</italic> SQ1 involving conjugative transfer of a mutagenic plasmid carrying the <italic>sacB</italic> selection system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Specific sets of primers were designed from the up and downstream sequences of each cluster (ketoadipate and naphtalen pathway). Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplicons were obtained from isolated <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 genomic DNA. Primers and conditions employed in the experiments are summarized in Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media">3</xref>. To facilitate cloning, the primer sequences included restriction sites: the ketoadipate cluster contained <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Xba</italic>I for the up fragment, and <italic>Xba</italic>I-<italic>Hin</italic>dIII for the down fragment; the naphtalen cluster contained <italic>Xho</italic>I<italic>-Hind</italic>III and <italic>Xba</italic>I-<italic>Hin</italic>dIII for the up and down fragment, respectively.</p><p id="Par25">PCR amplicons (up and down fragments) were first cloned separately into pGEM-T-Easy vectors and then combined in order to get an <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Hin</italic>dIII and <italic>Xho</italic>I-<italic>Hind</italic>III fragments containing a truncated cluster. Transformation into <italic>E.coli</italic> GM48 was necessary in order to avoid dam methylation of the <italic>Xba</italic>I site. The <italic>Eco</italic>RI-<italic>Hind</italic>III and <italic>Xho</italic>I-<italic>Hind</italic>III inserts, containing the fused up and down fragments, were transferred to pK18mobsacB plasmid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] to construct the mutagenic plasmid pK18(U&#8201;+&#8201;D) used for the partial deletion of the corresponding cluster from <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 chromosome.</p><p id="Par26">Every mutagenic plasmid was introduced into <italic>E. coli</italic> S17.1 and mobilized to <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 by conjugation as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. <italic>R. ruber</italic> transconjugants that had integrated the plasmid by homologous recombination were selected on LB plates supplemented with nalidixic acid. The cluster fragment deletion was achieved as a result of a second spontaneous homologous recombination process within the genome of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4. Colony PCR detection was performed to confirm the deletion in the <italic>nar</italic> and <italic>pca</italic> clusters in the mutant <italic>R. ruber</italic> strains.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Genome analysis and annotation</title><p id="Par27">Homology searches were performed using the BLAST server of the NCBI (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi">http://blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Blast.cgi</ext-link>). The annotation of the genome was carried out using the GenBank tool PGAP and the on-line service RAST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rast.nmpdr.org/">http://rast.nmpdr.org/</ext-link>). The complete genome sequence has been deposited at GenBank under accession number NZ_ANGC00000000.2. The program Circos was used to visualize genomic data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Pulsed field gel electrophoresis (PFGE)</title><p id="Par28">PFGE was performed from 10&#8201;mL of a cell culture grown at OD<sub>600nm</sub> of 0.8&#8211;1.0. Cells were collected by centrifugation and suspended in 0.5&#8201;mL of cell suspension solution (10&#8201;mM Tris-HCl pH&#8201;7.2, 20&#8201;mM NaCl, 100&#8201;mM EDTA). Plugs containing the cells were prepared with 1.5% agarose, placed in lysis buffer (1&#8201;mg/mL lysozyme, 10&#8201;mM Tris-HCl pH&#8201;7.2, 50&#8201;mM NaCl, 100&#8201;mM EDTA, 0.2% DOC, 0.5% N-laurylsarcosine sodium salt, 0.06&#8201;g/L RNase) and incubated for 1&#8201;h at 37&#8201;&#176;C with soft shaking. Lysis was followed by two washes in 20&#8201;mM Tris-HCl pH&#8201;8 and 50&#8201;mM EDTA. The plugs were placed in 3&#8201;mL proteinase solution (1&#8201;mg/mL proteinase K, 100&#8201;mM EDTA pH&#8201;8.0, 1% N-lauryilsarcosine sodium salt, 0.2% DOC) and incubated with gently shaken at 42&#8201;&#176;C for 18&#8201;h. After removing the proteinase solution, 9&#8201;mL TE containing 40&#8201;&#956;g/mL PMSF were added and kept at 50&#8201;&#176;C for one hour, repeating the whole process two times. After washing twice for 15&#8201;min in 20&#8201;mM Tris-HCl pH&#8201;8, 50&#8201;mM EDTA the DNA in plugs was resolved by PFGE on a contour-clamped homogeneous electric field II Mapper system (Bio-Rad Laboratories) in 0.5&#215; Tris-borate-EDTA and the following running conditions: 6&#8201;V/cm for 18&#8211;24&#8201;h at 13&#8201;&#176;C, with a 50-s switch time. Gels were stained in Gel Red solution (5&#8201;min) and photographed under UV light.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Phytosterol consumption followed by mass spectrometry- high performance liquid chromatography (MS-HPLC)</title><p id="Par29"><italic>R. ruber</italic> was grown at 30&#8201;&#176;C with 200&#8201;rpm shaking, in 25&#8201;mL of minimal medium (M457 of the DSMZ, Braunschweig, Germany) supplemented with a mixture of industrial phytosterols in powder (around 0.7&#8201;mg/mL), kindly given by Gadea S.A. Two mL aliquots were collected at different times and 1&#8201;mg of pregnenolone was added as internal control of the extraction. The steroid fraction was extracted twice with 2&#8201;mL of chloroform. HPLC and MS determination was carried out in the Chromatography Service of the Biological Research Center (&#8220;Centro de Investigaciones Biol&#243;gicas&#8221; CIB-CSIC). The relative peak area was calculated as the ratio between the HPLC peak area obtained for each phytosterol (brassicasterol, campesterol, stigmasterol and &#946;-sitosterol) and the peak area of pregnenolone used as internal control. The experiment was done twice.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>General genome features</title><p id="Par30"><italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 genome was sequenced using two different Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) technologies. First, a genomic library was generated and sequenced in a Roche 454 GS FLX instrument. After quality filtering and adapter clipping, this library rendered 242,042 reads with an average length of 400&#8201;bp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. A second library was independently generated and processed by pair-end sequencing in an Illumina HiSeq 2000 instrument (see methods). This library generated 2,782,965 pair end reads of 90&#8201;bp with an average fragment size of 500&#8201;bp between pairs. Single-reads from the 454 library and pair-end reads from the Illumina library were combined with four larger sequences (6.3 to 11.7 Kb) that we previously obtained by standard cloning and Sanger sequencing (GenBank accession numbers JQ083440.1, JQ083439.1, EU878550.1 and FJ842098.2). All the sequences were assembled using SPAdes de novo assembler v3.1.0 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. The initial assembly generated 129 sequence scaffolds between 128&#8201;bp and 1,025,475&#8201;bp covering 5.63&#8201;Mb, with N50 of 438,623&#8201;bp and L50 of 4). These scaffolds were named successively according to their length, being Scaffold_001 the longest and Scaffold_129 the shortest (Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM4" ref-type="media">4</xref>). This nomenclature was maintained in the final version of the assembly uploaded to GenBank (NZ_ANGC00000000.2). The vast majority (<italic>n</italic>&#8201;=&#8201;126) of these scaffolds were composed of a single sequence <italic>contig</italic> with no internal gaps. Hence, for all practical purposes, &#8216;scaffold&#8217; and &#8216;<italic>contig&#8217;</italic> denominations would be interchangeable in this work. To streamline the final assembly, twenty scaffolds shorter than 500&#8201;bp, and covering less than 3.5&#8201;kb in total, were discarded. Of the remaining 109 scaffolds, 65 (161.2&#8201;kb) exhibited a G&#8201;+&#8201;C content below 55%, and sequence similarity to plasmid vectors and genomes from unrelated species. These scaffolds presumably originated from cross-contamination of the NGS experiments, where several libraries were sequenced in parallel in the same flow cell, and therefore they were removed from the final assembly. The remaining 44 scaffolds of the final assembly exhibited a high G&#8201;+&#8201;C content (70.7%) typical of Rhodococci, and very high sequence similarity to other <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> genomes. These 44 scaffolds covered 5.46&#8201;Mb with N50 of 438,623&#8201;bp, L50 of 4, and an average read depth above 100X. These sequences are available from the NCBI GenBank database under the accession numbers NZ_ANGC00000NNN.1, where NNN indicates the scaffold number. We provide a more detailed report of the assembly in Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media">5</xref>.</p><p id="Par31">Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a shows the DNA sequence similarity between <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome and <italic>R. pyridinivorans</italic> SB3094 (GenBank: NC_023150.1), one of its closest relatives. The figure provides an approximation of how the <italic>R. ruber</italic> contigs might be arranged along its genome assuming a high degree of synteny with <italic>R. pyridinovorans</italic>. No evidence of circular plasmids in the genome of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 was found by pulsed-field gel electrophoresis. However, some genetic elements present in other <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> plasmids were found interspersed along the Chol-4 genome (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Sequence homology of the 44 scaffolds of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 genome assembly (in orange) with the genome of closely related <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> bacteria. In <bold>a</bold> the comparison with the chromosome of its closest relative, <italic>R. pyridinivorans</italic> (in purple). <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 scaffolds are ordered and oriented according to their probable genomic location assuming a high level of synteny between these two microorganisms. The internal blue edges indicate regions of sequence homology above 70% with a minimum length of 0.5&#8201;kb. Scaffold order and orientation were computed to minimize de number of cross-overs among edges. In <bold>b</bold> comparison with the chromosomes and extrachromosomic elements of <italic>R. pyridinivorans</italic> (purple), <italic>R. equi</italic> (green)<italic>, R.jostii</italic> (red) <italic>and R. opacus</italic> (blue). This color code is also use for the internal edges indicating regions of sequence homology above 70% with a minimum length of 0.5&#8201;kb. For simplicity, only the homology with extrachromosomal elements is shown. <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 genome scaffolds are ordered according to their length. Many of the sequences found in the large plasmids pPYR02 (<italic>R. pyridinovorans</italic>), pVAPA1037 (<italic>R. equi</italic>), pRHL1&#8211;3 (<italic>R. jostii</italic>) and pROB01&#8211;02 (<italic>R. opacus</italic>), are also present in the genome of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4. In both A and B, the small font numbers outside the scaffolds indicate their internal coordinate, in kb. The large font numbers indicate the chromosome, plasmid or scaffold names as they appear in the original GenBank entries</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Annotation of <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</title><p id="Par32">Genome annotation using RAST server [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] identified 5049 coding sequences and 59 RNAs. 53 out of the 59 RNAS are tRNAs representing 43 different anticodons are encoded in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> genome (Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). There were at least 7 tRNAs in multicopy: tRNA<sup>Met</sup> (ATG) is present in 4 copies, tRNA<sup>Gly</sup> (GGC) in 3 copies and tRNA<sup>Val</sup> (GTC), tRNA<sup>Glu</sup> (GAG), tRNA<sup>Ala</sup> (GCC), tRNA<sup>Asp</sup> (GAC) and tRNA<sup>Leu</sup> (CTC) in 2 copies. The codon usage correlated with the high G&#8201;+&#8201;C content of this strain as G&#8201;+&#8201;C codons are predominant in this organism (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media">6</xref>). Codons that have a T at the third position lacked a cognate tRNA in <italic>R. ruber</italic> with the single exception of Arg (CGT).</p><p id="Par33">The number of tRNAs was similar to others <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains that display a median value of 53 tRNAs although there are exceptions such as <italic>R. rhodnii</italic> ASM72037v1 that contains 69 tRNAs (EMBL: NZ_JOAA00000000.1). The genomic assembly revealed a single <italic>rrn</italic> operon located in the NZ_ANGC02000002.1 contig containing the genes for 16S, 23S and 5S rRNA.</p><p id="Par34">The 4861 protein-coding detected ORFs covered nearly 91% of the genome. Among the coding sequences, the analysis revealed at least 129 genes related to the metabolism of aromatic compounds: 15 of them involved in peripheral degradation pathways (quinate, benzoate and <italic>p</italic>-hydroxibenzoate degradation), 15 genes related to the aromatic amine catabolism and 6 genes associated with the gentisate degradation pathway. A small number of genes were involved in the resistance to antibiotics (resistance to vancomycin, fluoroquinolones, &#946;-lactamase), while a relatively large number of genes were related to the resistance to toxic compounds, such as mercury and arsenic.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Mobile elements</title><p id="Par35">Within the genome of the strain Chol-4 we found a few mobile elements (Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media">7</xref>), some of them remaining as pseudogenes. Surprisingly, 25% of these mobile elements were concentrated in a 120&#8201;kb region of NZ_ANGC020000011.1 contig.</p><p id="Par36"><italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome had two copies of IS<italic>1164</italic> from the IS<italic>256</italic> transposase family (the prototype of a major family of bacterial insertion sequence elements) in NZ_ANGC02000007.1 contig. This element has also been found in other <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. In the same contig there were two genes (D092_RS18300 and D092_RS17945) coding for an identical protein keeping a 90&#8211;92% base identity with elements of <italic>Rhodococcus pyridinivorans</italic> SB3094 plasmid (CP006997.1) and with elements of the pNSL1 plasmid (KJ605395.1) from <italic>Rhodococcus sp.</italic> NS1. Both genes share 84% identity with a transposase of <italic>Mycobacterium sp.</italic></p><p id="Par37">Other two IS elements, described for some <italic>Rhodocococcus,</italic> were absent in this genome: the IS<italic>2112</italic> element belonging to the IS<italic>110</italic> family found in <italic>R. rhodochrous</italic> NCIMB 13064 and related to genome rearrangements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and the IS<italic>1166</italic> element from the IS<italic>256</italic> family, found in <italic>R. erythropolis</italic> IGTS8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>].</p><p id="Par38">Apart from those derived of mobile elements, strain Chol-4 contains many different recombinases with different putative roles (Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM8" ref-type="media">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Other genetic elements</title><p id="Par39">Some actinobacteria such as <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> contain from 1 to 3 clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPR) elements (CRISPR database, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://crispr.i2bc.paris-saclay.fr/crispr/">https://crispr.i2bc.paris-saclay.fr/crispr/</ext-link>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. However, <italic>R. ruber</italic> apparently is a strain devoid of detectable CRISPRs systems, similarly to other <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains. On the other hand, we found a gene cluster related to specialized protein degradation systems that includes a 20S proteasome activity (subunits &#945; and &#946;), an ATPase (that use ATP to unfold proteins and translocate them into the proteasome) and a system of tagging proteins for degradation with Pup prokaryotic ubiquitin-like protein. Conjugation with Pup serves as a signal for degradation by the mycobacterial proteasome (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Most of the restriction modification systems detected in this genome are classified as type I or IV (Additional&#160;file&#160;<xref rid="MOESM9" ref-type="media">9</xref>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Pup proteasome in <italic>R. ruber</italic>. Abbreviations: <italic>recB</italic>: RecB family exonuclease; <italic>pimt:</italic> protein-L-isoaspartate methyltransferase; <italic>pan</italic>: bacterial proteasome-activating AAA-ATPase; <italic>pafA</italic>: proteasome accessory factor, Pup ligase PafA&#8217; paralog, possible component of postulated heterodimer PafA-PafA&#8217;; <italic>pup:</italic> prokaryotic ubiquitin-like protein Pup; <italic>protA</italic> and <italic>protB</italic>: proteasome subunit &#945; and &#946; bacterial; <italic>dgk</italic>: diacylglycerol kinase; <italic>deoR</italic>: putative DeoR-family transcriptional regulator; <italic>pafC</italic>: DNA-binding protein; <italic>tatA</italic> and <italic>tatC</italic>: twin-arginine translocation proteins; <italic>hel</italic>: DEAD/DEAH box helicase; <italic>yfcD</italic>: nudix hydrolase YfcD; <italic>kpr</italic>: 2-dehydropantoate 2-reductase. All <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 genes have the prefix &#8220;RHA1_&#8221; not included in the figure</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Aromatic compounds specific gene clusters</title><p id="Par40">The <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome annotation revealed the presence of a rich set of gene cluster that may code for several aromatic compounds catabolic pathways, reflecting a high potential for degrading this kind of compounds. The catabolism of aromatic compounds proposed for <italic>R. ruber</italic> is outlined in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> showing the peripheral, central and basic pathways.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Aromatic compounds metabolism. Scheme of the aromatic compounds catabolic pathways: <bold>I)</bold> &#946;-ketoadipate pathway, <bold>II)</bold> phenylacetate pathway, <bold>III)</bold> 2-hydroxypentadienoate pathway, <bold>IV)</bold> gentisate pathway, <bold>V)</bold> homogentisate pathway), <bold>VI)</bold> hydroxyquinol pathway, <bold>VII)</bold> homoprotocatechuate pathway, and <bold>VIII)</bold> a pathway found in <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 comprising a hydroxylase, an extradiol dioxygenase, and a hydrolase. Peripheral pathways are depicted outside the external ring. The &#8220;X&#8221; indicates the inability of <italic>R. ruber</italic> to grow in the presence of these compounds as single source of carbon and energy</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Central pathways</title><p id="Par41">There are eight central aromatic pathways chromosomally encoded in <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 and <italic>R. opacus</italic> B4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and 7 of them are found in <italic>R. ruber</italic>: 1) the &#946;-ketoadipate or ortho-cleavage pathway encoded by the <italic>pca</italic> and <italic>cat</italic> genes and responsible for the conversion of catechol and protocatechuate into acetyl-CoA and succinyl-CoA by intradiol cleavage of the catecholic intermediate (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> I); 2) the phenylacetate pathway encoded by the <italic>paa</italic> genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], that takes part in the catabolism of a variety of compounds, including homophthalate, tropate and phenylalkanoates. This pathway was not found in <italic>R. ruber</italic>); 3) the 2-hydroxypentadienoate pathway that transforms 2-hydroxypentadienoates into acetyl-CoA and pyruvate through the successive action of a hydratase, an aldolase and a dehydrogenase (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> III) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]; 4) the gentisate pathway encoded by the <italic>genABC</italic> gene cluster that converts gentisate to pyruvate and fumarate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> IV) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]; 5) the homogentisate pathway encoded by the <italic>hmgABC</italic> genes that involves the extradiol cleavage of homogentisate, followed by a C-C bond hydrolysis to finally yield fumarate and acetoacetate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> V) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]; 6) the hydroxyquinol pathway responsible of an intradiol-type cleavage of 4-hydroxysalicylate/hydroxyquinol leading to aceyl-CoA and succinyl-CoA (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> VI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]; 7) the homoprotocatechuate pathway encoded by the <italic>hpc</italic> genes and involved in the extradiol-type cleavage of homoprotocatechuate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> VII); 8) lastly, a putative metabolic pathway for an unknown substrate that would be made up of a hydroxylase, an extradiol dioxygenase and a hydrolase (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> VIII) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>].<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Gene clusters putatively involved in aromatic compounds catabolism identified in <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 and its comparison with <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1. Abbreviations: <bold>I</bold>) ketoadipate pathway: <italic>catR</italic>: transcriptional regulator CatR; <italic>catA</italic>: catechol 1,2 dioyxigenase; <italic>catB</italic>: muconate cycloisomerase; <italic>catC</italic>: mucolactone isomerase; <italic>pcaJ</italic>: succinyl-CoA:3-ketoacid-coenzyme A transferase subunit B; <italic>pcaI</italic>: succinyl-CoA:3-ketoacid-coenzyme A transferase subunit A; <italic>pcaH</italic>: protocatechuate 3,4-dioxygenase &#946; chain; <italic>pcaG</italic>: protocatechuate 3,4-dioxygenase &#945; chain; <italic>pcaB</italic>: 3-carboxy-cis,cis-muconate cycloisomerase; <italic>pcaL</italic>: 4-carboxymuconolactone decarboxylase; <italic>pcaR</italic>: Pca regulon regulatory protein; <italic>pcaF</italic>: &#946;-ketoadipyl-CoA thiolase. <bold>III</bold>) 2-hydroxypentandienoate pathway: <italic>nit</italic>: nitrilotriacetate monooxy7genase component B; <italic>xylF</italic>: 2-hydroxymuconic semialdehyde hydrolase; <italic>hsaE</italic>: 2-hydroxypentadienoate hydratase; <italic>hsaG</italic>: acetaldehyde dehydrogenase, acetylating, it is found in gene cluster for degradation of phenols, cresols, catechol; <italic>hsaF</italic>: 4-hydroxy-2-oxovalerate aldolase; <italic>hyd</italic>: hydroxylase; <italic>bphC</italic>: 2,3-dihydroxybiphenyl 1,2-dioxygenase; <italic>hsd4B</italic>: enoyl-CoA hydratase; <italic>kstD</italic>: 3-ketosteroid-&#916;<sup>1</sup>-dehydrogenase. <bold>IV</bold>) gentisate pathway: <italic>3hb6h</italic>:3-hydroxybenzoate 6-hydroxylase; <italic>benK</italic>: benzoate MFS transporter; <italic>genR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (IclR family); <italic>genA</italic>: gentisate 1,2-dioxygenase; <italic>genB</italic>: fumarylpyruvate hydrolase; <italic>genC</italic>: maleylpyruvate isomerase, mycothiol-dependent; <italic>xylF</italic>: 2-hydroxymuconic semialdehyde hydrolase; paa-oxy: 4-hydroxyphenylacetate 3-monooxygenase; <italic>oxo-red</italic>:3-oxoacyl-[acyl-carrier protein] reductase; <italic>xylE</italic>: catechol 2,3-dioxygenase; <italic>retron</italic>: retron-type RNA-directed DNA polymerase. <bold>V</bold>) homogentisate pathway: <italic>lp</italic>: uncharacterized protein Rv2599/MT2674 precursor; lipoprotein; <italic>hmgR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (MarR family); <italic>hmgA</italic>: homogentisate 1,2-dioxygenase; <italic>hmgB</italic>: fumarylacetoacetate hydrolase; <italic>ech</italic>: enoyl-CoA hydratase; <italic>acs:</italic> acetoacetyl-CoA synthetase, long-chain-fatty-acid-CoA ligase. <bold>VI</bold>) hydroxyquinol pathway: <italic>sh</italic>: salicylate hydroxylase; <italic>lCoA</italic>: long chain fatty acid CoA ligase; <italic>ad</italic>: acyl dehydratase; <italic>fm</italic>: FAD-binding monoxigenase; <italic>dh</italic>: iron-containing alcohol dehydrogenase; <italic>dxnF</italic>: hydroxyquinol 1,2-dioxygenase. <bold>VII</bold>) homoprotocatechuate pathway: <italic>xylE, hsaG, hsaF</italic> are previously described; <italic>chdh</italic>: 5-carboxymethyl-2-hydroxymuconate semialdehyde dehydrogenase; <italic>scdh</italic>: putative short chain dehydrogenase; <italic>tau</italic>: 4-oxalocrotonate tautomerase; <italic>nit</italic>: NADH-FMN oxidoreductase-nitrilotriacetate monooxygenase component B; <italic>hpa</italic>: 4-hydroxyphenylacetate 3-monooxygenase. <bold>VIII</bold>) A central pathway with an unknown substrate described in <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1: <italic>duf1486:</italic> protein of unknown function DUF1486 (probable NADH dehydrogenase/NAD(P)H nitroreductase); <italic>acDH</italic>: acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, type 2, C-terminal domain; <italic>dbps</italic>:3,4-dihydroxy-2-butanone 4-phosphate synthase /GTP cyclohydrolase II; <italic>ox:</italic> NADH-FMN oxidoreductase; <italic>dhbdII</italic>: biphenyl-2,3-diol-1,2-dioxygenase II (2,3-dihydroxybiphenyl dioxygenase <bold>II</bold>); <italic>hpcE</italic>: possible fumarylacetoacetate hydrolase; <italic>hyd</italic>: FAD-binding monooxygenase (PheA/TfdB family), conserved hypothetical hydroxylase, similar to 2,4-dichlorophenol 6-monooxygenase; <italic>syn</italic>: acetoacetyl-CoA synthetase; <italic>asnC</italic>: transcriptional regulator (AsnC family); <italic>pyrDH</italic>: pyruvate dehydrogenase E1 component. All <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 genes have the prefix &#8220;RHA1_&#8221; not included in the figure</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Peripheral pathways</title><p id="Par42">Some of the above aromatic compounds are intermediates in the degradation pathways of other more complex compounds that are also growing substrates of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 and whose catabolic pathways meet those previously presented as central pathways. The Chol-4 genes encoding the putative necessary enzymatic activities of these peripheral pathways are described below.</p><p id="Par43">Gene clusters <italic>ben</italic>, <italic>cat</italic> and <italic>pca</italic> (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>i and Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a) could be involved in the benzoate degradation. Isopropylbenzene degradation genes were found in a gene cluster in NZ_ANGC02000001.1 contig, and also in a different gene cluster in NZ_ANGC02000021.1 contig (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). In Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c some of the steroid catabolic gene clusters contained in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> genome are depicted. Transport systems related to steroid molecules are also of interest and therefore mammalian cell entry (MCE) systems that have been associated with steroid transport [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] were searched through the genomic data. Figure&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> collects all the MCE systems found in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> genome.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Peripherical routes in <italic>R. ruber</italic>. Abbreviations: <bold>a</bold> Benzoate degradation: <italic>red</italic>: flavin reductase; <italic>pvcC</italic>: pyoverdin chromophore biosynthetic protein; <italic>benR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (AraC family); <italic>cypX</italic>: cytochrome P450 monooxygenase; <italic>cypY</italic>: putative phenol hydroxylase; <italic>benA</italic>: benzoate 1,2-dioxygenase &#945; subunit; <italic>benB</italic>: benzoate 1,2-dioxygenase &#946; subunit; <italic>benC</italic>: benzoate dioxygenase, ferredoxin reductase component/1,2-dihydroxycyclohexa-3,5-diene-1-carboxylate dehydrogenase; <italic>benD</italic>: 1,2-dihydroxycyclohexa-3,5-diene-1-carboxylate dehydrogenase; <italic>benK</italic>: benzoate MFS transporter; <italic>luxR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (luxR family) putative.; <italic>ben</italic>: benzoate transport protein. <bold>b</bold> Isopropylbenzene pathway: <italic>ipbA4</italic>: ferredoxin reductase; <italic>bphD:</italic> 2-hydroxy-6-oxo-2,4-heptadienoate hydrolase; <italic>bphC</italic>: 2,3-dihydroxybiphenyl 1,2-dioxygenase; <italic>ipbA1</italic>: isopropylbenzene 2,3-dioxygenase or IPB-dioxygenase, ISP large subunit; <italic>ipbA2</italic>: IPB-dioxygenase (ISP small subunit); <italic>ipbA3</italic>: IPB-dioxygenase ferredoxin; <italic>hcaB</italic>: hydroxybenzaldehyde dehydrogenase<italic>; hsaF, hsaG; hsaE</italic>: previously described (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>); <italic>iclR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (IclR family); <italic>kin</italic>: sensor kinase; <italic>st</italic>: sterol-binding domain protein; <italic>dapA</italic>: 4-hydroxy-tetrahydrodipicolinate synthase. <bold>c</bold> Steroids pathway: <italic>syn</italic>: non-ribosomal peptide synthetase; <italic>kstD</italic>: 3-oxosteroid 1-dehydrogenase; <italic>kshA</italic>: ketosteroid-9-&#945;-hydroxylase, oxygenase; <italic>hyd</italic>: hydroxylase; <italic>hsaC</italic>: 2,3-dihydroxybiphenyl 1,2-dioxygenase; <italic>iclR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (IclR family); <italic>padR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (PadR family); <italic>ntaA</italic>: nitrilotriacetate monooxygenase component B; <italic>chnB</italic>: cyclohexanone monooxygenase; <italic>hsaA</italic>: flavin-dependent monooxygenase; <italic>hsaD</italic>: 2-hydroxy-6-oxo-6-phenylhexa-2,4-dienoate hydrolase; <italic>hsaC</italic>: iron-dependent extradiol dioxygenase; <italic>hsaB</italic>: flavin-dependent monooxygenase reductase subunit; <italic>sc-DH</italic>: short-chain dehydrogenase; <italic>hsa</italic>: monooxygenase; <italic>tetR</italic>: probable transcriptional regulator (TetR family); <italic>tran</italic>: acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase; <italic>dh</italic>: acyl-CoA dehydrogenase; <italic>fadA</italic>: 3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase; <italic>hsd17b4</italic>: 3-&#945;,7-&#945;,12-&#945;-trihydroxy-5-&#946;-cholest-24-enoyl-CoA hydratase; <italic>thio</italic>: thioesterase. <bold>d</bold> Vanillate: <italic>padR</italic>: transcriptional regulator (PadR family); <italic>vanA</italic>: vanillate <italic>o</italic>-demethylase oxygenase subunit, flavodoxin reductases (ferredoxin-NADPH reductases) family 1; <italic>vanB</italic>: vanillate <italic>o</italic>-demethylase oxidoreductase; <italic>pcaK</italic>: 4-hydroxybenzoate transporter; mt:methyltransferase. <bold>e</bold> Naphtalen. (<italic>nar</italic> genes<italic>: R. opacus</italic> plasmid pROB02:AP011117): <italic>narR1</italic> and <italic>narR2</italic>: putative naphthalene degradation regulatory protein; <italic>narAa</italic>: nidA, naphthalene dioxygenase large subunit; <italic>narAb</italic>: (nidB) naphthalene dioxygenase small subunit; <italic>narB</italic>: (nidC) 1,2-dihydro-1,2-dihydroxynaphthalene dehydrogenase; <italic>narC</italic>: (nidD) putative aldolase NarC. <bold>f</bold> Acetophenone carboxylase (anaerobic): <italic>apc1&#8211;4</italic>: acetophenone carboxylase subunits; <italic>fisR</italic>: transcriptional regulato (Fis family). <bold>g</bold> Aminoacid: <italic>iorAB</italic>: indolepyruvate ferredoxin oxidoreductase (&#945; and &#946; subunits); <italic>pdh</italic>: glutamate / leucine / phenylalanine / valine dehydrogenase; <italic>asnC</italic>: transcriptional regulator (AsnC family). All <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 genes have the prefix &#8220;RHA1_&#8221; not included in the figure</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p><italic>Mce</italic> systems in <italic>R. ruber</italic>. Abbreviations: <bold>a</bold>
<italic>red</italic>: enoyl-[acyl-carrier-protein] reductase [FMN]; <italic>hyd</italic>: enoyl-CoA hydratase; <italic>fadD5</italic>: long-chain fatty-acid-CoA ligase, <italic>Mycobacterial</italic> subgroup FadD5; <italic>yrbE1A</italic>: conserved hypothetical integral membrane protein YrbE1A (ABC-transporter permease); <italic>yrbE1B</italic>: conserved hypothetical integral membrane protein YrbE1B (ABC-transporter permease); <italic>mce1A-D</italic>: MCE-family protein MceA-D; <italic>mce1E</italic>: MCE-family lipoprotein LprK (MCE-family lipoprotein Mce1e); <italic>mceF</italic>: MCE family protein of Mce F Subgroup; <italic>mp</italic>: membrane protein. <bold>b</bold>
<italic>l10p</italic>: LSU ribosomal protein L10p (P0); <italic>l7/l12</italic>: LSU ribosomal protein L7/L12 (P1/P2); <italic>met-ABC</italic>: methionine ABC-transporter ATP-binding protein (<italic>npd</italic>:2-nitropropane dioxygenase, NPD). <bold>c</bold>
<italic>reg</italic>: possible transcriptional regulatory protein; <italic>fadD17</italic>: long-chain fatty-acid-CoA ligase (<italic>Mycobacterial</italic> subgroup FadD17); <italic>fadE27</italic>: butyryl-CoA dehydrogenase; <italic>fadE26</italic>: acyl-CoA dehydrogenase (<italic>Mycobacterial</italic> subgroup FadE26); <italic>fdx</italic>: ferredoxin; <italic>fabG</italic>: 3-ketoacyl-ACP reductase (hsd4A); <italic>supA</italic> and <italic>supB</italic>: ABC-transporter permease; <italic>ts-reg:</italic> two-component system response regulator; <italic>tps</italic>: &#945;,&#945;-trehalose-phosphate synthase [UDP-forming]; <italic>npd</italic>: acyl-CoA synthetase; <italic>epi</italic>: epimerase, dihydroflavonol-4-reductase. All <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 genes have the prefix &#8220;RHA1_&#8221; not included in the figure</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p id="Par44">A putative gene cluster for vanillate degradation was found in <italic>R. ruber</italic> genome (GenBank: Y11521, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d). Probably involved in naphtalene catabolism, a <italic>nar</italic> gene cluster containing two regulatory genes, <italic>narR1</italic> belonging to the GntR family and NarR2 of the NtrC family of enhancer-binding proteins has been also found in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). NZ_ANGC02000009.1 contig (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>f) contained a putative anaerobic degradation gene cluster for an acetophenone carboxylase activity. There was also another cluster containing a phenylalanine dehydrogenase putatively involved in amino acid catabolism (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>g).</p><p id="Par45">Other gene clusters that occur in related bacteria were not found in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome, such as the <italic>bph</italic> cluster for biphenyl catabolism, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and the <italic>pad</italic> cluster for phthalate catabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Growth in different organic compounds</title><p id="Par46">In order to determine the growth capabilities of <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4, we analyzed its ability to use several compounds as sole energy and carbon source (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Growth of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 wild type on minimum medium with different carbon sources</p></caption></table-wrap></p><p id="Par47">The growth curves of <italic>R. ruber</italic> with some of the metabolizable compounds (sodium benzoate, cholic acid, gentisate, naphthalene or DHEA as sole carbon source) are shown in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Growth curves of <italic>R. ruber</italic> WT in minimal medium 457 supplemented with cholic acid, sodium benzoate, gentisate or DHEA. In the case of cholic acid and DHEA 16.5&#8201;mM cyclodextrins were present in the medium to increase the solubility of the compounds (no growth when using only cyclodextrins was observed). <italic>R. ruber</italic> was also grown in minimal medium 457 supplemented with naphthalene in powder (1&#8201;mg/mL). Data of 3&#8211;4 independent experiments are depicted. The standard error of the mean was calculated by GraphPad Prism 5.0</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p><p id="Par48"><italic>R. ruber</italic> was isolated by its capacity to degrade steroid compounds like cholesterol. In this work, its growth capabilities using other steroids of interest such as plant sterols was investigated. Cells were grown on minimal medium supplemented with a mix of phytosterols (plant sterols that included brassicasterol, campesterol, stigmasterol and &#946;-sitosterol) as only source of energy and carbon. The sterol consumption was followed by HPLC. The results proved that sterol concentration was reduced to 5% of the initial value (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p><italic>R. ruber</italic> phytosterols comsumption. The strain was inoculated in minimal medium 457 supplemented with a mixture of phytosterols added in powder (brassicasterol, campesterol, stigmasterol and &#946;-sitosterol). The panel shows the consumption of each compound (y-axis, relative peak area) versus the time since the phytosterol addition to the medium (x-axis). The relative peak area is the ratio between the HPLC peak obtained for each phytosterol and the peak of pregnenolone used as internal control. A representative experiment is shown</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Mutant construction</title><p id="Par49">Unmarked gene deletions were carried out in the <italic>pca</italic> and <italic>nar</italic> gene clusters of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 to verify the involvement of these genes in the growth of protocatechuate and naphthalene, respectively. A scheme of the introduced deletions is depicted in Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> A. Mutants were confirmed by PCR and growth experiments proved that <italic>nar R. ruber</italic> mutants lost the ability to grow on naphthalene; similarly, <italic>pca R. ruber</italic> mutants were not able to grow on protocatechuate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> B).<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p><italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> mutants. <bold>a</bold> Scheme of <italic>R. ruber</italic> deletion <italic>pca</italic> mutant and <italic>nar</italic> mutant<bold>. b</bold> Growth of <italic>R. ruber</italic> on minimal medium supplemented with 10&#8201;mM PCA or naphthalene in powder (1&#8201;mg/mL), respectively. WT: wild type; <italic>pca</italic> mutant (3, 4 and 5) and <italic>nar</italic> mutant (1&#8211;3); control: non-existent growth in the absence of inoculum</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p><p id="Par50">On the other hand, the growth of the <italic>nar</italic> and <italic>pca R. ruber</italic> mutants was also checked with different carbon sources (Table&#160;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The <italic>nar</italic> mutant could grow in all alternative substrates tested. The <italic>pca</italic> mutant, however, lost the capability to grow in vanillate.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Growth of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 mutants on minimum medium with different carbon sources</p></caption><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Naph</italic> Naphthalen 7&#8201;mM, <italic>Benz</italic> Benzoate 10&#8201;mM, <italic>L-Tryp</italic> L-tryptophan 5&#8201;mM, <italic>Cat</italic> Catechol 10&#8201;mM, <italic>Homog</italic> Homogentisate 2&#8201;mM, <italic>Gen</italic> Gentisate 4&#8201;mM, <italic>PCA</italic> Protocatechuic acid 10&#8201;mM, <italic>Chol</italic> Cholic acid 2.2&#8201;mM, <italic>Vanill</italic> Vanillic acid 4&#8201;mM</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec20"><title>General genome features</title><p id="Par51">The sequence data employed in this study is the integrated results of two independent sequencing experiments (NCIB database: NZ_ANGC00000000.2). In this work, we present a more comprehensive genomic analysis on this revised sequence, and a comparative analysis with other already described <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> genome sequences. The published genome size of different <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> is in the range of 3.9 to 10&#8201;Mb. This large difference in genome size could be related both to the presence of large plasmids and to the extensive genome instability that occurs in several <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The genome of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 is 5.4&#8201;Mb long, a size close to <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> genome average size (5.69&#8201;Mb: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/13525">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/genome/13525</ext-link>) and quite similar to the <italic>R. equi</italic> ATCC 33707 (5.2&#8201;MB), <italic>R. pyridinivorans</italic> SB3094 (5.6&#8201;Mb), <italic>R. aetherivorans</italic> or <italic>R. fascians</italic> A44A (both with 5.9&#8201;Mb) genome.</p><p id="Par52">The analysis of the genomic data suggests that <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 contains several putative metabolic gene clusters of biotechnological interest, particularly those involved in the catabolism of aromatic compounds (clusters related to the metabolism of benzoate, vanillate, naphtalen, gentisate, etc.) and steroids (for instance, clusters related to cholesterol catabolism) supporting its potential as a model organism for studying aromatic molecules and steroid biodegradation.</p><p id="Par53">Rhodococci are very interesting microorganisms because of their ability to degrade a broad spectrum of aromatic molecules, which are structures very difficult to catabolize and widely distributed in the biosphere. In <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains, the catabolism of aromatic compounds is organized in a modular way that includes peripheral, central and basic pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). In the peripheral pathways, aromatic compounds (e.g. biphenyl and phthalate) are converted into specific intermediates (e.g. catechol and phenylacetate) that, in turn, are used in central aromatic pathways to produce a set of common intermediates (e.g. tricarboxylic acid cycle metabolites) that finally are substrates for the basic pathways (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. This kind of organization has been previously named catabolon in other organisms, such as <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p><p id="Par54">The central aromatic pathways constitute a catabolic core present in most rhodococci. <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome contains 7 out of the 8 central aromatic pathways described in both <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 and <italic>R. opacus</italic> B4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) being absent only the phenylacetate pathway. This pathway seems to be characteristic of larger genomes as most of the smallest <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> genomes (<italic>R. equi</italic>, <italic>R. aetherivorans</italic> and <italic>R. pyridinivorans</italic> among them) lack also the phenylacetate pathway. However, other pathways such as the genes encoding the gentisate, the homoprotocatechuate and the named VIII pathways found in RHA1 are absent in at least two <italic>R. erythropolis</italic> strains: PR4 and SK121 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Therefore, although most of the aromatic central pathways are conserved within rhodococci, there are metabolic differences among species that could be related to their genome size.</p><p id="Par55">On the other hand, some of the genes detected in the central pathways are redundant in the genome of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4. Apart from certain enzymatic activities such as KstD and Ksh isoforms previously described in this strain within the steroids catabolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>],there are also redundant clusters in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> genome such as 3 copies of <italic>pcaJ-pcaI</italic> involved in the catechol and protocatechuate pathways of the &#946;-ketoadipate and leucine catabolism that encodes a succinyl-CoA: 3-ketoacid-coenzyme A transferase (EC 2.8.3.5) in NZ_ANGC02000003.1 (D092_RS10690-RS10695), NZ_ANGC02000026.1 (D092_RS24595-RS24600) and NZ_ANGC02000008.1 (D092_RS18665-RS18670) contigs with an amino acid identity of 66&#8211;73% among them and the 2 copies of the <italic>hsaEGF</italic> cluster (NZ_ANGC02000004.1 contig; Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> III) with an amino acid identity of 65&#8211;78% belonging to the 2-hydroxypentanodienoate pathway. Gene redundancy in Rhodocci in both catabolic and anabolic pathways is proposed to facilitate high metabolic versatility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>&#8211;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] or as a mechanism to increase their potential to adapt to new carbon sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p><p id="Par56">More complex aromatic compounds are partially degraded in the peripheral pathways until they reach one of the intermediates that are substrates of the central aromatic pathways. The number of peripheral pathways present in every Rhodococcus species is variable, probably related with the genomic size or the plasmid content.</p><p id="Par57">In <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> the pathways related to the catabolism of benzoate, isopropylbenzene, vanillate, napthalen and steroids, among others has been identified. The benzoate clusters <italic>ben</italic>, <italic>cat</italic> and <italic>pca</italic>, are present in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome closely located and organized in a similar way to that in <italic>R. jostii</italic> RHA1 (Figs. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. <italic>Rhodococcus jostii</italic> strain RHA1 catabolizes benzoate via the cathecol pathway that includes a ring-hydroxylating oxygenase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. The cathecol and the protocatechuate branches of the &#946;-ketoadipate pathway converge at the &#946;-ketoadipate enol-lactone in this strain.</p><p id="Par58">In <italic>R. ruber</italic>, the genes encoding the isopropylbenzene catabolic pathway are located in NZ_ANGC02000001.1 and NZ_ANGC02000021.1 contigs (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). This aromatic hydrocarbon compound is a constituent in crude oil and refined fuels. The isopropylbenzene gene cluster <italic>ipbA1A2A3A4C</italic> codes for a reductase (<italic>ipbA4</italic>), a ferredoxin (<italic>ipbA3</italic>), a dioxygenase (<italic>ipbA1A2</italic>) and a 3-isopropylcatechol-2,3-dioxygenase (<italic>ipbC</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>].</p><p id="Par59">A gene cluster for vanillate catabolism is found in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome (GenBank: Y11521, Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>d) and it is similar to the gene loci <italic>vanA</italic> and <italic>vanB</italic> of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. strain HR199. Vanillate is a lignin-derived methoxylated monocyclic aromatic compound whose catabolism proceeds via protocatechuate in <italic>Comamonas testosteroni</italic> strain BR6020 and in <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. strain HR199 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</p><p id="Par60">The naphtalene-involved <italic>nar</italic> gene cluster found in <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e) is similar to the cluster present in the plasmid pROB02 of <italic>Rhodococcus opacus</italic> B4 (NC_012521). In <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain NCIMB 12038 and <italic>Rhodococcus opacus</italic> R7 the activities proposed to be encoded in the <italic>nar</italic> cluster are: i) a gentisate 1,2-dioxygenase that converts gentisate into maleylpyruvate; ii) a mycothiol-dependent maleylpyruvate isomerase that catalyzes the isomerization of maleylpyruvate to fumarylpyruvate; and iii) a fumarylpyruvate hydrolase that hydrolyzes fumarylpyruvate to yield fumarate and pyruvate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. The gentisate degradation pathway is shared by both the naphthalene and the 3-hydroxybenzoate catabolism. The <italic>nar</italic> gene cluster presents a diverse genetic organization with different kind of regulators among <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].Among the genes involved in the last pathway, the dioxygenase <italic>thnA1234</italic> cluster could correspond to the isopropylbenzene <italic>ipb1234</italic> cluster found in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> genome (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b). Therefore, naphthalene could be catabolized in <italic>R. ruber</italic> via either the <italic>nar</italic> genes or the isopropylbenzene cluster.</p><p id="Par61"><italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> contains many related-steroid clusters (Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c and Fig.&#160;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). We previously reported other steroid clusters, conferring the ability to grow in different steroids (such as cholesterol, cholestenone, testosterone, 1,4-adrostadien-3,17-dione or 4-7adrostene-3,17-dione), and the role of some enzymes such as ketosteroid dehydrogenases, ketosteroid 9-&#945; hydroxylases and cholesterol oxidase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>].</p><p id="Par62">Rhodococci are so broadly known as competent steroid degraders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>] that they could be considered as the steroid-consumer strains by excellence. The cholesterol catabolic pathway has been widely studied, revealing a notable complexity in part due to the existence of alternative pathways and the diversity of the enzymes involved. As steroid intermediates are highly appreciated in the pharmaceutical industries, the steroid catabolic capacity of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 represents a promising biotechnological platform for the production of steroid drugs.</p><p id="Par63">The steroid degradation genes are generally organized within large gene clusters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>] and this seems also to be the case in <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4. For instance, the cholate catabolic gene cluster found in RHA1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>] is also present in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). Other steroid genes, encompassing the MCE systems, are involved in steroid transport in actinobacteria. Every MCE system is an ATP-binding cassette transporter comprising more than eight distinct proteins. The number of MCE systems could vary among bacteria: from 4 in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> H37Rv to 6 in <italic>M. smegmatis</italic>. The MCE4 system of <italic>Rhodococcus jostii</italic> RHA1 or <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic> has been proved to be an active uptake system that requires ATP to transport steroids such as cholesterol, 5-&#945;-cholestanol, 5-&#945;-cholestanone or &#946;-sitosterol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The other <italic>mce</italic> operons could be involved in the cell envelope structure maintenance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. We found three MCE systems in <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). One of them, lying in NZ_ANGC02000015.1 contig, exhibited the higher similarity with the <italic>mce4</italic> system of RHA1. Consequently, we propose that this MCE system would be related to steroid transport.</p><p id="Par64">On the other hand, although <italic>R. ruber</italic> can grow on cholate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], no ORFs similar to the RHA1 cholate transport system, i.e. the ABC-transporter <italic>CamABCD</italic> ro04888 to ro04885 and <italic>CamM</italic> ro05792 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>] were detected. This suggest that cholate transport systems could differ within <italic>Rhodoccus</italic> species.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Experimental analysis of <italic>R. ruber</italic> catabolic capabilities</title><p id="Par65">The growth results were in accordance with the theoretical data from the identification of gene clusters within the genome of <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> Chol-4. For instance, the failure to grow on volatile compounds (benzene, toluene, etc.) could be explained by the absence of specific clusters involved in the catabolism of these compounds.</p><p id="Par66">However, there were some interesting exceptions: <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 did not grow on hydroxyquinol despite the fact that the pathway VI genes are present in its genome (see Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). It neither grew on salicylate, although up to two putative salicylate hydroxylases (EC 1.14.13.1) were found in its genome (D092_RS04015 in NZ_ANGC02000001.1 contig and D092_RS16585 NZ_ANGC02000006.1 contig).</p><p id="Par67">Some interesting observations were revealed by the in vitro growth experiments. <italic>R. ruber</italic> grew on benzoate, catechol and protocatechuic acid. Therefore, the catabolism of benzoate could take place via the cathecol pathway through a ring-hydroxylating oxygenase as it has been proposed for RHA1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. On the other hand, <italic>R. ruber</italic> grew on naphthalene as sole organic substrate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> and Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). As stated before, two different pathways for naphthalene catabolism have been described in <italic>Rhodococci</italic> to date, one relying on the <italic>nar</italic> cluster and the other relying on the isopropylbenzene cluster (<italic>ipb</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], both converging on salicylate which is subsequently hydroxylated to gentisate. Thus, the fact that <italic>R. ruber</italic> grew in naphthalene and gentisate, but not in salicylate, was perplexing, and suggested that the intake of this compound might be hampered or, a more provoking hypothesis, that this strain catabolizes naphthalene through an alternative pathway that would not involve salicylate as intermediate. More studies should be taken to elucidate this apparent paradox.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Mutant construction</title><p id="Par68">In order to check the functionality of several of the pathways putatively identified in <italic>R. ruber</italic> two groups of genes were deleted. On one hand, protocatechuate 3,4-dioxygenase &#945; chain (<italic>pcaG</italic>) and the 3-carboxy-cis,cis-muconate cycloisomerase (<italic>pcaB</italic>) genes of the cluster related to the protocatechuic acid pathway were deleted (Figs.&#160;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>I). Th<italic>e R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 <italic>pca</italic> mutants were not able to grow on protocatechuate (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>) showing that the <italic>pca</italic> gene cluster is directly involved in the metabolism of protocatechuate. The growth on vanillate also resulted to be dependent on the <italic>pca</italic> cluster in this strain (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). A RHA1 <italic>pc</italic>a mutant also failed to grow on vanillate as the sole organic substrate suggesting that this substrate is degraded via the &#946;-ketoadipate pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>]. On the other hand, deletion of the naphthalene dioxygenase <italic>nar</italic> genes led to the loss of growth on naphthalene (Figs. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e). Therefore, the <italic>nar</italic> gene cluster is responsible of the naphthalene catabolism in <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4, while the <italic>ipb</italic> gene cluster is not involved in that degradation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par69">In summary, the analysis of the <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 genome substantiated its relevance as a model organism for studying steroid and aromatic compounds biodegradation. The agreement between gene clusters found in the genome and the growth results of <italic>R. ruber</italic> has been established. <italic>R. ruber</italic> is able to grow in minimal medium with steroids (e.g. cholesterol, phytosterols, DHEA), bile acids (cholic acid) or several aromatic compounds (e.g. benzoate, naphthalene, gentisate) as the only source of carbon and energy. Deeper studies on Chol-4 degradation capabilities based on the construction of some mutants revealed that the <italic>nar</italic> gene cluster is indeed involved in the naphthalene catabolism in <italic>R. ruber</italic>, while the <italic>pca</italic> gene cluster is responsible of the metabolism of both protocatechuate and vanillate.</p><p id="Par70">Our results confirm and reinforce the biotechnological interest of <italic>R. ruber</italic> strain Chol-4 due to its metabolic potential that opens a great variety of applications as, for instance, its use in the bacterial transformation of steroids to produce pharmaceutically active steroid drugs. Further studies will be focused in exploring <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 novel potential biotechnological applications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec24"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S1.</bold> Bacterial strains and plasmids used in this work. (DOCX 17 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM2_ESM.jpg"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Growth in gas phase via saturated atmosphere. (JPG 88 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM3_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 3:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S2.</bold> Primers used in this work. (DOCX 13 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM4"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM4_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 4:</label><caption><p><bold>Figure S1.</bold> Sequence length vs GC content of the 129 scaffolds obtained in the initial assembly of <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome. (DOCX 428 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM5"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM5_ESM.pdf"><label>Additional file 5:</label><caption><p>Quast genome assembly evaluation. (PDF 30 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM6"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM6_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 6:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S3.</bold> Anticodons encoded in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome. (DOCX 20 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM7"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM7_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 7:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S4.</bold> List of mobile elements found in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome. (DOCX 25 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM8"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM8_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 8:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S5.</bold> List of recombinases identified in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome. (DOCX 19 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM9"><media xlink:href="12864_2019_5677_MOESM9_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 9:</label><caption><p><bold>Table S6.</bold> List of restriction modification systems identified in the <italic>R. ruber</italic> Chol-4 genome. (DOCX 18 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CRISPR</term><def><p id="Par5">Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DHEA</term><def><p id="Par6">Dehydroepiandrosterone</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HPLC</term><def><p id="Par7">High performance liquid chromatography</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LB</term><def><p id="Par8">Luria Bertani</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MCE</term><def><p id="Par9">Mammalian cell entry system</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NGS</term><def><p id="Par10">Next Generation Sequencing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p id="Par11">Open reading frame</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCR</term><def><p id="Par12">Polymerase chain reaction</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ack><p>We are very grateful to Jose Luis Garcia (CIB) for sharing his broad knowledge and support and to Laura Fern&#225;ndez de las Heras for her help at the initial stages of this work.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par71">This work has been supported by projects RTC-2014-2249-1 and BIO2012&#8211;39695-CO2&#8211;01 from MINECO, Spain. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par72">The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. The whole Genome Shotgun projects are linked to BioProjects PRJNA224116 and PRJNA176883. The Whole Genome Shotgun projects have been deposited at DDBJ/EMBL/GenBank under the accession number NZ_ANGC00000000. The version described in this paper is NZ_ANGC00000000.2.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#8217; contributions</title><p>JMN, JP and GG conceived and designed the experiments. GG and MCL made the mutants. GG, MCL and JMN made the growth experiments. SA, GG, JMN and JP analyzed the genomic data. SA contributed with analysis tools to this work. GG, SA, JMN and JP contributed to the writing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors have declared that they have no competing interests exist.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#8217;s Note</title><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finnerty</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology and genetics of the genus <italic>Rhodococcus</italic></article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.46.100192.001205</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1444254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sutcliffe</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dover</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Rhodococcal cell envelope: composition, organisation and biosynthesis</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Pachebat JA, van Keulen G, Whitten MM, Girdwood S, Del Sol R, Dyson PJ, Facey PD. Draft genome sequence of <italic>Rhodococcus rhodnii</italic> strain LMG5362, a symbiont of <italic>Rhodnius prolixus</italic> (<italic>Hemiptera, Reduviidae, Triatominae</italic>), the principle vector of <italic>Trypanosoma cruzi</italic>. Genome Announc. 2013;1(3):e00329-13. 10.1128/genomeA.00329-13.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuyukina</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivshina</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Application of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> in bioremediation of contaminated environments</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Biology of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic>, vol. 16</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>De Keyser</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>De Backer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon-Mateo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalkus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertry</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ardiles-Diaz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>De Rycke</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vandeputte</surname><given-names>OM</given-names></name><name><surname>El Jaziri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>pFiD188, the linear virulence plasmid of <italic>Rhodococcus fascians</italic> D188</article-title><source>Mol Plant-Microbe Interact</source><year>2012</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>637</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI-08-11-0215</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22482837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Masai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of the 450-kb linear plasmid in a polychlorinated biphenyl degrader, <italic>Rhodococcu</italic>s sp. strain RHA1</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>2021</fpage><lpage>2028</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.5.2021-2028.2001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11319076</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulakova</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Stafford</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulakov</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plasmid pRTL1 controlling 1-chloroalkane degradation by <italic>Rhodococcus rhodochrous</italic> NCIMB13064</article-title><source>Plasmid.</source><year>1995</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/plas.1995.1022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7568468</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunairi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Urai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Anzai</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular polysaccharides of <italic>Rhodococcus rhodochrous</italic> S-2 stimulate the degradation of aromatic components in crude oil by indigenous marine bacteria</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>2337</fpage><lpage>2343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.68.5.2337-2343.2002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mart&#237;nkov&#225;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhnakova</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Patek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesvera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kren</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodegradation potential of the genus <italic>Rhodococcus</italic></article-title><source>Environ Int</source><year>2009</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envint.2008.07.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18789530</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yam</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adventures in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> - from steroids to explosives</article-title><source>Can J Microbiol</source><year>2011</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/W10-115</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21358756</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuyukina</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ivshina</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Rhodococcus</italic> biosurfactants: biosynthesis, properties, and potential applications</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garc&#237;a</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Uh&#237;a</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catabolism and biotechnological applications of cholesterol degrading bacteria</article-title><source>Microb Biotechnol</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>699</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-7915.2012.00331.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22309478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#225;ndez de Las Heras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#237;a Fern&#225;ndez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro Llorens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drzyzga</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Morphological, physiological, and molecular characterization of a newly isolated steroid-degrading actinomycete, identified as <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</article-title><source>Curr Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>548</fpage><lpage>553</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00284-009-9474-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19688376</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fern&#225;ndez de las Heras L, Alonso S, de la Vega de Leon A, Xavier D, Perera J, Navarro Llorens JM. Draft genome sequence of the steroid degrader <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4. Genome Announc. 2013;1(3):e00215-13. 10.1128/genomeA.00215-13.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sambrook</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsch</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name><name><surname>Maniatis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular cloning: a laboratory manual</source><year>1989</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimpl</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahrenholz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alteration of the myometrial plasma membrane cholesterol content with b-cyclodextrin modulates the binding affinity of the oxytocin receptor</article-title><source>Biochemistry.</source><year>1995</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>13784</fpage><lpage>13793</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bi00042a009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7577971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#225;ndez de las Heras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mascaraque</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#237;a Fernandez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Llorens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drzyzga</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ChoG is the main inducible extracellular cholesterol oxidase of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain CECT3014</article-title><source>Microbiol Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>166</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micres.2010.05.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20630728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#225;ndez de las Heras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Geize</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Drzyzga</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Maria Navarro Llorens</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of three 3-ketosteroid-Delta (1)-dehydrogenase isoenzymes of <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2012.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22771584</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nurk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Antipov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dvorkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulikov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesin</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nikolenko</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Pham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Prjibelski</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title><source>J Comput Biol</source><year>2012</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/cmb.2012.0021</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saveliev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyahhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tesler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>QUAST: quality assessment tool for genome assemblies</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2013</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1072</fpage><lpage>1075</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btt086</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23422339</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Geize</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hessels</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name><name><surname>van Gerwen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Meijden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijkhuizen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Unmarked gene deletion mutagenesis of <italic>kstD</italic>, encoding 3-ketosteroid Delta1-dehydrogenase, in <italic>Rhodococcus erythropolis</italic> SQ1 using <italic>sacB</italic> as counter-selectable marker</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2001</year><volume>205</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2001.tb10947.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11750802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schafer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalinowski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thierbach</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Puhler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small mobilizable multi-purpose cloning vectors derived from the <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> plasmids pK18 and pK19: selection of defined deletions in the chromosome of <italic>Corynebacterium gluta</italic>micum</article-title><source>Gene.</source><year>1994</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(94)90324-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8045426</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krzywinski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Birol</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Connors</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gascoyne</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Horsman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marra</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1639</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.092759.109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19541911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aziz</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartels</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>DeJongh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Disz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Formsma</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerdes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Glass</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The RAST server: rapid annotations using subsystems technology</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-9-75</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18261238</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kulakov</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Poelarends</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of IS2112, a new insertion sequence from <italic>Rhodococcus</italic>, and its relationship with mobile elements belonging to the IS110 family</article-title><source>Microbiology.</source><year>1999</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>561</fpage><lpage>568</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/13500872-145-3-561</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10217489</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denome</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and activity of two insertion sequence elements in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain IGTS8</article-title><source>Gene.</source><year>1995</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(95)00241-W</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7642133</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Botelho</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Canto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Leao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats (CRISPRs) analysis of members of the <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> complex</article-title><source>Methods Mol Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>1247</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/978-1-4939-2004-4_27</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25399110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bode NJ, Darwin KH. The Pup-Proteasome System of Mycobacteria. Microbiol Spectr. 2014; 2(5). 10.1128/microbiolspec.MGM2-0008-2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voges</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baumeister</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The 26S proteasome: a molecular machine designed for controlled proteolysis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Biochem</source><year>1999</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>1015</fpage><lpage>1068</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.68.1.1015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10872471</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLeod</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Myhre</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazawa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lillquist</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The complete genome of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. RHA1 provides insights into a catabolic powerhouse</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>15582</fpage><lpage>15587</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0607048103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17030794</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yam</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Geize</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Catabolism of aromatic compounds and steroids by <italic>Rhodococcus</italic></source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Navarro Llorens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrauchan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenylacetate catabolism in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain RHA1: a central pathway for degradation of aromatic compounds</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>4497</fpage><lpage>4504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.13.4497-4504.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15968060</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van der Geize</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yam</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Heuser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilbrink</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderton</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijkhuizen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A gene cluster encoding cholesterol catabolism in a soil actinomycete provides insight into <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> survival in macrophages</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1947</fpage><lpage>1952</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0605728104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17264217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suemori</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurane</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>O-, m- and p-hydroxybenzoate degradative pathways in <italic>Rhodococcus erythropolis</italic></article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>1995</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1995.tb07331.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7867918</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arias-Barrau</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivera</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Luengo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Minambres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The homogentisate pathway: a central catabolic pathway involved in the degradation of L-phenylalanine, L-tyrosine, and 3-hydroxyphenylacetate in <italic>Pseudomonas putida</italic></article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2004</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>5062</fpage><lpage>5077</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.186.15.5062-5077.2004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15262943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Travkin</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Solyanikova</surname><given-names>IP</given-names></name><name><surname>Golovleva</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydroxyquinol pathway for microbial degradation of halogenated aromatic compounds</article-title><source>J Environ Sci Health B</source><year>2006</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1361</fpage><lpage>1382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/03601230600964159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17090498</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Geize</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dijkhuizen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The actinobacterial <italic>mce</italic>4 locus encodes a steroid transporter</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>35368</fpage><lpage>35374</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M805496200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klepp</surname><given-names>LI</given-names></name><name><surname>Forrellad</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Osella</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bianco</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Santangelo</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cataldi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impact of the deletion of the six <italic>mce</italic> operons in <italic>Mycobacterium smegmatis</italic></article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2012</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>590</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.micinf.2012.01.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22353253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Hara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazawa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptomic assessment of isozymes in the biphenyl pathway of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain RHA1</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>6183</fpage><lpage>6193</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00947-06</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16957245</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patrauchan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Florizone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dosanjh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Catabolism of benzoate and phthalate in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain RHA1: redundancies and convergence</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>4050</fpage><lpage>4063</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.12.4050-4063.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15937168</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larkin</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulakov</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>CCR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genomes and Plasmids in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic></source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luengo</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivera</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The phenylacetyl-CoA catabolon: a complex catabolic unit with broad biotechnological applications</article-title><source>Mol Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02344.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11260461</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guevara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez de Las Heras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro Llorens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional differentiation of 3-ketosteroid Delta (1)-dehydrogenase isozymes in <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</article-title><source>Microb Cell Factories</source><year>2017</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>42</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12934-017-0657-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guevara</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Heras</surname><given-names>LFL</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Llorens</surname><given-names>JMN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of 3-ketosteroid 9alpha-hydroxylases in <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain chol-4</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2017.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28642093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gr&#246;ning</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eulberg</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tischler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaschabek</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlomann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene redundancy of two-component (chloro)phenol hydroxylases in <italic>Rhodococcus opacus</italic> 1CP</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2014</year><volume>361</volume><fpage>68</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6968.12616</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25283988</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kesseler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabbs</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Averhoff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Studies on the isopropylbenzene 2,3-dioxygenase and the 3-isopropylcatechol 2,3-dioxygenase genes encoded by the linear plasmid of <italic>Rhodococcus erythropolis</italic> BD2</article-title><source>Microbiology.</source><year>1996</year><volume>142</volume><issue>Pt 11</issue><fpage>3241</fpage><lpage>3251</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/13500872-142-11-3241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8969521</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Providenti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of isovanillate, vanillate, and veratrate by <italic>Comamonas testosteroni</italic> strain BR6020</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2006</year><volume>188</volume><fpage>3862</fpage><lpage>3869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01675-05</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16707678</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priefert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabenhorst</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbuchel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of genes of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic> sp. strain HR199 involved in bioconversion of vanillin to protocatechuate</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1997</year><volume>179</volume><fpage>2595</fpage><lpage>2607</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.179.8.2595-2607.1997</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9098058</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional characterization of a gene cluster involved in gentisate catabolism in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain NCIMB 12038</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2011</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-010-3033-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21181154</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Di Gennaro</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Terreni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Masi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Botti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Ferra</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bestetti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and characterization of genes involved in naphthalene degradation in <italic>Rhodococcus opacus</italic> R7</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2010</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-010-2497-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20195856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#225;ndez de las Heras</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro Llorens</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cholesterol to cholestenone oxidation by ChoG, the main extracellular cholesterol oxidase of <italic>Rhodococcus ruber</italic> strain Chol-4</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2014</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jsbmb.2013.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24125733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bergstrand LH, Cardenas E, Holert J, Van Hamme JD, Mohn WW. Delineation of Steroid-Degrading Microorganisms through Comparative Genomic Analysis. MBio. 2016;7(2):e00166. 10.1128/mBio.00166-16.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilbrink</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Casabon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Geize</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene cluster encoding cholate catabolism in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> spp</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>6712</fpage><lpage>6719</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01169-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024343</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Casabon</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohn</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two transporters essential for reassimilation of novel cholate metabolites by <italic>Rhodococcus jostii</italic> RHA1</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2012</year><volume>194</volume><fpage>6720</fpage><lpage>6727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01167-12</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23024344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tomas-Gallardo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Santero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Floriano</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combination of degradation pathways for naphthalene utilization in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> sp. strain TFB</article-title><source>Microb Biotechnol</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1751-7915.12096</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24325207</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vanillin catabolism in <italic>Rhodococcus jostii</italic> RHA1</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2012</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>586</fpage><lpage>588</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.06876-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22057861</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>