<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD with OASIS Tables v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Channels (Austin)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Channels (Austin)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">KCHL</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">kchl20</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Channels</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1933-6950</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1933-6969</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &amp; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6527056</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30983497</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1600968</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19336950.2019.1600968</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CACHD1: A new activity-modifying protein for voltage-gated calcium channels</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-authors">G. J. STEPHENS AND G. S. COTTRELL</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-title">CHANNELS</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8966-4238</contrib-id><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>Gary J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="AN0001"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9098-7627</contrib-id><name><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>Graeme S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AFF0001"/></contrib><aff id="AFF0001"><institution>School of Pharmacy, University of Reading</institution>, Reading, <country>UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="AN0001">CONTACT Gary J. Stephens <email xlink:href="g.j.stephens@reading.ac.uk">g.j.stephens@reading.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn><p>Autocommentary to: Cottrell GS, Soubrane CH, Hounshell JA, Lin H, Owenson V, Rigby M, Cox PJ, Barker BS, Ottolini M, Ince S, Bauer, CC, Perez-Reyes E, Patel MK, Stevens EB, Stephens GJ (2018) CACHD1 is an &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;-like protein that modulates Ca<sub>V</sub>3 voltage-gated calcium channel activity J Neurosci 38:9186-9201.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>13</day><month>4</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage seq="11">120</fpage><lpage>123</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>20</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2019 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="kchl-13-01-1600968.pdf"/><counts><fig-count count="1"/><ref-count count="10"/><page-count count="4"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Understanding the mechanisms that regulate the trafficking and expression of voltage-gated calcium channels (VGCCs) at presynaptic and potentially postsynaptic plasma membrane microdomains is of paramount importance. VGCCs are subdivided into two main families: high voltage-activated calcium channels (HVACCs) and low voltage-activated calcium channels (LVACCs) (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0001">1</xref>]). HVACCs comprise Ca<sub>V</sub>1.1&#8211;4 (L-type current), Ca<sub>V</sub>2.1 (P/Q-type current), Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 (N-type current) and Ca<sub>V</sub>2.3 (R-type current) VGCCs, whereas LVACCs comprise the Ca<sub>V</sub>3 (T-type current) family. The expression, assembly, localization and biophysical properties of HVACCs can be modulated by &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; and &#946; auxiliary subunits. However, the modulation of Ca<sub>V</sub>3 channels by other proteins has remained less well defined. &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; and &#946; subunits are not considered to be auxilliary subunits for Ca<sub>V</sub>3 subunits and consensus opinion is that Ca<sub>V</sub>3 can form fully functional channels alone (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]). We have recently identified CACHD1 (Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel and chemotaxis receptor (cache) domain containing protein 1), a protein with structural similarities to the &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; family, as a modulator of Ca<sub>V</sub>3 VGCC activity in expression systems and in native neurons [<xref rid="CIT0003">3</xref>]. Our study adds to other recently defined modulators of Ca<sub>V</sub>3 subunits which include endogenous molecules such as the actin binding protein kelch-like 1 (KLHL1), the Stac adaptor protein 1 (Stac1), the endoplasmic reticulum integral membrane protein, calnexin and the ubiquitin-specific protease, USP5 (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0004">4</xref>]).</p><p>Primary sequence analysis reveals that although CACHD1 has limited sequence identity to &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; subunits, it similarly contains a VWA (von Willebrand Factor A) domain and putative bacterial chemosensory-like cache domains (<xref rid="F0001">Figure 1</xref>). However, there are a number of important differences compared to &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; subunits that will potentially affect CACHD1 function. For example, CACHD1 contains fewer predicted glycosylation sites, a variant metal ion-dependent adhesion site (MIDAS) motif (D<sup>234</sup>xGxS) within the VWA domain and a variant gabapentin binding site (R<sup>213</sup>-S-R). Of potential importance, CACHD1 is predicted to be a single transmembrane protein with a large intracellular C-terminal tail, unlike &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;, which is reportedly a glycophosphatidylinositol (GPI)-anchored protein (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]). In our study, we demonstrated that CACHD1 promoted the cell surface localization of Ca<sub>V</sub>3.1 in a heterologous expression system [<xref rid="CIT0003">3</xref>]. Furthermore, using proximity ligation assays, we showed that CACHD1 and Ca<sub>V</sub>3.1 are &lt;40&#160;nm apart at the cell surface, supporting the formation of CACHD1&#8729;Ca<sub>V</sub>3.1 complexes at the plasma membrane. Our electrophoretic analyses indicated that CACHD1 migrated slower than its predicted molecular mass of 142 kDa, migrating at approximately ~170&#160;kDa, possibly indicating post-translational glycosylation. Human CACHD1 was shown to cause clear effects on human Ca<sub>V</sub>3.1, Ca<sub>V</sub>3.2 and Ca<sub>V</sub>3.3 subunits, increasing peak current density with a corresponding increase in maximal conductance. In contrast, expression of &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 had no effect on T-type current under the same conditions. CACHD1 increased the open probability of the Ca<sub>V</sub>3.1 channel, pointing to mechanistic effects on the &#945;<sub>1</sub> subunit. We further demonstrated functional effects of CACHD1 on native T-type current in rat hippocampal neurons. CACHD1 transfected neurons fired at a higher frequency than control neurons, an effect that was prevented by the selective T-type current blocker TTA-P2. Furthermore, CACHD1 caused a significant increase in rebound firing frequency, a property mediated predominantly by T-type current; TTA-P2 similarly reversed this effect. Together, these data support a role for CACHD1 in increasing neuronal T-type current, which in turn promotes an increase in action potential firing frequency and neuronal excitability. The future study of neurons from CACHD1 knockout mice will further advance knowledge of the physiological role of CACHD1.<fig id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19336950.2019.1600968-F0001</object-id><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p><bold>Schematic comparison of the major domains and structural motifs of &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 and CACHD1. (Left)</bold> &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 is translated as a single polypeptide chain that is proteolytically processed into two chains (&#945;<sub>2</sub> and &#948;), which are covalently connected by a disulphide bridge. The &#948; chain is further processed to tether the protein to the plasma membrane, reportedly via a glycophosphatidylinositol anchor (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]). Crystallographic studies reveal that the large extracellular facing portion of &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 contains a von Willebrand Factor A (VWA) domain and four cache domains [<xref rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]. Within the VWA domain, &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 possesses a consensus metal ion-dependent adhesion site (MIDAS) motif that is important for its interaction with pore-forming &#945;<sub>1</sub> subunits. (<bold>Right</bold>) CACHD1 is a single polypeptide chain with a large extracellular N-terminal domain, a single transmembrane domain and an intracellular C-terminal tail. Similar to &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1, the extracellular region of CACHD1 contains a single VWA domain. Currently, CACHD1 has two predicted cache domains and contains a variant MIDAS motif within its VWA domain.</p></caption><graphic specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="kchl-13-01-1600968-g001"/></fig></p><p>A subsequent report has also identified a role for CACHD1 as a modulator of other VGCC subtypes, reporting effects on Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. Together, these studies suggest that CACHD1 may have broader therapeutic potential. However, although CACHD1 caused a significant increase in Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 current, this modulation was not as profound as seen for &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1; indeed, co-expression of CACHD1 caused a reduction in &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1-mediated actions on Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2. These data indicate that CACHD1 may have a dominant negative-like effect on N-type calcium current and led to the suggestion that CACHD1 and &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 may compete for the same structural motif on Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>], unlike the situation for Ca<sub>V</sub>3 subunits. In our original studies, we did not detect any significant increase in Ca<sup>2+</sup> current for human Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 co-expressed with human CACHD1 [<xref rid="CIT0006">6</xref>], in contrast to effects reported for rat Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 with zebrafish or rat CACHD1 [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. Of further interest was that these CACHD1 orthologues had no effect on rat Ca<sub>V</sub>2.1 [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. Therefore, it may be that CACHD1 effects are dependent on the species of both CACHD1 and the &#945;<sub>1</sub> subunit.</p><p>The &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; MIDAS motif (DxSxS) within its VWA domain plays a major role in their modulation of VGCC function (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0002">2</xref>]). Approximately 46% of VWA domain-containing proteins contain a conserved MIDAS motif [<xref rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. CACHD1 has a variant MIDAS motif (D<sup>234</sup>xGxS). Of functional importance, structural studies of VWA domains and biochemical analysis of a family of proteins called copines revealed that a perfectly conserved MIDAS motif is not required for metal ion binding [<xref rid="CIT0007">7</xref>]. Due to the difficulties of predicting non-contiguous structural motifs, such as cache domains, from primary sequences, it remains undetermined if the downstream Thr and Asp residues in human CACHD1 contribute to a conserved MIDAS motif. However, one could speculate, based on our preliminary sequence alignments, that these residues are Thr<sup>311</sup> and Asp<sup>338</sup>. Mutation of the Asp and Ser residues to Ala (AxAxA) in the &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 MIDAS motif caused disruption of the interaction between &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1 and Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 and this interaction was also prevented by mutation of Asp<sup>122</sup> to Ala on Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]; surprisingly, the D122A mutation did not prevent CACHD1-mediated enhancement of Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 currents. This data may indicate that CACHD1 does not interact with Ca<sub>V</sub>2.2 in exactly the same way as &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1. Future biochemical and electrophysiological studies involving mutated forms of the CACHD1 variant MIDAS motif will shed light on its role in the regulation of the function of both CACHD1 and VGCCs. The electrophoretic mobility of rat CACHD1 was increased to its predicted level by treatment of whole cell lysates with the N-linked deglycosylating enzyme, PNGase F, indicating that rat CACHD1 is modified by N-linked glycosylation [<xref rid="CIT0005">5</xref>]. This study highlighted seven high potential N-linked glycosylation sites on rat CACHD1. Similar sequence analysis of human CACHD1 reveals one very high probability site (Asn<sup>145</sup>), five other high probability Asn residues, with an additional three lower potential sites. Future experimentation will reveal precisely which residues are glycosylated and the role of glycosylation in the function of human CACHD1.</p><p>To date, CACHD1 and the &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; isoforms are the only mammalian proteins known to contain bacterial chemosensory-like cache domains. Cache domains are the most important extracellular sensors in prokaryotes (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0008">8</xref>]) and may represent potential drug targets. The current predicted CACHD1 structure, including two predicted cache domains, is based on extant Uniprot data (Q5VU97). For &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948;1, the initial description of a single cache domain (Uniprot data, P54289) has been revised to two and most recently to four domains following the latest crystal structure at 3.6&#160;&#8491; [<xref rid="CIT0009">9</xref>]. A similar crystal structure will be required to determine the number of cache domains in CACHD1, but the presence of multiple cache domains adds another dimension to the possible functionality of both &#945;<sub>2</sub>&#948; and CACHD1.</p><p>With regard to our recent work, CACHD1 is predicted to act mechanistically to increase Ca<sub>V</sub>3 channel open probability and promote T-type currents. Such physiological actions may have implications in targeting diseases involving aberrant neuronal firing. In particular, Ca<sub>V</sub>3 channels have been proposed as therapeutic targets to combat pain and epilepsy (reviewed [<xref rid="CIT0004">4</xref>]). It is of particular interest that CACHD1 transcripts are highly expressed in mouse dorsal root ganglia [<xref rid="CIT0010">10</xref>], key transducers of nociceptive information. However, the therapeutic potential of Ca<sub>V</sub>3-targeting drugs remains largely unrealized, as clinical drugs such as ethosuximide lack Ca<sub>V</sub>3 selectivity and an earlier agent, mibefradil, was withdrawn due to serious drug interaction issues. It will be of interest to identify the functions of the domains and sequence motifs present in CACHD1 responsible for its effects on T-type currents and the sequences within Ca<sub>V</sub>3 channels that may participate in the interaction with CACHD1. Targeting proteins such as CACHD1 that modulate Ca<sub>V</sub>3 function may provide an attractive alternative to the direct blocking of the &#945;<sub>1</sub> subunit pore and we propose that CACHD1 represents an important new protein with excellent potential for future therapeutic targeting.</p></body><back><sec id="S0002"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zamponi</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Striessnig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koschak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The physiology, pathology, and pharmacology of voltage-gated calcium channels and their future therapeutic potential</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Rev</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>821</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>870</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26362469</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dolphin</surname><given-names>AC.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium channel auxiliary alpha2delta and beta subunits: trafficking and one step beyond</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>542</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>555</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22805911</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soubrane</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hounshell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>CACHD1 is an alpha2delta-like protein that modulates CaV3 voltage-gated calcium channel activity</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>9186</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>9201</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30181139</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zamponi</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>T-type calcium channels: from molecule to therapeutic opportunities</article-title>. <source>Int J Biochem Cell Biol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>108</volume>:<fpage>34</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>39</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30648620</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dahimene</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Page</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kadurin</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>The alpha2delta-like protein cachd1 increases N-type calcium currents and cell surface expression and competes with alpha2delta-1</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1610</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1621 e1615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30404013</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Soubrane</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Expression and functional studies of the novel CNS protein CACHD1</article-title>. <conf-name>Proceedings of The Physiological Society; Edinburgh</conf-name>;&#160;Vol. <volume>27</volume>, <fpage>PC74</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Whittaker</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hynes</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Distribution and evolution of von Willebrand/integrin A domains: widely dispersed domains with roles in cell adhesion and elsewhere</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Cell</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>3369</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12388743</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anantharaman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aravind</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Cache - a signaling domain common to animal Ca<sup>2+</sup>-channel subunits and a class of prokaryotic chemotaxis receptors</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>25</volume>:<fpage>535</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>537</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11084361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Structure of the voltage-gated calcium channel Ca<sub>V</sub>1.1 at 3.6 A resolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>537</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>196</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27580036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Torck</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, et al</person-group>
<article-title>Comparative transcriptome profiling of the human and mouse dorsal root ganglia: an RNA-seq-based resource for pain and sensory neuroscience research</article-title>. <source>Pain</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>159</volume>:<fpage>1325</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1345</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29561359</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>