<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J R Soc Interface</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J R Soc Interface</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">RSIF</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">royinterface</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of the Royal Society Interface</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1742-5689</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1742-5662</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Royal Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6127169</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30111663</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2018.0256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">rsif20180256</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1004</subject><subject>30</subject><subject>44</subject><subject>124</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Life Sciences&#8211;Physics interface</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="leader"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Oxygen diffusion in ellipsoidal tumour spheroids</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">Oxygen diffusion in ellipsoidal tumour spheroids</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-3140-3278</contrib-id><name><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>David Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Currell</surname><given-names>Frederick J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3">3</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Centre for Advanced and Interdisciplinary Radiation Research (CAIRR) School of Mathematics and Physics</addr-line>, <institution>Queen's University Belfast</institution>, <addr-line>Belfast BT7 1NN</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Cancer Research UK/MRC Oxford Institute for Radiation Oncology</addr-line>, <addr-line>Gray Laboratory</addr-line>, <institution>University of Oxford</institution>, <addr-line>Old Road Campus Research Building</addr-line>, <addr-line>Off Roosevelt Drive</addr-line>, <addr-line>Oxford OX3 7DQ</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="af3"><label>3</label><addr-line>The Dalton Cumbrian Facility and School of Chemistry</addr-line>, <institution>University of Manchester</institution>, <addr-line>Westlakes Science and Technology Park</addr-line>, <addr-line>Moor Row, Whitehaven CA24 3HA</addr-line>, <country>UK</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">e-mail: <email>d.r.grimes@qub.ac.uk</email> or <email>davidrobert.grimes@oncology.ox.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>Electronic supplementary material is available online at <uri xlink:href="https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.4183505">https://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.4183505</uri>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>15</volume><issue>145</issue><elocation-id>20180256</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>7</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#169; 2018 The Authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>Published by the Royal Society under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</uri>, which permits unrestricted use, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license><?release-delay 0|0?></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="rsif20180256.pdf"/><abstract><p>Oxygen plays a central role in cellular metabolism, in both healthy and tumour tissue. The presence and concentration of molecular oxygen in tumours has a substantial effect on both radiotherapy response and tumour evolution, and as a result the oxygen micro-environment is an area of intense research interest. Multi-cellular tumour spheroids closely mimic real avascular tumours, and in particular they exhibit physiologically relevant heterogeneous oxygen distribution. This property has made them a vital part of <italic>in vitro</italic> experimentation. For ideal spheroids, their heterogeneous oxygen distributions can be predicted from theory, allowing determination of cellular oxygen consumption rate (OCR) and anoxic extent. However, experimental tumour spheroids often depart markedly from perfect sphericity. There has been little consideration of this reality. To date, the question of how far an ellipsoid can diverge from perfect sphericity before spherical assumptions break down remains unanswered. In this work, we derive equations governing oxygen distribution (and, more generally, nutrient and drug distribution) in both prolate and oblate tumour ellipsoids, and quantify the theoretical limits of the assumption that the spheroid is a perfect sphere. Results of this analysis yield new methods for quantifying OCR in ellipsoidal spheroids, and how this can be applied to markedly increase experimental throughput and quality.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>oxygen</kwd><kwd>spheroids</kwd><kwd>modelling</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Cancer Research UK</institution><institution-id>http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000289</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>A19834</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>August, 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><label>1.</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Oxygen plays a seminal role in cancer treatment and patient prognosis. The presence of molecular oxygen in a tumour markedly increases radio-sensitivity, with well-oxygenated regions responding to radiotherapy by up to a factor of 3 relative to anoxic sub-volumes [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This oxygen enhancement ratio is also seen in emerging modalities such as proton therapy [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], raising the tantalizing prospect of dose painting, where dose is selectively boosted to hypoxic regions to boost therapy response [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The basic idea underpinning dose painting has been discussed for over a decade, but application has been hampered by difficulty in non-invasive hypoxia imaging. Methods such as F-MISO PET (fluoromisonidazole positron emission tomography) have a maximum resolution in the millimetre regime, while oxygenation varies over a micrometre scale. As a consequence, mathematical modelling is vital for bridging the resolution gap [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].</p><p>Aside from therapeutic considerations, oxygen has a marked impact on patient prognosis. The pioneering work of Gray and colleagues in the early 1950s established that tumour oxygen concentration was correlated with prognosis, and extensive hypoxia was a negative prognostic marker [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. This finding has been well replicated to present day [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSIF20180256C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and is not solely due to hypoxia-induced treatment resistance. Under severe hypoxia, tumour cells can respond to such pressure by activating oxygen-sensitive signalling pathways [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Current biological thinking suggests that these signalling pathways act to alter gene expression to promote cell survival under adverse conditions. Hypoxia is also a major driver of angiogenesis, giving rise to new routes for cells to travel along [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], endowed with the ability to metastasize [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>The extraordinary importance of oxygen in cancer treatment and evolution has made it an important avenue of study, with an urgent need for further research. Despite the fundamental importance of molecular oxygen in tumours, investigations have been complicated by the significant experimental difficulty in ascertaining oxygen concentration <italic>in situ</italic> [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Real tumours have highly heterogeneous oxygen supply and complex tortured vasculature, and even well-oxygenated regions are frequently inter-spaced with pockets of anoxia [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Standard two-dimensional monolayers of cells are not an ideal experimental model, typically exhibiting an unrealistically homogeneous oxygen contribution. There is however a more realistic experimental option in the form of tumour spheroids. These clusters of cancer cells grow in approximately spherical three-dimensional aggregates, and exhibit signalling and metabolic profiles more similar to real tumours than is observed in monolayer approaches [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSIF20180256C19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>Like monolayers, spheroids are relatively easy to culture, and growing interest has seen them used for a variety of purposes, including radiobiological application as a means to test fractionation [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSIF20180256C23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], as a model for drug delivery [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSIF20180256C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], for investigation of the stem-cell hypothesis [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and for exploring FDG-PET (fludeoxyglucose positron emission tomography) dynamics [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] for hypoxia in solid tumours. Crucially, the non-homogeneous oxygen distributions in tumour spheroids have been well studied [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSIF20180256C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Research to date shows that cellular oxygen consumption rate (OCR) has a known influence on the oxygen concentration throughout a spheroid, and directly influences the extent of central anoxia and the viable rim thickness by known mathematical relationships [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]; thus measuring these aspects allows an experimenter to determine OCR with relative ease compared with other methods [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>Such methods and the underlying theory are exceptionally important to understanding the factors that influence tumour oxygen distribution, yet all these methods rely on an implicit assumption of perfect sphericity. There is a clear rationale behind this, as symmetry considerations simplify the problem greatly. Yet in experimental conditions, imperfect spheroids are common, frequently growing as extended ellipsoids. When the eccentricity of these shapes is extreme, an experimenter may reasonably choose to discard them from analysis. But this prompts a question: quite how extreme do such deformations have to be before a spherical assumption breaks down? Presumably small departures from sphericity should not impact analysis, whereas highly eccentric ellipsoids could reasonably be presumed to violate the underlying theoretical assumptions. The question of how such eccentricities might skew analysis of spheroids, and how trustworthy results of such analysis might be, has not yet been considered in the literature, despite its obvious practical importance.</p><p>These questions are as of yet unanswered, and are of paramount importance given the growing adoption of spheroids for cancer research, and their utility in estimating OCR [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Knowing the acceptable limits of eccentricity for spheroid analysis would be of considerable benefit to experimenters, providing error estimates and limits of reliability. A full analytic expression for &#8216;ellipsoidals&#8217; (analogous to the spherical case) would also be of substantial benefit, allowing the analysis of eccentric shapes and potentially increasing experimental throughput. In this work, we seek to address these issues by deriving an expression for oxygen diffusion in both prolate and oblate geometries. This is contrasted to the spherical case to determine the limits of validity for experimental data, and the implications of this are discussed. A schematic of this is depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F1">figure 1</xref>.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Schematic analysis in this work. Below a calculated threshold for eccentricity, spheroids can be treated as having perfect sphericity without introducing unacceptable error, and their OCR and oxygen distribution established by previously published methods [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. At greater eccentricities, however, a spherical assumption is no longer valid. If the inner and outer sections are concentric ellipses, these can be analysed by the methods outlined in this work to ascertain OCR and oxygen distribution. If eccentricity is higher than a threshold value, and inner and outer ellipses are not concentric, this suggests the spheroid is severely warped or the section is off the central axis, and should be discarded from analysis. See text for details. (Online version in colour.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g1"/></fig></p><sec id="s1a"><label>1.1.</label><title>Spheroids and ellipsoids</title><p>The general equation of an ellipsoid is given by
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M1x1"><label>1.1</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>where <italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic> and <italic>c</italic> are the major axes' lengths. For an ellipsoid with azimuthal symmetry, <italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic>. When all axes are equal (<italic>a</italic> = <italic>b</italic> = <italic>c</italic>), the result is a perfect sphere. To date, this is the only case which has been well studied from a theoretical standpoint [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>&#8211;<xref rid="RSIF20180256C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. While the mathematical treatments to date have assumed spheroids are perfect spheres, the nomenclature &#8216;spheroid&#8217; still applies to the more general case, including prolate and oblate spheroids. In this work, we broaden the mathematical framework to be applicable to ellipsoids without full spherical symmetry, which are namely
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>(1)&#8195;<italic>Prolate spheroids</italic>. In the case where <italic>c</italic> &gt; <italic>a</italic>, the resulting ellipsoid is an ellipse rotated around its major axis, the line joining its foci. This yields a rugby ball-type shape.</p></list-item><list-item><p>(2)&#8195;<italic>Oblate spheroids</italic>. Where <italic>a</italic> &gt; <italic>c</italic>, an oblate spheroid results, equivalent to an ellipse rotated around its minor axes. The resulting shape is discus-like.</p></list-item></list></p><p>Examples of these ellipsoids are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F2">figure 2</xref>. To avoid confusion, we use the term spheroid to refer to an ellipsoidal collection of cells, although we do not limit this to perfect spheres, qualifying with terms &#8216;prolate&#8217; or &#8216;oblate&#8217; as appropriate. We use the term ellipsoid to refer to surfaces of iso-concentration of oxygen.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) Prolate spheroid and (<italic>b</italic>) oblate spheroid. The anoxic central core in both cases (<italic>e</italic> = 0.75) is depicted in grey, and the hypoxic extent in red, while well-oxygenated cells are shown in green. Both ellipsoids have the same volume necrotic core, but their resultant oxygen distributions are slightly different. See text for discussion.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g2"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="s2"><label>2.</label><title>Model derivation</title><p>The full mathematical derivation for oxygen partial pressure in prolate and oblate spheroids is rather involved, and here we shall confine ourselves to stating results with a cursory outline of how they are derived. A full mathematical outline is provided in the electronic supplementary material, appendix, S1. Essentially, we are concerned with solving a steady-state reaction&#8211;diffusion problem for oxygen field <italic>P</italic> of the form
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x1"><label>2.1</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>where <italic>D</italic> is the oxygen diffusion constant in water (typically <italic>D</italic> = 2 &#215; 10<sup>&#8722;9</sup> m<sup>2</sup> s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) and <italic>a&#937;</italic> is the oxygen consumption rate in mmHg s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. This must be solved subject to two crucial boundary conditions, namely that the surface flux and oxygen partial pressure at the anoxic boundary must both be zero. For simple geometries such as perfectly spherical spheroids and cylindrical vessels, symmetry can be exploited to readily yield analytical solutions [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In elliptical geometry, the problem is more involved but the basic premise remains the same, and is outlined below. The geometry of the problem is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F3">figure 3</xref>.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Geometry of a spheroid with outer semi-major axis length <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> and inner semi-major axis length <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>. On the surface <italic>&#963;</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>, both partial pressure and oxygen flux are zero. On the outer surface <italic>p</italic>(<italic>&#963;</italic><sub>o</sub>) = <italic>p</italic><sub>o</sub>. In spherical coordinates, a point <italic>p</italic> is specified by a radial distance from centre <italic>r</italic> and an angle <italic>&#952;</italic>. The focal length of the inner spheroid is <italic>f</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g3"/></fig></p><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title>Prolate spheroids</title><p>In a prolate spherical geometry, we employ the prolate spherical coordinate system, using a geometrically intuitive definition where curves of constant <italic>&#963;</italic> are prolate spheroids, while curves of constant <italic>&#964;</italic> correspond to hyperboloids of revolution [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This is outlined in detail in the electronic supplementary material, text S1. This yields an analytical solution, which can be converted directly into spherical coordinates to yield
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x2"><label>2.2</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>where <italic>f</italic> = <italic>er</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> is the distance from the ellipse centre to the foci.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title>Oblate spheroids</title><p>In oblate spherical geometry, a similar geometrical definition exists [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] and can be solved through similar methods, also outlined in the electronic supplementary material, S1. The full solution in spherical coordinates is
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x3"><label>2.3</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e4.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>Both the prolate and oblate form can be alternatively cast in terms of <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>, the outer semi-major axis length, if preferable. These forms are also given in the electronic supplementary material, S1.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title>Ellipsoidal confocality</title><p>Analogous to the perfect spherical case, confocal elliptical surfaces in a spheroid are at the same oxygen partial pressure. For confocal ellipsoidal shells, focal length is constant, related to the eccentricity <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> and semi-major axis of the shell <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>c</italic></sub> by
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x4"><label>2.4</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e5.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>It follows that the innermost (anoxic) and outermost ellipsoidal shells are confocal, thus for a true spheroid <italic>e</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> = <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub><italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>. Within the bounds of acceptable experimental error, this relationship can be used to determine whether a given spheroid displaying apparent eccentricity is ellipsoidal or not. This is important from an experimental perspective, as sectioning can introduce serious distortions in fixed spheroid sections, or can miss the central axis of the spheroid [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. In these cases, an ostensible ellipsoidal shape might be observed, but may in fact be a sectioning distortion or off-centre cut. Testing for confocality thus determines the underlying reality.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title>OCR estimation in spheroids</title><p>In the perfectly spherical case, OCR (in mmHg s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>) is related to the anxoic radius <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> and outer radius <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] by
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x5"><label>2.5</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e6.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>For a prolate tumour spheroid, it is possible to estimate OCR in a manner analogous to the spherical case by re-arranging the equations for <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub> to yield
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x6"><label>2.6</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e7.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>Similarly for oblate spheroids, OCR is given by re-arrangement of <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>O</italic></sub> to arrive at
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x7"><label>2.7</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e8.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>One complication that may arise is that it may be impossible to ascertain whether an ellipsoidal spheroid is prolate or oblate. In that case, one can produce a &#8216;combined&#8217; expression for average OCR by taking the average of equations&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x2">2.2</xref>) and&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x3">2.3</xref>) and re-arranging to arrive at
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x8"><label>2.8</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e9.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>An example of the implementation of these forms including error analysis is included in the code given in electronic supplementary material, S2.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><label>2.5.</label><title>Spherical error metrics</title><p>It is worthwhile introducing metrics to quantify how divergent the estimated oxygen profile in a given ellipsoidal spheroid is from a related perfectly symmetric spheroid. A perfect spheroid has radial symmetry, and thus <italic>P</italic>(<italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>) = <italic>p</italic><sub>o</sub> at all points. Consider related prolate and oblate spheroids with both semi-major axis <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> and eccentricity <italic>e</italic>, nested inside a sphere of radius <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>. We can define the root mean square error (RMSE) by contrasting the expected outer shell partial pressure <italic>p</italic><sub>o</sub> with what would be measured for spheroids at <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>P</italic></sub>(<italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>, <italic>&#952;</italic>) and <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>O</italic></sub>(<italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>, <italic>&#952;</italic>), respectively. The RMSE for prolate and oblate spheroids, respectively, is
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x9"><label>2.9</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e10.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>and
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x10"><label>2.10</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e11.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>These equations can readily be solved by numerical integration methods, and solutions are demonstrated in the electronic supplementary material, code S2. Percentage error is simply 100(RMSE/<italic>p</italic><sub>o</sub>), and thus the variation in RMSE with eccentricity can be readily calculated. The other instance when deviation from spherical assumptions must be quantified is in OCR calculation; for example, when the OCR in a spheroid is calculated assuming the perfectly spherical form in equation&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x5">2.5</xref>) rather than a more appropriate prolate or oblate form. This might occur when eccentricity is low and the spheroid appears to be entirely symmetric to a first approximation. The distance from the centroid of a spheroid with semi-major axis <italic>r</italic> and focal length <italic>f</italic> to a point on the spheroid at an angle <italic>&#952;</italic> is given by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-i1.jpg"/></inline-formula>, and thus the average values for outer radius <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> and anoxic radius <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> are given by integrating this over a full revolution, yielding
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x11"><label>2.11</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e12.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>and
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x12"><label>2.12</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e13.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>where <italic>E</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub> is the complete elliptic integral of the second kind. Analogous to the discrete standard deviation, the distance function can be integrated over a full rotation (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-i2.jpg"/></inline-formula>) to yield an expression for standard deviation across these spheroids of
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x13"><label>2.13</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e14.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>and
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x14"><label>2.14</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e15.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>Applying the form in equation&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x5">2.5</xref>) for spherical OCR yields an approximation (which is incorrect when <italic>e</italic> &gt; 0) of
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x15"><label>2.15</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e16.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>The uncertainty calculation associated with this can be calculated with the variance formula, in this case given by
<disp-formula id="RSIF20180256M2x16"><label>2.16</label><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-e17.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/></disp-formula>This is analytically tractable, and is given in the electronic supplementary material, S1. An implementation in several code languages is also provided in the electronic supplementary material, S2.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s3"><label>3.</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title>Spheroid oxygen profiles</title><p>The models derived in this work were used to create oxygen profiles for spheroids of both prolate and oblate classes, which were contrasted to conventional perfectly spherical profiles.</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title>Quantifying differences between prolate and oblate cases</title><p>Prolate and oblate forms have some mathematical differences, as can be seen by inspection of equations&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x2">2.2</xref>) and&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x3">2.3</xref>). Whether this difference is experimentally significant is an important question; from a single projection of a tumour spheroid it might be impossible to ascertain whether an experimenter is dealing with a prolate or oblate case. As an experimentalist might not be able to determine whether a given spheroid is prolate or oblate from a single section, quantifying differences in measured OCR under each assumption is an important goal of this work. This was simulated by producing prolate and oblate spheroids with properties as outlined in <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>, and observing the differences in their profiles. In addition, OCR estimates under the &#8216;wrong&#8217; assumptions were also calculated and inspected. Specifically, the &#8216;wrong&#8217; assumption occurs when one applies oblate equations for a prolate spheroid or vice versa. OCR was also calculated with the combined assumption (equation&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x8">2.8</xref>)), which can also be used when the underlying form is unknown. These spheroids were produced with physical properties as per <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>, with OCR given by equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x5">2.5</xref>)&#8211;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x8">2.8</xref>).
<table-wrap id="RSIF20180256TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Simulation parameters.</p></caption></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><label>3.3.</label><title>Comparisons with the spherical case</title><p>As OCR from spheroids is estimated assuming spherical symmetry, a major aspect of this work was quantifying precisely how close to perfect sphericity spheroids must be so that such an assumption holds, and how departures from sphericity impact estimates of OCR and oxygen profiles. To study this, spheroids with known OCR and varying eccentricity were simulated, and analysed with equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x9">2.9</xref>)&#8211;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x16">2.16</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3d"><label>3.4.</label><title>Experimental proof of concept</title><p>To date, non-spherical tumour spheroids have been somewhat neglected, and have been frequently discarded from analysis due to their inherent uncertainty. It is thus difficult to find non-spherical tumour spheroid data. A potential example was taken from a previously analysed set of sectioned DLD-1 tumour spheroids [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], dual-stained with proliferation marker Ki-67 and EF5. Spheroids from this set were experimentally determined to have an OCR of 22.10 &#177; 4.24 mmHg s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. The sample spheroid was excluded from prior analysis because of its high eccentricity (external eccentricity <italic>e</italic> &#8776; 0.66). This was then analysed using methods outlined in this work as a proof of concept to determine OCR, contrasting it with known values and spherical estimates.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><label>4.</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s4a"><label>4.1.</label><title>Oxygen distributions in spheroids</title><p>Eccentric spheroids were simulated with properties shown in <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. Unlike the spherical case, oxygen profiles here are not radially symmetric, so profiles were plotted along both the semi-major and semi-minor axis for clarity. Examples of these profiles are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F4">figure 4</xref>. Oxygen gradients through spheroids are simulated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F5">figure 5</xref>, for both prolate and oblate cases with increasing eccentricity.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Oxygen profiles for both prolate and oblate spheroids along the semi-major and semi-minor axis for (<italic>a</italic>) a spheroid with inner eccentricity <italic>e</italic> = 0.25. There is relatively little difference between prolate and oblate cases and profiles largely overlap, being close to the spherical case. (<italic>b</italic>) A spheroid with inner eccentricity <italic>e</italic> = 0.90. Small differences between prolate and oblate cases can be readily seen, and a very large divergence from the perfectly spherical case is apparent. (Online version in colour.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g4"/></fig>
<fig id="RSIF20180256F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>&#8211;<italic>f</italic>) Contour oxygen maps for prolate and oblate spheroids with increasing eccentricity with semi-major axis 500 &#956;m and OCR of 20 mmHg s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. Prolate and oblate have broadly similar oxygen maps, with divergence manifesting as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-i3.jpg"/></inline-formula>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s4b"><label>4.2.</label><title>Quantification of differences in prolate and oblate spheroids</title><p>From two-dimensional sectioning or imagining alone, it can be experimentally difficult to ascertain whether a given spheroid is either prolate or oblate. It is thus important to quantify differences between the ellipsoids. Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F5">5</xref> suggest that prolate and oblate spheroids have broadly similar oxygen profiles until eccentricity approaches unity. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F6">Figure 6</xref> depicts internal anoxic radii with eccentricity. These differ only slightly, typically less than or equal to 1% for both major and minor axes for 0 &lt; <italic>e</italic> &lt; 0.9. More interesting perhaps is the variation in OCR estimate with eccentricity under the &#8216;wrong&#8217; assumption (namely assuming oblate form when the actual entity is prolate or vice versa) shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F7">figure 7</xref>. This suggests strongly that OCR estimates arrived at under the &#8216;wrong&#8217; assumption are still accurate up until high eccentricity. Even at very high eccentricity, an average value of both incorrect OCRs was extremely close to true OCR. This suggests that incorrectly specifying the type of spheroid should not greatly impact OCR estimates. For improved accuracy, employing the combined estimate in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x8">2.8</xref>) yields even smaller errors, suggesting this could readily be used by experimentalists without introducing major error even when the underlying form is unknown.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Variation of anoxic radii with eccentricity of outer shell from equations (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x2">2.2</xref>) and&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x3">2.3</xref>) for spheroids with properties as per <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>. Differences between radii in the prolate and oblate case are generally very small up to high eccentricity. (Online version in colour.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g6"/></fig>
<fig id="RSIF20180256F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>OCR estimates under &#8216;wrong&#8217; assumptions for increasing inner eccentricity, calculated from equations&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x6">2.6</xref>)&#8211;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x8">2.8</xref>). Combined OCR estimate yields smaller errors in all cases. True OCR is 20 mmHg s<sup>&#8722;1</sup>. (Online version in colour.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g7"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="RSIF20180256TB2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>RMSE and OCR estimates assuming sphericity for spheroids of varying eccentricity <italic>e</italic>.</p></caption></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s4c"><label>4.3.</label><title>Comparisons with spherical case</title><p><xref rid="RSIF20180256TB2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> depicts the impact of assuming perfect sphericity on derived OCR estimates for properties in <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB1" ref-type="table">table 1</xref>. At low <italic>e</italic> (typically <italic>e</italic> &#8804; 0.3), treating spheroids as perfect spheres yields acceptable accuracy for both OCR estimates. However, as <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-i4.jpg"/></inline-formula>, the reliability of OCR estimates rapidly breaks down, and errors become increasingly large and unreliable.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><label>4.4.</label><title>Experimental proof of concept</title><p>For this work, a simple image analysis algorithm was written for the spheroid image, which found the ellipsoid centre and cast best fit ellipses from this position. The analysis algorithm was broadly similar to previously described methods [<xref rid="RSIF20180256C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], yielding estimates of <italic>e</italic> &#8776; 0.66, <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> = 488.5 &#956;m and <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> = 400.15 &#956;m. This analysis suggested the best-fit inner and outer ellipses were approximately confocal to within experimental error, as required by the confocality condition in equation (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x4">2.4</xref>) (<italic>e</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> &#8776; <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub><italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> to within an error of 1.13%). Uncertainty on the lengths of <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>
<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> were taken from this to be 5.53 &#956;m and 4.52 &#956;m, respectively. Results of this analysis are depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F8">figure 8</xref> and <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>, and suggest values in agreement with those previously measured when considered as a prolate/oblate spheroid, and unrealistic values if presumed perfectly spherical.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>(<italic>a</italic>) Eccentric DLD-1 spheroid (contrast enhanced for clarity). (<italic>b</italic>) Demonstration of analysis with a spheroid image analysis algorithm detecting best-fit ellipses (blue ellipse best fit to outer boundary, red to inner). Calculated focal lengths from both are checked for confocality from equation&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x4">2.4</xref>) and OCR estimated. See text for details.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g8"/></fig>
<table-wrap id="RSIF20180256TB3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3.</label><caption><p>OCR estimates for sample spheroid.</p></caption></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><label>5.</label><title>Discussion</title><p>Analysis of spheroids to date tends to pivot on the presumption of sphericity, as symmetry arguments reduce the complexity required. However, real spheroids tend to depart from perfect sphericity to varying extents. In this work, we provide a metric for determining how reliable the simpler spherical assumption will be as eccentricity increases, as outlined in <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>. The methods outlined in this work can be employed to generate reliable estimates of OCR and oxygen distribution. Another major benefit of this work is that it allows an experimenter to determine OCR even in non-spherical cases when high eccentricity might otherwise render the spheroids in question ill-suited for analysis. Provided the inner and outer ellipses are suitably confocal, the analysis outlined in this work can be employed, and thus should help increase experimental throughput.</p><p>As depicted in <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB2" ref-type="table">table 2</xref>, presuming sphericity with eccentric sections yields acceptable accuracy when eccentricity is small, but rapidly begins to produce completely unrealistic results for OCR and massive uncertainty. When analysed as either prolate or oblate spheroids, however, OCR estimates are in agreement with the previously measured values. This suggests strongly that, for eccentricity greater than approximately <italic>e</italic> = 0.3, spherical assumptions for OCR cease to be appropriate and ellipsoidal analysis must be employed. While data for this are currently sparse, we were able to demonstrate the principle on the highly eccentric spheroid illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F8">figure 8</xref>, determined by image analysis to have <italic>f</italic> = 318.89 &#177; 2.57 &#956;m. When analysed as a spheroid, OCR estimates were completely unrealistic with huge uncertainty, as seen in <xref rid="RSIF20180256TB3" ref-type="table">table 3</xref>. However, when considered as either a prolate or oblate spheroid, OCR measurements were within previously measured values. This is promising, but, as only a single datum point is available, this should be interpreted solely as a proof of concept.</p><p>It is worth noting that, from single section images or microscopy, there is no obvious way to ascertain whether a spheroid is prolate or oblate. As the mathematical forms for these are slightly different, this adds an extra uncertainty and prompts the question about which form is preferable to employ. The analysis in this work (figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F6">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F7">7</xref>) indicates that, even if one incorrectly assumes the wrong form, OCR estimates are still very good, with only minimal errors introduced. This holds with only negligible errors until very high eccentricity. The combined OCR form in equation&#160;(<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="RSIF20180256M2x8">2.8</xref>) yields only negligible error even when the underlying form is unknown. Thus, an experimenter should opt to use this form for OCR estimation when they have no other information on whether the specimen is prolate or oblate, as this does not introduce large errors even at high eccentricity.</p><p>While modelling of elliptical oxygen diffusion has the potential to greatly extend experimental throughput, there are a number of scenarios in which an ostensible eccentric spheroid might not be what it appears. For fixed and sectioned spheroids, the act of sectioning itself can be enough to induce substantial deformations, stretching it along a particular axis. Ostensibly, the resultant shape might appear ellipsoidal, but is in reality a warped spheroid, and cannot be reliably analysed with the methods outlined. Such an example is show in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F9">figure 9</xref>, for a spherical spheroid sheared along an axis. From the mathematics established in this work, we can distinguish between true spheroids and warped spheroids&#8212;if the inner and outer ellipses are not confocal (<italic>e</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub>&#8800;<italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub><italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>) then the shape is a warped spheroid, and should be discounted from analysis, as per <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F1">figure 1</xref>. Crucially, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSIF20180256F9">figure 9</xref> demonstrates that warped spheroids can only satisfy the ellipsoidal confocality condition under two circumstances: either when its eccentricity is 0 (a perfect sphere), or the non-physical situation when <italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> = <italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>. Thus, a sheared spheroid in one direction will never come close to satisfying the ellipsoidal confocality condition. In practice, all experimental work comes with inherent uncertainty, so <italic>e</italic><sub>o</sub><italic>r</italic><sub>o</sub> &#8776; <italic>e</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub><italic>r</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub> within the bounds of image analysis uncertainty is sufficient to determine whether a spheroid can be treated as an ellipsoidal case.
<fig id="RSIF20180256F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9.</label><caption><p>The eccentricity of a sheared spheroid is the same for both anoxic and outer ellipsoids (<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-i5.jpg"/></inline-formula>) and thus not confocal as <italic>f</italic> is not constant. Sheared spheroids are not true spheroids, as the confocality condition is not met. (Online version in colour.)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="rsif20180256-g9"/></fig></p><p>There is a more subtle issue with sectioned spheroids, which becomes even more crucial with sectioned eccentric spheroids. Analysis relies on a section through the central axis of the spheroid. In the perfectly spherical case, if the section is off-centre, the net result will be two concentric circles but with a misleading ratio, rendering any OCR calculation derived from this suspect. By contrast, any plane through an ellipsoid produces an ellipse, but if these cuts are off the central axis then the inner and outer ellipses will no longer have a common centre, and will not be confocal. In this regard, determining an off-centre ellipsoid section is relatively straight-forward. A proof of this is provided in the electronic supplementary material, S1.</p><p>The theoretical analysis outlined here presents biological investigators with new methods for extending spheroid analysis, and the means to interpret data which depart from sphericity. It also establishes uncertainty bounds on existing spherical analysis techniques, and methods for determining OCR and oxygen distribution in tumour ellipsoids. The findings of this work will increase experimental confidence with tumour spheroids, and have the potential to substantially increase experimental throughput, improving our insights on everything from tumour hypoxia to drug delivery. Such an approach is imperative if we are to fully exploit this unique experimental tool, and ultimately marshal the new insights obtained towards better cancer treatment and diagnostics.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1"><caption><title>S1 Appendix. Mathematical appendix and full derivations.</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="rsif20180256supp1.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1502" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2"><caption><title>S2 Appendix. Sample code for ellipsoid oxygen distribution and OCR 287 calculation (Mathematica, MATLAB / Octave, Excel spreadsheet)</title></caption><media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="rar" xlink:href="rsif20180256supp2.rar" orientation="portrait" id="d35e1510" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec id="s6"><title>Data accessibility</title><p>All data are available with the paper. Mathematical derivations and related theorems are contained in the electronic supplementary material, S1. Sample implementations in Matlab, Octave, Mathematica and Excel spreadsheet are included in the electronic supplementary material, S2.</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>D.R.G. and F.J.C. conceived the theory outlined in this work; D.R.G. derived the model, performed the analysis and wrote the manuscript. Both authors reviewed the manuscript and authored supplementary texts.</p></sec><sec id="s8" sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>We declare we have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>The authors acknowledge Queen's University Belfast for funding the CAIRR initiative. D.R.G. also thanks Cancer Research UK for its support.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="RSIF20180256C1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>A mechanistic investigation of the oxygen fixation hypothesis and oxygen enhancement ratio</article-title>. <source>Biomed. Phys. Eng. Express</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <fpage>45209</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/2057-1976/1/4/045209</pub-id>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giaccia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<source>Radiobiology for the radiologist</source>, vol. <volume>6</volume>
<publisher-loc>Philadelphia, PA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wenzl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilkens</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Modelling of the oxygen enhancement ratio for ion beam radiation therapy</article-title>. <source>Phys. Med. Biol.</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>3251</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>3268</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1088/0031-9155/56/11/006</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21540489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>An approximate analytical solution of the Bethe equation for charged particles in the radiotherapeutic energy range</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>9781</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-10554-0</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28852130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bentzen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregoire</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Molecular imaging-based dose painting: a novel paradigm for radiation therapy prescription</article-title>. <source>Semin. Radiat. Oncol.</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>101</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>110</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.semradonc.2010.10.001</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21356478</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Hypoxia imaging and radiotherapy: bridging the resolution gap</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Radiol.</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <elocation-id content-type="artnum">20160939</elocation-id> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1259/bjr.20160939</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28540739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hornsey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1953</year>
<article-title>The concentration of oxygen dissolved in tissues at the time of irradiation as a factor in radiotherapy</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Radiol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>638</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>648</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1259/0007-1285-26-312-638</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13106296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaupel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thews</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hoeckel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Treatment resistance of solid tumors</article-title>. <source>Med. Oncol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>243</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>259</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/MO:18:4:243</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11918451</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaupel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Briest</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;ckel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Hypoxia in breast cancer: pathogenesis, characterization and biological/therapeutic implications</article-title>. <source>Wiener Medizinische Wochenschrift</source>
<volume>152</volume>, <fpage>334</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>342</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1563-258X.2002.02032.x</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12168517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vaupel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>H&#246;ckel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Tumor hypoxia and malignant progression</article-title>. In <source>Methods in enzymology</source> (eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abelson</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group>), vol.&#160;<volume>381</volume>, pp.&#160;<fpage>335</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>354</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Amsterdam, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Hypoxia and hypoxia-inducible factors: master regulators of metastasis</article-title>. <source>Clin. Cancer. Res.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>5928</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>5935</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-10-1360</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20962028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mujcic</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Koritzinsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wouters</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Hypoxia signaling and the metastatic phenotype</article-title>. <source>Curr. Mol. Med.</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>565</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24894165</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Hypoxia-driven selection of the metastatic phenotype</article-title>. <source>Cancer Metastasis Rev.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>319</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>331</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10555-007-9062-2</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17458507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Markelc</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bates</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muschel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Estimating oxygen distribution from vasculature in three-dimensional tumour tissue</article-title>. <source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <elocation-id content-type="artnum">20160070</elocation-id> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2016.0070</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26935806</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rankin</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giaccia</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Hypoxia: signaling the metastatic cascade</article-title>. <source>Trends Cancer</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>304</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trecan.2016.05.006</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28741527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Secomb</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>EY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dewhirst</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Green's function methods for analysis of oxygen delivery to tissue by microvascular networks</article-title>. <source>Ann. Biomed. Eng.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>1519</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1529</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15636112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschhaeuser</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Menne</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dittfeld</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>West</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller-Klieser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kunz-Schughart</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Multicellular tumor spheroids: an underestimated tool is catching up again</article-title>. <source>J. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>148</volume>, <fpage>3</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>15</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jbiotec.2010.01.012</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20097238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillaume</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fehrenbach</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lobjois</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducommun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Oxygen partial pressure is a rate-limiting parameter for cell proliferation in 3D spheroids grown in physioxic culture condition</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e0161239</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0161239</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27575790</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Methods: using three-dimensional culture (spheroids) as an <italic>in vitro</italic> model of tumour hypoxia</article-title>. In <source>Tumor microenvironment</source> (eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koumenis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coussens</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giaccia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>), pp. <fpage>167</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>196</lpage>. <publisher-loc>Berlin, Germany</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rainaldi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Indovina</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Multicellular tumour spheroids in radiation biology</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Radiat. Biol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>, <fpage>787</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>799</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/095530099139845</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10489890</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dubessy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Merlin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marchal</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillemin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Spheroids in radiobiology and photodynamic therapy</article-title>. <source>Crit. Rev. Oncol. Hematol.</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>192</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1040-8428(00)00085-8</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11033305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Madsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tromberg</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cristini</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Magalh&#160;aes</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Multicell tumor spheroids in photodynamic therapy</article-title>. <source>Lasers Surg. Med.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>555</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>564</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/lsm.20350</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16788918</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kempf</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bleicher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meyer-Hermann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Spatio-temporal cell dynamics in tumour spheroid irradiation</article-title>. <source>Eur. Phys. J. D</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>193</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1140/epjd/e2010-00178-4</pub-id>)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dufau</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frongia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sicard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dedieu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cordelier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ausseil</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducommun</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Valette</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Multicellular tumor spheroid model to evaluate spatio-temporal dynamics effect of chemotherapeutics: application to the gemcitabine/CHK1 inhibitor combination in pancreatic cancer</article-title>. <source>BMC Cancer</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2407-12-15</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22244109</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ingram</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Luker</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Opportunities and challenges for use of tumor spheroids as models to test drug delivery and efficacy</article-title>. <source>J. Control. Release</source>
<volume>164</volume>, <fpage>192</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>204</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jconrel.2012.04.045</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22613880</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mount</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gombotz</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pun</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The delivery of doxorubicin to 3-D multicellular spheroids and tumors in a murine xenograft model using tumor-penetrating triblock polymeric micelles</article-title>. <source>Biomaterials</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>7386</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>7397</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2010.06.004</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20598741</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vinci</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Advances in establishment and analysis of three-dimensional tumor spheroid-based functional assays for target validation and drug evaluation</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1741-7007-10-29</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22439642</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kannan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kavanagh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Siddiky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wigfield</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The role of oxygen in avascular tumor growth</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <fpage>e0153692</fpage> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0153692</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27088720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<italic>et al.</italic>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Expansion of CD133<sup>+</sup> colon cancer cultures retaining stem cell properties to enable cancer stem cell target discovery</article-title>. <source>Br. J. Cancer</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>1265</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>1275</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.bjc.6605610</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20332776</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hussien</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Muschel</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>3D tumour spheroids as a model to assess the suitability of [18F] FDG-PET as an early indicator of response to PI3K inhibition</article-title>. <source>Nucl. Med. Biol.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>986</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>992</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nucmedbio.2012.04.006</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22682985</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mueller-Klieser</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1984</year>
<article-title>Method for the determination of oxygen consumption rates and diffusion coefficients in multicellular spheroids</article-title>. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>343</fpage>&#8211;<lpage>348</lpage>. (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(84)84030-8</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6487734</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A method for estimating the oxygen consumption rate in multicellular tumour spheroids</article-title>. <source>J. R. Soc. Interface</source>
<volume>11</volume>, <elocation-id content-type="artnum">20131124</elocation-id> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2013.1124</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24430128</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grimes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Partridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Oxygen consumption dynamics in steady-state tumour models</article-title>. <source>R. Soc. open. sci.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, <elocation-id content-type="artnum">140080</elocation-id> (<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.140080</pub-id>)<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26064525</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Prolate spheroidal coordinates (Wikipedia entry). 2018 See <uri xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prolate_spheroidal_coordinates">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prolate_spheroidal_coordinates</uri></comment>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="RSIF20180256C35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><comment>Oblate spheroidal coordinates (Wikipedia entry). 2018 See <uri xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oblate_spheroidal_coordinates">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oblate_spheroidal_coordinates</uri></comment>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>