<!DOCTYPE article SYSTEM "xmlstuff">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3378692</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22723975</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-04153</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0039247</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Polymorphism</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Autoimmunity</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Clinical Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetic Testing</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Clinical Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject><subj-group><subject>Immunity to Infections</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Allergy and Hypersensitivity</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Otorhinolaryngology</subject><subj-group><subject>Rhinology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="9738" pm="."><plain>Polymorphisms in RYBP and AOAH Genes Are Associated with Chronic Rhinosinusitis in a Chinese Population: A Replication Study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">SNPs in RYBP and AOAH and Chronic Rhinosinusitis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yuan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Endam</surname><given-names>Leandra Mfuna</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Filali-Mouhim</surname><given-names>Abdelali</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Liping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Desrosiers</surname><given-names>Martin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Demin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Luo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Beijing TongRen Hospital, Capital Medical University, Beijing, People’s Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Key Laboratory Otolaryngology Head and Neck Surgery, Ministry of Education of China, Beijing Institute of Otolaryngology, Beijing, People’s Republic of China</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Department of Otolaryngology, Centre de Recherche du Centre Hospitalier de l’Université de Montréal (CRCHUM), Montreal, Quebec, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery, Montreal General Hospital, McGill University, Montreal, Quebec, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>Luzia Helena</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">Centro de Pesquisa Rene Rachou/Fundação Oswaldo Cruz (Fiocruz-Minas), Brazil</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>dr.luozhang@gmail.com</email> (LZ); <email>handm@trhos.com</email> (DH); <email>desrosiers_martin@hotmail.com</email> (MD)</corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="9739" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: YZ MD L. Zhang. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9741" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: YZ LE AF MD L. Zhao. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9743" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: YZ LE AF L. Zhao MD DH L. Zhang. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9746" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: YZ LE AF L. Zhao MD DH L. Zhang. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9749" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: YZ MD L. Zhang. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e39247</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>2</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Zhang et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9751" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9752" pm="."><plain>The development of CRS is believed to be the result of combined interactions between the genetic background of the affected subject and environmental factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9753" pm="."><plain>Objectives </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9754" pm="."><plain>To replicate and extend our recent findings from genetic association studies in chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS) performed in a Canadian Caucasian population in a Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9755" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9756" pm="."><plain>In a case-control replication study, DNA samples were obtained from CRS with (n = 306; CRSwNP) and without (n = 332; CRSsNP) nasal polyps, and controls (n = 315) in a Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9757" pm="."><plain>A total of forty-nine single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) selected from previous identified SNPs associated with CRS in Canadian population, and SNPs from the CHB HapMap dataset were individually genotyped. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9758" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9759" pm="."><plain>We identified two SNPs respectively in RYBP (rs4532099, p = 2.15E–06, OR = 2.59) and AOAH (rs4504543, p = 0.0001152, OR = 0.58) significantly associated with whole CRS cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9760" pm="."><plain>Subgroup analysis for the presence of nasal polyps (CRSwNP and CRSsNP) displayed significant association in CRSwNP cohorts regarding to one SNP in RYBP (P = 3.24E–006, OR = 2.76). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9761" pm="."><plain>Evidence of association in the CRSsNP groups in terms of 2 SNPs (AOAH_rs4504543 and RYBP_rs4532099) was detected as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9762" pm="."><plain>Stratifying analysis by gender demonstrated that none of the selected SNPs were associated with CRSwNP as well as CRSsNP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9763" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile 3 SNPs (IL1A_rs17561, P = 0.005778; IL1A_rs1800587, P = 0.009561; IRAK4_rs4251513, P = 0.03837) were associated with serum total IgE level. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="9764" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9765" pm="."><plain>These genes are biologically plausible, with roles in regulation of transcription (RYBP) and inflammatory response (AOAH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9766" pm="."><plain>The present data suggests the potential common genetic basis in the development of CRS in Chinese and Caucasian population. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="9767" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9768" pm="."><plain>Chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS) is a common inflammatory disorder of the sinus and paranasal sinus mucosa with a highly heterogeneous pathogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9769" pm="."><plain>Because of its negative impact on patients’ quality of life and the concomitant increasing social economic burden, CRS has become a global health problem [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9770" pm="."><plain>The development of CRS is believed to be the result of combinations between the genetic background of the affected subject and environmental factors [1], [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9771" pm="."><plain>However, there is still no clear answer as to their exact contributions to the process and the mechanisms of pathogenesis of CRS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9772" pm="."><plain>A genetic basis to sinusitis is strongly suggested by clinical and experimental evidence [3]–[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9773" pm="."><plain>In humans, genetic disorder such as cystic fibrosis and primary ciliary dyskinesia [11] are frequently associated with development of sinusitis in knockout mouse models, deletion of several genes leads to development of sinusitis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9774" pm="."><plain>It has been demonstrated that single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in several genes are associated with CRS [3]–[10] These are biologically plausible, with roles in regulation of transcription (Ring1A and YY1 binding protein, RYBP) [12]_ENREF_13, inflammatory response (acyloxyacyl hydroxylase, AOAH) [13] and innate immune response (IL1RL1 [5], [14] and interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase 4 (IRAK4) [6], [15]), are associated with chronic rhinosinusitis (CRS) in a Canadian Caucasian population [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9775" pm="."><plain>Replication of results of a genetic disease association study in independent samples has emerged as a standard for demonstrating the relevance of a candidate gene for a complex trait. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9776" pm="."><plain>Given the evidence above, genetic backgroung plays potencial roles in the development of CRS and we hypothesized genes which were demontrated as susceptible genes for CRS in Caucasian population also exerted effects in Chinese cohort. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9777" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the aim of this study was to replicate polymorphisms in the genes performed in Canadian Caucasian population previously are associated with the Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9778" pm="."><plain>A population-based case-control association analysis was used to assess the risk of CRS conferred by SNPs in the candidate genes in our Han Chinese cohort. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="9779" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="9780" pm="."><plain>Study Subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9781" pm="."><plain>306 CRS with nasal polyps (CRSwNP subjects) (180 males and 126 females) and 332 individuals affected with CRS without nasal polyps (CRSsNP) (190 males and 142 females) were prospectively recruited from the rhinology ward of Beijing Tongren Hospital between February 2008 to July 2009. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9782" pm="."><plain>A total of 315 healthy controls, of which 146 (46.3%) were female, were recruited as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9783" pm="."><plain>All the subjects were of Chinese Han ethnic origin and all from the north region of China. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9784" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the Beijing Tongren Hospital Ethics Committee, and written informed consent was obtained from all participants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="9785" pm="."><plain>Diagnosis of CRSwNP and CRSsNP was based on American Academy of Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery (AAO-HNS) 2004 guidelines [17], based on assement by a single ENT doctor specialized in sinus diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9786" pm="."><plain>All the CRS cases recruited in present study were unresponsive to all forms of medical therapies such as topical or intranasal corticosteroid and long term-low dose antibiotic or presented persistent signs/symptoms of CRS despite previous endoscopic sinus surgery (ESS). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9787" pm="."><plain>Patients were interviewed by trained personnel, and a standardized questionnaire was used to obtain items including demographic variables and personal and familial antecedents of allergies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9788" pm="."><plain>Patients also underwent a standard set of laboratory tests that included measurements of total IgE to assess allergic status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9789" pm="."><plain>Controls were recruited following two strategies: either spouses or non-blood relatives living in the same household and individuals recruited from a geographic area similar to that of CRS patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9790" pm="."><plain>The only attempt at matching subjects and control is their geographical location to minimize differences secondary to differences in potential environmental exposures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9791" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, a standardized questionnaire assessing age, sex and ethnic origin (but not smoking, history of atopy or physician diagnosed asthma) was obtained for controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9792" pm="."><plain>Moreover, all the controls showed negative of serum phadiatop determination. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="9793" pm="."><plain>SNP Selection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="9794" pm="."><plain>A total of forty-one single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) selected from previous identified associated with CRS in Canadian population [3], [5]–[7], [9], [10], [16], [18], [19] were choose for genotying (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9795" pm="."><plain>In addition, SNPs in IRAK4 gene from the CHB HapMap dataset were also individually genotyped. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9796" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the International Haplotype Mapping (HapMap) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hapmap.org">www.hapmap.org</ext-link>) SNP databases were used to select SNPs in the IRAK4 gene region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9797" pm="."><plain>The screened region was extended 10 kilobases upstream of the annotated transcription start site and downstream at the end of the last IRAK4 exon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9798" pm="."><plain>The SNPs were selected to extract the most genetic information based on CHB haplotype data using the HAPMAP database (Hapmap Data Rel 27 Phase II+III, Feb09) [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9799" pm="."><plain>From this dataset, 34 SNPs in IRAK4 gene region were selected using a pairwise tagging algorithm implemented in Haploview version 4.1 program [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9800" pm="."><plain>In addition, when we set Hardy-Weinberg p value cutoff, minor allele frequency and r2 thresholds at 0.01, 0.05 and 0.8, respectively, the LD pattern for IRAK4 gene in our population showed strong LD in several groups of SNPs, indicating that the SNPs in each group represent a common region (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9801" pm="."><plain>Consequently, we choose 10 SNPs including rs4251513, rs1461567, rs3794262, rs4251481, rs4251540, rs4251569, rs6582484, rs4251431, rs1870765 and rs12302873 to represent the entire 34 loci for eventual genotyping and the former two SNPs were composed in the selected SNPs from the previous identified associated with CRS in Canadian population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9802" pm="."><plain>Therefore, 49 SNPs constituted the selection set to be genotyped in our patient and controls eventually. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="10311" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="10312" pm="."><plain>In this study, we replicate a number of genes in CRS in previously identified in Caucasians in a Han Chinese population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10313" pm="."><plain>Genes associated with CRS and the Caucasian population has not yet being replicated in the Chinese population and the replication suggests a common basis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10314" pm="."><plain>The genes identified are of potential important biological significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10315" pm="."><plain>RYBP is a regulator of transcription [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10316" pm="."><plain>ILIRL1 is associated with Toll-like receptor (TLR) signaling regulation [14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10317" pm="."><plain>SNPs in the IL1RL1 gene have previously been shown to affect serum level of eosinophilia and IgE in other models [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10318" pm="."><plain>IRAK4 also is implicated as a signaling intermediate in the TLR signaling pathway [16], [22], and SNPs in the IRAK4 gene have been documented to have a functional impact, within genotype specific effect on serum IgE level [6], [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10319" pm="."><plain>Importance of TLR signaling is suggested by their role in detecting and regulating responses to gram-positive and gram-negative bacteria. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10320" pm="."><plain>Importance of IRAK-4 is suggested by the description of an enhanced susceptibility to infection with gram-positive bacteria in IRAK-4 deficient children. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10321" pm="."><plain>Previous work from the Desrosiers group has identified altered function of the TLR signaling system as key to the pathogenesis of CRS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10322" pm="."><plain>Using complex-model analysis of pooling-based genome wide association testing on the Canadian population with CRS, they identified the polymorphisms at multiple levels of the TLR signaling cascade all confer an increased risk in CRS [2], [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10323" pm="."><plain>Functional support for this concept has been provided by in vitro model of epithelial cell culture documenting reduced response to TLR agonists in epithelial cells from CRS patients [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10324" pm="."><plain>The identification of the AOAH gene is also of potential significant interest and suggests a novel mechanism for the development of CRS, again implicating an innate immune signaling, but in a novel fashion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10325" pm="."><plain>AOAH is responsible for degrading lipopolysaccharide (LPS), and dysfunctional AOAH gene function leads to decreased LPS degradation with unopposed continued LPS stimulation via a TLR-4 dependant mechanism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10326" pm="."><plain>In AOAH knockout mouse models, persistent inflammation following LPS stimulation is observed [25]–[27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10327" pm="."><plain>Supporting a role in airway disease, the AOAH gene has previously been implicated in a genome wide scan for asthma [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10328" pm="."><plain>Corresponding to the above literature, here we presented that rs4504543 in the AOAH gene played a protective role (OR = 0.58) in CRS with a strong P value (P = 0.0001152). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10329" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the AOAH_ rs4504543 loci was also revealed as a protective factor (OR = 0.30) in CRSsNP group with a stronger P value (P = 8.11–011), indicating that AOAH gene might exert a crucial protective role in the development of CRS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10330" pm="."><plain>RYBP is a zinc finger protein with an essential role during embryonic development, which binds transcriptional factors, polycomb products, and mediators of apoptosis, suggesting roles in apparently,unrelated functions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10331" pm="."><plain>Gene products of the RYBP gene inhibit ubiquitination and subsequent degradation of TP53, and, by interacting with MDM2, play a role in regulating transcription of TP53 target genes and promoting apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10332" pm="."><plain>Recent findings have also suggested that RYBP may also play a role in epigenetic regulation [28], and contribute to defense against retroviruses [29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10333" pm="."><plain>It is thus possible that polymorphisms in the RYBP gene may be implicated in CRS by dysregulating TP53 activity in TP53 or in its target genes via alteration of RYBP gene products or by altering binding at regulatory binding sites in the RYBP gene promotor area, which contains binding sites for the following transcription factors (YY1, IRF-1, C/EBPA, GATA-1, POU2F1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10334" pm="."><plain>This may contribute to the inflammation observed in CRS, promoting epithelial dysfunction with secondary bacterial colonization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10335" pm="."><plain>In contrast to AOAH gene, polymorphisms in the RYBP gene was exhibited here for the first time as a significantly risk factor of CRS and either of the subgroups (CRSsNP and CRSwNP) with high OR values (ORCRS = 2.59; ORCRSsNP = 2.76; ORCRSwNP = 2.45), suggesting the variation of rs4532099 in RYBP could increase the risk of CRS development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10336" pm="."><plain>IL1RL1 gene is involved in regulation of TLR signaling and has recently also been implicated as the receptor for IL-33. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10337" pm="."><plain>Its role in development of CRS may be via interfering with TLR signaling, or via an alteration of IL-33 homeostasis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10338" pm="."><plain>Taken overall, all of the replicated genes have disparate functions, but evidence supports that dysfunctions in each these genes may conceivably contribute to development of CRS, underlining the concept that CRS represents a common morphological appearance of clinical disease as an endpoint of multiple unique pathogenic mechasnisms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10339" pm="."><plain>Our study has obvious limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10340" pm="."><plain>First and most noticeable is the small group size of the sample used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10341" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, given the limited number of genes genotyped in this replication study, feet corrected P value remains significant and, in the case of the RYBP and AOAH genes, is highly significant with a high odds ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10342" pm="."><plain>A second consideration is the ethnic variability in SNP frequency known for these genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10343" pm="."><plain>It is clear that in this study, we have replicated SNPs associated in a Caucasian population, and have not performed extensive fine mapping studies of the gene which might identify other risk SNPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10344" pm="."><plain>As shown in this example however, when gene coverage is adjusted to better reflect tagging SNP selection for the CHB data set, we are able to identify significant polymorphisms within the IRAK4 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="10345" pm="."><plain>We replicate several genes which were proved to be associated with CRS in Caucasian population in a Chinese population, suggesting a common basis to the development of the disease in both population types. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10346" pm="."><plain>Of interest is the potential implication of inflammatory pathways, suggesting dysfunction in TLR signaling as a critical element in chronic rhinosinusitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10347" pm="."><plain>While these studies have significant limitations, they nevertheless offer a basis for further exploration of a role for immune signaling and response to bacteria in further studies of CRS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="10348" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors declare that co-author Luo Zhang is a PLoS ONE Editorial Board member. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10349" pm="."><plain>This does not alter the authors’ adherence to all the PLoS ONE policies on sharing data and materials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10350" pm="."><plain>All other authors declare that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="10351" pm="."><plain>Funding: This work was supported by grants from the National Science Fund for Distinguished Young Scholars (81025007), the National Natural Science Foundation of China (30973282 and 81100706), the Beijing Natural Science Foundation (7102030), the Special Fund of Sanitation Elite Reconstruction of Beijing (2009-2-007), and Beijing Nova Program (2010B022) to LZ and YZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10352" pm="."><plain>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0039247-Tewfik1"><text><SENT sid="10353" pm="."><plain>1 TewfikMABosseYAl-ShemariHDesrosiersM 2010 Genetics of chronic rhinosinusitis: a primer. J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 39 62 68 20122347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-MfunaEndam1"><text><SENT sid="10354" pm="."><plain>2 Mfuna-EndamLZhangYDesrosiersMY 2011 Genetics of rhinosinusitis. Curr Allergy Asthma Rep 11 236 246 21499907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Castano1"><text><SENT sid="10355" pm="."><plain>3 CastanoRBosseYEndamLMFilali-MouhimADesrosiersM 2010 c-MET pathway involvement in chronic rhinosinusitis: a genetic association analysis. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 142: 665–671 e661–662  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Tournas1"><text><SENT sid="10356" pm="."><plain>4 TournasAMfunaLBosseYFilali-MouhimAGrenierJP 2010 A pooling-based genome-wide association study implicates the p73 gene in chronic rhinosinusitis. J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 39 188 195 20211107 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Castano2"><text><SENT sid="10357" pm="."><plain>5 CastanoRBosseYEndamLMDesrosiersM 2009 Evidence of association of interleukin-1 receptor-like 1 gene polymorphisms with chronic rhinosinusitis. Am J Rhinol Allergy 23 377 384 19671251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Tewfik2"><text><SENT sid="10358" pm="."><plain>6 TewfikMABosseYLemireMHudsonTJVallee-SmejdaS 2009 Polymorphisms in interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase 4 are associated with total serum IgE. Allergy 64 746 753 19254290 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-MfunaEndam2"><text><SENT sid="10359" pm="."><plain>7 Mfuna EndamLCormierCBosseYFilali-MouhimADesrosiersM 2010 Association of IL1A, IL1B, and TNF gene polymorphisms with chronic rhinosinusitis with and without nasal polyposis: A replication study. Arch Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 136 187 192 20157068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Nader1"><text><SENT sid="10360" pm="."><plain>8 NaderMEAbou-JaoudePCabalunaMDesrosiersM 2010 Using Response to a Standardized Treatment to Identify Phenotypes for Genetic Studies of Chronic Rhinosinusitis. Journal of Otolaryngology-Head &amp; Neck Surgery 39 69 75 20122348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Kilty1"><text><SENT sid="10361" pm="."><plain>9 KiltySJBosseYCormierCEndamLMDesrosiersMY 2010 Polymorphisms in the SERPINA1 (Alpha-1-Antitrypsin) gene are associated with severe chronic rhinosinusitis unresponsive to medical therapy. Am J Rhinol Allergy 24 e4 9 20109307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Zhang1"><text><SENT sid="10362" pm="."><plain>10 ZhangYEndamLMFilali-MouhimABosseYCastanoR 2011 Polymorphisms in the nitric oxide synthase 1 gene are associated with severe chronic rhinosinusitis. Am J Rhinol Allergy 25 e49 54 21679499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Lee1"><text><SENT sid="10363" pm="."><plain>11 LeeLCampagnaDRPinkusJLMulhernHWyattTA 2008 Primary ciliary dyskinesia in mice lacking the novel ciliary protein Pcdp1. Mol Cell Biol 28 949 957 18039845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Bejarano1"><text><SENT sid="10364" pm="."><plain>12 BejaranoFGonzalezIVidalMBusturiaA 2005 The Drosophila RYBP gene functions as a Polycomb-dependent transcriptional repressor. Mech Dev 122 1118 1129 16125914 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Barnes1"><text><SENT sid="10365" pm="."><plain>13 BarnesKCGrantAGaoPBaltadjievaDBergT 2006 Polymorphisms in the novel gene acyloxyacyl hydroxylase (AOAH) are associated with asthma and associated phenotypes. J Allergy Clin Immunol 118 70 77 16815140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Savenije1"><text><SENT sid="10366" pm="."><plain>14 SavenijeOEKerkhofMReijmerinkNEBrunekreefBde JongsteJC 2011 Interleukin-1 receptor-like 1 polymorphisms are associated with serum IL1RL1-a, eosinophils, and asthma in childhood. J Allergy Clin Immunol 127: 750–756 e751–755  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Kim1"><text><SENT sid="10367" pm="."><plain>15 KimTWStaschkeKBulekKYaoJPetersK 2007 A critical role for IRAK4 kinase activity in Toll-like receptor-mediated innate immunity. J Exp Med 204 1025 1036 17470642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Bosse1"><text><SENT sid="10368" pm="."><plain>16 BosseYBacotFMontpetitARungJQuHQ 2009 Identification of susceptibility genes for complex diseases using pooling-based genome-wide association scans. Hum Genet 125 305 318 19184112 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Meltzer1"><text><SENT sid="10369" pm="."><plain>17 MeltzerEOHamilosDLHadleyJALanzaDCMarpleBF 2004 Rhinosinusitis: Establishing definitions for clinical research and patient care. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 131 S1 62 15577816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Endam1"><text><SENT sid="10370" pm="."><plain>18 EndamLMBosseYFilali-MouhimACormierCBoisvertP 2009 Polymorphisms in the interleukin-22 receptor alpha-1 gene are associated with severe chronic rhinosinusitis. Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 140 741 747 19393422 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Cormier1"><text><SENT sid="10371" pm="."><plain>19 CormierCBosseYMfunaLHudsonTJDesrosiersM 2009 Polymorphisms in the tumour necrosis factor alpha-induced protein 3 (TNFAIP3) gene are associated with chronic rhinosinusitis. J Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg 38 133 141 19344623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-1"><text><SENT sid="10372" pm="."><plain>20 2005 A haplotype map of the human genome. Nature 437 1299 1320 16255080 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Barrett1"><text><SENT sid="10373" pm="."><plain>21 BarrettJCFryBMallerJDalyMJ 2005 Haploview: analysis and visualization of LD and haplotype maps. Bioinformatics 21 263 265 15297300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Suzuki1"><text><SENT sid="10374" pm="."><plain>22 SuzukiNSaitoT 2006 IRAK-4–a shared NF-kappaB activator in innate and acquired immunity. Trends Immunol 27 566 572 17046325 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Zhang2"><text><SENT sid="10375" pm="."><plain>23 ZhangYLinXDesrosiersMZhangWMengN 2011 Association pattern of interleukin-1 receptor-associated kinase-4 gene polymorphisms with allergic rhinitis in a Han Chinese population. PLoS One 6 e21769 21738793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-C1"><text><SENT sid="10376" pm="."><plain>24 CDivoySRousseauJBerubeL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10377" pm="."><plain>MfunaEndamAFilali-Mouhim 2011 Epithelial Cells From Chronic Rhinosinusitis Patients Are Hyporesponsive To Bacteria: Evidence Of Innate Immune Dysfunction In CRS. J Allergy Clin Immunol AB2 AB3  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Shao1"><text><SENT sid="10378" pm="."><plain>25 ShaoBLuMKatzSCVarleyAWHardwickJ 2007 A host lipase detoxifies bacterial lipopolysaccharides in the liver and spleen. J Biol Chem 282 13726 13735 17322564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Ojogun1"><text><SENT sid="10379" pm="."><plain>26 OjogunNKuangTYShaoBGreavesDRMunfordRS 2009 Overproduction of acyloxyacyl hydrolase by macrophages and dendritic cells prevents prolonged reactions to bacterial lipopolysaccharide in vivo. J Infect Dis 200 1685 1693 19860560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Lu1"><text><SENT sid="10380" pm="."><plain>27 LuMVarleyAWOhtaSHardwickJMunfordRS 2008 Host inactivation of bacterial lipopolysaccharide prevents prolonged tolerance following gram-negative bacterial infection. Cell Host Microbe 4 293 302 18779055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Tavares1"><text><SENT sid="10381" pm="."><plain>28 TavaresLDimitrovaEOxleyDWebsterJPootR 2012 RYBP-PRC1 complexes mediate H2A ubiquitylation at polycomb target sites independently of PRC2 and H3K27me3. Cell 148 664 678 22325148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0039247-Hisada1"><text><SENT sid="10382" pm="."><plain>29 HisadaKSanchezCEndoTAEndohMRoman-TruferoM 2012 RYBP represses endogenous retroviruses and preimplantation- and germ line-specific genes in mouse embryonic stem cells. Mol Cell Biol 32 1139 1149 22269950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
