<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4827067</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">srep24104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep24104</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="39457" pm="."><plain>Prickle3 synergizes with Wtip to regulate basal body organization and cilia growth </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Chih-Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ossipova</surname><given-names>Olga</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>Andriani</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>Sergei Y.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Department of Developmental and Regenerative Biology, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai</institution>, New York, NY 10029, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label><email>sergei.sokol@mssm.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>04</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>24104</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>03</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2016, Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Macmillan Publishers Limited</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article’s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="39458" pm="."><plain>PCP proteins maintain planar polarity in many epithelial tissues and have been implicated in cilia development in vertebrate embryos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39459" pm="."><plain>In this study we examine Prickle3 (Pk3), a vertebrate homologue of Drosophila Prickle, in Xenopus gastrocoel roof plate (GRP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39460" pm="."><plain>GRP is a tissue equivalent to the mouse node, in which cilia-generated flow promotes left-right patterning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39461" pm="."><plain>We show that Pk3 is enriched at the basal body of GRP cells but is recruited by Vangl2 to anterior cell borders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39462" pm="."><plain>Interference with Pk3 function disrupted the anterior polarization of endogenous Vangl2 and the posterior localization of cilia in GRP cells, demonstrating its role in PCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39463" pm="."><plain>Strikingly, in cells with reduced Pk3 activity, cilia growth was inhibited and γ-tubulin and Nedd1 no longer associated with the basal body, suggesting that Pk3 has a novel function in basal body organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39464" pm="."><plain>Mechanistically, this function of Pk3 may involve Wilms tumor protein 1-interacting protein (Wtip), which physically associates with and cooperates with Pk3 to regulate ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39465" pm="."><plain>We propose that, in addition to cell polarity, PCP components control basal body organization and function. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="39466" pm="."><plain>During development, embryonic cells often become oriented in the plane of the tissue, causing visibly polarized patterns, such as in the Drosophila cuticle or mammalian hair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39467" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon is known as planar cell polarity (PCP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39468" pm="."><plain>Studies of Drosophila epithelia demonstrated that PCP is maintained largely by molecular interactions that lead to mutually exclusive distribution of two ‘core’ protein complexes, Frizzled (Fz)-Dishevelled (Dvl) and Van Gogh (Vang)-Prickle (Pk) to opposite sides of an epithelial cell12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39469" pm="."><plain>In vertebrate embryos, planar cell polarity signaling has been documented in several tissues, such as the cochlea, the skin, and the neural plate345678910. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39470" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, loss-of-function studies established a requirement of vertebrate PCP components in diverse cell behaviors including mediolateral and radial cell intercalations, apical constriction and cell migration8111213141516. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39471" pm="."><plain>This evidence demonstrates the expanded roles of vertebrate PCP proteins in multiple developmental processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39472" pm="."><plain>Besides morphogenetic events, PCP components are involved in other processes associated with cell polarity, such as asymmetric cell division1718 or left-right patterning19202122. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39473" pm="."><plain>Several core PCP proteins are enriched at the centrosome and/or basal body232425262728, but the functional significance of this localization is not understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39474" pm="."><plain>Consistent with a possible function at the basal body, core PCP proteins have been shown to control cilia development and function1920212223293031. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39475" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, the role of PCP proteins in basal body organization largely remains to be investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39476" pm="."><plain>Drosophila Prickle is a cytoplasmic LIM domain protein, which physically associates with Vang and functions in PCP establishment3233. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39477" pm="."><plain>The existence of four vertebrate prickle gene homologues suggests that they may have diverged from each other and acquired unique functions, as reported for celsr/flamingo genes34. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39478" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this possibility, the vertebrate Prickle family has been implicated in a number of developmental processes, including convergent extension movements, apicobasal and planar cell polarity3536373839. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39479" pm="."><plain>Moreover, interference with Pk1 and Pk2 functions resulted in defective cilia growth and morphology40414243. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39480" pm="."><plain>Prickle3 (Pk3), also known as LMO6, is a largely unstudied family member that has been implicated in radial intercalation of multi-ciliated cells in Xenopus ectoderm13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39481" pm="."><plain>In mammalian cells, Pk3 was reported to localize to mitotic spindle poles and centrioles4445, suggesting that it may be involved in centrosome function. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39482" pm="."><plain>To study roles of Pk3 in PCP and basal body/centrosome function, we examined Xenopus gastrocoel roof plate (GRP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39483" pm="."><plain>GRP is homologous to mouse posterior notochord or zebrafish Kupffer’s vesicle and represents the posterior-most part of the archenteron (Fig. 1A)4647484950. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39484" pm="."><plain>In this tissue, motile cilia generate unilateral fluid flow critical for left-right patterning, which is controlled by PCP signaling51. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39485" pm="."><plain>We report that GFP-Pk3 is enriched at the basal body of GRP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39486" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of Vangl2 leads to the recruitment of Pk3 to anterior cell borders in GRP cells, consistent with endogenous Vangl2 distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39487" pm="."><plain>Interference with Pk3 activity in GRP cells suppressed anterior Vangl2 polarization, posterior cilia positioning and cilia growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39488" pm="."><plain>In addition to the roles of Pk3 in PCP and cilia formation, we find that Pk3 is required for γ-tubulin and Nedd1 recruitment to the basal body, indicating a new function in basal body organization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39489" pm="."><plain>We show that this function may be mediated through the association and functional synergy of Pk3 with Wilm’s tumor protein-1-interacting protein (Wtip), a vertebrate-specific LIM domain protein. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="39490" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39491" pm="."><plain>Pk3 is localized to the basal body of GRP cells, but becomes polarized to the anterior cell boundary in the presence of Vangl2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39492" pm="."><plain>We have recently shown that RNA encoding Pk3 is present in the early Xenopus embryo13 and decided to assess protein subcellular localization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39493" pm="."><plain>The GRP tissue allows the examination of both basal body/cilia development and planar polarity, which is manifested by posterior positioning of cilia in each cell224952. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39494" pm="."><plain>In GRP cells, GFP-Pk3 was present throughout the cytoplasm and enriched at the base of the cilium (Fig. 1A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39495" pm="."><plain>By contrast, we observed that endogenous Vangl2 was enriched at anterior cell edges (Fig. 1C), virtually identical to its distribution in neural plate cells6. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39496" pm="."><plain>Since Prickle and Vang are known to physically interact3353, we wanted to test whether Vangl2 can promote Pk3 polarization at the cell cortex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39497" pm="."><plain>Indeed, in the presence of Vangl2, Pk3 was recruited to the anterior cell boundary in mosaically-expressing GRP cells (Fig. 1D–D’’), consistent with the anterior distribution of endogenous Vangl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39498" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests that Pk3 cortical localization may be regulated by Vangl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39499" pm="."><plain>We next evaluated physical association between Pk3 and Vangl2 in transfected human embryonic kidney 293T (HEK293T) cells, in order to identify the Pk3 domain responsible for this interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39500" pm="."><plain>Although Drosophila Pk binds Vang through its C-terminal tail33, the C-termini of Pk3 and Pk are highly divergent, with less than 11% amino acid identity (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39501" pm="."><plain>We, therefore, generated the C-terminal Pk3 construct (Pk3C) and the one that lacks the C-terminus (Pk3ΔC) to test their association with Vangl2 (Fig. 1E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39502" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitation analysis showed that HA-Vangl2 was efficiently pulled down with FLAG-tagged Pk3 and Pk3C but not Pk3∆C (Fig. 1F), indicating that the Vangl2-binding domain is located at the C terminus of Pk3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39503" pm="."><plain>Together, these observations demonstrate that Pk3 accumulates at the basal body of GRP cells and can be recruited to the anterior cell boundary by Vangl2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39504" pm="."><plain>Interference with Pk3 activity reveals its roles in cell polarity and ciliogenesis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39505" pm="."><plain>To further investigate the function of Pk3 by depleting the protein in GRP cells, we designed two anti-sense morpholino oligonucleotides (MOs) with nonoverlapping target sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39506" pm="."><plain>Upon injection into early embryos, both Pk3MO1 and Pk3MO2 efficiently blocked the in vivo translation of Pk3-GFP RNA but not FLAG-GFP RNA in co-expression experiments (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39507" pm="."><plain>When targeted to GRP cells, both MOs severely impaired the positioning of cilia (Fig. 2B–E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39508" pm="."><plain>Cilia were positioned posteriorly in 68% of the GRP cells that received control MO (CoMO), but the same position of cilia was observed only in 21% of Pk3MO1- and Pk3MO2-injected cells (Fig. 2E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39509" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that Pk3 controls proper cilia positioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39510" pm="."><plain>Notably, cilia in embryos depleted of Pk3 were significantly shorter (Fig. 2C,D,F), indicating an additional role of Pk3 in ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39511" pm="."><plain>These effects were partially rescued by coinjected GFP-Pk3 RNA (Fig. 2G–I), further demonstrating specificity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39512" pm="."><plain>A role for Pk3 in planar polarity was confirmed by the disruption of Vangl2 polarization in Pk3MO1-injected GRP cells but not in CoMO-injected cells (Fig. 3A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39513" pm="."><plain>As Pk3MO2 was less effective and required higher doses, Pk3MO1 was chosen for subsequent analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39514" pm="."><plain>Given that the C-terminus of Pk3 interacts with Vangl2 (Fig. 1F), we suspected that Pk3C expression may have a dominant interfering effect leading to similar PCP defects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39515" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the asymmetric distribution of Vangl2 was lost in cells expressing GFP-Pk3C (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39516" pm="."><plain>In addition, cilia in these cells were short and failed to locate posteriorly, phenocopying Pk3MO injections (Fig. 3D) and suggesting that the C-terminal tail regulates Pk3 activity both in PCP and in ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39517" pm="."><plain>These effects were not observed after GFP or GFP-Pk3ΔC expression (Supplementary Fig. 1A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39518" pm="."><plain>Of note, the manipulation of Pk3 levels led to occasional alteration of cell size, supporting a possible role of Pk3 in cell cycle regulation (Fig. 3B,C and data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39519" pm="."><plain>Since these changes were variable and visible only in some embryos, we did not assess this defect in subsequent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39520" pm="."><plain>Taken together, our observations demonstrate roles of Pk3 in PCP and cilia development in GRP cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39521" pm="."><plain>Pk3 is required for pericentriolar material recruitment to the basal body </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39522" pm="."><plain>Given the cilia growth defects in Pk3-depleted cells, we examined centrosomal markers in GRP cells depleted of Pk3. γ-tubulin, a component of the pericentriolar material (PCM) required for microtubule nucleation, colocalized with the centriole marker Centrin1 at the basal body in GRP cells (Supplementary Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39523" pm="."><plain>We also noticed that γ-tubulin gradually accumulated at the basal body by stage 17 (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39524" pm="."><plain>While this localization of γ-tubulin was unaffected in CoMO-injected GRP cells, the staining was strongly reduced in the majority of Pk3-depleted GRP cells (Fig. 4A,B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39525" pm="."><plain>We next assessed the localization of Nedd1 that is essential for γ-tubulin recruitment to the centrosome545556. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39526" pm="."><plain>Endogenous Nedd1 colocalized with γ-tubulin at the basal body in GRP cells (Supplementary Fig. 2B), and this staining pattern was disrupted by Pk3MO1 but not by CoMO (Fig. 4C,D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39527" pm="."><plain>By contrast, localization of Centrin1 remained unchanged in cells injected with either Pk3MO1 or CoMO (Fig. 4E,F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39528" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that Pk3 regulates basal body organization by modulating the recruitment of γ-tubulin and Nedd1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39529" pm="."><plain>Wtip associates with Pk3 and modulates its localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39530" pm="."><plain>With the exception of Vangl2, proteins that bind Pk3 and may regulate its functions in PCP and at the basal body are unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39531" pm="."><plain>Wilm’s tumor protein 1-interacting protein (Wtip) is a member of the Ajuba LIM protein family57 and plays essential roles in cilia functions and Vangl2-dependent mitotic spindle orientation58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39532" pm="."><plain>Wtip is, therefore, among a few proteins implicated in both PCP and ciliogenesis; however, the biochemical link of Wtip to PCP components has not been established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39533" pm="."><plain>Since both Wtip and Pk3 contain LIM domains that are capable of dimerization59, we hypothesized that the two proteins may physically interact. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39534" pm="."><plain>Supporting this possibility, robust biochemical association of Wtip and Pk3 was observed in pulldown assays using lysates from transfected HEK293 cells (Fig. 5A). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39535" pm="."><plain>To confirm that Wtip is present in GRP cells during the relevant developmental stages, we carried out whole-mount in situ hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39536" pm="."><plain>Wtip transcripts were only weakly detected in gastrula embryos, but became abundantly expressed in the neural and neural crest tissue of stage 18 neurulae (Supplementary Fig. 3A–E), consistent with a previous study60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39537" pm="."><plain>Both Wtip and Pk3 RNAs were present in GRP explants (Supplementary Fig. 3F-J), supporting the possibility of the interaction between the two proteins in the GRP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39538" pm="."><plain>We next assessed Wtip distribution in GRP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39539" pm="."><plain>GFP-Wtip was visible as two puncta at the base of the cilium (Fig. 5B), and coexpression of GFP-Pk3 and HA-RFP-Wtip revealed substantial but not identical colocalization of both proteins at the basal body (Fig. 5C–C”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39540" pm="."><plain>At higher levels, Wtip formed cytoplasmic aggregates that included GFP-Pk3 (Fig. 5D–D”). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39541" pm="."><plain>These observations demonstrate that Pk3 and Wtip interact in vitro and in vivo and suggest that Wtip is involved in the recruitment of Pk3 to the basal body in GRP cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39542" pm="."><plain>Pk3 and Wtip function together in GRP cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39543" pm="."><plain>To gain insight into the role of Wtip in basal body organization, we interfered with its function using two nonoverlapping MOs (WtipMO1 and WtipMO2), which inhibited in vivo translation of Wtip-FLAG RNA carrying MO target sequences but not HA-RFP-Wtip RNA (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39544" pm="."><plain>Injection of both MOs caused cilia positioning and growth defects in GRP cells, while CoMO had no effect, confirming specificity (Fig. 6A–D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39545" pm="."><plain>In contrast to CoMO injections, cilia in Wtip-depleted cells were short and failed to acquire a posterior position (Fig. 6E,F), phenocopying Pk3 depletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39546" pm="."><plain>Co-injection of HA-RFP-Wtip partially rescued Wtip knockdown phenotype (Fig. 6G–I). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39547" pm="."><plain>Similar to the effect of Pk3 depletion, we found that γ-tubulin staining at the basal body was reduced in cells injected with WtipMO1 (Fig. 6J,K), demonstrating a possible function of Wtip at the basal body. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39548" pm="."><plain>We next decided to investigate whether Wtip and Pk3 function together to regulate PCP and ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39549" pm="."><plain>When sub-threshold doses of WtipMO1 or Pk3MO1 were separately injected into embryos, the positioning and length of GRP cilia were largely unaffected (Fig. 7A–C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39550" pm="."><plain>Coinjection of both MOs, however, significantly decreased cilia length and the percentage of cells with posteriorly localized cilia (Fig. 7D–F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39551" pm="."><plain>These findings indicate that Pk3 and Wtip cooperate to control GRP cilia development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="39552" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39553" pm="."><plain>Our study examined subcellular localization and developmental roles of Pk3, a Prickle family member. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39554" pm="."><plain>Pk3 was enriched at the basal body of GRP cells and was recruited to the anterior cell cortex in the presence of exogenous Vangl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39555" pm="."><plain>Besides the involvement of Pk3 in PCP, loss-of-function experiments revealed its novel role in basal body organization and function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39556" pm="."><plain>We propose that this role may be mediated by Wtip, another LIM domain protein that binds Pk3 and synergizes with Pk3 to regulate ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39557" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that, in addition to cell polarity, PCP proteins regulate centrosome/basal body organization. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39558" pm="."><plain>We hypothesize that the polarization of the exogenous Pk3-Vangl2 complex to anterior boundaries of GRP cells reflects the distribution of endogenous proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39559" pm="."><plain>In support of this hypothesis, we demonstrate anterior enrichment of endogenous Vangl2 in the GRP using a previously characterized antibody6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39560" pm="."><plain>We have also raised Pk3-specific antibodies that recognize the Xenopus protein by immunoblot analysis and in immunofluorescence staining but failed to detect endogenous Pk3 due to its low abundance (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39561" pm="."><plain>These results are consistent with PCP protein distribution reported for the mouse node and other vertebrate tissues346202261. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39562" pm="."><plain>The polarization of GFP-Pk3 is only apparent in the presence of exogenous Vangl2, suggesting that the amount of endogenous Vangl2 is limiting in this assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39563" pm="."><plain>In contrast to our findings, a recent study demonstrated posterior rather than anterior enrichment of GFP-Prickle2 (Pk2) and GFP-Vangl1 in Xenopus skin at tailbud stages39. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39564" pm="."><plain>This diverse localization could relate to functional differences between Pk3 and Pk2 proteins, as exemplified by the opposite distribution of PricklePK and PrickleSPLE isoforms in Drosophila6263. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39565" pm="."><plain>To address this issue, we assessed Pk3 polarity in stage 30 epidermal cells with or without Vangl2 coexpression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39566" pm="."><plain>Unlike Pk2, Pk3 did not exhibit cortical polarization on its own (Supplementary Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39567" pm="."><plain>In the presence of Vangl2, some cells revealed Pk3 enrichment at the posterior or anterior domain, but Pk3 was uniformly cortical in other cells (Supplementary Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39568" pm="."><plain>Thus, Pk3 polarization requires specific protein structure and is context-dependent (i.e. determined by tissue type and the developmental stage). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39569" pm="."><plain>Our analysis reveals the critical role of Pk3 C-terminal fragment for its association with Vangl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39570" pm="."><plain>Whereas Drosophila Pk also binds to Vang via its C-terminus33, the C-termini of Drosophila Pk and Xenopus Pk3 are not conserved (only 10% identity, data not shown), indicating that the secondary or tertiary protein structure may be important for the interaction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39571" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of Pk3 C-terminus (Pk3C) interfered with Vangl2 localization and posterior cilia positioning, providing further support to the view that formation of the Pk3-Vangl2 complex is essential for PCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39572" pm="."><plain>Since Pk3C was unable to polarize on its own or in response to exogenous Vangl2 (data not shown), other domains of Pk3 must be required for its process. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39573" pm="."><plain>Besides the role of Pk3 in PCP, our findings also revealed a novel function of Pk3 in basal body organization and ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39574" pm="."><plain>We observed GFP-Pk3 localized at the basal body of GRP cells, consistent with the distribution of Pk3 in mammalian cells44. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39575" pm="."><plain>Moreover, depletion of Pk3 led to reduced staining of γ-tubulin and Nedd1 at the basal body without affecting Centrin1 and acetylated α-tubulin, indicating that pericentriolar material is disorganized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39576" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, Pk3 knockdown inhibited ciliogenesis, possibly related to the abnormal basal body function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39577" pm="."><plain>Notably, vertebrate Vangl proteins are thought to promote the posterior positioning of nodal cilia without a significant effect on cilia length192122. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39578" pm="."><plain>This evidence implies that Pk3 regulates basal body and ciliogenesis independently of Vangl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39579" pm="."><plain>In addition to these effects on basal body organization, Pk3 may regulate microtubule orientation and vesicular trafficking as suggested for other Prickle family proteins416465. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39580" pm="."><plain>Future studies are needed to further define mechanisms that involve Pk3 and regulate ciliogenesis and PCP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39581" pm="."><plain>We propose that Pk3 function in basal body organization is mediated by Wtip, a vertebrate-specific LIM-domain-containing protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39582" pm="."><plain>Wtip belongs to the Ajuba LIM family that localize to the centrosome and has been implicated in Wnt and Rho GTPase signaling576667. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39583" pm="."><plain>Our hypothesis is supported by several lines of evidence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39584" pm="."><plain>First, Wtip physically interacts with Pk3 and is able to recruit it to the cytosolic puncta. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39585" pm="."><plain>Second, Wtip knockdown phenocopies Pk3 depletion by affecting both cilia length and γ-tubulin recruitment to the basal body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39586" pm="."><plain>Third, Wtip synergizes with Pk3 to regulate ciliogenesis in the GRP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39587" pm="."><plain>Supporting the role of Wtip in basal body organization, zebrafish Wtip morphants exhibit striated rootlet deficiencies58. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39588" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the effect of Wtip depletion on posterior cilia positioning suggests that, similar to Pk3, Wtip is involved in the establishment of PCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39589" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this possibility, Wtip binds Ror2, a known Wnt5a receptor implicated in morphogenesis and PCP686970, and synergizes with Vangl2 to regulate spindle orientation in zebrafish embryos5871. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39590" pm="."><plain>It remains to be investigated whether Wtip is directly involved in PCP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39591" pm="."><plain>At present, the relationship between roles of Pk3 in basal body organization and PCP is unclear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39592" pm="."><plain>One possibility is the localization of Pk3 at the cell cortex specifies its function in PCP, whereas its enrichment at the basal body is relevant for ciliogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39593" pm="."><plain>In support of this hypothesis, we observe that Pk3 is recruited to the anterior cortex in the presence of Vangl2, which binds Pk3 and is essential for PCP, whereas Wtip may function to recruit Pk3 to the basal body. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39594" pm="."><plain>The other possibility is that the two functions of Pk3 are interconnected, so that basal body regulation by Pk3 per se contributes to PCP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39595" pm="."><plain>This is in agreement with the proposed roles of the centrosome in directing cell polarity in different systems72. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39596" pm="."><plain>Our current data do not allow us to distinguish between the two possibilities. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="39597" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39598" pm="."><plain>Plasmids, in vitro RNA synthesis and morpholino oligonucleotides (MOs) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39599" pm="."><plain>Cloning of Xenopus Prickle3 (Pk3, GenBank accession number BC154995) into pCS2-FLAG and pcDNA3 has been described13. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39600" pm="."><plain>Pk3C (amino acids 373–538) and Pk3∆C (amino acids 1–372) constructs were generated by PCR and subcloned into pXT7-GFP and pCS2-FLAG73. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39601" pm="."><plain>FLAG-GFP-Pk3 was made by subcloning GFP-Pk3 into pCS2-FLAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39602" pm="."><plain>The full-length coding sequence plus the 5′UTR sequence of Pk3 (JGI Laevis) was obtained by PCR from neurula cDNA and ligated to GFP and pCS107 to produce Pk3-GFP-pCS107. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39603" pm="."><plain>FLAG-GFP was made by subcloning GFP from pEGFP-C1 to pCS2-FLAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39604" pm="."><plain>The plasmids encoding the following constructs have been described: GFP-C174, Histone-GFP (a gift of P. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39605" pm="."><plain>Skourides)75, membrane-associated mCherry76. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39606" pm="."><plain>Mouse HA-Vangl2 plasmid was a gift of Yingzi Yang (Gao et al.70). Xenopus Myc-Wtip was a gift of Greg Longmore60. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39607" pm="."><plain>The coding sequence of Wtip was subcloned into pXT7-GFP and pCS105-HA-RFP to generate pXT7-GFP-Wtip, pXT7-GFP-WtipN, pCS2-Wtip-FLAG and pCS105-HA-RFP-Wtip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39608" pm="."><plain>pXT7-GFP-WtipN contains Wtip cDNA fragment corresponding to Wtip amino acids 1–480. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39609" pm="."><plain>Wtip-FLAG-pCS2 encodes Wtip with the C-terminal FLAG epitope. Xenopus HA-Vangl2-pCS2 (for immunoprecipitation experiments) was generated by PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39610" pm="."><plain>Details of cloning are available upon request. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39611" pm="."><plain>Capped mRNAs were synthesized using mMessage mMachine kit (Ambion, Austin, TX). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39612" pm="."><plain>MOs were purchased from Gene Tools (Philomath, OR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39613" pm="."><plain>The following MOs were used: Pk3MO1, 5′-GGATGCCGCCCGCTCTCTCCCTTA-3′; Pk3MO2, 5′-CTCCTCCTGGAATTACGGAACATCC-3′; control MO (CoMO), 5′-GCTTCAGCTAGTGACACATGCAT-3′13, WtipMO1, 5′- TGTCCTCATCGTACTTCTCCATGTC-3′, WtipMO2, 5′-AAGAATCCCTTATGTCACTTGAGCC-3′. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39614" pm="."><plain>Xenopus embryo culture, microinjections, and in situ hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39615" pm="."><plain>In vitro fertilization and culture of Xenopus laevis embryos were carried out as previously described77. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39616" pm="."><plain>Staging was according to Nieuwkoop and Faber78. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39617" pm="."><plain>For microinjections, four-cell embryos were transferred into 3% Ficoll in 0.5x MMR buffer (50 mM NaCl, 1 mM KCl, 1 mM CaCl2, 0.5 mM MgCl2, 2.5 mM HEPES pH 7.4) and 10 nl of mRNA or MO solution was injected into one or more blastomeres. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39618" pm="."><plain>Amounts of injected mRNA per embryo have been optimized in preliminary dose-response experiments (data not shown) and are indicated in figure legends. In situ hybridization was carried out largely as described79. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39619" pm="."><plain>The digoxigenin-labeled antisense and sense RNA probes were synthesized in vitro with T7 or Sp6 RNA polymerases using Megascript kit (Ambion) from pcDNA3-Pk3 and pXT7-WtipN, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="39620" pm="."><plain>After in situ hybridization, the explants were embedded in cold-water fish gelatin/sucrose mixture and cryosectioned using the Leica cryostat CM3050 at 20 μm as described previously80. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39621" pm="."><plain>Images were digitally acquired on a Zeiss Axiophot microscope. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39622" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39623" pm="."><plain>For immunofluorescence staining, stage 17–18 embryos were manually devitellinized and dissected to isolate GRP explants as described by22. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39624" pm="."><plain>Epidermal explants were prepared at stage 30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39625" pm="."><plain>The explants were fixed with MEMFA (0.1 M MOPS, pH 7.4, 2 mM EGTA, 1 mM MgSO4 and 3.7% formaldehyde)79, MEMFA + 0.1% Triton X-100 for staining of Centrin181, Dent’s fixative (80% methanol +20% DMSO)82 for staining of γ-tubulin and Nedd1 or 2% trichloracetic acid (TCA)83 for Vangl2 staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39626" pm="."><plain>Indirect immunofluorescence staining was performed as described previously80, except for Centrin1 staining, the blocking solution was PBS + 0.1% Triton X-100 + 3% BSA + 3% goat serum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39627" pm="."><plain>The following primary antibodies were used: mouse anti-GFP 1:200 (B-2, Santa Cruz), rabbit anti-GFP 1:400 (A6455, Invitrogen), rabbit anti-HA 1:3000 (Bethyl Labs), mouse anti-acetylated tubulin 1:500 (6-11B-1, Santa Cruz), mouse anti-ZO1 1:200 (Invitrogen), mouse anti-γ-tubulin 1:500 (GTU-88, Sigma), rabbit anti-γ-tubulin 1:500 (ab11321, Abcam), rabbit anti-Vangl284, mouse anti-Nedd1 1:200 (39-J, Santa Cruz), rabbit anti-Centrin1 1:1000 (ab11257, Abcam). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39628" pm="."><plain>Secondary antibodies were Alexa Fluor 488-conjugated (Invitrogen) or Cy3-conjugated 1:300 (Jackson ImmunoResearch). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39629" pm="."><plain>Stained explants were mounted for observation in the Vectashield mounting medium (Vector). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39630" pm="."><plain>Images were captured using a Zeiss AxioImager microscope with the Apotome attachment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39631" pm="."><plain>Results shown are representative images from 2 to 5 independent experiments with 6–15 explants per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39632" pm="."><plain>Cell culture and transfection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39633" pm="."><plain>Human embryonic kidney 293T cells were maintained in DMEM (Corning) with 10% FBS (Gemini) and penicillin/streptomycin (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39634" pm="."><plain>Cells growing at 70% confluence were transiently transfected using linear polyethylenimine (M.W. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39635" pm="."><plain>25,000, Polysciences) as described85. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39636" pm="."><plain>Each 35 mm dish of cells received 1.5 μg of pCS2 plasmids encoding FLAG-Pk3, FLAG-GFP, HA-Vangl2 or Myc-Wtip as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39637" pm="."><plain>For transfection, pCS2 vector DNA was added to plasmid DNA mixture to reach the total DNA amount of 3 μg. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39638" pm="."><plain>Immunoprecipitation and Western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39639" pm="."><plain>For immunoprecipitation, cells transfected for 24 hours were lysed in IP buffer (10 mM HEPES pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EGTA, 1 mM MgCl2, 1% Triton X-100, 1 mM Na3VO4, 10 mM NaF, 25 mM β-glycerol phosphate), containing protease inhibitor cocktail (cOmplete Mini EDTA-free, Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39640" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation at 16,000 g, the supernatant was incubated with anti-FLAG agarose beads (Sigma) at 4 °C for 1.5 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39641" pm="."><plain>The beads were washed three times with IP buffer, boiled in the SDS-PAGE sample buffer, and subjected to SDS-PAGE and imunoblotting following standard protocols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39642" pm="."><plain>Western analysis of embryo lysates was carried out essentially as described86. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39643" pm="."><plain>Briefly, 5 embryos at stage 10.5 were homogenized in the lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.6, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% Triton X-100, 10 mM NaF, 1 mM Na3VO4, 25 mM β-glycerol phosphate, 1 mM PMSF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39644" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation at 16,000 g, the supernatant was boiled in the sample buffer and subjected to SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39645" pm="."><plain>The following primary antibodies were used: mouse anti-GFP (B-2, Santa Cruz), mouse anti-FLAG (M2, Sigma), rabbit anti-HA (Bethyl Labs), mouse anti-Myc (9E10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39646" pm="."><plain>Staining with anti-α-Tubulin antibody (B512, Sigma) was used as loading control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39647" pm="."><plain>Chemiluminescence was captured by the ChemiDoc MP imager (BioRad). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="39648" pm="."><plain>Image analysis and quantification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39649" pm="."><plain>For quantification of GRP cilia length, we used Axiovision software (Zeiss). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39650" pm="."><plain>Ciliated cells were divided equally into anterior, middle and posterior zones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39651" pm="."><plain>Cilium position was assigned to one of the zones and was scored only when unambiguous. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39652" pm="."><plain>Data were collected from 6–15 explants in 2–3 independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39653" pm="."><plain>Two-tailed Student’s t test and one-way ANOVA were performed using Excel (Microsoft) and SigmaPlot (Systat) respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="39654" pm="."><plain>Additional Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="39655" pm="."><plain>How to cite this article: Chu, C.-W. et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39656" pm="."><plain>Prickle3 synergizes with Wtip to regulate basal body organization and cilia growth. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39657" pm="."><plain>Rep. 6, 24104; doi: 10.1038/srep24104 (2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="39658" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d33e26" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="39659" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-s1.pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="39660" pm="."><plain>We thank Kristen Kroll, Greg Longmore, Yingzi Yang and Paris Skourides for plasmids, Kyeongmi Kim for Xenopus HA-Vangl2, Malgorzata Kloc for advice on centrosomal markers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39661" pm="."><plain>We also thank members of the Sokol laboratory for discussions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39662" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by NIH grants to S.S. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="39663" pm="."><plain>PengY. &amp; AxelrodJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39664" pm="."><plain>D. Asymmetric protein localization in planar cell polarity: mechanisms, puzzles, and challenges. Curr Top Dev Biol 101, 33–53 (2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="39665" pm="."><plain>SimonsM. &amp; MlodzikM. Planar cell polarity signaling: from fly development to human disease. Annu Rev Genet 42, 517–540 (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="39666" pm="."><plain>DevenportD. &amp; FuchsE. Planar polarization in embryonic epidermis orchestrates global asymmetric morphogenesis of hair follicles. Nat Cell Biol 10, 1257–1268 (2008).18849982 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="39667" pm="."><plain>CirunaB., JennyA., LeeD., MlodzikM. &amp; SchierA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39668" pm="."><plain>F. Planar cell polarity signalling couples cell division and morphogenesis during neurulation. Nature 439, 220–224 (2006).16407953 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="39669" pm="."><plain>NishimuraT., HondaH. &amp; TakeichiM. Planar cell polarity links axes of spatial dynamics in neural-tube closure. Cell 149, 1084–1097 (2012).22632972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="39670" pm="."><plain>OssipovaO., KimK. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39671" pm="."><plain>Y. Planar polarization of Vangl2 in the vertebrate neural plate is controlled by Wnt and Myosin II signaling. Biol Open 4, 722–730 (2015).25910938 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="39672" pm="."><plain>WangY. &amp; NathansJ. Tissue/planar cell polarity in vertebrates: new insights and new questions. Development 134, 647–658 (2007).17259302 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="39673" pm="."><plain>MontcouquiolM. . Identification of Vangl2 and Scrb1 as planar polarity genes in mammals. Nature 423, 173–177 (2003).12724779 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="39674" pm="."><plain>WallingfordJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39675" pm="."><plain>B. Planar cell polarity and the developmental control of cell behavior in vertebrate embryos. Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol 28, 627–653 (2012).22905955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="39676" pm="."><plain>MitchellB. . The PCP pathway instructs the planar orientation of ciliated cells in the Xenopus larval skin. Curr Biol 19, 924–929 (2009).19427216 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="39677" pm="."><plain>TissirF. &amp; GoffinetA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39678" pm="."><plain>M. Planar cell polarity signaling in neural development. Curr Opin Neurobiol 20, 572–577 (2010).20554443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="39679" pm="."><plain>GrayR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39680" pm="."><plain>S., RoszkoI. &amp; Solnica-KrezelL. Planar cell polarity: coordinating morphogenetic cell behaviors with embryonic polarity. Dev Cell 21, 120–133 (2011).21763613 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="39681" pm="."><plain>OssipovaO. . The involvement of PCP proteins in radial cell intercalations during Xenopus embryonic development. Dev Biol 408, 316–27 (2015).26079437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="39682" pm="."><plain>SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39683" pm="."><plain>Y. Analysis of Dishevelled signalling pathways during Xenopus development. Curr Biol 6, 1456–1467 (1996).8939601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="39684" pm="."><plain>SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39685" pm="."><plain>Y. Spatial and temporal aspects of Wnt signaling and planar cell polarity during vertebrate embryonic development. Semin Cell Dev Biol 42, 78–85 (2015).25986055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="39686" pm="."><plain>TorbanE. . Genetic interaction between members of the Vangl family causes neural tube defects in mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 105, 3449–3454 (2008).18296642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="39687" pm="."><plain>BellaicheY., Beaudoin-MassianiO., StuttemI. &amp; SchweisguthF. The planar cell polarity protein Strabismus promotes Pins anterior localization during asymmetric division of sensory organ precursor cells in Drosophila. Development 131, 469–478 (2004).14701683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="39688" pm="."><plain>LakeB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39689" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39690" pm="."><plain>Y. Strabismus regulates asymmetric cell divisions and cell fate determination in the mouse brain. J Cell Biol 185, 59–66 (2009).19332887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="39691" pm="."><plain>SongH. . Planar cell polarity breaks bilateral symmetry by controlling ciliary positioning. Nature 466, 378–382 (2010).20562861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="39692" pm="."><plain>HashimotoM. . Planar polarization of node cells determines the rotational axis of node cilia. Nat Cell Biol 12, 170–176 (2010).20098415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="39693" pm="."><plain>BorovinaA., SuperinaS., VoskasD. &amp; CirunaB. Vangl2 directs the posterior tilting and asymmetric localization of motile primary cilia. Nat Cell Biol 12, 407–412 (2010).20305649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="39694" pm="."><plain>AnticD. . Planar cell polarity enables posterior localization of nodal cilia and left-right axis determination during mouse and Xenopus embryogenesis. PLoS One 5, e8999 (2010).20126399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="39695" pm="."><plain>YasunagaT., ItohK. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39696" pm="."><plain>Y. Regulation of basal body and ciliary functions by Diversin. Mech Dev 128, 376–386 (2011).21843637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="39697" pm="."><plain>ItohK., JennyA., MlodzikM. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39698" pm="."><plain>Y. Centrosomal localization of Diversin and its relevance to Wnt signaling. J Cell Sci 122, 3791–3798 (2009).19789178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="39699" pm="."><plain>ParkT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39700" pm="."><plain>J., MitchellB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39701" pm="."><plain>J., AbituaP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39702" pm="."><plain>B., KintnerC. &amp; WallingfordJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39703" pm="."><plain>B. Dishevelled controls apical docking and planar polarization of basal bodies in ciliated epithelial cells. Nat Genet 40, 871–879 (2008).18552847 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="39704" pm="."><plain>RossA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39705" pm="."><plain>J. . Disruption of Bardet-Biedl syndrome ciliary proteins perturbs planar cell polarity in vertebrates. Nat Genet 37, 1135–1140 (2005).16170314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="39706" pm="."><plain>WatanabeD. . The left-right determinant Inversin is a component of node monocilia and other 9+0 cilia. Development 130, 1725–1734 (2003).12642479 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="39707" pm="."><plain>ZilberY. . The PCP effector Fuzzy controls cilial assembly and signaling by recruiting Rab8 and Dishevelled to the primary cilium. Mol Biol Cell 24, 555–565 (2013).23303251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="39708" pm="."><plain>WallingfordJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39709" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; MitchellB. Strange as it may seem: the many links between Wnt signaling, planar cell polarity, and cilia. Genes Dev 25, 201–213 (2011).21289065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="39710" pm="."><plain>May-SimeraH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39711" pm="."><plain>L. . Bbs8, together with the planar cell polarity protein Vangl2, is required to establish left-right asymmetry in zebrafish. Dev Biol 345, 215–225 (2010).20643117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="39712" pm="."><plain>CaoY., ParkA. &amp; SunZ. Intraflagellar transport proteins are essential for cilia formation and for planar cell polarity. J Am Soc Nephrol 21, 1326–1333 (2010).20576807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="39713" pm="."><plain>GubbD. . The balance between isoforms of the prickle LIM domain protein is critical for planar polarity in Drosophila imaginal discs. Genes Dev 13, 2315–2327 (1999). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="39714" pm="."><plain>JennyA., DarkenR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39715" pm="."><plain>S., WilsonP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39716" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; MlodzikM. Prickle and Strabismus form a functional complex to generate a correct axis during planar cell polarity signaling. EMBO J 22, 4409–4420 (2003).12941693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="39717" pm="."><plain>BoutinC. . A dual role for planar cell polarity genes in ciliated cells. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 111, E3129–E3138 (2014).25024228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="39718" pm="."><plain>VeemanM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39719" pm="."><plain>T., SlusarskiD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39720" pm="."><plain>C., KaykasA., LouieS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39721" pm="."><plain>H. &amp; MoonR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39722" pm="."><plain>T. Zebrafish prickle, a modulator of noncanonical Wnt/Fz signaling, regulates gastrulation movements. Curr Biol 13, 680–685 (2003).12699626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="39723" pm="."><plain>TakeuchiM. . The prickle-Related Gene in Vertebrates Is Essential for Gastrulation Cell Movements. Curr Biol 13, 674–679 (2003).12699625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="39724" pm="."><plain>Carreira-BarbosaF. . Prickle 1 regulates cell movements during gastrulation and neuronal migration in zebrafish. Development 130, 4037–4046 (2003).12874125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="39725" pm="."><plain>TaoH. . Mouse prickle1, the homolog of a PCP gene, is essential for epiblast apical-basal polarity. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 106, 14426–14431 (2009).19706528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="39726" pm="."><plain>ButlerM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39727" pm="."><plain>T. &amp; WallingfordJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39728" pm="."><plain>B. Control of vertebrate core planar cell polarity protein localization and dynamics by Prickle 2. Development 142, 3429–3439 (2015).26293301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="39729" pm="."><plain>SowersL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39730" pm="."><plain>P., YinT., MahajanV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39731" pm="."><plain>B. &amp; BassukA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39732" pm="."><plain>G. Defective motile cilia in Prickle2-deficient mice. J Neurogenet 28, 146–152 (2014).24708399 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="39733" pm="."><plain>MeiX. . Functional characterization of Prickle2 and BBS7 identify overlapping phenotypes yet distinct mechanisms. Dev Biol 392, 245–255 (2014).24938409 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="39734" pm="."><plain>OteizaP. . Planar cell polarity signalling regulates cell adhesion properties in progenitors of the zebrafish laterality organ. Development 137, 3459–3468 (2010).20843857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="39735" pm="."><plain>LiuC. . Null and hypomorph Prickle1 alleles in mice phenocopy human Robinow syndrome and disrupt signaling downstream of Wnt5a. Biol Open 3, 861–70 (2014).25190059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="39736" pm="."><plain>JakobsenL. . Novel asymmetrically localizing components of human centrosomes identified by complementary proteomics methods. Embo J 30, 1520–1535 (2011).21399614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="39737" pm="."><plain>HutchinsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39738" pm="."><plain>R. . Systematic analysis of human protein complexes identifies chromosome segregation proteins. Science 328, 593–599 (2010).20360068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="39739" pm="."><plain>BlumM., SchweickertA., VickP., WrightC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39740" pm="."><plain>V. &amp; DanilchikM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39741" pm="."><plain>V. Symmetry breakage in the vertebrate embryo: when does it happen and how does it work? Dev Biol 393, 109–123 (2014).24972089 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="39742" pm="."><plain>OkadaY., TakedaS., TanakaY., Izpisua BelmonteJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39743" pm="."><plain>C. &amp; HirokawaN. Mechanism of nodal flow: a conserved symmetry breaking event in left-right axis determination. Cell 121, 633–644 (2005).15907475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="39744" pm="."><plain>CooperM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39745" pm="."><plain>S. &amp; VirtaV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39746" pm="."><plain>C. Evolution of gastrulation in the ray-finned (actinopterygian) fishes. J Exp Zool B Mol Dev Evol 308, 591–608 (2007).17285635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="39747" pm="."><plain>SchweickertA. . Cilia-driven leftward flow determines laterality in Xenopus. Curr Biol 17, 60–66 (2007).17208188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="39748" pm="."><plain>EssnerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39749" pm="."><plain>J. . Conserved function for embryonic nodal cilia. Nature 418, 37–38 (2002).12097899 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="39750" pm="."><plain>DevenportD. The cell biology of planar cell polarity. J Cell Biol 207, 171–179 (2014).25349257 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="39751" pm="."><plain>WalentekP., SchneiderI., SchweickertA. &amp; BlumM. Wnt11b is involved in cilia-mediated symmetry breakage during Xenopus left-right development. Plos one 8, e73646 (2013).24058481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="39752" pm="."><plain>BastockR., StruttH. &amp; StruttD. Strabismus is asymmetrically localised and binds to Prickle and Dishevelled during Drosophila planar polarity patterning. Development 130, 3007–3014 (2003).12756182 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="39753" pm="."><plain>HarenL. . NEDD1-dependent recruitment of the gamma-tubulin ring complex to the centrosome is necessary for centriole duplication and spindle assembly. J Cell Biol 172, 505–515 (2006).16461362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="39754" pm="."><plain>LudersJ., PatelU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39755" pm="."><plain>K. &amp; StearnsT. GCP-WD is a gamma-tubulin targeting factor required for centrosomal and chromatin-mediated microtubule nucleation. Nat Cell Biol 8, 137–147 (2006).16378099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="39756" pm="."><plain>ManningJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39757" pm="."><plain>A., LewisM., KoblarS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39758" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; KumarS. An essential function for the centrosomal protein NEDD1 in zebrafish development. Cell Death Differ 17, 1302–1314 (2010).20150915 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="39759" pm="."><plain>KadrmasJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39760" pm="."><plain>L. &amp; BeckerleM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39761" pm="."><plain>C. The LIM domain: from the cytoskeleton to the nucleus. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 5, 920–931 (2004).15520811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="39762" pm="."><plain>BubenshchikovaE. . Wtip and Vangl2 are required for mitotic spindle orientation and cloaca morphogenesis. Biol Open 1, 588–596 (2012).23213452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="39763" pm="."><plain>FeuersteinR., WangX., SongD., CookeN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39764" pm="."><plain>E. &amp; LiebhaberS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39765" pm="."><plain>A. The LIM/double zinc-finger motif functions as a protein dimerization domain. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 91, 10655–10659 (1994).7938009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="39766" pm="."><plain>LangerE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39767" pm="."><plain>M. . Ajuba LIM proteins are snail/slug corepressors required for neural crest development in Xenopus. Dev Cell 14, 424–436 (2008).18331720 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="39768" pm="."><plain>YinC., KiskowskiM., PouilleP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39769" pm="."><plain>A., FargeE. &amp; Solnica-KrezelL. Cooperation of polarized cell intercalations drives convergence and extension of presomitic mesoderm during zebrafish gastrulation. J Cell Biol 180, 221–232 (2008).18195109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="39770" pm="."><plain>AyukawaT. . Dachsous-dependent asymmetric localization of spiny-legs determines planar cell polarity orientation in Drosophila. Cell Rep 8, 610–621 (2014).24998533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="39771" pm="."><plain>AmbegaonkarA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39772" pm="."><plain>A. &amp; IrvineK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39773" pm="."><plain>D. Coordination of planar cell polarity pathways through Spiny legs. eLife 4, e09946 (2015).26505959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="39774" pm="."><plain>EhaidebS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39775" pm="."><plain>N. . prickle modulates microtubule polarity and axonal transport to ameliorate seizures in flies. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 111, 11187–92 (2014).25024231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="39776" pm="."><plain>OlofssonJ., SharpK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39777" pm="."><plain>A., MatisM., ChoB. &amp; AxelrodJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39778" pm="."><plain>D. Prickle/spiny-legs isoforms control the polarity of the apical microtubule network in planar cell polarity. Development 141, 2866–2874 (2014).25005476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66"><text><SENT sid="39779" pm="."><plain>NolaS. . Ajuba is required for Rac activation and maintenance of E-cadherin adhesion. J Cell Biol 195, 855–871 (2011).22105346 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67"><text><SENT sid="39780" pm="."><plain>HirotaT. . Aurora-A and an interacting activator, the LIM protein Ajuba, are required for mitotic commitment in human cells. Cell 114, 585–598 (2003).13678582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68"><text><SENT sid="39781" pm="."><plain>NishitaM., EnomotoM., YamagataK. &amp; MinamiY. Cell/tissue-tropic functions of Wnt5a signaling in normal and cancer cells. Trends Cell Biol 20, 346–354 (2010).20359892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69"><text><SENT sid="39782" pm="."><plain>HikasaH., ShibataM., HirataniI. &amp; TairaM. The Xenopus receptor tyrosine kinase Xror2 modulates morphogenetic movements of the axial mesoderm and neuroectoderm via Wnt signaling. Development 129, 5227–5239 (2002).12399314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70"><text><SENT sid="39783" pm="."><plain>GaoB. . Wnt signaling gradients establish planar cell polarity by inducing Vangl2 phosphorylation through Ror2. Dev Cell 20, 163–176 (2011).21316585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71"><text><SENT sid="39784" pm="."><plain>van WijkN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39785" pm="."><plain>V. . The LIM domain protein Wtip interacts with the receptor tyrosine kinase Ror2 and inhibits canonical Wnt signalling. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 390, 211–216 (2009).19785987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72"><text><SENT sid="39786" pm="."><plain>TangN. &amp; MarshallW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39787" pm="."><plain>F. Centrosome positioning in vertebrate development. J Cell Sci 125, 4951–4961 (2012).23277534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73"><text><SENT sid="39788" pm="."><plain>HikasaH. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39789" pm="."><plain>Y. Phosphorylation of TCF proteins by homeodomain-interacting protein kinase 2. J Biol Chem 286, 12093–12100 (2011).21285352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74"><text><SENT sid="39790" pm="."><plain>KimK., LakeB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39791" pm="."><plain>B., HaremakiT., WeinsteinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39792" pm="."><plain>C. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39793" pm="."><plain>Y. Rab11 regulates planar polarity and migratory behavior of multiciliated cells in Xenopus embryonic epidermis. Dev Dyn 241, 1385–1395 (2012).22778024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75"><text><SENT sid="39794" pm="."><plain>PetridouN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39795" pm="."><plain>I. &amp; SkouridesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39796" pm="."><plain>A. FAK transduces extracellular forces that orient the mitotic spindle and control tissue morphogenesis. Nat Commun 5, 5240 (2014).25341507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76"><text><SENT sid="39797" pm="."><plain>ChoiS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39798" pm="."><plain>C. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39799" pm="."><plain>Y. The involvement of lethal giant larvae and Wnt signaling in bottle cell formation in Xenopus embryos. Dev Biol 336, 68–75 (2009).19782678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77"><text><SENT sid="39800" pm="."><plain>DollarG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39801" pm="."><plain>L., WeberU., MlodzikM. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39802" pm="."><plain>Y. Regulation of Lethal giant larvae by Dishevelled. Nature 437, 1376–1380 (2005).16251968 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b78"><text><SENT sid="39803" pm="."><plain>NieuwkoopP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39804" pm="."><plain>D. &amp; FaberJ. Normal table of Xenopus laevis (Daudin): a systematical and chronological survey of the development from the fertilized egg till the end of metamorphosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39805" pm="."><plain>(Garland Pub., New York; 1994). </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b79"><text><SENT sid="39806" pm="."><plain>HarlandR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39807" pm="."><plain>M. In situ hybridization: an improved whole-mount method for Xenopus embryos. Methods Cell Biol 36, 685–695 (1991).1811161 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b80"><text><SENT sid="39808" pm="."><plain>OssipovaO. . Role of Rab11 in planar cell polarity and apical constriction during vertebrate neural tube closure. Nat Commun 5, 3734 (2014).24818582 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b81"><text><SENT sid="39809" pm="."><plain>KlocM., BilinskiS., DoughertyM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39810" pm="."><plain>T., BreyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39811" pm="."><plain>M. &amp; EtkinL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39812" pm="."><plain>D. Formation, architecture and polarity of female germline cyst in Xenopus. Dev Biol 266, 43–61 (2004).14729477 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b82"><text><SENT sid="39813" pm="."><plain>DentJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39814" pm="."><plain>A., PolsonA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39815" pm="."><plain>G. &amp; KlymkowskyM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39816" pm="."><plain>W. A whole-mount immunocytochemical analysis of the expression of the intermediate filament protein vimentin in Xenopus. Development 105, 61–74 (1989).2806118 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b83"><text><SENT sid="39817" pm="."><plain>NandadasaS., TaoQ., MenonN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39818" pm="."><plain>R., HeasmanJ. &amp; WylieC. N- and E-cadherins in Xenopus are specifically required in the neural and non-neural ectoderm, respectively, for F-actin assembly and morphogenetic movements. Development 136, 1327–1338 (2009).19279134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b84"><text><SENT sid="39819" pm="."><plain>OssipovaO., ChuykinI., ChuC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39820" pm="."><plain>W. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39821" pm="."><plain>Y. Vangl2 cooperates with Rab11 and Myosin V to regulate apical constriction during vertebrate gastrulation. Development 142, 99–107 (2015).25480917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b85"><text><SENT sid="39822" pm="."><plain>OssipovaO., EzanJ. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39823" pm="."><plain>Y. PAR-1 phosphorylates Mind bomb to promote vertebrate neurogenesis. Dev Cell 17, 222–233 (2009).19686683 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b86"><text><SENT sid="39824" pm="."><plain>ChuC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39825" pm="."><plain>W., GerstenzangE., OssipovaO. &amp; SokolS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39826" pm="."><plain>Y. Lulu regulates Shroom-induced apical constriction during neural tube closure. Plos One 8, e81854 (2013).24282618 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="39827" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions C.C. and S.S. designed the experiments, A.I. characterized Wtip knockdown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39828" pm="."><plain>O.O. contributed data to Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39829" pm="."><plain>Figure 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39830" pm="."><plain>C.C. performed the rest of the experiments and analyzed the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39831" pm="."><plain>C.C. and S.S. wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39832" pm="."><plain>All authors reviewed the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Localization of Pk3 and Vangl2 in the gastrocoel roof plate (GRP).</title><p><text><SENT sid="39833" pm="."><plain>(A) Schematic neurula embryo section illustrating the position of the GRP (yellow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39834" pm="."><plain>The dorsal (D)- ventral (V) axis is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39835" pm="."><plain>NP, neural plate; N, notochord; S, somites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39836" pm="."><plain>(B) Enrichment of GFP-Pk3 at the base of cilium in GRP cells (arrowhead). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39837" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with GFP-Pk3 RNA (0.25 ng). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39838" pm="."><plain>Protein localization is detected by GFP fluorescence in stage 15 GRP explants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39839" pm="."><plain>Cilium is stained by anti-acetylated α-tubulin (Ac-tub) antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39840" pm="."><plain>(C) En face immunostaining of endogenous Vangl2 in the GRP of stage 15 embryos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39841" pm="."><plain>The anterior (A) - posterior (P) axis is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39842" pm="."><plain>Note the accumulation of Vangl2 at anterior cell boundaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39843" pm="."><plain>There is no staining in the absence of primary antibody (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39844" pm="."><plain>(D–D”) GRP cells coexpressing GFP-Pk3 and HA-Vangl2 (150 pg of RNA each) at stage 15. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39845" pm="."><plain>Arrowheads mark anterior cell borders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39846" pm="."><plain>(E) Scheme of Pk3 constructs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39847" pm="."><plain>(F) Physical interaction between Pk3 and Vangl2 in transfected HEK293T cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39848" pm="."><plain>The indicated FLAG-Pk3 proteins were pulled down using anti-FLAG-agarose beads, and co-precipitation of HA-Vangl2 was examined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39849" pm="."><plain>Protein levels are shown by immunoblotting with anti-FLAG and anti-HA antibodies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Pk3 is required for the posterior localization and growth of GRP cilia.</title><p><text><SENT sid="39850" pm="."><plain>(A) Efficiency of the Pk3 knockdown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39851" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with Pk3-GFP RNA (2 ng) that contains MO target sites, control FLAG-GFP RNA (0.1 ng), control MO (CoMO, 80 ng), Pk3MO1 (15 ng), or Pk3MO2 (80 ng) as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39852" pm="."><plain>Embryo lysates obtained at stage 11 were immunoblotted with anti-GFP antibody. α-tubulin (αtub) is a control for loading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39853" pm="."><plain>(B–I) Effects of Pk3 depletion (B–F) and rescue (G–I) on GRP cilia position and length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39854" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected at the 4–8 cell stage with CoMO (B), Pk3MO1 (C), Pk3MO2 (D) or Pk3MO1 plus GFP-Pk3 RNA (10 pg, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39855" pm="."><plain>GRP explants were prepared from stage 17 embryos and stained with anti-acetylated α-tubulin (Ac-tub) antibody to visualize cilia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39856" pm="."><plain>Coinjection of membrane-associated mCherry RNA (Cherry, 100 pg) marks cell boundaries. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39857" pm="."><plain>(E,H) Percentage of cells with the indicated cilia position. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39858" pm="."><plain>Representative cells with the anterior (A), middle (M) or posterior (P) position of cilia are indicated in (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39859" pm="."><plain>Significance was assessed by two-tailed t test comparing the frequencies of cilia positioned posteriorly (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39860" pm="."><plain>(E) Pk3MO1 to CoMO: p = 0.0003, Pk3MO2 to CoMO: p &lt; 0.0001. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39861" pm="."><plain>(H) Pk3MO1+Pk3 to Pk3MO1: p = 0.0002. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39862" pm="."><plain>(F,I) Cilia length in GRP cells depleted of Pk3, presented as means +/− s.d. ****p &lt; 0.0001, two-tailed t test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39863" pm="."><plain>Representative images from three to five experiments are shown, and at least 14 explants were examined per group in each experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39864" pm="."><plain>The effects of Pk3MO1 and Pk3MO2 were evident in approximately 90% of the explants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39865" pm="."><plain>Co-expression of GFP-Pk3 with Pk3MO1 reduced the frequency of short cilia phenotype to 36% (n = 58). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39866" pm="."><plain>(E,F,H,I) Data were collected from 6 to 10 explants per group in three independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Pk3 is required for the anterior polarization of Vangl2.</title><p><text><SENT sid="39867" pm="."><plain>(A,B) Immunostaining of Vangl2 (arrowheads) in stage 15 GRP cells from embryos injected with GFP RNA (0.2 ng, lineage tracer) and CoMO (15 ng, A,A’) or Pk3MO1 (15 ng, B,B’). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39868" pm="."><plain>(C,D) Embryos were injected with 2 ng of GFP-Pk3C RNA, and Vangl2 localization (C,C’) and cilia (marked by Ac-tub, D,D’) were visualized in GRP cells at stage 15 (C) and 17 (D) respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39869" pm="."><plain>ZO-1 co-staining reveals cell boundaries. En face staining is shown, anterior is to the top. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39870" pm="."><plain>Representative images from three independent experiments are shown, with 6–10 explants per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Pk3 depletion prevents γ-tubulin and Nedd1 recruitment to the basal body.</title><p><text><SENT sid="39871" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with 0.2 ng of RNA encoding GFP (A–D) or Histone-GFP (E,F) as a lineage tracer and CoMO (A,C,E) or Pk3MO1 (B,D,F) (15 ng each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39872" pm="."><plain>GRP explants from stage 17 embryos were double stained for GFP and γ-tubulin (A,B), Nedd1 (C,D) or Centrin1 (E,F). En face staining is shown, anterior is at the top. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39873" pm="."><plain>Representative images from three to five independent experiments are shown, with 6–10 explants examined per group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39874" pm="."><plain>The effects of Pk3MO1 on γ-tubulin and Nedd1 are detectable in the majority of cells depleted of Pk3 (n &gt; 100). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Pk3 and Wtip physically interact and colocalize at the basal body of GRP cells.</title><p><text><SENT sid="39875" pm="."><plain>(A) Protein interactions between Wtip and Pk3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39876" pm="."><plain>HEK293T cells expressing Myc-Wtip and FLAG-Pk3 proteins were lysed and immunoprecipitated with anti-FLAG agarose beads. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39877" pm="."><plain>Protein levels were assessed after immunoblotting with anti-FLAG and anti-Myc antibodies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39878" pm="."><plain>(B) Localization of Wtip at the base of the cilium in GRP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39879" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with GFP-Wtip RNA (150 pg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39880" pm="."><plain>Protein localization is revealed by epifluorescence and staining of acetylated α-tubulin (Ac-tub) in stage 15 GRP explants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39881" pm="."><plain>(C,D) Colocalization of Pk3 and Wtip in the GRP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39882" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with 250 pg of GFP-Pk3 RNA plus 100 pg (C) or 250 pg (D) of HA-RFP-Wtip RNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39883" pm="."><plain>Epifluorescence in stage 15 GRP explants is shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title>Wtip depletion affects posterior localization and growth of GRP cilia.</title><p><text><SENT sid="39884" pm="."><plain>(A) Efficiency and specificity of the Wtip knockdown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39885" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with Wtip-FLAG RNA (1 ng), HA-RFP-Wtip RNA (HR-Wtip, 0.5 ng), control MO (CoMO, 30 ng), WtipMO1 (10 ng), or WtipMO2 (30 ng) as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39886" pm="."><plain>Embryo lysates obtained at stage 12 were immunoblotted with anti-FLAG and anti-HA antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39887" pm="."><plain>Asterisks mark nonspecific signals from anti-HA antibody. α-tubulin (αtub) is a control for loading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39888" pm="."><plain>(B–I) Effects of Wtip depletion (B–F) and rescue (G–I) on cilia position and length. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39889" pm="."><plain>Embryos were injected with CoMO (B), WtipMO1 (C), WtipMO2 (D) or WtipMO1 plus HA-RFP-Wtip RNA (75 pg) (G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39890" pm="."><plain>GRP explants were prepared at stage 17 and stained with anti-acetylated α-tubulin (Ac-tub) antibody to visualize cilia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39891" pm="."><plain>Membrane-associated mCherry marks the boundaries of cells injected with MOs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39892" pm="."><plain>Anterior is to the top. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39893" pm="."><plain>(E,H) Percentage of cells with the indicated cilia position. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39894" pm="."><plain>The position of each cilium was assigned to the A, M or P location in each cell, as in Fig. 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39895" pm="."><plain>Significance was assessed by two-tailed t test comparing the frequencies of cilia positioned posteriorly (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39896" pm="."><plain>WtipMO1 to CoMO: p &lt; 0.0001, WtipMO2 to CoMO: p = 0.0009. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39897" pm="."><plain>WtipMO1+ Wtip to WtipMO1: p = 0.35. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39898" pm="."><plain>(F,I) Bar graph showing the means +/− s.d. of cilia length in GRP cells depleted of Wtip. ****p &lt; 0.0001, two-tailed t test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39899" pm="."><plain>Representative images from three independent experiments are shown, and at least 7 explants were examined per group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39900" pm="."><plain>The effects of WtipMO1 and WtipMO2 were visible in over 80% of the explants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39901" pm="."><plain>Co-expression of HA-RFP-Wtip with WtipMO1 reduced the frequency of short cilia phenotype to 48% (n = 23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39902" pm="."><plain>(E,F,H,I) Data are collected from six embryos in two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39903" pm="."><plain>(J,K) Embryos were injected with 100 pg of Histone-GFP RNA and CoMO (J,J’) or WtipMO1 (K,K’) (10 ng each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39904" pm="."><plain>GRP explants from stage 17 embryos were double stained for GFP and γ-tubulin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39905" pm="."><plain>Representative images from three independent experiments are shown, 6–10 explants were examined per group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39906" pm="."><plain>The effect of WtipMO1 on γ-tubulin staining was visible in approximately 80% of the explants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f6"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title>Wtip functionally interacts with Pk3 to regulate GRP cilia growth and positioning.</title><p><text><SENT sid="39907" pm="."><plain>(A–D) Synergistic effects of Wtip and Pk3 depletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39908" pm="."><plain>Embryos injected with membrane-mCherry (Cherry) RNA and CoMO (5 ng, A), WtipMO1 (2.5 ng, B), Pk3MO1 (2.5 ng, C) or WtipMO1 plus Pk3MO1 (D) were stained with anti-acetylated α-tubulin (Ac-tub) antibody to visualize cilia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39909" pm="."><plain>Membrane-mCherry marks the boundaries of the targeted cells. En face staining is shown, anterior is to the top. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39910" pm="."><plain>Representative images from three independent experiments are shown, with at least 14 explants examined per group in each experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39911" pm="."><plain>While WtipMO1 and Pk3MO1 alone caused short cilia in 20% and none of the explants respectively, co-injection of both MOs increased the frequency of short cilia phenotype to 84% (n = 32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39912" pm="."><plain>(E) Percentage of cells with the indicated cilia position. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39913" pm="."><plain>The position of each cilium was assigned to the A, M or P location in each cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39914" pm="."><plain>Significance was assessed by one-way ANOVA comparing frequencies of posteriorly positioned cilia (green) in the WtipMO1+Pk3MO1 group and the WtipMO1 group (p &lt; 0.001) or the Pk3MO1 group (p &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39915" pm="."><plain>(F) Bar graph showing the means +/− s.d. of cilia length in GRP cells injected with MOs. ***p &lt; 0.001, one-way ANOVA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39916" pm="."><plain>(E,F) Data are collected from six embryos in two independent experiments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="srep24104-f7"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
