<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4266608</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25506915</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-17131</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114713</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Anatomy</subject><subj-group><subject>Biological Tissue</subject><subj-group><subject>Epithelium</subject><subj-group><subject>Epithelial Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Endothelial Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Biomarkers</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cancer Treatment</subject><subj-group><subject>Antiangiogenesis Therapy</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="25816" pm="."><plain>A Subpopulation of Circulating Endothelial Cells Express CD109 and is Enriched in the Blood of Cancer Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">CEC109+ in Cancer Patients</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mancuso</surname><given-names>Patrizia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calleri</surname><given-names>Angelica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gregato</surname><given-names>Giuliana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Labanca</surname><given-names>Valentina</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quarna</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Antoniotti</surname><given-names>Pierluigi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cuppini</surname><given-names>Lucia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Finocchiaro</surname><given-names>Gaetano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eoli</surname><given-names>Marica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rosti</surname><given-names>Vittorio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bertolini</surname><given-names>Francesco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Hematology-Oncology, European Institute of Oncology, Milan, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Neuro-Oncology, Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Neurologico C. Besta, Milan, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Center for the Study and Treatment of Myelofibrosis, Research Laboratories of Biotechnology, Fondazione IRCCS Policlinico San Matteo, Pavia, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Lu-Gang</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Liverpool, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>patrizia.mancuso@ieo.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="25817" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="25818" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: PM FB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25819" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AC GG VL JQ PA PM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25820" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: PM AC GG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25821" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: PM FB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25822" pm="."><plain>Contributed with patients enrollment: LC GF ME VR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e114713</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Mancuso et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Mancuso et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="25823" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="25824" pm="."><plain>The endothelium is not a homogeneous organ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25825" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cell heterogeneity has been described at the level of cell morphology, function, gene expression, and antigen composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25826" pm="."><plain>As a consequence of the genetic, transcriptome and surrounding environment diversity, endothelial cells from different vascular beds have differentiated functions and phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25827" pm="."><plain>Detection of circulating endothelial cells (CECs) by flow cytometry is an approach widely used in cancer patients, and their number, viability and kinetic is a promising tool to stratify patient receiving anti-angiogenic treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="25828" pm="."><plain>Methodology/Principal Findings </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="25829" pm="."><plain>Currently CECs are identified as positive for a nuclear binding antigen (DNA+), negative for the pan leukocyte marker CD45, and positive for CD31 and CD146. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25830" pm="."><plain>Following an approach recently validated in our laboratory, we investigated the expression of CD109 on CECs from the peripheral blood of healthy subject and cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25831" pm="."><plain>The endothelial nature of these cells was validated by RT-PCR for the presence of m-RNA level of CDH5 (Ve-Cadherin) and CLDN5 (Claudin5), two endothelial specific transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25832" pm="."><plain>Before treatment, significantly higher levels of CD109+ CECs and viable CD109+CECs were found in breast cancer patients and glioblastoma patients compared to healthy controls, and their number significantly decreased after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25833" pm="."><plain>Higher levels of endothelial specific transcripts expressed in developing endothelial cells CLEC14a, TMEM204, ARHGEF15, GPR116, were observed in sorted CD109+CECs when compared to sorted CD146+CECs, suggesting that these genes can play an important role not only during embryogenesis but also in adult angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25834" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, mRNA levels of TEM8 (identified as Antrax Toxin Receptor1, Antrax1) were expressed in CD109+CECs+ but not in CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="25835" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="25836" pm="."><plain>Taken together our results suggest that CD109 represent a rare population of circulating tumor endothelial cells, that play a potentially useful prognostic role in patients with glioblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25837" pm="."><plain>The role of CD109 expression in cancer vessel-specific endothelial cells deserves to be further investigated by gene expression studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>Supported in part by AIRC (Associazione Italiana per la Ricerca sul Cancro), Fondazione Umberto Veronesi, and Ministero della Salute. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data and supporting information originating from flow-cytometry files and molecular biology study are within the paper.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>The authors confirm that all data underlying the findings are fully available without restriction. All relevant data and supporting information originating from flow-cytometry files and molecular biology study are within the paper.</p></notes></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="25838" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25839" pm="."><plain>Angiogenesis plays a crucial role in tumor growth and progression [1]–[3] and based on the theory that targeting of endothelial cells may be a more effective strategy than targeting tumor cells, during the last decade many anti-angiogenic drugs have been introduced to the clinical setting [4]–[8]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25840" pm="."><plain>In order to assess circulating biomarkers of angiogenesis that may predict outcome to antiangiogenic therapies in cancer patients, many approaches have been tested in both preclinical and clinical studies [9]–[11] and among these the quantification of circulating endothelial cells (CECs) by flow cytometry has found wide application [12]–[14]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25841" pm="."><plain>CECs are mature endothelial cells released from vessels during physiological endothelial turnover or, in cancer patients, from the tumour vasculature, where they likely reflect endothelial damage or dysfunction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25842" pm="."><plain>These cells are increased in cancer patients when compared to healthy subjects, and their modifications in number and viability has shown predictive, prognostic, dynamic or escape biomarker value [15]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25843" pm="."><plain>The endothelium is not a homogeneous organ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25844" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cell heterogeneity has been described at the level of cell morphology, function, gene expression, and antigen composition [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25845" pm="."><plain>As a consequence of the genetic, transcriptome and surrounding environment diversity, endothelial cells from different vascular beds have differentiated functions and phenotype [20]–[24], [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25846" pm="."><plain>Currently endothelial markers used to identify CECs are CD34, CD31 and CD146 in combination with CD45, to exclude leucocytes, and a nuclear staining marker (like Syto16, Hoechst or DRAQ5) to eliminate counting of noncellular endothelial microparticles [14], [25]–[26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25847" pm="."><plain>The CD109 gene encodes a glycosyl-phosphatidylinositolanchored glycoprotein that is a member of the alpha (2)-macroglobulin/C3, C4, C5 family of thioester-containing proteins [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25848" pm="."><plain>CD109 interacts directly with the type I transforming growth factor -beta (TGF-β) signaling receptor and negatively modulates TGF-β signalling [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25849" pm="."><plain>It is expressed on a subpopulation of CD34+ cells [29], on activated platelets and activated T-cells [30] and on a subpopulation of endothelial cells [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25850" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, it has been reported that CD109 is one of 12 endothelial markers over-expressed in tumor endothelial cells [23], [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25851" pm="."><plain>In order to gain a more comprehensive understanding of CEC phenotype, we investigated the expression of CD109 on cultured endothelial cells and on CECs from the peripheral blood of healthy subject and cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25852" pm="."><plain>We used a flow cytometry approach validated in our laboratory, and the endothelial nature of these cells was validated by RT-PCR and gene expression. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="25853" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="25854" pm="."><plain>Ethics Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25855" pm="."><plain>All patients gave written informed consent before inclusion in the therapeutic protocol and for research purpose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25856" pm="."><plain>All clinical investigation were conducted according to the principles expressed in the Declaration of Helsinki. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25857" pm="."><plain>For Breast Cancer patients: The trial was conducted at the European Institute of Oncology, Milan, Italy and approved by the “IRCCS - Istituto Europeo di Oncologia e Centro Cardiologico Monzino” Ethic Committee and registered in the Institute database (# 2007-006025-27). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25858" pm="."><plain>For Glioblastoma patients: The trial was conducted at the Neurological Institute “Carlo Besta” of Milan, Italy and approved by the “ Regione Lombardia Sezione Fondazione IRCCS Istituto Neurologico Besta” Ethic Committee and registered in the Institute database (#1/08). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="25859" pm="."><plain>Detection of CD109 on endothelial colonies </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25860" pm="."><plain>To validate by flow-cytometry the expression of CD109 on endothelial cells, in vitro endothelial colonies were obtained from peripheral blood (PB) of 10 healthy donors (7 female, 3 male) and 23 cancer patients as previously described [32]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25861" pm="."><plain>Briefly, mononuclear cells (MNCs) were isolated from PB using Ficoll-Paque gradient centrifugation, resuspended into EGM2 medium (Lonza, Walkersville, MD) and seeded onto Collagen I petri dishes (35 mm, Biocoat, BD Labware, Bedford, MA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25862" pm="."><plain>Cultures were incubated at 37°C, 5% CO2, 95% relative humidity for 3–4 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25863" pm="."><plain>Medium was changed every 2 days for 7 days and then twice a week until first passage, and culture monitored for the detection of endothelial colonies on the basis of morphological features, as previously described [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25864" pm="."><plain>After 15–20 days, cells were detached with trypsin/EDTA (Gibco, BRL, UK) and stained with monoclonal antibodies (MoAbs) anti- CD31-PeCy7, CD34-APC, CD45-H7, and 7-AAD (all from Beckman Coulter) CD146-Pe (Chemicon), VEGFR-2- PE (R&amp;D) and CD109-Pe (Abcam) for flow cytometry studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="25865" pm="."><plain>Sorting of CD109+ and CD146+ cells from Peripheral Blood </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25866" pm="."><plain>To perform a microarray analysis for genes expressed in circulating endothelial cells positive for CD109 (CD109+CECs) and CEC positive for CD146 (CD146+CECs), a three laser Influx high speed cell sorter (BD) was used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25867" pm="."><plain>Briefly, in two different experiments, 150 ml of blood from 8 healthy subjects were collected and after MNCs isolation with Ficoll- gradient, cells were depleted of white blood cells using anti-CD45 antibody coupled with magnetic MACS MicroBeads (Miltenyi Biotech) following the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25868" pm="."><plain>Cells were stained for Syto16, CD45, CD31 and CD109 and in the second experiment for Syto16, CD45, CD31 and CD146. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25869" pm="."><plain>During sorting procedure, samples were continuously cooled to 4°C and a forward scatter pulse height and side scatter analyses were performed to exclude cell clusters and doublets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25870" pm="."><plain>A two way cell sorting procedure was performed with a140 um nozzle with a 5.5 PSI pressure, and with an events rate of 1,000–1,500 events per second, using a sort pure mode. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25871" pm="."><plain>The sorting gate was painted on Syto16+CD45−CD31+CD109+ cells and on Syto16+CD45−CD31+CD146+ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25872" pm="."><plain>Samples were collected into sterile polypropylene tubes containing RPMI and used for molecular analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25873" pm="."><plain>Purity was always greater than 95% with a recovery of 70–80%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="25874" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR and gene expression analysis of sorted CD109+ CECs cells and CD146+ CECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25875" pm="."><plain>RNA isolation of sorted CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs, was carried out using ArcturusPicoPureRNA Isolation Kit, and cDNA was generated from the total amount of RNA using the high-capacity cDNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25876" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) was carried out after pre-amplification of cDNA (TaqManPreAmp Master Mix Kit) with an ABI Prism 7000 platform using TaqMan Gene Expression Assay for CDH5 (Ve-Cadherin), CLDN5, (Claudin 5) VWF (Von Willebrand Factor), CD34, VCAM-1, CLEC14a, TMEM204, ARHGEF15, GPR116, ARAP3, TEM8 (ANTRAX1 receptor) [33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="25877" pm="."><plain>Characterization of CD109+ CEC and CD146+ CEC phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25878" pm="."><plain>To characterize CD109+ CEC and CD146+ CEC phenotype, a combination of 10 monoclonal antibodies was used (Syto 16 FITC, CD146 PE, 7-AAD, CD31 PeCy7, CD34 ECD, CD13 APC, CD90 APC-AF700, CD117 APC-AF750, CD45 Pacific Blue and CD109 Pacific Orange). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25879" pm="."><plain>CD90 and CD 117 were purchased by Beckman Coulter. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25880" pm="."><plain>Unlabeled CD109 (Abcam) was conjugated with pacific orange, using the Zenon R Kit labeling technologies (Life Technologies), according to the manufacturer instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25881" pm="."><plain>CD34, CD90 and CD117 expression were evaluated on DNA+ (Syto16+) CD45−CD31+ CD109+ and on DNA+ (Syto16+) CD45−CD31+CD146+ cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25882" pm="."><plain>To confirm by flow cytometry the endothelial nature of CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs, we used Ulex Europeaus lectin and Ac-LDL FITC up take. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25883" pm="."><plain>For Ac-LDL FITC up take, we collected 5 mL of blood from 5 different breast cancer patients, and after MNCs isolation with Ficoll-gradient, cells were incubated with Ac-LDL FITC according to the manufacture's instruction (10 µg/mL for 4 hours at 37°C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25884" pm="."><plain>After Ac-LDL incubation, we stained cells with Syto16, CD45, CD31 and CD109 to investigate the presence of AcLDL+CD109+ cells among CD45-Syto16+(nucleated) CD31+ cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25885" pm="."><plain>Five different experiments were performed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="25886" pm="."><plain>Detection of CD109+ CECs and CD146+ CECs in Healthy Subjects and Cancer Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25887" pm="."><plain>Following a flow-cytometry protocol validated in our laboratory for CEC detection (Fig. 1), [ref 14], the number and viability of CD109+ CECs and CD146+ CECs were evaluated in the peripheral blood of 50 healthy subjects and 200 cancer patients (66 metastatic breast cancer and 134 glioblastoma patients). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0114713-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114713.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="25888" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry strategy to detect CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25889" pm="."><plain>Fluorescence Minus One for each fluorescence is reported. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0114713.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="25890" pm="."><plain>Briefly, the nuclear staining Syto16 was used to discriminate between DNA containing cells, platelets and cell debris, and 7AAD to determine the viability status of the cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25891" pm="."><plain>The panel of MoAbs used included anti-CD45 (to exclude hematopoietic cells), anti-CD31 (an endothelial cell differentiation marker), anti-CD34 (as endothelial and progenitor cells marker) and anti-CD109 or anti-CD146. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25892" pm="."><plain>After incubation of 2.5×106 total cells with MoAbs (4°C for 20 minutes) and cells lysis with ammonium chloride (NH4Cl), at least 2×106 total cells were acquired at flow-cytometer (Facs-Canto, BD, from 2007 to 2010 and Navios, Beckman Coulter, from 2010 until February 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25893" pm="."><plain>Analysis was performed on cells positive for Syto16 (DNA) negative for CD45, and positive for CD31 and CD109 or for CD31 and CD146. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25894" pm="."><plain>The combination of Syto16 and 7AAD was used to evaluate CEC viability according to van der Pol et al. [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25895" pm="."><plain>Necrotic cells were identified as Syto16 low/7AAD positive, apoptotic cells as Syto16 low/7AAD negative and viable cells as Syto16 bright/7AAD negative. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title><text><SENT sid="25896" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25897" pm="."><plain>Continuous variables are reported as mean ± SEM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25898" pm="."><plain>Two-way ANOVA, or two-tailed Student's t test, were used where appropriate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25899" pm="."><plain>Statistical significance was taken at p&lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="25900" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="25901" pm="."><plain>Endothelial colonies phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25902" pm="."><plain>Peripheral blood MNC (30×106 cells plated) generated endothelial colonies from 9 of 10 healthy subjects and from 14 of 23 patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25903" pm="."><plain>All endothelial colonies were positive for CD31, CD146, CD34 and VEGFR-2 and negative for CD45. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25904" pm="."><plain>Endothelial colonies from all healthy subjects and from 10 cancer patients were also evaluated for CD109 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25905" pm="."><plain>CD109 was expressed on 1/9 endothelial cultures from healthy subject (11%) and on 5/10 (50%) endothelial cultures from cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="25906" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR of sorted CD109+ CECs and CD146+ CECs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25907" pm="."><plain>Fold changes of down- or up-regulated genes are expressed comparing cDNA from CD109+CECs to CD146+ CECs as reference cells (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0114713-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114713.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="25908" pm="."><plain>Real-time quantitative PCR analysis comparing changes in gene expression between CD109+ cells and CD146+ cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25909" pm="."><plain>Fold changes of down- or up-regulated genes are expressed comparing cDNA from CD109+ to CD146+ cells as reference cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25910" pm="."><plain>To ensure biological reproducibility, blood for cDNA collection were obtained from 8 different donors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0114713.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="25911" pm="."><plain>In both CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs we confirmed the expression of mRNA level of CDH5 (Ve-Cadherin) and CLDN5 (Claudin V), two endothelial specific transcripts, suggesting that both cells are related and of endothelial nature [23]–[24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25912" pm="."><plain>Same results were obtained for mRNA levels of vWF, VCAM1 and CD34. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25913" pm="."><plain>Higher levels of endothelial specific transcripts expressed in developing endothelial cells [33] CLEC14a, TMEM204, ARHGEF15, GPR116, were observed in sorted CD109+CECs when compared to sorted CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25914" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, mRNA levels of TEM8 (identified as Antrax Toxin Receptor1, Antrax1) were expressed only in CD109+CECs+ but not in CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="25915" pm="."><plain>CD109+ and CD146+ CEC phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25916" pm="."><plain>As shown in Fig. 3, among Syto16+7-AAD-CD31+CD45− cells, we detected two different population of CECs, being one positive for CD109+ but negative for CD146, and one positive for CD146 but negative for CD109. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25917" pm="."><plain>Both CD146+ CECs and CD109+ CECs were negative for CD90 and CD117, to confirm these cells are likely differentiated cells and not progenitors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25918" pm="."><plain>CD34 was positive on 30% of CD146+ CECs and on 20% of CD109+ CECs, and CD13 was positive on 50% and 60% of CD146+CECs and CD109+CECs respectively, confirming these cells are activated cells of angiogenic vasculature [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0114713-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114713.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="25919" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry strategy to detect CD109+CEC and CD146+CEC phenotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25920" pm="."><plain>After exclusion of debris (A) and selection of CD45− (B), nucleated (Syto16+) and CD31+ cells (C), CEC were identified as positive for CD109 or CD146 (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25921" pm="."><plain>(D): negative control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25922" pm="."><plain>CD109+ CECs and CD146+CECs were evaluated by flow cytometry for the expression of CD34, CD117, CD90 and CD13. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0114713.g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="25923" pm="."><plain>Both CD146+CECs and CD109+CECs were positive for the Ulex Europeaus Lectin (Fig. 4 A–B1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25924" pm="."><plain>To exclude epithelial cells contamination, we stained nucleated (Syto16+) CD45− cells for Epcam and even if a subpopulation of Epcam+ cells is present, these cells are negative for CD31 expression (Fig. 4 C–C1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0114713-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114713.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="25925" pm="."><plain>Expression of Ulex Europeaus Lectin.on CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs+ (4A–B1). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25926" pm="."><plain>Epcam staining (4C–C1) confirmed that Epithelial Cells even if present in the DNA+CD45− cell compartment, are negative for the expression of CD31 present only on endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0114713.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="25927" pm="."><plain>To examine CD109+CECs function, we performed Ac-LDL up-take. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25928" pm="."><plain>As Ac-LDL is taken up by macrophages/monocytes, we used these cells as “internal positive control” to confirm endocytosis activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25929" pm="."><plain>As reported in Fig. 5, among Ac-LdL+ cells both CD45+CD31+CD14+ (monocytes) and CD45−CD31+CD109+ (endothelial cells) were detected. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0114713-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0114713.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="25930" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometry strategy to detect Ac-LDL uptake. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25931" pm="."><plain>After dublets (A) and debris (B) exclusion, Ac-LDL+ cells were detected (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25932" pm="."><plain>Among these cells, CD45+CD31+ and CD45−CD31+ cells were detected (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25933" pm="."><plain>CD45+CD31+ were also positive for CD14 (monocytes,E) and CD45−CD31+ were also positive for CD109+ (endothelial cells, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25934" pm="."><plain>Ac-LDL+ cells were nucleated (Syto16+, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25935" pm="."><plain>C1, D1, E1 and F1 are the negative controls. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0114713.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="25936" pm="."><plain>Detection of CD109+ CECs in Healthy Subjects and Cancer Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25937" pm="."><plain>Patients characteristics are reported in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="26012" pm="."><plain>CD146+CECs were 43±23/mL in healthy subject (n = 50), 103±83/mL in breast cancer patients (n = 64, p&lt;0.0001) and 117±87 in glioblastoma patients (n = 134, p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26013" pm="."><plain>The fraction of apoptotic/necrotic CD146+CECs was 67±20% in healthy subject, 62±20% in breast cancer patients and 66±18/mL in glioblastoma patients before treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26014" pm="."><plain>After treatment CD146+CECs and viable CD146+CECs were 96±121/mL and 41±88/mL respectively in breast cancer patients, and 78±84/mL and 23±31/mL in glioblastoma patients (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="26015" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26016" pm="."><plain>Endothelial cell heterogeneity has been described at the level of cell morphology, function, gene expression, and antigen composition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26017" pm="."><plain>Because blood vessels are distributed throughout the body, the endothelial cells are exposed to an enormous variety of tissue microenvironments, and the wide range of signal inputs is sufficient to generate phenotypic heterogeneity across the vascular tree [19], [21], [35]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26018" pm="."><plain>Detection of circulating endothelial cells by flow cytometry is an approach widely used in cancer patients, and the identification of the number, viability and kinetic of endothelial cells is a promising tool to stratify patient receiving anti-angiogenic treatment [15]–[18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26019" pm="."><plain>Currently, CECs are enumerated by a multiparametric flow-cytometry approach combining CD146, CD31, CD45, a nuclear binding antigen (Syto16, Dapi or HOECST) along with a viability cellular staining (like 7-AAD or Annexin V). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26020" pm="."><plain>CD109 is a glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored cell surface glycoprotein and is one of 12 endothelial markers over-expressed in tumor endothelial cells [23], [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26021" pm="."><plain>In this work, following an approach recently validated in our laboratory [14], we sorted CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs and we confirmed by RT-PCR, in both population the expression of mRNA level of CDH5 (Ve-Cadherin) and CLDN5 (Claudin5) two genes selectively expressed in endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26022" pm="."><plain>Higher levels of CLEC14a, TMEM204, ARHGEF15, Gpr116 expressed in developing endothelial cells [33], were present in CD109+CECs when compared to CD146+CECs, suggesting that these genes may play an important role not only in developing endothelial cells but also in adult angiogenesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26023" pm="."><plain>We demonstrated that CD109+CECs and CD146+CECs are two different subpopulation of endothelial cells, being these two antigens not expressed on the same cells, while CD34 (a marker currently used to identify progenitor cells) was positive on 20% of CD109+CECs and on 30% of CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26024" pm="."><plain>We evaluated the number, viability and kinetic of CD109+CECs and of CD146+ CECs and observed that both subpopulation of endothelial cells are enriched in the blood of glioblastoma and breast cancer patients, are more viable when compared to value observed in healthy subject, and their number decrease significantly after treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26025" pm="."><plain>In our previous experience, we reported that in patients with breast cancer treated with metronomic chemotherapy, CD146+CEC levels after two months of treatment were associated with prolonged PFS [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26026" pm="."><plain>In another clinical trial, in breast cancer patients treated with metronomic chemotherapy and bevacizumab, baseline CEC levels were also associated with PFS [36], [37] confirming that the quantification of CD146+ CECs is useful to identify patients who might benefit from antiangiogenic treatments [38]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26027" pm="."><plain>In a series of patients with glioblastoma treated with AZD2171, a pan-VEGF receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor, Batchelor found that viable CEC levels were higher in patients who experienced disease progression during AZD2171 therapy compared to patients without progression at day 112 [39]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26028" pm="."><plain>We recently reported [40] that in glioblastoma patients treated with bevacizumab and irinotecan or with bevacizumab alone, PFS and OS were significantly increased in patients with baseline counts of CD109+CECs higher than 41.1/mls, (1stquartile), while no prognostic factor was associated to CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26029" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that CEC heterogeneity may reflect vascular tumor complexity and that CD109+ CECs might be a potentially useful prognostic marker for glioblastoma patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26030" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that CD109 is over-expressed in tumor vasculature [24], and in this study we observed that all endothelial colonies from healthy subjects and from 10 cancer patients were positive for CD31, CD146, CD34 and VEGFR-2 and negative for CD45, while CD109 was positive on 1/9 endothelial cultures from healthy subject (11%) and on 5/10 (50%) endothelial cultures from cancer patients. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26031" pm="."><plain>Moreover m-RNA level of TEM8, a cell surface glycoprotein identified as Anthrax Toxin Receptor 1, were detectable in CD109+CECs but not in CD146+CECs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26032" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that TEM8, is up-regulated in tumor vessels [41], [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26033" pm="."><plain>In TEM8 Knockout mice physiological angiogenesis and wound healing occur normally, but in tumor bearing mice, tumor growth is impaired, showing that TEM8 may be required to promote tumor angiogenesis but not normal development [43]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26034" pm="."><plain>Taken together these results suggest that CD109 could represent a rare population of circulating tumor endothelial cells, that play a potentially useful prognostic role in patients with glioblastoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26035" pm="."><plain>The role of CD109 expression in cancer vessel-specific endothelial cells deserves to be further investigated by gene expression studies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="26036" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="26037" pm="."><plain>There is a growing need in identifying circulating biological marker to stratify patients who may benefit of anti-angiogenic treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26038" pm="."><plain>In this work we report that CD109 is a potential useful prognostic marker in glioblastoma patients, and that its role in cancer angiogenesis need to be investigated in different tumor setting. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="26039" pm="."><plain>Supported in part by AIRC, (Associazione Italiana per la Ricerca sul Cancro), Fondazione Umberto Veronesi, and Ministero della Salute. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0114713-Kerbel1"><text><SENT sid="26040" pm="."><plain>1 KerbelR, FolkmanJ (2002) Clinical translation of angiogenesis inhibitors. Nat Rev Cancer. 2(10):727–739 Review.12360276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Ferrara1"><text><SENT sid="26041" pm="."><plain>2 FerraraN, KerbelRS (2005) Angiogenesis as a therapeutic target. Nature. 15;438(7070):967–974. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Kerbel2"><text><SENT sid="26042" pm="."><plain>3 KerbelRS (2008) Tumor angiogenesis. N Engl J Med 8;358(19):2039–2049. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Ferrara2"><text><SENT sid="26043" pm="."><plain>4 FerraraN, HillanKJ, GerberHP, NovotnyW (2004) Discovery and development of bevacizumab, an anti-VEGF antibody for treating cancer. Nat Rev Drug Discov 3:391–400.15136787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Hurwitz1"><text><SENT sid="26044" pm="."><plain>5 HurwitzH, FehrenbacherL, Novotny, CartwrightT, HainsworthJ, et al (2004) Bevacizumab plus irinotecan, fluorouracil, and leucovorin for metastatic colorectal cancer. N Engl Med 350:2335–2340. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Keedy1"><text><SENT sid="26045" pm="."><plain>6 KeedyVL, SandlerAB (2007) Inhibition of angiogenesis in the treatment of non-small cell lung cancer. Cancer Sci 98(12):1825–1830.17892508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Motzer1"><text><SENT sid="26046" pm="."><plain>7 MotzerRJ, MichaelsonMD, RedmanBG, HudesGR, WildingG, et al (2006) Activity of SU11248, a multitargeted inhibitor of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor and platelet-derived growth factor receptor, in patients with metastatic renal cell carcinoma. J Clin Oncol 24(1):16–24.16330672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Escudier1"><text><SENT sid="26047" pm="."><plain>8 EscudierB, EisenT, StadlerWM, SzczylikC, OudardS, et al (2007) Sorafenib in advanced clear-cell renal-cell carcinoma. N Engl J Med 356(2):125–134.17215530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Shaked1"><text><SENT sid="26048" pm="."><plain>9 ShakedY, EmmeneggerU, ManS, CerviD, BertoliniF, et al (2005) Optimal biologic dose of metronomic chemotherapy regimens is associated with maximum antiangiogenic activity. Blood 106:3058–3061.15998832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Bertolini1"><text><SENT sid="26049" pm="."><plain>10 BertoliniF, PaulS, MancusoP, MonestiroliS, GobbiA, et al (2003) Maximum tolerable dose and low-dose metronomic chemotherapy have opposite effects on the mobilization and viability of circulating endothelial progenitor cells. Cancer Res 63:4342–4346.12907602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Frstenberger1"><text><SENT sid="26050" pm="."><plain>11 FürstenbergerG, von MoosR, LucasR, ThürlimannB, SennHJ, et al (2006) Circulating endothelial cells and angiogenic serum factors during neoadjuvant chemotherapy of primary breast cancer. Br J Cancer 94:524–531.16450002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Blann1"><text><SENT sid="26051" pm="."><plain>12 BlannAD, WoywodtA, BertoliniF, BullTM, BuyonJP, et al 2005) Circulating endothelial cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26052" pm="."><plain>Biomarker of vascular disease. Thromb Haemost 93:228–235.15711737 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Goon1"><text><SENT sid="26053" pm="."><plain>13 GoonPK, BoosCJ, StonelakePS, BlannAD, LipGY (2006) Detection and quantification of mature circulating endothelial cells using flow cytometry and immunomagnetic beads: A methodological comparison. Thromb Haemost 96:45–52.16807650 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Mancuso1"><text><SENT sid="26054" pm="."><plain>14 MancusoP, AntoniottiP, QuarnaJ, CalleriA, RabascioC, et al (2009) Validation of a standardized method for enumerating circulating endothelial cells and progenitors: flow cytometry and molecular and ultrastructural analyses. Clin Cancer Res 5 (1):267–273. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Mancuso2"><text><SENT sid="26055" pm="."><plain>15 MancusoP, ColleoniM, CalleriA, OrlandoL, MaisonneuveP, et al (2006) Circulating endothelial-cell kinetics and viability predict survival in breast cancer patients receiving metronomic chemotherapy. Blood 15;108(2):452–459. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Beerepoot1"><text><SENT sid="26056" pm="."><plain>16 BeerepootLV, MehraN, VermaatJS, ZonnenbergBA, GebbinkMF, et al (2004) Increased levels of viable circulating endothelial cells are an indicator of progressive disease in cancer patients. Ann Oncol 15(1):139–145.14679134 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Fleitas1"><text><SENT sid="26057" pm="."><plain>17 FleitasT, Martínez-SalesV, VilaV, ReganonE, MesadoD, et al (2012) Circulating endothelial cells and microparticles as prognostic markers in advanced non-small cell lung cancer. PLoS One. 2012;7(10):e47365. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Kawaishi1"><text><SENT sid="26058" pm="."><plain>18 KawaishiM, FujiwaraY, FukuiT, KatoT, YamadaK, et al (2009) Circulating endothelial cells in non-small cell lung cancer patients treated with carboplatin and paclitaxel. J Thorac Oncol 4(2):208–213.19179898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Aird1"><text><SENT sid="26059" pm="."><plain>19 AirdWC (2012) Endothelial cell heterogeneity. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med 2(1):a006429 10.1101/cshperspect.a006429 22315715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Garlanda1"><text><SENT sid="26060" pm="."><plain>20 GarlandaC, DejanaE (1997) Heterogeneity of endothelial cells. Specific markers Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol 17:1193–1202.9261246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Aird2"><text><SENT sid="26061" pm="."><plain>21 AirdWC (2009) Molecular heterogeneity of tumor endothelium. Cell Tissue Res 335(1):271–281.18726119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Rajotte1"><text><SENT sid="26062" pm="."><plain>22 RajotteD, ArapW, HagedornM, KoivunenE, PasqualiniR, et al (1998) Molecular heterogeneity of the vascular endothelium revealed by in vivo phage display. J Clin Invest 102:430–437.9664085 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-StCroix1"><text><SENT sid="26063" pm="."><plain>23 St CroixB, RagoC, VelculescuV, TraversoG, RomansKE, et al (2000) Genes expressed in human tumor endothelium. Science 289:1197–202.10947988 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Seaman1"><text><SENT sid="26064" pm="."><plain>24 SeamanS, StevensJ, YangMY, LogsdonD, Graff-CherryC, et al (2007) Genes that distinguish physiological and pathological angiogenesis. Cancer Cell 11(6):539–554.17560335 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Strijbos1"><text><SENT sid="26065" pm="."><plain>25 StrijbosMH, GratamaJW, KraanJ, LamersCH, den BakkerMA, et al (2008) Circulating endothelial cells in oncology: pitfalls and promises. Br J Cancer 98(11):1731–1735.18506173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Kraan1"><text><SENT sid="26066" pm="."><plain>26 KraanJ, StrijbosMH, SieuwertsAM, FoekensJA, den BakkerMA, et al (2012) A new approach for rapid and reliable enumeration of circulating endothelial cells in patients. J Thromb Haemost 10(5):931–939.22385979 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Lin1"><text><SENT sid="26067" pm="."><plain>27 LinM, SutherlandDR, HorsfallW, TottyN, YeoE, et al (2002) Cell surface antigen CD109 is a novel member of the alpha(2) macroglobulin/C3, C4, C5 family of thioester-containing proteins. Blood 99:1683–1691.11861284 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Finnson1"><text><SENT sid="26068" pm="."><plain>28 FinnsonKW, TamBY, LiuK, MarcouxA, LepageP, et al (2006) Identification of CD109 as part of the TGF-beta receptor system in human keratinocytes. FASEB 20:1525–1527. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Murray1"><text><SENT sid="26069" pm="."><plain>29 MurrayLJ, BrunoE, UchidaN, HoffmanR, NayarR, et al (1999) CD109 is expressed on a subpopulation of CD34+ cells enriched in hematopoietic stem and progenitor cells. Experimental Hematology 27:8 1282–1294. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Sutherland1"><text><SENT sid="26070" pm="."><plain>30 SutherlandDR, YeoE, RyanA, MillsGB, BaileyD, et al (1991) Identification of a cell-surface antigen associated with activated T lymphoblasts and activated platelets. Blood 77(1):84–93.1984805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Mutin1"><text><SENT sid="26071" pm="."><plain>31 MutinM, Dignat-GeorgeF, SampolJ (1997) Immunologic phenotype of cultured endothelial cells: quantitative analysis of cell surface molecules. Tissue Antigens 50(5):449–458.9389318 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Ingram1"><text><SENT sid="26072" pm="."><plain>32 IngramDA, MeadLE, TanakaH, MeadeV, FenoglioA, et al (2004) Identification of a novel hierarchy of endothelial progenitor cells using human peripheral and umbilical cord blood. Blood 104(9):2752–2760.15226175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Takase1"><text><SENT sid="26073" pm="."><plain>33 TakaseH, MatsumotoK, YamaderaR, KubotaY, OtsuA, et al (2012) Genome-wide identification of endothelial cell-enriched genes in the mouse embryo. Blood 120(4):914–923.22535667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-vanderPol1"><text><SENT sid="26074" pm="."><plain>34 van der PolMA, BroxtermanHJ, WestraG, OssenkoppeleGJ, SchuurhuisGJ (2003) Novel multiparameter flow cytometry assay using Syto16 for the simultaneous detection of early apoptosis and apoptosis-corrected P-glycoprotein function in clinical samples. Cytometry B Clin Cytom 55(1):14–21.12949955 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Aird3"><text><SENT sid="26075" pm="."><plain>35 AirdWC (2007) Phenotypic heterogeneity of the endothelium: I. Structure, function, and mechanisms. Circ Res 100(2):158–173.17272818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Dellapasqua1"><text><SENT sid="26077" pm="."><plain>36 DellapasquaS, BertoliniF, BagnardiV, CampagnoliE, ScaranoE, et al (2008) Metronomic cyclophosphamide and capecitabine combined with bevacizumab in advanced breast cancer. J Clin Oncol 20;26(30):4899–4905. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Calleri1"><text><SENT sid="26078" pm="."><plain>37 CalleriA, BonoA, BagnardiV, QuarnaJ, MancusoP, et al (2009) Predictive Potential of Angiogenic Growth Factors and Circulating Endothelial Cells in Breast Cancer Patients Receiving Metronomic Chemotherapy Plus Bevacizumab. Clin Cancer Res 15(24):7652–7657.19996223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Bertolini2"><text><SENT sid="26079" pm="."><plain>38 BertoliniF, ShakedY, MancusoP, KerbelRS (2006) The multifaceted circulating endothelial cell in cancer: towards marker and target identification. Nat Rev Cancer 6(11):835–845.17036040 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Batchelor1"><text><SENT sid="26080" pm="."><plain>39 BatchelorTT, SorensenAG, di TomasoE, ZhangWT, DudaDG, et al (2007) AZD2171, a pan-VEGF receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor, normalizes tumor vasculature and alleviates edema in glioblastoma patients. Cancer Cell 11(1):83–95.17222792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Cuppini1"><text><SENT sid="26081" pm="."><plain>40 CuppiniL, CalleriA, BruzzoneMG, ProdiE, AnghileriE, et al (2013) Prognostic value of CD109+ circulating endothelial cells in recurrent glioblastomas treated with bevacizumab and irinotecan. PLoS One 12;8(9):e74345 10.1371/journal.pone.0074345.eCollection2013  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Mehran1"><text><SENT sid="26082" pm="."><plain>41 MehranR1, NilssonM, KhajaviM, DuZ, CasconeT, et al (2014) Tumor endothelial markers define novel subsets of cancer-specific circulating endothelial cells associated with antitumor efficacy. Cancer Res. 10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-13-2044  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Chaudhary1"><text><SENT sid="26083" pm="."><plain>42 ChaudharyA, HiltonMB, SeamanS, HainesDC, StevensonS, et al (2012) TEM8/ANTXR1 blockade inhibits pathological angiogenesis and potentiates tumoricidal responses against multiple cancer types. Cancer Cell 21(2):212–226.22340594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Cullen1"><text><SENT sid="26084" pm="."><plain>43 CullenM, SeamanS, ChaudharyA, YangMY, HiltonMB, et al (2009) Host-derived tumor endothelial marker 8 promotes the growth of melanoma. Cancer Res 69(15):6021–6026.19622764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0114713-Bhagwat1"><text><SENT sid="26085" pm="."><plain>44 BhagwatSV, LahdenrantaJ, GiordanoR, ArapW, PasqualiniR, et al (2001) CD13/APN is activated by angiogenic signals and is essential for capillary tube formation. Blood 97:652–659.11157481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
