<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Breast Cancer Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Breast Cancer Research : BCR</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1465-5411</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1465-542X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4423106</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25882602</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">548</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13058-015-0548-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="30576" pm="."><plain>Tumor expression, plasma levels and genetic polymorphisms of the coagulation inhibitor TFPI are associated with clinicopathological parameters and survival in breast cancer, in contrast to the coagulation initiator TF </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tinholt</surname><given-names>Mari</given-names></name><address><email>mari.tinholt@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vollan</surname><given-names>Hans Kristian Moen</given-names></name><address><email>hans.kristian.vollan@me.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sahlberg</surname><given-names>Kristine Kleivi</given-names></name><address><email>kristine.kleivi@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jernström</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name><address><email>Sandra.Nyberg@rr-research.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaveh</surname><given-names>Fatemeh</given-names></name><address><email>fatemeh.kaveh@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lingjærde</surname><given-names>Ole Christian</given-names></name><address><email>ole@ifi.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kåresen</surname><given-names>Rolf</given-names></name><address><email>rolf.karesen@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>Torill</given-names></name><address><email>torill.sauer@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>Vessela</given-names></name><address><email>v.n.kristensen@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Børresen-Dale</surname><given-names>Anne-Lise</given-names></name><address><email>a.l.borresen-dale@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sandset</surname><given-names>Per Morten</given-names></name><address><email>p.m.sandset@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Iversen</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name><address><email>nina.iversen@medisin.uio.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Medical Genetics, Oslo University Hospital and University of Oslo, BOX 4956, Nydalen, Oslo, N-0424 Norway </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Haematology and Research Institute of Internal Medicine, Oslo University Hospital, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Institute of Clinical Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Genetics, Institute for Cancer Research, Oslo University Hospital Radiumhospitalet, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label/>The K.G. Jebsen Center for Breast Cancer Research, Institute of Clinical Medicine, Faculty of Medicine, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label/>Department of Oncology, Division of Surgery, Transplantation and Cancer Medicine, Oslo University Hospital Radiumhospitalet, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label/>Department of Research, Vestre Viken, Drammen, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label/>Biomedical Informatics Research Group, Department of Informatics, University of Oslo, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff9"><label/>Department of Breast and Endocrine Surgery, Oslo University Hospital, Oslo, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff10"><label/>Department of Pathology, Akershus University Hospital, Lørenskog, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff11"><label/>Department of Clinical Molecular Biology (EpiGen), Akershus University Hospital, Lørenskog, Norway </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>44</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Tinholt et al.; licensee BioMed Central. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30577" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="30578" pm="."><plain>Hypercoagulability in malignancy increases the risk of thrombosis, but is also involved in cancer progression. Experimental studies suggest that tissue factor (TF) and tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) are involved in cancer biology as a tumor- promoter and suppressor, respectively, but the clinical significance is less clear. Here, we aimed to investigate the clinical relevance of TF and TFPI genetic and phenotypic diversity in breast cancer. </p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30581" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="30582" pm="."><plain>The relationship between tumor messenger RNA (mRNA) expression and plasma levels of TF and TFPI (α and β), tagging single nucleotide polymorphisms (tagSNPs) in F3 (TF) (n = 6) and TFPI (n = 18), and clinicopathological characteristics and molecular tumor subtypes were explored in 152 treatment naive breast cancer patients. The effect of tumor expressed TF and TFPIα and TFPIβ on survival was investigated in a merged breast cancer dataset of 1881 patients. </p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30584" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="30585" pm="."><plain>Progesterone receptor negative patients had higher mRNA expression of total TFPI (α + β) (P = 0.021) and TFPIβ (P = 0.014) in tumors. TF mRNA expression was decreased in grade 3 tumors (P = 0.003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30587" pm="."><plain>In plasma, total TFPI levels were decreased in patients with larger tumors (P = 0.013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30588" pm="."><plain>SNP haplotypes of TFPI, but not TF, were associated with specific clinicopathological characteristics like tumor size (odds ratio (OR) 3.14, P = 0.004), triple negativity (OR 2.4, P = 0.004), lymph node spread (OR 3.34, P = 0.006), and basal-like (OR 2.3, P = 0.011) and luminal B (OR 3.5, P = 0.005) molecular tumor subtypes. Increased expression levels of TFPIα and TFPIβ in breast tumors were associated with better outcome in all tumor subtypes combined (P = 0.007 and P = 0.005) and in multiple subgroups, including lymph node positive subjects (P = 0.006 and P = 0.034). </p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30590" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="30591" pm="."><plain>This study indicates that genetic and phenotypic variation of both TFPIα and TFPIβ, more than TF, are markers of cancer progression. Together with the previously demonstrated tumor suppressor effects of TFPI, the beneficial effect of tumor expressed TFPI on survival, renders TFPI as a potential anticancer agent, and the clinical significance of TFPI in cancer deserves further investigation. </p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="30593" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="30594" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13058-015-0548-5) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="30595" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30596" pm="."><plain>There is now convincing evidence of a relationship between cancer and hemostasis. An oncogene driven thrombophilic environment frequently arises in cancer and involves the capacity of tumor- and stimulated host stroma cells to express and release clotting factors, inflammatory cytokines, proangiogenic factors, and procoagulant microparticles (MPs) [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30598" pm="."><plain>One obvious manifestation of cancer-associated coagulopathy is the increased risk of venous thrombosis (VT) among cancer patients [2-4], however, the procoagulant state may also promote tumor progression [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30599" pm="."><plain>Full-length tissue factor (TF) [GenBank: NM_001993] is the most extensively studied coagulation factor in cancer, and its activity is regulated by TF pathway inhibitor (TFPI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30600" pm="."><plain>Expression of both TF and TFPI has been detected in tissues and cell lines of several human cancers including breast cancer [6-10], suggesting a role in cancer biology. TF is known to be a trigger of angiogenesis, proliferation, migration, and invasion, and to prevent apoptosis [11-14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30602" pm="."><plain>These effects may either be coagulation dependent, indirectly through fibrin formation and platelet activation, or through coagulation independent signaling via factor VIIa (FVIIa) and activation of protease activated receptor 2 (PAR-2), enhanced by β1 integrin [5,12]. <p><text><SENT sid="30603" pm="."><plain>Full-length TFPI (TFPIα) [GenBank: NM_006287] consists of three Kunitz-type inhibitor domains and a positively charged carboxy-terminal (C-terminal) end, while the alternatively spliced TFPIβ [GenBank: NM_001032281] lacks the third Kunitz domain and has a unique C-terminal that directs binding to a glycosylphosphatidylinisotol (GPI) anchor on the cell surface [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30604" pm="."><plain>There is growing evidence for non-hemostatic tumor-suppressive activities of TFPI. Studies of endothelial cell cultures have shown that recombinant TFPIα induces apoptosis [16], inhibits proliferation via the very low density lipoprotein receptor [17], and show anti-angiogenic and anti-migratory properties [18,19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30606" pm="."><plain>In addition, manipulation of their expression revealed that both the TFPIα and the TFPIβ isoform have tumor-suppressive features in breast cancer cells, similar to that observed in endothelial cells [20,21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30607" pm="."><plain>Supporting the in vitro observations, in vivo studies have demonstrated that both circulating recombinant TFPI and TFPI-expressing tumor cells significantly attenuated tumor growth [13,22] and lung metastasis in mice [13,23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30608" pm="."><plain>A transgenic murine model of TFPI overexpression suggested that the C-terminal end of TFPIα caused impaired angiogenesis by inhibition of phosphorylation of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor 2 [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30609" pm="."><plain>A few TFPI and TF (F3) single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) have been reported and assigned a possible, but not definite role in modifying transcription or plasma levels of TFPI and TF [24-30]. <p><text><SENT sid="30610" pm="."><plain>Breast cancer is a highly heterogeneous disease and several subgroups exist that differ in prognosis and management options. Three main tumor subtypes may be determined using traditional immunohistochemistry (IHC); hormone receptor (HR) positive (i.e., estrogen receptor (ER) and progesterone receptor (PR) positive), human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) positive, and triple negative tumors. In addition, whole-genome gene expression profiling has enabled categorization of tumors into the intrinsic molecular subtypes luminal A, luminal B, HER2-enriched, basal-like and normal-like [31]. <p><text><SENT sid="30613" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we aimed to investigate the clinical relevance of TFPI and TF in breast cancer. The inter-relationships between TFPI and TF tagSNPs, tumor mRNA expression and plasma levels, and their association with breast cancer subtypes and survival were explored in either 152 treatment naive breast cancer patients or a merged 1881-sample breast tumor data set. </sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="30615" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="30616" pm="."><plain>Case subjects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30617" pm="."><plain>The study comprised 152 primary operable (cT1-cT2) female breast cancer patients (Table 1) enrolled between June 2008 and August 2010 at the Oslo University Hospital Ullevål, Oslo, and the Akershus University Hospital, Nordbyhagen, Norway. All subjects were of Scandinavian descent (mainly Norwegian, some Swedish or Danish). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30619" pm="."><plain>The cases were included at the time of primary surgery (mastectomy or lumpectomy), without receiving any pre-operative treatment. Blood samples were drawn immediately before surgery and tumor tissue was fresh frozen in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80°C after macroscopic evaluation of the surgical specimen by an experienced breast pathologist. None of the subjects were pregnant or received any anticoagulant- or hormone replacement therapy. The age average at the time of surgery and blood sampling was 56.0 (standard deviation (SD) 12.4) years. The Norwegian southeastern Regional Committee for Medical and Health Research Ethics approved the study protocols (approval number 1.2006.1607, amendment 1.2007.1125 for Ullevål patients and 429–04148 for Akershus patients) and all included women gave their written informed consent to participate.Table 1 Clinicopathological characteristics of the 152 breast cancer patients  Characteristic  Number (%)  Gender  Female152 (100) Male0 (0) Age  ≤5580 (52.6) &gt;5572 (47.4) Mean (±SD)56.0 (12.4) Tumor size (T-status)  T1 (0–20 mm)77 (50.7) T2 (20–50 mm)68 (44.7) T3 (&gt;50 mm)7 (4.6) (T2-T3)(75 (49.3)) Grade  G1 (well differentiated)21 (13.8) G2 (moderately differentiated)53 (34.9) (G1-G2)(74 (48.7)) G3 (poorly differentiated)78 (51.3) Estrogen receptor (ER) status  Negative35 (23.0) Positive117 (77.0) Progesterone receptor (PR) status  Negative51 (33.6) Positive101 (66.4) Human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2) status  Negative137 (90.1) Positive15 (9.9) Hormone receptor (HR) negative status (ER/PR negative)  Yes34 (22.4) No118 (77.6) Triple negative (TN) status (ER/PR/HER2 negative)  Yes29 (19.1) No123 (80.9) Lymph node (N) status  N0 (0 lymph nodes)98 (64.5) N1 (1–3 lymph nodes)40 (26.3) N2 (4–9 lymph nodes)11 (7.2) N3 (≥10 lymph nodes)3 (2.0) (N1-N2-N3)a (54 (35.5)) Molecular tumor subtypes (PAM50 signatures)  Basal25 (16.7) HER2 enriched15 (10.0) Luminal A63 (42.0) Luminal B39 (26.0) Normal-like8 (5.3) aLymph node positive group. </sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="30624" pm="."><plain>Clinicopathological characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30625" pm="."><plain>Clinicopathological data were retrieved from pathology reviews, and the following clinicopathological characteristics were included in the study; tumor size (T-status), lymph node (N) status, tumor grade (well/moderately/poorly differentiated), ER status, PR status, and HER2 status (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30626" pm="."><plain>T-status, N-status and tumor grade was specified according to national (NBCG, [32] guidelines and World Health Organization (WHO) recommendations. ER and PR status of the tumors were determined by IHC, and tumor cell nuclei were scored according to pathology guidelines. HER2 status was determined by IHC and/or by silver enhancement in situ hybridization (SISH) (Roche, Dual SISH HER-2) where a HER2 gene/centrosome 17 (CEP17) ratio of &gt; 2.2 defined HER2 positivity. </sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="30629" pm="."><plain>Tumor preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30630" pm="."><plain>Tumor tissue from each patient was cut into three pieces and two frozen sections were taken, Hematoxylin and Eosin (HE) stained, and evaluated for the presence of tumor cells. Afterwards, the three tumor pieces were combined and cut into small pieces. DNA and RNA isolation were thereafter performed from the mixed tumor tissue. </sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="30633" pm="."><plain>RNA isolation and TFPI and TF mRNA expression in tumor </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30634" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was isolated from the breast tumors with Trizol and quality controlled using the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer. 100 ng total RNA was applied to the SurePrint G3 Human GE 8x60K one-color microarrays (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30636" pm="."><plain>Scanning was performed with Agilent Scanner G2565A, using AgilentG3_GX_1Color as profile. Signals were extracted using FE v.10.7.3.1 and protocol GE1_107_Sep09 (Agilent Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30638" pm="."><plain>Probe-values were log2-transformed, and samples were quantile normalized and hospital-adjusted by subtracting from each probe value the median probe value among samples from the same hospital. In the present study, only expression ratio results obtained with TFPI and TF (F3) probes were used for further analysis (Additional file 1: Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30640" pm="."><plain>The three TFPI probes present on the microarray were specific for 1) the TFPIα isoform, 2) the TFPIβ isoform, and 3) total TFPI expression (TFPIα + TFPIβ). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30641" pm="."><plain>Four SNPs were observed in these probe regions (TFPI rs79927400, TFPI rs187580582, TF rs3917635, and TF rs191529173), however, according to the 1000 genome project [33] all were low frequent with a minor allele frequency (MAF) ≤1%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30642" pm="."><plain>A deletion (rs71653267) in the TF probe has been reported (dbSNP build 138), however, with unknown significance and frequency. No repetitive DNA elements were found within any of the probe regions. <p><text><SENT sid="30644" pm="."><plain>The microarray data have been submitted to the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database with accession number GSE58215. </sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="30645" pm="."><plain>PAM50 subtyping </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30646" pm="."><plain>The prediction analysis of microarray 50 (PAM50) subtype algorithm described by Parker et al. [34] was used to assign a subtype label to each sample. In short, a combined centroid was defined as a weighted average of the centroids for ER-negative and ER-positive samples, and each sample was centered by aligning the combined centroid with the centroid of the training data set provided in [34], achieved by subtracting the combined centroid from the expression vector of each sample and then adding the centroid of the training data set. Subtype labels (luminal A, luminal B, basal, HER2 enriched, and normal-like) were assigned by calculating the Spearman correlation between the expression vector of each individual sample and each of the five PAM50 centroids. The subtype with the highest correlation was selected. </sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="30650" pm="."><plain>DNA isolation from whole-blood and tumor material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30651" pm="."><plain>DNA from whole blood was either isolated on the BioRobot Universal with the QIAamp DNA Blood BioRobot MDx Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) and eluted in Qiagen buffer AE (10 mM Tris-Cl 0.5 mM EDTA; pH 9.0), or with the Gentra Autopure LS machine using the Puregene Genomic DNA purification Kit (Gentra Systems, Minneapolis, MN 55441 USA), or manually using the MasterPure TM DNA Purification Kit for Blood Version II (Epicentre® Biotechnologies, Madison, WI, USA). <p><text><SENT sid="30652" pm="."><plain>Fresh frozen tumor tissue was cut with scalpel, and one piece was used for DNA isolation using the Maxwell® 16 instrument (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) and the Maxwell® 16 tissue DNA Purification Kit (Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30653" pm="."><plain>DNA was isolated according to the manufacturer’s protocol. The isolation procedure is automated, starting with sample lysis and tissue homogenization, followed by bead isolation of DNA, and finally the washing steps. The DNA was eluted in TE buffer (pH 8.5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30656" pm="."><plain>DNA was stored at −20°C. DNA concentration and quality were measured using NanoDrop® ND-1000 (NanoDrop Technologies, Wilmington, DE, USA). </sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="30658" pm="."><plain>SNP selection, genotyping, and quality control </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30659" pm="."><plain>SNPs in the TFPI and TF gene regions were selected using a SNP tagging approach. The tagSNP selection was performed using the Tagger program [35] implemented in Haploview v. 4.2. and genotype data from the Caucasian population (Utah residents with ancestry from Northern and Western Europe) from the HapMap project release 27, phase III on NCBI B36 assembly, dbSNPb126. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30662" pm="."><plain>Using a MAF criterion of ≥5% and pairwise r2 ≥ 0.8 as a cut-off for proxies, sixteen tagSNPs in the TFPI gene and four tagSNPs in the TF gene were selected for genotyping. In addition, three SNPs in TFPI (rs5940, rs10931292 and rs10176633) and two SNPs in TF (rs958587 and rs3917643) with a previously suggested expression regulatory function were included. Thus the final SNP selection consisted of nineteen TFPI SNPs and six TF SNPs. However, one of the TFPI SNPs failed to design (rs8176500), leaving eighteen TFPI SNPs for genotyping. <p><text><SENT sid="30666" pm="."><plain>Germline SNPs were genotyped in whole blood (fourteen TFPI SNPs and six TF SNPs) or tumor tissue (four TFPI SNPs) using the iPLEX Gold massarray platform (Sequenom) at the Centre for Integrative Genetics, Norwegian University of Life Sciences, Ås, Norway, or the Affymetrix® Genome-Wide Human SNP Array 6.0 at AROS Applied Biotechnology AS, Aarhus, Denmark, respectively. Due to the tumor genome being prone to mutational and copy number changes, including loss of heterozygosity (LOH), the tumor-derived SNP genotypes may occasionally deviate from the germline genotypes. Therefore, the tumor-derived SNP data were processed to deduce germline SNPs. With access to blood-derived germline genotype data for all patients on a set of 22 SNPs (rs8176548, rs3917615, rs696619, rs2227607, rs2227589, rs12488200, rs9332542, rs9332618, rs6012, rs4524, rs491098, rs421766, rs4149762, rs4149674, rs473598, rs3211752, rs2227426, rs2070022, rs153311, rs2227750, rs37246, rs2070852) present on the Human SNP Array 6.0, we verified a convergence of 93.8% between the deduced germline SNPs (from tumor) and the true germline SNPs (from blood). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30670" pm="."><plain>Due to this fairly high genotype agreement, we concluded that the tumor-derived SNPs included in this study (n = 4, indicated in Additional file 2: Table S2) could be considered as germline SNPs. <p><text><SENT sid="30671" pm="."><plain>All SNPs were in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (significance threshold P &lt; 0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30672" pm="."><plain>Genotyping was successful for ≥50% of the SNPs in all individuals. Three TFPI SNPs had genotyping call rates &lt;97% (rs2041778, rs10931292 and rs8176508), and one TFPI SNP was monomorphic (rs10176633). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30674" pm="."><plain>After removal of these four SNPs, fourteen TFPI SNPs (Additional file 2: Table S2 and Additional file 3: Figure S1) and six TF SNPs (Additional file 2: Table S2) remained for further analysis. </sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="30675" pm="."><plain>Blood sampling and TFPI/TF protein levels in plasma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30676" pm="."><plain>Venous blood samples were collected in Vacutainer® vacuum tubes (Becton-Dickinson, Plymouth, UK) containing 0.5 mL buffered sodium citrate (0.129 mol/L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30677" pm="."><plain>Whole blood was centrifuged for 15 min at 2000 g at room temperature within 1 hour to prepare platelet poor plasma, and aliquots were stored at −70°C until analyzed. TFPI protein levels in plasma were determined using the commercial Free and Total TFPI ELISA kits (Asserachrom®, Diagnostica Stago, Asnière, France), while the Zymutest Tissue Factor full-length (RK035A, Hyphen BioMed, Neuville-Sur-Oise, France) was used to measure TF protein. The manufacturers’ recommended protocols were followed. </sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="30680" pm="."><plain>Statistical methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30681" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyzes were performed using SPSS (version 21.0; SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA), PLINK v.1.07 [36], and R 3.1.0 [37]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30682" pm="."><plain>Associations between continuous-valued expression levels were assessed with Pearson correlation or Spearman rank correlation. The relation between SNP genotypes and expression levels was investigated by linear regression. Genotypes were treated as ordinal variables (0, 1 or 2 copies of the minor allele), thus assuming potential allele-dosage effects to be linear. Regression coefficients are denoted B and the correlation coefficients are denoted r. <p><text><SENT sid="30686" pm="."><plain>For associations between expression levels and clinicopathological characteristics, heatmaps were constructed in R. Missing value imputation of the gene expression data was performed with LSimpute [38] using the row mean method. Two-group comparisons of expression levels were performed using the t-test or the Mann–Whitney U test as appropriate. One-way ANOVA or Kruskal-Wallis test was used for multi-group comparisons. Associations between SNPs and binary clinicopathological characteristics were examined using logistic regression under the additive risk model, with the clinicopathological variable(s) as the dependent variable and genotype(s) (coded 0, 1, 2 for each extra risk allele) as the categorical independent variable. Risk alleles were defined as the alleles being more prevalent among the non-reference category, thus consequently obtaining positive odds ratios (ORs &gt;1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30692" pm="."><plain>ORs with corresponding 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were reported. <p><text><SENT sid="30693" pm="."><plain>Independence between SNPs was tested by conditional analysis in PLINK, where the allelic dosage for a given SNP was added as a covariate in a logistic regression model. Pairwise SNP dependencies exist if individual effects disappear when conditioned on the other SNP. The expectation–maximization (EM) algorithm was used to estimate haplotype frequencies, and haplotype-based association analysis was conducted using logistic regression (additive model) for associations with clinicopathological variables and linear regression for associations with expression levels. Haploview v. 4.2 was used for creating linkage disequilibrium (LD) plots. False discovery rate (FDR, [39]) was used to account for multiple testing, and tests with P &lt; 0.05 and FDR &lt; 0.20 were reported. </sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="30699" pm="."><plain>Bioinformatic analysis using the Gene expression based Outcome for Breast cancer Online (GOBO) database </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30700" pm="."><plain>The GOBO database is a web-based tool that enables a variety of analyzes of gene expression data in a merged 1881-sample breast tumor data set of 11 different publicly available datasets, all generated on Affymetrix U133A microarrays [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30701" pm="."><plain>Four TFPI specific probe sets (one for total TFPI (α + β), two for TFPIα, one for TFPIβ) and one probe set for TF gene expression were identified (Additional file 4: Table S3). <p><text><SENT sid="30702" pm="."><plain>Using the Gene Set Analysis application, the TFPI and TF gene expressions were dichotomized to levels above the median (high expression) or below the median (low expression) before Kaplan-Meier plots were created and univariate analyzes (log-rank) were performed to predict 10-year censored overall and relapse free survival. This was conducted in the complete 1881-sample merged clinical data set (hereafter termed “all tumors”) as well as in clinical subgroups. Multivariate Cox proportional hazards regression analyzes were carried out to account for possible survival effects of the following covariates; tumor size, age, histological tumor grade, lymph node status and ER-status. In addition, GOBO was used to assess the distribution of TFPI and TF gene expressions across clinical subgroups. </sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="30706" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="30707" pm="."><plain>TFPI and TF expression in breast cancer subtypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30708" pm="."><plain>First, we investigated the clinical relevance of TFPI or TF mRNA expression in breast tumors and TFPI or TF plasma concentrations. Patients were stratified according to clinicopathological tumor characteristics as defined in Table 2, with median expression levels for each group. Significant differences in mRNA expression or protein levels are illustrated by heatmaps (Additional file 5: Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30711" pm="."><plain>TFPI or TF mRNA expression in breast tumors and plasma concentrations were then compared between the five molecular tumor subtypes (Figures 1 and 2, respectively).Table 2 TFPI and TF tumor mRNA expression across clinicopathological breast cancer subtypes  mRNA expression (tumor)  Protein levels (plasma)  Characteristic  Groups  Total TFPI (α + β)  P  TFPIα  P  TFPIβ  P  TF  P  Total TFPI  P  Free TFPI  P  TF  P T-statusT1−0.1460.054−0.1350.257−0.0840.201−0.0230.65272.01 0.013 10.820.9974.140.125T2-T30.0850.0180.0600.05465.0210.824.66GradeG1-G2−0.0220.850−0.0050.424−0.0330.7430.271 0.003 71.040.08210.660.6824.630.557G3−0.045−0.1130.004−0.22966.1210.974.14N-statusNegative−0.1090.091−0.1360.127−0.0820.1040.0050.88169.930.18310.770.8694.950.282Positive0.1040.0780.1100.03266.0010.904.14ER statusPositive−0.0670.317−0.0820.557−0.0560.1830.0010.78469.420.24010.910.6714.420.409PR statusNegative0.0760.0110.1230.05765.4410.525.28Positive−0.131 0.021 −0.1450.075−0.112 0.014 0.0850.24469.810.19511.190.1754.320.246HER2-statusNegative0.1610.1080.182−0.12765.9210.085.04Negative−0.0720.054−0.1010.073−0.0410.1540.0040.73168.450.89310.680.2874.470.428Positive0.3130.3010.2280.10369.0912.054.78HR statusYes0.0760.3260.0070.5870.1140.2210.0160.99164.780.16110.410.5685.260.470No−0.066−0.080−0.0520.01469.5710.944.47Triple-negative statusYes−0.0510.886−0.1100.7180.0410.635−0.1580.32663.210.07210.060.3455.230.969No−0.029−0.048−0.0270.05569.7310.994.57Median values for TFPI and TF mRNA expression in tumors and protein levels in plasma according to clinically defined groups. Corresponding P-values (unadjusted) are shown. Significant P-values in bold. TFPI, tissue factor pathway inhibitor; TF, tissue factor; HER2, human epidermal growth factor receptor 2.Abbreviations: T, tumor; G, grade; N, node; ER, estrogen receptor; PR, progesterone receptor; HR, hormone receptor.Figure 1 Tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) and tissue factor (TF) mRNA expression across molecular breast cancer subtypes. Box and whisker plot showing the distribution of log2-transformed total TFPI (α + β), TFPIα, and TFPIβ (A), and TF tumor mRNA expression (B) across the following intrinsic molecular subtypes of 150 of the 152 breast cancer patients; basal (n = 25), human epidermal growth factor 2 (HER2)-enriched (n = 15), luminal A (n = 63), luminal B (n = 39) and normal-like (n = 8). P-values for multi-group comparison are indicated.Figure 2 Tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) and tissue factor (TF) plasma levels across molecular breast cancer subtypes. Box and whisker plot showing the distribution of plasma levels of total TFPI and free TFPI (A) and TF (B) across the following intrinsic molecular subtypes of 148 of the 152 breast cancer patients; basal (n = 24), human epidermal growth factor 2 (HER2) HER2-enriched (n = 15), luminal A (n = 62), luminal B (n = 39) and normal-like (n = 8). P-values for multi-group comparison are indicated. <p><text><SENT sid="30715" pm="."><plain>Total TFPI (α + β) mRNA expression was increased in patients with PR-negative tumors (P = 0.021), and in patients with HER2-positive tumors, larger tumor sizes, and positive lymph nodes, although power was lacking to achieve statistical significance. Expression of the TFPIα isoform was higher in PR-negative and HER2-positive patients, whereas TFPIβ was significantly higher only in PR-negative patients (P = 0.014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30717" pm="."><plain>No differences in TFPI mRNA expression were observed between the stratified groups for grade, ER status, HR status, or triple-negative status (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30718" pm="."><plain>Moreover, total TFPI (α + β), TFPIα and TFPIβ expression levels were differentially distributed among the five molecular breast cancer subtypes; with higher expression in the HER2-enriched and the normal-like group, and lower in luminal B tumors (Figure 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30719" pm="."><plain>These observations were mainly supported by equivalent analyses of the merged breast cancer dataset in GOBO (Additional file 6: Figure S3). <p><text><SENT sid="30720" pm="."><plain>TF mRNA expression was significantly decreased in patients with grade-3 tumors compared with patients with grade 1 or 2 (P = 0.003) (Table 2), and this was validated by gene expression pattern analysis of the merged breast cancer dataset (Additional file 7: Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30721" pm="."><plain>When stratified by molecular subtypes, TF mRNA expression was higher in luminal A and the normal-like tumors, and lowest in luminal B tumors (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30722" pm="."><plain>Similar results were obtained using the merged breast cancer dataset (Additional file 6: Figure S3). <p><text><SENT sid="30723" pm="."><plain>In plasma, antigen levels of free TFPI and TF were similar between all stratified clinical groups, whereas total TFPI was decreased in patients with larger tumors (P = 0.013), and patients with grade-3 or triple-negative tumors (not significant) (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30724" pm="."><plain>Total TFPI or free TFPI (Figure 2A), and TF plasma levels (Figure 2B) were not significantly different across molecular subtypes. <p><text><SENT sid="30725" pm="."><plain>As expected, the total TFPI (α + β), TFPIα and TFPIβ mRNA expression levels in breast tumors were highly correlated (r = 0.82 to 0.91, P &lt;0.001), and did also correlate significantly to TF expression (r = 0.37-0.50, P &lt;0.001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30726" pm="."><plain>In plasma, total TFPI protein levels correlated significantly to free TFPI (r = 0.36, P &lt;0.001) and TF (ρ = 0.25, P = 0.002), whereas no correlation was found between free TFPI and TF. No significant correlation between protein levels (in plasma) and mRNA expression (in tumors) was found for TFPI or TF. </sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="30728" pm="."><plain>Association between SNPs in TFPI and TF and breast cancer subtypes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30729" pm="."><plain>Next, we evaluated if TFPI or TF SNPs (Additional file 2: Table S2) were associated with any clinicopathological characteristics and molecular tumor subtypes. Four TFPI SNPs (rs8176541, rs3213739, rs8176479, and rs2192824) were associated with triple-negative status (Table 3) as well as ER status and HR status (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30731" pm="."><plain>Strong pairwise LD existed (Additional file 3: Figure S1), and conditional association analysis supported SNP dependency (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30732" pm="."><plain>Haplotype-based analysis showed that the common G-G-C-T haplotype (frequency 0.41) formed by the four SNPs (rs8176541-rs3213739-rs8176479-rs2192824) showed an OR of 2.4 (P = 0.004) in triple-negative patients (Table 3).Table 3 Significant association between TFPI single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and clinicopathological characteristics and molecular subtypes  Characteristic  SNP  Risk allele  Odds ratio  95% CI  P  False discovery rate  T status T1ReferenceReferenceReferenceReferenceT2 to T3rs10153820A3.141.44, 6.860.0040.056 TN status (ER-/PR-/HER2-negative)NoReferenceReferenceReferenceReferenceYesrs8176541a G2.621.11, 5.350.0260.092rs3213739a G2.581.34, 4.990.0050.033rs8176479a C3.101.24, 7.720.0150.071rs2192824a T2.441.39, 4.930.0020.033 N status PositiveReferenceReferenceReferenceReferenceNegativers10179730G3.341.42, 7.890.0060.083 Basal tumor subtype Non-basalReferenceReferenceReferenceReferenceBasalrs3213739a G2.231.15, 4.340.0180.107rs8176479a C2.791.12, 6.960.0280.107rs2192824a T2.411.24, 4.650.0090.107rs10187622a C5.201.17, 23.200.0310.107 Luminal B tumor subtype Non-luminal BReferenceReferenceReferenceReferenceLuminal Brs16829086a T2.091.03, 4.250.0410.191rs10179730a G3.531.47, 8.460.0050.066rs10187622a T2.731.24, 6.030.0130.091 Normal-like tumor subtype Non-normal-likeReferenceReferenceReferenceReferenceNormal-likers5940T22.174.43, 110.80.00020.003 aSNPs representing a haplotype effect. SNPs are listed by ascending chromosome positions. TFPI, tissue factor pathway inhibitor; ER, estrogen receptor; PR, progesterone receptor; HER2, human epidermal growth factor 2. <p><text><SENT sid="30735" pm="."><plain>The G-C-T-C haplotype (frequency 0.42) formed by the four SNPs (rs3213739-rs8176479-rs2192824-rs10187622) was associated with the basal tumor subtype with OR 2.3 (P = 0.011) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30736" pm="."><plain>The three-SNP haplotype T-G-T (rs16829086-rs10179730-rs10187622) was associated with the luminal B subtype (OR 3.5, P = 0.005, frequency 0.09), and rs5940 was associated with the normal-like subtype (OR 22.2, P = 0.0002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30737" pm="."><plain>No associations between TFPI SNPs and tumor grade, PR-status, HER2 status, the HER2-enriched subtype or the luminal A subtype were observed. TF SNPs did not associate with any of the clinicopathological characteristics or molecular tumor subtypes herein evaluated (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30738" pm="."><plain>Age did not correlate to any of the SNP genotypes and adjusting for age did not affect the associations (data not shown). </sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="30739" pm="."><plain>Associations between SNPs and TFPI and TF expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30740" pm="."><plain>Further, we aimed to explore whether the TFPI or the TF SNPs had any transcriptional or translational regulatory effects on the TFPI or TF mRNA expression in the breast tumors, or on the protein levels in plasma, respectively. A total of six intronic TFPI SNPs correlated to TFPIβ mRNA expression (Table 4), and accompanied by conditional association analysis, the LD pattern between the six SNPs encouraged haplotype analysis. The T-A-C-C-T-C haplotype (frequency 0.03), made up of the minor alleles of the six SNPs (rs3213739-rs8176479-rs2192824-rs12613071-rs2192825-rs7594359 correlated positively to TFPIβ mRNA (B = 0.76, r = 0.23, P = 0.004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30743" pm="."><plain>Among these six SNPs, three also correlated to total TFPI (α + β) mRNA expression (rs2192824-rs12613071-rs7594359) with an inverse correlation of r = −0.22 (B = −0.25, P = 0.008) for the T-T-T haplotype (frequency 0.40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30744" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the minor allele T-T haplotype formed by two of these SNPs (rs2192824-rs7594359) correlated inversely to TFPIα mRNA expression with r = −0.23 (B = −0.29, P = 0.004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30745" pm="."><plain>No significant correlation between TF SNPs and TF mRNA expression was observed (P &gt;0.05, data not shown).Table 4 Significant correlations between TFPI single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and TFPI mRNA expression in breast tumors  Probe  SNP  Region  Alleles a  Minor allele frequency  Beta  r  P  False discovery rate TFPIαrs2192824b IntronicC:T0.490−0.209−0.1800.0290.200TFPIαrs7594359b IntronicC:T0.483−0.219−0.1840.0250.200TFPIβrs3213739b IntronicG:T0.4170.1870.2130.0100.032TFPIβrs8176479b IntronicC:A0.2380.1840.1920.0210.049TFPIβrs2192824b IntronicC:T0.490−0.267−0.2730.0010.011TFPIβrs12613071b IntronicT:C0.1580.2840.2080.0110.032TFPIβrs2192825b IntronicT:C0.466−0.251−0.2490.0020.012TFPIβrs7594359b IntronicC:T0.483−0.248−0.2470.0020.012TFPIα + βrs2192824b IntronicC:T0.490−0.168−0.1610.0500.187TFPIα + βrs12613071b IntronicT:C0.1580.2380.1640.0480.187TFPIα + βrs7594359b IntronicC:T0.483−0.190−0.1780.0300.187 aMajor:minor. bSNPs representing a haplotype effect. mRNA expression was assayed by the Agilent Human V2 Gene Expression 8x60k array, and probes for tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI)α, TFPIβ and total TFPI (TFPIα + β) mRNA were analyzed. Alleles for the positive DNA strand (UCSC annotated) are shown, and SNPs are listed by ascending chromosome positions. <p><text><SENT sid="30747" pm="."><plain>Eight TFPI SNPs were found to be correlated to total TFPI protein levels in patient plasma (Table 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30748" pm="."><plain>The A-T-A-C-T-A-C-G haplotype composed of these eight SNPs (rs8176541-rs3213739-rs8176479-rs2192824-rs2192825-rs16829088-rs7594359-rs10153820) represented a common haplotype (frequency 0.19) with quite strong correlation to total TFPI protein; r = 0.481 (B = 14.62, P = 6.35 × 10−10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30749" pm="."><plain>No correlation between TFPI SNPs and free TFPI protein, or between TF SNPs and TF protein in plasma was observed (P &gt;0.05, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30750" pm="."><plain>Adjusting for age had no effect on the correlation (data not shown).Table 5 Significant correlations between TFPI single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and total TFPI protein levels in plasma  Protein  SNP  Region  Alleles a  Minor allele frequency  Beta  r  P  False discovery rate Total TFPIrs8176541b IntronicG:A0.28315.640.5717.69 × 10−14 1.08 × 10−12 Total TFPIrs3213739b IntronicG:T0.41711.350.4885.38 × 10−10 3.77 × 10−9 Total TFPIrs8176479b IntronicC:A0.23812.220.4801.20 × 10−9 5.62 × 10−9 Total TFPIrs2192824b IntronicC:T0.490−9.88−0.4043.81 × 10−7 1.07 × 106 Total TFPIrs2192825b IntronicT:C0.466−7.55−0.3012.40 × 10−4 5.30 × 10−4 Total TFPIrs16829088b IntronicG:A0.25011.230.4241.00 × 10−7 3.51 × 10−7 Total TFPIrs7594359b IntronicC:T0.483−6.90−0.2756.90 × 10−4 0.001Total TFPIrs10153820b Near 5UTRG:A0.125−7.79−0.2150.0090.016 aMajor:minor. bSNPs representing a haplotype effect for total tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30751" pm="."><plain>Alleles for the positive DNA strand (UCSC annotated) are shown. </sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="30752" pm="."><plain>TFPI and TF tumor mRNA expression and survival </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30753" pm="."><plain>Survival data were not available for our patient cohort, however, access to a merged breast cancer dataset from GOBO allowed us to investigate possible associations between TFPI or TF gene expression and outcome. Low expression of total TFPI (α + β) showed significant association with decreased overall survival when considering all breast cancer subtypes together (all tumors) (P = 0.015), and the effect was even more profound in the high-proliferative poor outcome classes; HER2-enriched (P = 0.004) and lymph node-positive cancers (P = 8*10−5) (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30755" pm="."><plain>A survival effect was also observed for normal-like tumors (P = 0.040). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30756" pm="."><plain>Similarly, low expression of TFPIα and TFPIβ were predictive of reduced overall survival in all tumors (P = 0.007 and 0.005), lymph node-positive (P = 0.006 and 0.034), grade-2 (P = 0.008 and 0.001), ER-positive (P = 0.022 and 0.0007), and HER2-enriched tumors (P = 0.097 (not significant) and 0.007) (Figure 3B and C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30757" pm="."><plain>Similar patterns were observed for relapse-free survival (Additional file 8: Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30758" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, multivariate hazard ratio analysis of all tumors, showed that tumor size and lymph node status were highly associated with overall survival (P &lt;0.00001) and abolished the effect of low TFPI expression (P &gt;0.05) (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30759" pm="."><plain>This result implied that the survival effect of TFPI expression involves lymph node metastasis and proliferation (reflected by tumor size), thus providing a possible explanation for why low TFPI expression had an even greater impact to the subgroup-stratified survival analysis, compared to analysis of all tumors (Figure 3A-C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30760" pm="."><plain>This was further demonstrated by multivariate analyses in the lymph node-positive group. This covariate-adjusted analysis showed that low total TFPI (α + β) expression was a prognostic indicator for overall survival, independent of the strong association with tumor size (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30762" pm="."><plain>Notably, TF expression rates did not correlate with overall survival in all tumors (Figure 3D) or in any of the clinical subgroups, nor with relapse-free survival (data not shown).Figure 3 Overall survival in breast cancer patients stratified by tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) and tissue factor (TF) expression in tumors. Kaplan-Meier survival curve with overall survival (OS) with 10-year censoring as endpoint, stratified according to high (above the median) and low (below median) total TFPI (α + β) gene expression levels (A), TFPIαa gene expression levels (B), TFPIβ gene expression levels (C), and TF gene expression levels (D), in all tumors and selected clinical subgroups in which survival data were available. Analyses were performed using the Gene expression based Outcome for Breast cancer Online (GOBO) database, and the log-rank test was used to calculate P-values. aFor TFPIα expression results were obtained by merging the two available probe sets, as specified in Additional file 4: Table S3.Figure 4 Multivariate survival analysis in breast cancer patients stratified by tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) and tissue factor (TF) expression in tumors. Multivariate survival analysis derived from the Gene expression based Outcome for Breast cancer Online (GOBO) database of (A) total TFPI (α + β), TFPIα, and TFPIβ tumor expression in all tumors, and (B) total TFPI (α + β) tumor expression in the lymph node-positive group. Tumor size, age, histological tumor grade, lymph node statusa and estrogen receptor (ER) status were included as covariates. Hazard ratios, 95% CIs and corresponding P-values are specified for each covariate. aOmitted from the analysis of the lymph node-positive group. </sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec18" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="30766" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30767" pm="."><plain>TF and TFPI exert opposing effects in coagulation, but also in cancer biology; although TF seems to be a tumor-promoting factor, TFPI exerts tumor suppressor activities. The mechanisms in which these actions take place, however, are not fully elucidated. <p><text><SENT sid="30769" pm="."><plain>Here, we report several indications that TFPI have clinical significance in breast cancer. First, mRNA expression of both total TFPI (α + β) and TFPIβ were significantly associated with PR negativity. Our study lacked power to detect an association with ER negativity due to a smaller number of ER-negative (n = 35) than PR-negative (n = 51) patients. However, PR-negativity is a surrogate marker of a non-functioning ER pathway [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30773" pm="."><plain>There was also a tendency towards increased mRNA expression of either total TFPI (α + β) or TFPIα or TFPIβ in highly proliferative and poor-outcome groups, such as those with larger tumors and HER2 positivity, in keeping with the survival analysis discussed later. In accordance with the IHC determination of HER2 status, enhanced TFPI expression was evident also in the HER2-enriched molecular subgroup (in the merged dataset). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30775" pm="."><plain>Moreover, TFPI expression tended to be increased in tumors of patients with lymph node metastases, supporting the results and the proposal of Sierko et al. that TFPI localized in regional lymph nodes may indicate a role for TFPI in lymphatic spread [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30776" pm="."><plain>Additionally, tumor-expressed TFPI and TF were positively correlated, which is in line with our previous findings in breast cancer cell lines that TFPI expression follows TF expression and the aggressive basal-like tumor subtype [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30777" pm="."><plain>Stavik et al. proposed a role for TFPI in cancer progression as they showed that overexpression of TFPIα or TFPIβ in breast cancer cell lines affected expression of genes involved in cancer-related cellular functions (for example, proliferation, migration, and invasion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30778" pm="."><plain>Additionally, they revealed that the gene signatures following overexpression of either TFPI isoform were associated with tumor grade and ER status, and that TFPIα expression correlated with tumor size [42]. <p><text><SENT sid="30779" pm="."><plain>Taken together, we hypothesize that TFPI is a marker of more aggressive tumors while at the same time being a tumor suppressor. Paradoxical as it may seem, these two hypotheses are not mutually exclusive. This is because TFPI has previously been recognized as a tumor suppressor in experimental studies [16-21], and because higher TFPI expression in tumors was associated with increased survival in the present study. TFPI expression in tumors may then serve to oppose and protect against tumor progression. TFPI may therefore represent a prognostic marker, but also an anti-cancer candidate with potential for being translated into the clinic. <p><text><SENT sid="30784" pm="."><plain>Contrasting the observations we made in tumors, the plasma levels of total TFPI tended to be lower in larger tumors, triple-negative tumors, and grade-3 tumors. These results comply with the lack of correlation between TFPI tumor expression and TFPI plasma levels, suggesting that the systemic plasma concentrations of TFPI were not influenced by or derived from the tumor cells and thereby cannot predict plasma levels of TFPI. Yet, no directly comparable data are available, but Lindahl et al. reported that TFPI activity in plasma increased in parallel with gastrointestinal cancer progression [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30787" pm="."><plain>Although we measured levels of TFPI instead of activity, this suggests that the behavior of plasma TFPI proceeds differently in different cancers. Later, Iversen et al. reported that the median TFPI activity levels were within the normal range in breast cancer. These authors also observed that TFPI activity was higher in metastatic cancer patients [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30790" pm="."><plain>In our study none of the patients had developed distant metastases at the time of inclusion. <p><text><SENT sid="30791" pm="."><plain>The complexity of the different forms of circulating TFPI (that is, full-length TFPI, C-terminal truncated, and lipid-bound) [15] was illustrated, as free TFPI, unlike total TFPI, could not be designated as having any clinical relevance. In line with this, no differences in free TFPI plasma levels were detected between breast cancer patients and controls in our preceding study [45]. <p><text><SENT sid="30793" pm="."><plain>We identified several TFPI SNPs (with haplotype effects) that were more frequent in specific clinicopathological tumor characteristics, such as tumor size, triple-negative status and lymph node status, as well as basal and luminal B tumor subtypes. Although the precise role for these SNP associations is still to be elucidated, this study pinpoints the importance of focusing on breast cancer heterogeneity, as in a recent study we found that the frequencies of TFPI SNPs in a group of breast cancer patients with all subtypes combined (n = 366), were no different from healthy control subjects [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30795" pm="."><plain>Some of the SNPs that followed distinct clinical groups (rs3213739, rs8176479, rs2192824, rs8176541 and rs10153820) also correlated with total TFPI (α + β), TFPIα or TFPIβ tumor mRNA expression, or total TFPI plasma levels. Certain SNPs with a regulatory effect on total TFPI plasma levels also associated with triple-negative status (rs8176541, rs3213739, rs8176479 and rs2192824) and tumor size (rs10153820), thereby providing a possible mechanistic rationale for why total TFPI levels were decreased in patients with triple-negative and larger tumors. However, the exact mechanism(s) by which these SNPs regulate TFPI protein levels demand experimental verification. Most SNPs in this study were positioned in introns, but many of them were in strong LD with SNPs located in 3′ UTR and 5′ UTR (not shown), which are regions known to have potential influence on gene expression. <p><text><SENT sid="30799" pm="."><plain>The minor allele of rs10153820 (−399C/T) was associated with decreased total TFPI plasma levels, and the minor allele of rs8176541, a perfect predictor of rs8176592 (−33 T/C) (pairwise LD r2 = 1.00), correlated to higher total TFPI plasma levels. This result is in line with another study that genotyped rs8176592 [46], whilst another study failed to show an effect of this SNP on total TFPI plasma levels [29]. <p><text><SENT sid="30801" pm="."><plain>In light of the abundant TF expression in cancers [6-8,10] and involvement in angiogenesis, metastasis and tumor growth [11-14], the virtual absence of clinical significance of TF tumor mRNA expression or plasma levels, or TF genetic polymorphisms was not anticipated, that is, with the exception of a reverse association between TF mRNA tumor expression and tumor grade. This result is in conflict with Kocatürk et al. who found positive correlation between TF and grade [6], but in agreement with the merged GOBO breast cancer dataset in this study. We could hypothesize that tumor expressed TF may be more important in the earlier phases of malignant transformation, as suggested in pancreatic cancer [47]. <p><text><SENT sid="30804" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the experimental evidence that points to TF as an important contributor in tumor progression, studies investigating the clinical relevance of tissue factor in breast cancer patients have generated less conclusive results. Adding to the hypothesis that a procoagulant state extends beyond the risk of venous thromobosis (VT), Hernández et al. reported that increased TF plasma levels and activity in a number of cancers, amongst them breast cancer, was indicative of worse prognosis, but not of VT [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30806" pm="."><plain>Also Ueno et al. demonstrated that TF plasma levels were elevated in breast cancer patients compared to controls. However, neither TF plasma levels nor tumor expression were found related to clinical stage, HR status or lymph-node metastasis [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30808" pm="."><plain>Yet another study failed to detect any correlation between breast tumor-expressed TF and HR status, node status, grade or tumor size [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30809" pm="."><plain>Kocatürk et al., found that both flTF and alternatively spliced TF (asTF) [GenBank:NM_001178096] were associated with increasing tumor grade, while asTF was also associated with increasing breast tumor size [6], suggesting that the clinical significance of asTF is at least as important as that of flTF. Consequently, future studies addressing TF in relation to cancer should include the different forms of TF (that is, asTF and flTF [6,49], cryptic versus active TF [50], and phosphorylated TF [10]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30811" pm="."><plain>Also noteworthy; methodological discrepancies in measuring TF may to some extent account for the conflicting results among studies addressing TF in cancer (for example, mRNA versus protein and use of different TF detection antibodies). <p><text><SENT sid="30812" pm="."><plain>In clinical cancer research, death is a common endpoint of interest. Because survival data were not available for the patients included in our study, we made use of a merged clinical dataset to investigate the effect of TFPI and TF tumor expression on survival among breast cancer patients. No difference in overall or relapse-free survival was observed between patients with high or low levels of TF. This is somehow contradictory to the study of Ueno et al. who found that breast cancer patients with TF-positive tumors were associated with reduced overall survival, however, not with disease-free survival [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30816" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, no previous studies have described survival data directly in relation to tumor expressed TFPI, but Stavik et al. reported that the gene expression signature resulting from TFPIβ overexpression correlated with relapse-free survival in breast cancer [42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30817" pm="."><plain>We now report that breast cancer patients with low tumor expression of both isoforms of TFPI had worse outcome in terms of both overall- and relapse free survival compared to patients with higher TFPI expression. Therefore, it seems that increased tumor expression of TFPI may be beneficial in breast cancer. </sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec19" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="30819" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="30820" pm="."><plain>Here we provide results suggesting that TFPI represents a promising marker of breast cancer progression and prognosis. This was especially evident in clinically relevant groups such as lymph node-positive patients. The clinical relevance of expression and genetic variants of TFPI in breast cancer appeared distinct from that of TF. Together with the previously demonstrated tumor suppressor effects of TFPI, the beneficial survival effect of tumor-expressed TFPI highlights the potential of TFPI as a candidate in cancer therapy, and this clearly deserves further investigation for possible translation to clinical practice. </sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="APPENDIX"><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec20"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1: Table S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30824" pm="."><plain>Probes from the Agilent Human V2 Gene Expression 8x60k array in which results were used in the study. SNPs occurring in probes are shown in bold. </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2: Table S2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30826" pm="."><plain>All analyzed single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) in tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) and tissue factor (TF) genes. Alleles for the positive strand are shown (UCSC-annotated). </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM3_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM3"><label>Additional file 3: Figure S1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30828" pm="."><plain>Linkage disequilibrium (LD) map of all fourteen TFPI SNPs included in the study. Dʹ values are shown. </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM4_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM4"><label>Additional file 4: Table S3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30830" pm="."><plain>Probe set regions for the Affymetrix U133A microarray used in the study. </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM5_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM5"><label>Additional file 5: Figure S2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30831" pm="."><plain>Expression heatmaps for A) total TFPI (α + β), TFPIβ and TF mRNA expression in breast tumors differentiated by clinically relevant subgroups of PR-status (PR negative and PR positive) and tumor grade (G1 + 2 and G3), and B) plasma levels of total TFPI according to T-status (T1 and T2 + T3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30832" pm="."><plain>The color key is indicated. </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM6_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM6"><label>Additional file 6: Figure S3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30833" pm="."><plain>Box and Whiskers plot showing the distribution of log2 transformed total TFPI (α + β), TFPIα, and TFPIβ and TF tumor mRNA expression across the following PAM50 subtype signatures of 150* breast cancer patients; basal (n = 304/357), HER2 enriched (n = 240/152), luminal A (n = 465/482), luminal B (n = 471/289) and normal-like (n = 304/257). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30834" pm="."><plain>Data were derived from the GOBO database. P-values for ANOVA testing are indicated. </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM7_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM7"><label>Additional file 7: Figure S4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30835" pm="."><plain>Box and Whiskers plot showing the distribution of TF gene expression for tumor samples across the three classes of histological grade. Expression rates are analyzed by Affymetrix Human Genome U133A arrays and data were derived from all tumors of the GOBO database. </caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13058_2015_548_MOESM8_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM8"><label>Additional file 8: Figure S5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="30837" pm="."><plain>Kaplan-Meier survival curve with relapse-free survival (RFS) with 10-year censoring as the endpoint, stratified according to high (above the median) and low (below median) total tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) (α + β) gene expression levels (A), TFPIα a gene expression levels (B), and TFPIβ gene expression levels (C), in all tumors and selected clinical subgroups in which survival data were available. Analyses were performed using the Gene expression based Outcome for Breast cancer Online (GOBO) database, and the log-rank test was used to calculate P-values. aFor TFPIα expression results were obtained by merging the two available probe sets, as specified in Additional file 4: Table S3. </caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbrevations</title><def-list><def-item><term>asTF</term><def><p>alternatively spliced tissue factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ANOVA</term><def><p>analysis of variance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ELISA</term><def><p>enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FDR</term><def><p>false discovery rate</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GOBO</term><def><p>Gene expression based Outcome for Breast cancer Online</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ER</term><def><p>estrogen receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HE</term><def><p>hematoxylin and eosin</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HER2</term><def><p>human epidermal growth factor receptor 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HR</term><def><p>hormone receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IHC</term><def><p>immunohistochemistry</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LD</term><def><p>linkage disequilibrium</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAF</term><def><p>minor allele frequency</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OR</term><def><p>odds ratio</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PR</term><def><p>progesterone receptor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PAM50</term><def><p>prediction analysis of microarray 50</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SNP</term><def><p>single nucleotide polymorphism</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TF</term><def><p>tissue factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFPI</term><def><p>tissue factor pathway inhibitor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TN</term><def><p>triple negative</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>UTR</term><def><p>untranslated region</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>VT</term><def><p>venous thromobosis</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="30839" pm="."><plain>Competing interests <p><text><SENT sid="30840" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="30841" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions <p><text><SENT sid="30842" pm="."><plain>NI, PMS, and MT conceived and designed the study. HKMV, KKS, SJ, OCL, RK, TS, VK, ALBD, and NI participated in acquisition of the data. MT analyzed the data and drafted the manuscript. HKMV, KKS, FK, and OCL made substantial contributions to the data analyzes. MT, HKMV, FK, ALBD, PMS, NI interpreted the data. All authors critically revised the manuscript for important intellectual content and approved the final version of the manuscript to be published, and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work, ensuring that the accuracy or integrity of the work are appropriately investigated and resolved. </fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgement</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="30848" pm="."><plain>We would like to thank Oslo Breast Cancer Consortium (OSBREAC) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ous-research.no/kgjebsen/">http://ous-research.no/kgjebsen/</ext-link>) for providing patient samples, and Eldri U Due for tumor preparation and DNA isolation of the tumor tissue. The South-Eastern Norway Regional Health Authority, Hamar, Norway, the Norwegian Radium Hospital Research Foundation, and Eckbo foundation provided research grants. </p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="30850" pm="."><plain>1.FalangaARussoLMilesiVThe coagulopathy of cancerCurr Opin Hematol.201421423910.1097/MOH.0000000000000072<?supplied-pmid 25054907?>25054907 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="30851" pm="."><plain>2.HeitJASilversteinMDMohrDNPettersonTMO'FallonWMMeltonLJ3rdRisk factors for deep vein thrombosis and pulmonary embolism: a population-based case–control studyArch Intern Med.20001608091510.1001/archinte.160.6.809<?supplied-pmid 10737280?>10737280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="30852" pm="."><plain>3.BlomJWDoggenCJOsantoSRosendaalFRMalignancies, prothrombotic mutations, and the risk of venous thrombosisJAMA.20052937152210.1001/jama.293.6.715<?supplied-pmid 15701913?>15701913 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="30853" pm="."><plain>4.KhoranaAADalalMLinJConnollyGCIncidence and predictors of venous thromboembolism (VTE) among ambulatory high-risk cancer patients undergoing chemotherapy in the United StatesCancer.20131196485510.1002/cncr.27772<?supplied-pmid 22893596?>22893596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="30854" pm="."><plain>5.FalangaAMarchettiMVignoliACoagulation and cancer: biological and clinical aspectsJ Thromb Haemost.2013112233310.1111/jth.12075<?supplied-pmid 23279708?>23279708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="30855" pm="."><plain>6.KocaturkBVan den BergYWTiekenCMieogJSde KruijfEMEngelsCCAlternatively spliced tissue factor promotes breast cancer growth in a beta1 integrin-dependent mannerProc Natl Acad Sci USA2013110115172210.1073/pnas.1307100110<?supplied-pmid 23801760?>23801760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="30856" pm="."><plain>7.Stavik B, Tinholt M, Sletten M, Skretting G, Sandset PM, Iversen N. TFPIalpha and TFPIbeta are expressed at the surface of breast cancer cells and inhibit TF-FVIIa activity. J Hematol Oncol. 2013; 6. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="30860" pm="."><plain>8.UenoTToiMKoikeMNakamuraSTominagaTTissue factor expression in breast cancer tissues: its correlation with prognosis and plasma concentrationBr J Cancer.2000831647010.1054/bjoc.2000.1272<?supplied-pmid 10901365?>10901365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="30861" pm="."><plain>9.SierkoEWojtukiewiczMZZimnochLKisielWExpression of tissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) in human breast and colon cancer tissueThromb Haemost.201010319820410.1160/TH09-06-0416<?supplied-pmid 20062932?>20062932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="30862" pm="."><plain>10.RydenLGrabauDSchaffnerFJonssonPERufWBeltingMEvidence for tissue factor phosphorylation and its correlation with protease-activated receptor expression and the prognosis of primary breast cancerInt J Cancer.2010126233040<?supplied-pmid 19795460?>19795460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="30863" pm="."><plain>11.HjortoeGMPetersenLCAlbrektsenTSorensenBBNorbyPLMandalSKTissue factor-factor VIIa-specific up-regulation of IL-8 expression in MDA-MB-231 cells is mediated by PAR-2 and results in increased cell migrationBlood.200410330293710.1182/blood-2003-10-3417<?supplied-pmid 15070680?>15070680 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="30864" pm="."><plain>12.VersteegHHSchaffnerFKerverMPetersenHHAhamedJFelding-HabermannBInhibition of tissue factor signaling suppresses tumor growthBlood.2008111190910.1182/blood-2007-07-101048<?supplied-pmid 17901245?>17901245 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="30865" pm="."><plain>13.HembroughTASwartzGMPapathanassiuAVlasukGPRoteWEGreenSJTissue factor/factor VIIa inhibitors block angiogenesis and tumor growth through a nonhemostatic mechanismCancer Res.20036329973000<?supplied-pmid 12782609?>12782609 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="30866" pm="."><plain>14.JiangXGuoYLBrombergMEFormation of tissue factor-factor VIIa-factor Xa complex prevents apoptosis in human breast cancer cellsThromb Haemost.200696196201<?supplied-pmid 16894464?>16894464 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="30867" pm="."><plain>15.BrozeGJJrGirardTJTissue factor pathway inhibitor: structure-functionFront Biosci (Landmark Ed).2012172628010.2741/3926<?supplied-pmid 22201743?>22201743 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="30868" pm="."><plain>16.HamuroTKamikuboYNakaharaYMiyamotoSFunatsuAHuman recombinant tissue factor pathway inhibitor induces apoptosis in cultured human endothelial cellsFEBS Lett.199842119720210.1016/S0014-5793(97)01559-7<?supplied-pmid 9468305?>9468305 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="30869" pm="."><plain>17.HembroughTARuizJFPapathanassiuAEGreenSJStricklandDKTissue factor pathway inhibitor inhibits endothelial cell proliferation via association with the very low density lipoprotein receptorJ Biol Chem200127612241810.1074/jbc.M010395200<?supplied-pmid 11278667?>11278667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="30870" pm="."><plain>18.ProvencalMMichaudMBeaulieuERatelDRivardGEGingrasDTissue factor pathway inhibitor (TFPI) interferes with endothelial cell migration by inhibition of both the Erk pathway and focal adhesion proteinsThromb Haemost.20089957685<?supplied-pmid 18327407?>18327407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="30871" pm="."><plain>19.HolroydEWDelacroixSLarsenKHarbuzariuAPsaltisPJWangLTissue factor pathway inhibitor blocks angiogenesis via its carboxyl terminusArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol.2012327041110.1161/ATVBAHA.111.243733<?supplied-pmid 22223730?>22223730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="30872" pm="."><plain>20.StavikBSkrettingGAasheimHCTinholtMZernichowLSlettenMDownregulation of TFPI in breast cancer cells induces tyrosine phosphorylation signaling and increases metastatic growth by stimulating cell motilityBmc Cancer.20111135710.1186/1471-2407-11-357<?supplied-pmid 21849050?>21849050 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="30873" pm="."><plain>21.StavikBSkrettingGSiettenMSandsetPMIversenNOverexpression of Both TFPI alpha and TFPI beta Induces Apoptosis and Expression of Genes Involved in the Death Receptor Pathway in Breast Cancer CellsMol Carcinog.2010499516310.1002/mc.20679<?supplied-pmid 20886581?>20886581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="30874" pm="."><plain>22.WilliamsLTuckerTAKoenigKAllenTRaoLVPendurthiUTissue factor pathway inhibitor attenuates the progression of malignant pleural mesothelioma in nude miceAm J Respir Cell Mol Biol.201246173910.1165/rcmb.2011-0276OC<?supplied-pmid 21852688?>21852688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="30875" pm="."><plain>23.AmirkhosraviAMeyerTChangJYAmayaMSiddiquiFDesaiHTissue factor pathway inhibitor reduces experimental lung metastasis of B16 melanomaThromb Haemost.2002879306<?supplied-pmid 12083498?>12083498 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="30876" pm="."><plain>24.MoattiDHaidarBFumeronFGauciLBoudvillainOSeknadjiPA new T-287C polymorphism in the 5' regulatory region of the tissue factor pathway inhibitor gene. Association study of the T-287C and C-399 T polymorphisms with coronary artery disease and plasma TFPI levelsThromb Haemost2000842449<?supplied-pmid 10959696?>10959696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="30878" pm="."><plain>25.SkrettingGStavikBLandvikNEMyklebustCFIversenNZienolddinySFunctional characterization of polymorphisms in the human TFPI geneBiochem Biophys Res Commun.20103971061110.1016/j.bbrc.2010.05.078<?supplied-pmid 20519147?>20519147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="30879" pm="."><plain>26.MoattiDMeirhaegheAOllivierVBautersCAmouyelPde ProstDPolymorphisms of the tissue factor pathway inhibitor gene and the risk of restenosis after coronary angioplastyBlood Coagul Fibrinolysis.2001123172310.1097/00001721-200106000-00013<?supplied-pmid 11460016?>11460016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="30880" pm="."><plain>27.ArnaudEBarbalatVNicaudVCambienFEvansAMorrisonCPolymorphisms in the 5' regulatory region of the tissue factor gene and the risk of myocardial infarction and venous thromboembolism: the ECTIM and PATHROS studies. Etude Cas-Temoins de l'Infarctus du Myocarde. Paris Thrombosis case–control StudyArterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol200020892810.1161/01.ATV.20.3.892<?supplied-pmid 10712418?>10712418 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="30883" pm="."><plain>28.KwonAJoSHJoYAParkJYKimMKangHJGenetic polymorphisms and plasma levels of tissue factor and tissue factor pathway inhibitor in venous thromboembolismBlood Coagul Fibrinolysis.2014254162110.1097/MBC.0000000000000063<?supplied-pmid 24448154?>24448154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="30884" pm="."><plain>29.SegersOSimioniPTormeneDCastoldiEInfluence of single nucleotide polymorphisms on thrombin generation in factor V Leiden heterozygotesThromb Haemost.20141114384610.1160/TH13-05-0360<?supplied-pmid 24226152?>24226152 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="30885" pm="."><plain>30.OpstadTBEilertsenALHoibraatenESkrettingGSandsetPMTissue factor pathway inhibitor polymorphisms in women with and without a history of venous thrombosis and the effects of postmenopausal hormone therapyBlood Coagul Fibrinolysis.2010215162110.1097/MBC.0b013e32833a06cd<?supplied-pmid 20453636?>20453636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="30886" pm="."><plain>31.KittanehMMonteroAJGluckSMolecular profiling for breast cancer: a comprehensive reviewBiomark Cancer.201356170<?supplied-pmid 24250234?>24250234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="30887" pm="."><plain>32.Norsk bryst cancer gruppe. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://nbcg.no/retningslinjer/">http://nbcg.no/retningslinjer/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="30888" pm="."><plain>33.AbecasisGRAutonABrooksLDDePristoMADurbinRMHandsakerREAn integrated map of genetic variation from 1,092 human genomesNature.2012491566510.1038/nature11632<?supplied-pmid 23128226?>23128226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="30889" pm="."><plain>34.ParkerJSMullinsMCheangMCLeungSVoducDVickeryTSupervised risk predictor of breast cancer based on intrinsic subtypesJ Clin Oncol.2009271160710.1200/JCO.2008.18.1370<?supplied-pmid 19204204?>19204204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="30890" pm="."><plain>35.de BakkerPIYelenskyRPe'erIGabrielSBDalyMJAltshulerDEfficiency and power in genetic association studiesNat Genet.20053712172310.1038/ng1669<?supplied-pmid 16244653?>16244653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="30891" pm="."><plain>36.Purcell S, Neale B, Todd-Brown K, Thomas L, Ferreira MA, Bender D, et al. PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based linkage analyses. Am J Hum Genet. 2007;81:559–75. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/plink/">http://pngu.mgh.harvard.edu/~purcell/plink/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="30895" pm="."><plain>37.R project. Institute for Statistics and Mathematics, Vienna, Austria. 2014. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">http://www.r-project.org</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30898" pm="."><plain>Accessed 10 April 2014. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="30899" pm="."><plain>38.BoTHDysvikBJonassenILSimpute: accurate estimation of missing values in microarray data with least squares methodsNucleic Acids Res.200432e3410.1093/nar/gnh026<?supplied-pmid 14978222?>14978222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="30900" pm="."><plain>39.BenjaminiYHochbergYControlling the False Discovery Rate: A Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple TestingJ R Stat Soc Series B Stat Methodol199557289300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="30901" pm="."><plain>40.RingnerMFredlundEHakkinenJBorgAStaafJGOBO: gene expression-based outcome for breast cancer onlinePLoS One.20116e1791110.1371/journal.pone.0017911<?supplied-pmid 21445301?>21445301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="30902" pm="."><plain>41.VuongDSimpsonPTGreenBCummingsMCLakhaniSRMolecular classification of breast cancerVirchows Arch.201446511410.1007/s00428-014-1593-7<?supplied-pmid 24878755?>24878755 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="30903" pm="."><plain>42.StavikBSkrettingGOlstadOKSlettenMDehli VigelandMSandsetPMTFPI alpha and beta regulate mRNAs and microRNAs involved in cancer biology and in the immune system in breast cancer cellsPLoS One.20127e4718410.1371/journal.pone.0047184<?supplied-pmid 23071754?>23071754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="30904" pm="."><plain>43.LindahlAKSandsetPMAbildgaardUAnderssonTRHarbitzTBHigh plasma levels of extrinsic pathway inhibitor and low levels of other coagulation inhibitors in advanced cancerActa Chir Scand.198915538993<?supplied-pmid 2596246?>2596246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="30905" pm="."><plain>44.IversenNLindahlAKAbildgaardUElevated TFPI in malignant disease: relation to cancer type and hypercoagulationBr J Haematol.19981028899510.1046/j.1365-2141.1998.00875.x<?supplied-pmid 9734635?>9734635 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="30906" pm="."><plain>45.TinholtMVikenMDahmAEVollanHSahlbergKGarredØIncreased coagulation activity and genetic polymorphisms in the F5, F10 and EPCR genes are associated with breast cancer: a case–control studyBmc Cancer.20141484510.1186/1471-2407-14-845<?supplied-pmid 25407022?>25407022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="30907" pm="."><plain>46.AmezianeNSeguinCBorgelDFumeronFMoattiDAlhenc-GelasMThe -33 T- &gt; C polymorphism in intron 7 of the TFPI gene influences the risk of venous thromboembolism, independently of the factor V Leiden and prothrombin mutationsThromb Haemost.2002881959<?supplied-pmid 12195688?>12195688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="30908" pm="."><plain>47.KhoranaAAAhrendtSARyanCKFrancisCWHrubanRHHuYCTissue factor expression, angiogenesis, and thrombosis in pancreatic cancerClin Cancer Res.2007132870510.1158/1078-0432.CCR-06-2351<?supplied-pmid 17504985?>17504985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="30909" pm="."><plain>48.HernandezCOrbeJRoncalCAlvarez-HernandezMMartinez de LizarrondoSAlvesMTTissue factor expressed by microparticles is associated with mortality but not with thrombosis in cancer patientsThromb Haemost201311059860810.1160/TH13-02-0122<?supplied-pmid 23803792?>23803792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="30910" pm="."><plain>49.van den BergYWvan den HengelLGMyersHRAyachiOJordanovaERufWAlternatively spliced tissue factor induces angiogenesis through integrin ligationProc Natl Acad Sci U S A.20091061949750210.1073/pnas.0905325106<?supplied-pmid 19875693?>19875693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="30911" pm="."><plain>50.ChenVMHoggPJEncryption and decryption of tissue factorJ Thromb Haemost2013112778410.1111/jth.12228<?supplied-pmid 23809131?>23809131 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
