<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.2.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art520.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_JARE265 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Adv Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Adv Res</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Advanced Research</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2090-1232</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2090-1224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4348445</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2090-1232(13)00140-9</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jare.2013.11.004</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="28813" pm="."><plain>Roles of dehydrin genes in wheat tolerance to drought stress </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>Nemat M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El-Bastawisy</surname><given-names>Zeinab M.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>El-Sayed</surname><given-names>Ahamed K.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ebeed</surname><given-names>Heba T.</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nemat Alla</surname><given-names>Mamdouh M.</given-names></name><email>mamnematalla@du.edu.eg</email><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af005">Botany Department, Faculty of Science, Damietta University, Egypt</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author. Tel.: +20 57 2400233; fax: +20 57 2403868. <email>mamnematalla@du.edu.eg</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>3</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2013 Production and hosting by Elsevier B.V. on behalf of Cairo University.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="28814" pm="."><plain>Physiological parameters and expression levels of drought related genes were analyzed in early vegetative stage of two bread wheat cultivars (Sids and Gmiza) differ in drought tolerance capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28815" pm="."><plain>Both cultivars were imposed to gradual water depletion started on day 17 till day 32 after sowing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28816" pm="."><plain>Sids, the more tolerant cultivar to drought showed higher fresh and dry weights than the drought sensitive genotype, Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28817" pm="."><plain>Under water stress, Sids had higher membrane stability index (MSI), lower accumulated H2O2 and higher activity of the antioxidant enzymes; catalase (CAT), guaiacol peroxidase (GPX), ascorbate peroxidase (APX) and superoxide dismutase (SOD) than Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28818" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the differential expression patterns of the genes dhn, wcor and dreb were observed due to water deficit intensity according to cultivar’s tolerance to drought. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28819" pm="."><plain>The DNA sequence alignment of dun showed high similarity of about 80–92% identities with other related plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28820" pm="."><plain>The most striking overall observed trend was the highly induction in the expression of dun, wcor and dreb in leaves of the tolerant genotype, Sids under severe water stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Antioxidants</kwd><kwd><italic>dhn</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>dreb</italic></kwd><kwd>Drought stress</kwd><kwd><italic>wcor</italic></kwd><kwd>Wheat cultivars</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s0005"><title><text><SENT sid="28821" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28822" pm="."><plain>Drought is a wide world problem constraining global crop production seriously [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28823" pm="."><plain>Common wheat possesses a very complex and huge genome with size of ∼16 × 109 bp, which consists of about 90% repeated sequences [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28824" pm="."><plain>Under drought stress, H2O2 generated as a result of electron leakage from the photosynthetic and respiratory electron transport chains to oxygen or during photorespiration resulting from the oxygenase activity of Rubisco. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28825" pm="."><plain>Also, drought results in changes in antioxidant enzymes activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28826" pm="."><plain>High antioxidant activities could be interpreted as symptoms of oxidative stress or damage, the plant upregulates antioxidant enzymes because it produces more reactive oxygen species (ROS) [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28827" pm="."><plain>Conversely, high antioxidant activity could be interpreted as higher tolerance to oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28828" pm="."><plain>Alteration of gene expression is always involved in preparing plants for an existence under stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28829" pm="."><plain>Under conditions of water deficit (dehydration), numerous processes are modified or impaired resulting in growth inhibition [4] to cope with osmotic changes in their tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28830" pm="."><plain>Modification of gene expression results in a strict control of the physiological and biochemical responses to stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28831" pm="."><plain>Identification and isolation of these genes are essential for developing tolerant crops. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28832" pm="."><plain>Expression profiling has become an important tool to investigate responses of an organism to environmental changes at the transcriptional level [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28833" pm="."><plain>One of these adaptations is to produce proteins called dehydrins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28834" pm="."><plain>Dehydration responsive element binding proteins (DREBs) constitute a large family of TFs that induce the expression of a large number of functional genes and impart stress endurance to plants [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28835" pm="."><plain>The dehydration responsive element (DRE) as a cis-acting element was found in the promoter regions of many drought- and low-temperature-inducible genes [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28836" pm="."><plain>All dreb genes feature three conserved regions, an EREBP/AP2 DNA binding domain, an N-terminal nuclear localization signal, and conserved Ser/Thr rich region adjacent to the EREBP/AP2 domain. dreb tfs play key roles in plant stress signaling transduction pathway, they can specifically bind to DRE/CRT element (G/ACCGAC) and activate the expression of many stress inducible genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28837" pm="."><plain>In several cases, the overexpression of these dreb/cbf genes was associated with retardation of plant growth under non stressful conditions [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28838" pm="."><plain>It was suggested that the overexpression of these genes under stress-inducible promoter but not constitutive promoter may be a solution to avoid the change in plant growth [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28839" pm="."><plain>Dehydrins dhn are associated with crucial protective functions [10]. dhn are part of the late embryogenesis abundant proteins (LEA) [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28840" pm="."><plain>They are produced in response to abscisic acid (ABA) [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28841" pm="."><plain>They are primarily distributed in cytosol, nucleus and plasma membranes [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28842" pm="."><plain>Dreb controls expression of cold-regulated (cor) gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28843" pm="."><plain>Wcor410 is a dehydrin that accumulates around the plasma membrane and is present in lesser amounts in the intercellular space [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28844" pm="."><plain>It is up regulated by low temperatures, dehydration, ABA, salt, wounding and polyethylene glycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28845" pm="."><plain>So, the present work is aimed at studying the expression of wdhn, dreb and wcor410 in order to find their roles in drought tolerance of two wheat cultivars that differentially tolerate water stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s0010"><title><text><SENT sid="28846" pm="."><plain>Material and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s0015"><title><text><SENT sid="28847" pm="."><plain>Plant material and growing conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28848" pm="."><plain>Seeds of two bread wheat (Triticum aestivum) cultivars, (Sids 4, and Gmiza 10) were obtained from Wheat Research Department, Field Crops Research Institute, Agricultural Research Center, Giza, Egypt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28849" pm="."><plain>The seeds were sown in a mixture of sand and clay culture (1:1) in plastic pots (25 cm diameter) under field conditions in greenhouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28850" pm="."><plain>Ten seeds of each cultivar were sown per pot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28851" pm="."><plain>Seedlings, shortly after seedling emergence, were thinned to five per pot (11 days after sowing, 11 DAS) and watered by tap water twice in week. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28852" pm="."><plain>On the 17th DAS, the pots of each cultivar were divided into two groups: one was left as control and irrigated with tap water and the other was restricted to drought by withholding water up to the end of the experiment (33 DAS). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28853" pm="."><plain>The experimental design was a complete block randomized design and repeated twice in triplicates so that the mean values ± SE values were of n = 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28854" pm="."><plain>The design consisted of 144 pots [2 cultivars × 2 sets (2 treatments) × 3 pots per set (3 replications per treatment each pot contained 5 plants) × 2 experimental repetitions × 6 intervals]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28855" pm="."><plain>At each interval starting from the 17th DAS every 3 days up to the 33rd DAS, the full analysis of variance (ANOVA) was calculated at p = 0.05 for 24 samples [2 cultivars × 2 treatments × 6 replications]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28856" pm="."><plain>At harvest, samples from different pots of each cultivar were collected and used for fresh and dry weight determinations while leaves from the remaining individuals were collected, frozen immediately in liquid nitrogen and stored at −80 °C for subsequent analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title><text><SENT sid="28857" pm="."><plain>Activity assay of antioxidant enzymes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28858" pm="."><plain>Frozen leaf samples were ground in liquid nitrogen and homogenized in 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) containing 2 mM EDTA, 5 mM β-mercaptoethanol and 4% (w/v) polyvinylpyrrolidine-40 (PVP-40). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28859" pm="."><plain>The homogenate was centrifuged at 30,000×g for 30 min at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28860" pm="."><plain>The supernatant was used for assay of the antioxidant enzymes catalase (CAT), guaiacol peroxidase (GPX), ascorbate peroxidase (APX) and superoxide dismutase (SOD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28861" pm="."><plain>CAT activity was assayed according to the method of Aebi [14], GPX activity was assayed according to the method of Chance and Maehly [15], APX activity was assayed according to the method of Nakano and Asada [16] and SOD activity was measured according to Giannopolitis and Ries [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0025"><title><text><SENT sid="28862" pm="."><plain>Membrane stability index and H2O2 content </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28863" pm="."><plain>The Membrane stability index (MSI) was determined indirectly by measuring the electrical conductivity according the protocol of Kocheva et al. [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28864" pm="."><plain>Leaf membrane stability was estimated using the equation, MSI = [1−(C1/C2)] × 100 [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28865" pm="."><plain>Relative Injury percentage was calculated as: RI(%) = 100−{[1−(T1/T2)]/[1−(C1/C2)] × 100}, where C and T refer to electrical conductivity of control and drought treated samples, and the subscript 1 and 2 refer to electric conductivity readings before and after autoclaving, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28866" pm="."><plain>H2O2 was measured according to Alexieva et al. [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0030"><title><text><SENT sid="28867" pm="."><plain>RNA isolation and cDNA preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28868" pm="."><plain>Total RNAs were extracted from 500 mg of shoot samples by using easy-BLUETM TRI-reagent (iNtrON Biotechnology) according to Chomczynski et al. [21] DNA was removed from RNA samples by using RNase-free DNaseI (Thermo scientific) following the instruction protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28869" pm="."><plain>Purity of total RNA was assessed at 260/280 nm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28870" pm="."><plain>Quality of the RNA was assured with ethidium-bromide stain analysis by agarose gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28871" pm="."><plain>About 0.1–1 μg DNA-free RNA in distilled water (DEPC-treated) were added into Maxime RT PreMix tubes with Oligo dT primer to a total volume of 20 μl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28872" pm="."><plain>The tubes were left for 2 min at room temperature and then the pellet was dissolved by pipetting. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28873" pm="."><plain>The cDNA synthesis reaction was performed using Thermal counter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28874" pm="."><plain>The mixture was incubated at 45 °C for 60 min followed by 5 min at 95 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28875" pm="."><plain>The reactant was diluted by adding 20–50 μl sterile water then stored at −20 °C for RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28876" pm="."><plain>To check if the cDNAs were properly synthesized, 18S rRNA of Arabidopsis (amplicon length is about 800 bp) was amplified by PCR conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28877" pm="."><plain>These results were used as positive controls of cDNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0035"><title><text><SENT sid="28878" pm="."><plain>Primer design and DNA analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28879" pm="."><plain>Specific primer pairs were designed to recognize a conserved regions which were predetermined using alignment of dehydrin genes sequences from wheat that are available at the GenBank. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28880" pm="."><plain>The alignment for these identified genes was performed by CLUSTALW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28881" pm="."><plain>The primer pair for dhn and wcor genes was designed by PRIMER 3 program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fokker.wi.mit.edu/primer3/input.htm" id="ir0005">http://fokker.wi.mit.edu/primer3/input.htm</ext-link>) and was checked by OligoAnalyzer 3.1, while the primer pair for dreb gene was designed according to the sequence of Triticum aesitivum dreb gene (wdreb) available in the NCBI database under the accession number AB193608 (Table 1) [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28882" pm="."><plain>The PCR conditions were modified according to the primer properties, and the PCR products. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0040"><title><text><SENT sid="28883" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitative PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28884" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitative PCR of the three genes (dhn, wcor and dreb) was performed in 50 μl reaction mixtures containing 16 μl RNase–DNase-free water, 25 μl Dream Taq Green PCR Master Mix (2×) (Thermo Scientific Cat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28885" pm="."><plain>No. #K1081) and 10 μl of each of the forward and reverse primers (10 mM each) as indicated in Table 1, 1 μl cDNA template. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28886" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) was performed as follows: initial denaturation at 95 °C for 5 min followed by (26–40) cycles of denaturation at 95 °C for 30 s, annealing at (43–58 °C) for (30–45 s) for different template cDNAs and genes specific primers were optimized, extension at 72 °C for 30 s, and final extension for 10 min at 72 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28887" pm="."><plain>For semi-quantitative analysis, 10 μl of PCR products was collected after different cycles before reaching the plateau phase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28888" pm="."><plain>The PCR cycles were adjusted to be in the linear range by viewing the RT-PCR product after each cycle on agarose gels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28889" pm="."><plain>For ascertaining equal RNA loading in RT reaction, 18S rRNA was used as an internal control and the fold expression of the target genes was normalized accordingly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28890" pm="."><plain>The resolved gel images were introduced into LabImage V 2.7.2 to measure the band volumes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28891" pm="."><plain>Each experiment was repeated three times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28892" pm="."><plain>Optical densities of bands that represent Arabidopsis 18S rRNA were obtained for normalization of data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28893" pm="."><plain>Ratio of gene band intensity to 18S rRNA band intensity was calculated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0045"><title><text><SENT sid="28894" pm="."><plain>Isolation and identification of DNA sequence of dhn and wcor genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28895" pm="."><plain>PCR product for dhn was extracted from agarose gels while wcor was isolated from PCR mix by ISOLATE PCR and Gel Kit (Cat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28896" pm="."><plain>No.: BIO-52029) following the instruction protocol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28897" pm="."><plain>The extracted PCR products were sequenced in both directions by GATC Biotech. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28898" pm="."><plain>Ltd. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gatc-biotech.com/en/home.html" id="ir0010">http://www.gatc-biotech.com/en/home.html</ext-link>, ORF was found by Six-frame translation, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioline.com/calculator/01_13" id="ir0015">http://www.bioline.com/calculator/01_13</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28899" pm="."><plain>A database analysis was done for each sequence in NCBI and BioEdit Sequence Alignment Editor Software, Version 7.04.1 using Megablast (nucleotides) search to test out the homology of the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28900" pm="."><plain>DNA alignment was done by multalin (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinfo.genotoul.fr/multalin/multalin.html" id="ir0020">http://bioinfo.genotoul.fr/multalin/multalin.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0050"><title><text><SENT sid="28901" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28902" pm="."><plain>The experimental design exhibited that water regimes were in main plots, and wheat genotypes in sub plots with three random replications of two experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28903" pm="."><plain>For individual experiments, standard error of means of each ratio was calculated from n = 6 and analysis of variance (ANOVA) was carried out at every interval at 0.05 significance level [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s0055"><title><text><SENT sid="28904" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s0060"><title><text><SENT sid="28905" pm="."><plain>Growth parameters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28906" pm="."><plain>As Shown in Table 2, both cultivars showed gradual increase in the fresh weight with time progress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28907" pm="."><plain>Drought resulted in decreases in fresh weight of both cultivars, the magnitude of decrease was more pronounced in Gmiza than in Sids especially at the last harvest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28908" pm="."><plain>Shoot dry weight also showed a gradual increase in both cultivars (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28909" pm="."><plain>At the end of the experiment there was a significant decrease in dry weight in Gmiza cultivar compared with control, otherwise drought caused insignificant decrease in dry weight in both cultivars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28910" pm="."><plain>The results also show that there was a progressive increase in the leaf area in both cultivars under normal conditions (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28911" pm="."><plain>Sids had larger leaf area than Gmiza during the whole experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28912" pm="."><plain>Drought decreased Sids leaf area comparing control value only after 26 and 30 DAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28913" pm="."><plain>Conversely, drought stress caused insignificant decrease in leaf area in Gmiza comparing control values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28914" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the largest increase and the greatest decrease in leaf area were observed in watered and drought stressed Sids plants respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0065"><title><text><SENT sid="28915" pm="."><plain>Membrane stability index (MSI) and H2O2 content </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28916" pm="."><plain>In Table 3, withholding water resulted in severe damage to membranes of Gmiza comparing with control while Sids did not encounter any damage in MSI along the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28917" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, after three days of withholding water, Sids and Gmiza cultivars had H2O2 content significantly higher than control, the magnitude of increase was most pronounced in Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28918" pm="."><plain>Only on 30 and 33 DAS there was significant increases in the H2O2 content in accumulated in Gmiza due to drought comparing with control values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28919" pm="."><plain>However, there was not any significant difference in the H2O2 content between watered and drought stressed Sids plants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0070"><title><text><SENT sid="28920" pm="."><plain>Antioxidant enzymes activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28921" pm="."><plain>Drought stress enhanced significantly CAT activity in Sids plants compared with its control all over the experiment (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28922" pm="."><plain>Conversely, drought stress inhibited CAT activity in Gmiza plants compared with its control; this inhibition was significant and most pronounced starting from the 26th DAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28923" pm="."><plain>Similarly, drought stress enhanced GPX activity in Sids plants compared with the control values all over the experiment (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28924" pm="."><plain>Contrarily, drought stress inhibited GPX activity in Gmiza plants compared with the control; but this inhibition was insignificant at all intervals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28925" pm="."><plain>Generally, Sids has higher activity of SOD than Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28926" pm="."><plain>Moreover, drought resulted in a significant increase in SOD activity comparing control until the end of the experiment (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28927" pm="."><plain>However Gmiza plants encountered nonsignificant decrease in SOD activity during withholding water throughout the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28928" pm="."><plain>In the same pattern, Sids generally has higher activity of APX than Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28929" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, APX activity was inhibited in both Sids and Gmiza cultivar due to drought, however this inhibition was significant only from 30 DAS onward comparing control values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28930" pm="."><plain>The magnitude of inhibition in APX activity was greater in Gmiza than in Sids. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0075"><title><text><SENT sid="28931" pm="."><plain>Responses of dhns, wcor and dreb to drought stress </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28932" pm="."><plain>Drought stress increased the transcript level of dhn in both cultivars after three days stress by about 2-folds (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28933" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, after six days of stress, the mRNA level of dhn declined slightly in Gmiza but increased by 3-folds in Sids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28934" pm="."><plain>Drought stress for 10 days resulted in an increase in the transcript level of dhn gene by 2-folds again in Gmiza however it reached the highest value in Sids as it went up by about more than 4-folds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28935" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, after 2 days of rehydration, the transcript level of dhn declined to the minimum level in both cultivars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28936" pm="."><plain>It is worth mentioning that the early expression of dhn gene after 26 cycles in the drought stressed Sids plants was after 6 days drought. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28937" pm="."><plain>The transcript level of wcor gene was over regulated following drought stress for 3 days by 2-folds in Gmiza (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28938" pm="."><plain>However, there was an increase in about 30% in Sids as compared with control transcript levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28939" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, after 6 days drought the increase in the wcor transcript level was restricted to Sids cultivar as there was a decline in the mRNA level of wcor in Gmiza plants by about 40% as compared with control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28940" pm="."><plain>Afterward, there was up-regulation in the mRNA level of wcor gene in both cultivars as a result of drought stress for 10 days in both cultivars but the increase in the expression level was highly significant in Sids plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28941" pm="."><plain>On other hand, rewatering both plants resulted in sharp reduction in the transcript level to reach minimum level during treatment period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28942" pm="."><plain>It is noticed that there was a dense early expression for wcor gene after 37 cycles in the droughted Gmiza after 6 days drought. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28943" pm="."><plain>Drought stress differentially regulated the expression level of dreb gene in both cultivars (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28944" pm="."><plain>After 3 days stress, the mRNA level in Gmiza went up 4.5 times of the control level but decreased slightly in Sids plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28945" pm="."><plain>However 6 days stress led to a sharp decrease in the dreb mRNA level in Gmiza and significant increase in case of Sids plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28946" pm="."><plain>The increase in the dreb transcript level continued up to the maximum value after 10 days stress while the transcript level of the droughted Gmiza plants was slightly higher than the transcript level of control plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28947" pm="."><plain>Afterward, the transcript level of dreb went down to lowest values in both cultivars after 2 days rehydration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0080"><title><text><SENT sid="28948" pm="."><plain>Characterization of tadhn and wcor </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28949" pm="."><plain>The sequence analysis results showed that the fragment size of tadhn was 307 bp; (G + C) content was 58.63% (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28950" pm="."><plain>The predicted molecular weight for this fragment was 93.888 kDa for single strand and 187.111 kDa for double strand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28951" pm="."><plain>This fragment encoded a polypeptide of 102 amino acids (20.4% Gly). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28952" pm="."><plain>A comparison of the deduced protein sequence of tadhn with known dhns sequences from wheat, Hordeum vulgare and Prunus persica showed the conserved Ser-repeat in the N-terminus, Y-segment and has one Lys-rich region at the C-terminus of the protein (K-segments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28953" pm="."><plain>The predicted protein was found to have similarity with other dehydrin proteins by about 35–79%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28954" pm="."><plain>The similarity was 35% with P. persica dehydrin, AAC49658; 79% with T. aestivum dehydrin, BAF30987; 68% with T. aestivum LEA D-11 dehydrin, BAC01112 and H. vulgare subsp. spontaneum dehydrin5, AAQ55342. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28955" pm="."><plain>Results of BLAST search using Megablast (nucleotide) indicated that the Tadhn DNA sequence shared high nucleotide sequence homology with wheat and other plants at about 91–96% identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28956" pm="."><plain>The similarity percentages were 96% with T. aestivum wcor726, U73213; 95% with T. aestivum wdhn gene, FN393741; DHN14, AB272228; 93% with Lophopyrum elongatum dehydrin AF031250; 91% T. aestivum rab15B, X62476 and 91% with T. turgidum subsp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28957" pm="."><plain>Durum dhn5, AM180933. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28958" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the fragment size of wcor was 429 bp; (G + C) content was 55.94% (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28959" pm="."><plain>The predicted molecular weight for this fragment was 130.722 kDa for single strand and 261.259 kDa for double strand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28960" pm="."><plain>This fragment encoded a polypeptide of 144 amino acids (with 17.12% Glu and 15% Ser) and the predicted protein with molecular weight of 16.26 kDa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28961" pm="."><plain>The deduced amino acid sequences corresponding to the partial genomic fragment which was similar to previously reported DHNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28962" pm="."><plain>The amino acid sequence of wcor contains Ser-repeat and has two Lys-rich regions (K-segments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28963" pm="."><plain>The predicted deduced protein was found to 45 to 86% similarity with other dehydrins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28964" pm="."><plain>78% similarity with H. vulgare dehydrin8, AAD02259; 81% with T. aesitivum wcor410, AEJ88292; 62% with Oryza sativa SK3-type dehydrin, ABS44866 and 45% with DHN2-like protein in Zea mays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28965" pm="."><plain>Results from BLAST search using Megablast (nucleotide) indicated that the DNA sequence was highly identical to dhn sequence from wheat and other plants at about 80–92% identity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28966" pm="."><plain>The similarity percentages were 89% with T. aesitivum wcor410c, U73211; 89% with T. turgidum subsp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28967" pm="."><plain>Durum dhn11, AJ890140; 86% with T. aesitivum wcor410b, U73210; 85% with T. aesitivum WZY1-2, EU124658; 82% with H. vulgare dehydrin8, AF181458 and 77% with Oryza sativa SK3-type dehydrin, EF444534. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s0085"><title><text><SENT sid="28968" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28969" pm="."><plain>The present results revealed that the drought stress significantly declined the fresh weight in both cultivars but only Sids could tolerate the stress and retained its fresh weight at the end of the experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28970" pm="."><plain>Sayar et al. [24] reported that there was a decrease in the seedling fresh weight of both drought tolerant and sensitive durum wheat cultivars as osmotic potentials increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28971" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the dry weight of Sids was not significantly affected by drought by the end of the experiment although drought significantly decreased dry weight of Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28972" pm="."><plain>Drought may limit the growth of the plant organs thereby reducing meristems and finally decreasing the capacity of vegetation [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28973" pm="."><plain>More increase in dry weight of Sids was detected after 16 days drought stress than the other cultivar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28974" pm="."><plain>This means that Sids was the superior cultivar in its growth and this probably due to the vigor and strength of its genotype. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28975" pm="."><plain>Specific leaf area is a marker for the regulation of plant leaf following abiotic stress factors including drought [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28976" pm="."><plain>The specific leaf area was larger in Sids, the more tolerant cultivar, than in Gmiza the less tolerant one. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28977" pm="."><plain>According to our results, drought did not change Sids leaf area at early stress but led to a significant decrease during the period from 26 to 30 DAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28978" pm="."><plain>Conversely, drought stress caused insignificant decrease in leaf area in Gmiza comparing control values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28979" pm="."><plain>Sayar et al. [24] found decrease in leaf area in both tolerant and sensitive cultivars of durum wheat linearly as osmotic potentials in PEG increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28980" pm="."><plain>Reduction of leaf area in the more tolerant cultivar, Sids may be a try to decrease the transpiring area as an adaptive response to water deficit for avoiding water loss. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28981" pm="."><plain>Cell membranes are among the first targets of adverse stresses and the maintenance of membrane integrity and stability under abiotic stress conditions is a major component of environmental stress tolerance in plants [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28982" pm="."><plain>Our results showed a reduction in membrane stability index in both genotypes due to mild drought stress followed by severe reduction in sensitive genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28983" pm="."><plain>The decrease in MSI progressively augmented with increasing drought severity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28984" pm="."><plain>These results are in agreement with those of Filippou et al. [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28985" pm="."><plain>In addition, the present results revealed that mild drought induced H2O2 generation in Sids and Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28986" pm="."><plain>H2O2 content sharply dropped in Sids at 23 DAS but its accumulation continued in Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28987" pm="."><plain>These findings are in accordance with the results of Wang et al. [29] who found that exposure of plants to moderate stress can induce tolerance to severe stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28988" pm="."><plain>Such treatment can improve tolerance to other stress as so-called cross-acclimation to stress usually functions to rescue plants from oxidative stress and lipid peroxidation [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28989" pm="."><plain>Severe drought stimulates H2O2 production in Gmiza plants suggesting a lack of an enhanced capacity for protection from oxidative damage caused by drought stress in this sensitive cultivar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28990" pm="."><plain>Actually, H2O2 produced by photorespiration can act on the redox states of leaf antioxidant pools, implicating the possibility of photorespiratory H2O2 as a signal role under drought [31]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="28991" pm="."><plain>The results of antioxidant enzymes showed variation and differentiation between tolerant and sensitive genotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28992" pm="."><plain>CAT enzyme showed high significant activity in Sids genotype at all intervals and reached its maximum activity at moderate drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28993" pm="."><plain>Contrarily, there was no significant response to drought stress in the sensitive cultivar Gmiza except on 30 DAS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28994" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, Rivero et al. [32] found that CAT remained more active for a greater duration of drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28995" pm="."><plain>APX and POD might be responsible for the fine modulation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) for signaling, whereas CAT might be responsible for or the removal of excess ROS during stress [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28996" pm="."><plain>Moreover, GPX activity showed significant increase in Sids genotype nearly during all the experimental period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28997" pm="."><plain>However, there was no significant response in Gmiza to drought. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28998" pm="."><plain>Various stressful conditions of the environment have been shown to induce the activity of GPX [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28999" pm="."><plain>POD, APX and glutathione reductase are involved in fine regulation of ROS and loss of their activities resulted in build up of ROS to high levels that resulted in CAT induction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29000" pm="."><plain>It appears that there was an association between the higher antioxidant capacity and higher tolerance to drought stress in our tolerant wheat cultivar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29001" pm="."><plain>The association between the levels/activities of antioxidant enzymes and plant drought tolerance has been previously observed [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29002" pm="."><plain>This strong antioxidant system under stress conditions plays a major role in stress tolerance of both leaves and roots of many species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29003" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that dehydrin accumulation is correlated with dehydration when dehydrin accumulation was compared in dried cereal seedlings [36]. dhn data of the present results were in accordance with that observed by Lopez et al. [37] in drought-tolerant wheat compared with drought-sensitive plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29004" pm="."><plain>Dehydrins were thought to be associated with crucial protective functions [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29005" pm="."><plain>Recently, antioxidative activity has been proposed to be an important function of dehydrins [38], since CuCOR19 was proposed to have antioxidative activity [39] and PvSR3 dehydrin was suggested to protect cells against oxidative damage caused by ROS and metal ions [40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29006" pm="."><plain>In accordance, the present results exhibited a general relationship between enzymatic antioxidants and dhn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29007" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the more tolerant cultivar, Sids showed greater stimulation of antioxidant enzymes and also a 3-fold increase in the mRNA of dhn. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29008" pm="."><plain>Regarding the transcript level of wcor gene, drought stress resulted in over regulation in Sids cultivar more than Gmiza. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29009" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, rewatering both cultivars resulted in sharp reduction in the transcript level of wcor gene to reach its minimum level during treatment period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29010" pm="."><plain>Moreover, there was a dense early expression for wcor gene after 37 cycles in the droughted Gmiza after 6 days drought. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29011" pm="."><plain>Similarly, findings of Kurahashi et al. [41] on wild wheat Aegilops tauschii showed that KU-2829A, with high ABA sensitivity and drought tolerance, showed more rapid response in cold-responsive / late embryogenesis abundant (cor/lea) gene expression than the ABA-insensitive and drought-sensitive KU-2811. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29012" pm="."><plain>As indicated for dhn, there was a relationship between wcor and the efficiency of the antioxidant enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29013" pm="."><plain>The transcript level of wcor was increased more in the tolerant cultivar, Sids than in the sensitive one particularly under severe drought stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29014" pm="."><plain>The same pattern was also detected regarding the antioxidant enzymes supporting their relationship. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29015" pm="."><plain>dreb2 homologs contribute to increase multiple stress tolerance in several plant species [42–45] expression is induced by low temperature, drought, NaCl exposure, and exogenous ABA treatment [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29016" pm="."><plain>Drought stress differentially regulated the expression level of dreb gene in both cultivars. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29017" pm="."><plain>The increased dreb expression by drought was reported by Chen et al. [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29018" pm="."><plain>In this context, the level of mRNA of dreb was sharply decreased after 6 days of dehydration in the sensitive cultivar, Gmiza but increased in the more tolerant one, Sids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29019" pm="."><plain>Such increase continued to become maximum value after 10 days of water stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29020" pm="."><plain>A similar trend was also detected in enzymatic antioxidants pointing out to the presence of a general relationship between antioxidants and dreb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29021" pm="."><plain>Altering the expression level of a single dreb/cbf can increase or decrease levels of expression of other transcription factors, which in turn, can lead to activation of a larger number of target genes, some of which may be directly activated not by the initially over-expressed dreb/cbf but by downstream drebs/cbfs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29022" pm="."><plain>Several research groups have shown that raising levels of dreb/cbf expression by plant transformation enhance expression of downstream target genes encoding late embryogenesis abundant (LEA) proteins, also known as dehydrins (DHNs), and cold-responsive (COR) proteins [48]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s1055"><title><text><SENT sid="29023" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29024" pm="."><plain>The present work is an attempt to clarify the direct relationship between wdreb and the two cor and dhn genes in development of drought stress tolerance in wheat using two cultivars with different drought tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29025" pm="."><plain>According to the present results, dreb seemed to activate the transcription process of Tadhn and wcor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29026" pm="."><plain>Almost all genes examined in Sids and Gmiza appeared to be regulated by drought stress and subsequent rewatering in a variable manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29027" pm="."><plain>The most striking overall trend observed was the acute induction in expression of dhn, wcor and dreb in leaves tissue during severe water stress conditions in tolerant genotype Sids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29028" pm="."><plain>Moreover, there was a general relationship of the enzymatic antioxidants with the genes dhn, wcor and dreb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29029" pm="."><plain>A further study is needed to elucidate the transcription factors in relation to these antioxidant enzymes with the dreb genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29030" pm="."><plain>Some transcription factors that regulate the expression of several genes related to stress have been discovered [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29031" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analysis has revealed that dozens of transcription factors are involved in the plant response to various stresses [49,50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29032" pm="."><plain>Transcription factors control the rates of transcription to regulate the amounts of gene products (RNA and protein) available to the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29033" pm="."><plain>DREBs are important plant transcription factors that regulate the expression of many stress-inducible genes [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29034" pm="."><plain>So, the data presented here indicate a cross-talk between physiological and molecular tolerance mechanisms in response to drought stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="s0155"><title><text><SENT sid="29035" pm="."><plain>Conflict of interest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29036" pm="."><plain>The authors have declared no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec id="s0160"><title><text><SENT sid="29037" pm="."><plain>Compliance with Ethics Requirements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="29038" pm="."><plain>This article does not contain any studies with human or animal subjects. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><text><SENT sid="29039" pm="."><plain>1PennisiE.Plant genetics: the blue revolution, drop by drop, gene by geneScience320200817117318403686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0010"><text><SENT sid="29040" pm="."><plain>2LiW.ZhangP.FellersJ.P.FriebeB.GillB.S.Sequence composition, organization, and evolution of the core Triticeae genomePlant J40200450051115500466 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0015"><text><SENT sid="29041" pm="."><plain>3Nemat AllaM.M.HassanN.M.Changes of antioxidants and GSH-associated enzymes in isoproturon-treated maizeActa Physiol Plant292007247258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0020"><text><SENT sid="29042" pm="."><plain>4LawlorD.W.CornicG.Photosynthetic carbon assimilation and associated metabolism in relation to water deficits in higher plantsPlant Cell Environ25200227529411841670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0260"><text><SENT sid="29043" pm="."><plain>5MolinaC.RotterB.HorresR.UdupaS.M.BesserB.BellarminoL.SuperSAGE: the drought stress-responsive transcriptome of chickpea rootsBMC Genomics9200855319025623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0030"><text><SENT sid="29044" pm="."><plain>6AgarwalP.K.AgarwalP.ReddyM.K.SoporyS.K.Role of DREB transcription factors in abiotic and biotic stress tolerance in plantsPlant Cell Reports2520061263127416858552 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0035"><text><SENT sid="29045" pm="."><plain>7ShinozakiK.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK.Gene networks involved in drought stress response and toleranceJ Exp Bot58200722122717075077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0040"><text><SENT sid="29046" pm="."><plain>8LeeS.J.KangJ.Y.ParkH.J.KimM.D.BaeM.S.ChoiH.I.DREB2C interacts with ABF2 a bZIP protein regulating abscisic acid responsive gene expression and its overexpression affects abscisic acid sensitivityPlant Physiol153201071672720395451 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0045"><text><SENT sid="29047" pm="."><plain>9KasugaM.LiuQ.MiuraS.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK.Improving plant drought salt and freezing tolerance by gene transfer of a single stress-inducible transcription factorNat Biotechnol17199928729110096298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0050"><text><SENT sid="29048" pm="."><plain>10AllagulovaC.R.GimalovF.R.ShakirovaF.M.VakhitovV.A.The plant dehydrins: structure and putative functionsBiochemistry68200394595114606934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0055"><text><SENT sid="29049" pm="."><plain>11WahidA.CloseT.Expression of dehydrins under heat stress and their relationship with water relations of sugarcane leavesBiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29050" pm="."><plain>Plant512007104109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0060"><text><SENT sid="29051" pm="."><plain>12DanylukJ.PerronA.HoudeM.LiminA.FowlerB.BenhamounN.Accumulation of an acidic dehydrin in the vicinity of the plasma membrane during cold acclimation of wheatPlant Cell1019986236389548987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0065"><text><SENT sid="29052" pm="."><plain>13RoratT.Plant dehydrins-tissue location structure and functionCell Mol Biol Lett11200653655616983453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0070"><text><SENT sid="29053" pm="."><plain>14AebiH.Catalase in vitroMethod Enzymol1051984121126 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0075"><text><SENT sid="29054" pm="."><plain>15ChanceB.MaehlyA.C.Assay of catalase and peroxidaseMethod Enzymol21955764775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0080"><text><SENT sid="29055" pm="."><plain>16NakanoY.AsadaK.Hydrogen peroxide is scavenged by ascorbate-specific peroxidise in spinach chloroplastsPlant Cell Physiol.221981867880 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0085"><text><SENT sid="29056" pm="."><plain>17GiannopolitisC.N.RiesS.K.Superoxide dismutase I. Occurrence in higher plantsPlant Physiol59197730931416659839 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0090"><text><SENT sid="29058" pm="."><plain>18KochevaK.V.GeorgievG.I.KochevV.K.A diffusion approach to the electrolyte leakage from plant tissuesPhysiol Plant125200519 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0095"><text><SENT sid="29059" pm="."><plain>19BlumA.EberconA.Cell membrane stability as a measure of drought and heat tolerance in wheatCrop Sci2119814347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0100"><text><SENT sid="29060" pm="."><plain>20AlexievaV.SergievI.MapelliS.KaranovE.The effect of drought and ultraviolet radiation on growth and stress markers in pea and wheatPlant Cell Environ24200113371344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0105"><text><SENT sid="29061" pm="."><plain>21ChomczynskiP.MackeyK.DrewsR.WilfingerW.DNAzol: a reagent for the rapid isolation of zgenomic DNABiotechniques2219975505539067036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0110"><text><SENT sid="29062" pm="."><plain>22FuminoriK.TakumiS.EgawaC.IshibashiM.NakamuraC.Expression pattern of the low temperature responsive genes in a dominant ABA-less-sensitive mutant of common wheatPhysiol Plant1272006612623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0115"><text><SENT sid="29063" pm="."><plain>23SnedecorW.CochranG.Statistical methods7th ed1980The Lowa State University PressAmes, IA </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0120"><text><SENT sid="29064" pm="."><plain>24SayarR.BchiniH.MosbahiM.KhemiraH.Response of durum wheat (Triticum durum Desf.) growth to salt and drought stresses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29065" pm="."><plain>Czech J GenetPlant Breed4620105463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0125"><text><SENT sid="29066" pm="."><plain>25SankarB.JaleelC.A.ManivannanP.KishorekumarA.SomasundaramR.PanneerselvamR.Drought induced biochemical modifications and proline metabolism in Abelmoschus esculentus (L)Moench Acta Bot Croat6620074356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0130"><text><SENT sid="29067" pm="."><plain>26MonclusR.DreyerE.VillaM.DelmotteF.M.DelayD.PetitJ.-M.Impact of drought on productivity and water use efficiency in 29 genotypes of Populus deltoids3Populus nigraNew Phytologist169200676577716441757 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0135"><text><SENT sid="29068" pm="."><plain>27LevittJ.Response of plants to environmental stresses: chilling, freezing and high temperature stresses1980Academic PressNew York </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0140"><text><SENT sid="29069" pm="."><plain>28FilippouP.ChrystallaA.VasileiosF.Effect of drought and rewatering on the cellular status and antioxidant response of Medicago truncatula plantsPlant Sign Behav62011270277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0145"><text><SENT sid="29070" pm="."><plain>29WangW.X.BarakT.VinocurB.ShoseyovO.AltmanA.Abiotic resistance and chaperones: possible physiological role of SP1, a stable and stabilizing protein from PopulusVasilI.K.Plant biotechnology2000DordrechtKluwer439443 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0150"><text><SENT sid="29071" pm="."><plain>30BowlerC.FluhrR.The role of calcium and activated oxygens as signals for controlling cross-toleranceTrends Plant Sci5200024124610838614 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0155"><text><SENT sid="29072" pm="."><plain>31NoctorG.S.Veljovic-JovanovicS.DriscollL.NovitskayaV.FoyerC.H.Drought and oxidative load in the leaves of C3 plants: a predominant role for photorespirationAnn Bot89200284185012102510 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0160"><text><SENT sid="29073" pm="."><plain>32RiveroR.M.KojimaM.GepsteinA.SakakibaraH.MittlerR.GepsteinS.Delayed leaf senescence induces extreme drought tolerance in a flowering plantProc Nat Acad Sci USA1042007196311963618048328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0165"><text><SENT sid="29074" pm="."><plain>33MittlerR.Oxidative stress, antioxidants and stress toleranceTrends Plant Sci7200240541012234732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0170"><text><SENT sid="29075" pm="."><plain>34KovalchukI.Multiple roles of radicles in plantsDutta Gupta SEd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29076" pm="."><plain>Reactive oxygen species and antioxidants in higher plants2010CRC Press3144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0175"><text><SENT sid="29077" pm="."><plain>35BenesovaM.HolaD.FischerL.JedelskyP.L.HnilickaF.The physiology and proteomics of drought tolerance in maize: early stomatal closure as a cause of lower tolerance to short-term dehydration?Plos One72012e3801722719860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0180"><text><SENT sid="29078" pm="."><plain>36CloseT.FentonR.MoonanF.A view of plant dehydrates using antibodies specific to carboxyl terminal peptidePlant Mol Biol2319932792867693020 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0185"><text><SENT sid="29079" pm="."><plain>37LopezC.G.BanowetzG.M.PetersonC.J.KronstadW.E.Differential accumulation of a 24-kd dehydrin protein in wheat seedlings correlates with drought stress tolerance at grain fillingHereditas135200117518112152331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0190"><text><SENT sid="29080" pm="."><plain>38HaraM.ShinodaY.TanakaY.KuboiT.DNA binding of citrus dehydrin promoted by zinc ionPlant Cell Environ32200953254119183287 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0195"><text><SENT sid="29081" pm="."><plain>39HaraM.TerashimaS.FukayaT.KuboiT.Enhancement of cold tolerance and inhibition of lipid peroxidation by citrus dehydrin in transgenic tobaccoPlanta217200329029812783337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0200"><text><SENT sid="29082" pm="."><plain>40ZhangJ.H.JiaW.S.YangJ.C.IsmailA.M.Role of ABA in integrating plant responses to drought and salt stressesField Crops Res972006111119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0205"><text><SENT sid="29083" pm="."><plain>41KurahashiY.TerashimaA.TakumiS.Variation in dehydration tolerance, ABA sensitivity and related gene expression patterns in D-genome progenitor and synthetic hexaploid wheat linesInt J Mol Sci1020092733275119582226 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0210"><text><SENT sid="29084" pm="."><plain>42SakumaY.MaruyamaK.OsakabeY.QinF.SekiM.ShinozakiK.Functional analysis of an arabidopsis transcription factor, DREB2A, involved in drought- responsive gene expressionPlant Cell1820061292130916617101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0215"><text><SENT sid="29085" pm="."><plain>43QinF.KakimotoM.SakumaY.MaruyamaK.OsakabeY.Phan TranL.S.Regulation and functional analysis of ZmDREB2A in response to drought and heat stresses in Zea mays LPlant J502007546917346263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0220"><text><SENT sid="29086" pm="."><plain>44KobayashiF.IshibashiM.TakumiS.Transcriptional activation of Cor/Lea genes and increase in abiotic stress tolerance through expression of a wheat DREB2 homolog in transgenic tobaccoTransgenic Res17200875576718034365 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0225"><text><SENT sid="29087" pm="."><plain>45MorranS.EiniO.PyvovarenkoT.ParentB.SinghR.IsmagulA.Improvement of stress tolerance of wheat and barley by modulation of expression of DREB/CBF factorsPlant Biotechnol J9201123024920642740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0230"><text><SENT sid="29088" pm="."><plain>46EgawaC.KobayashiF.IshibashiM.NakamuraT.NakamuraC.TakumiS.Differential regulation of transcript accumulation and alternative splicing of a DREB2 homolog under abiotic stress conditions in common wheatGene Genet Syst8120067791 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0235"><text><SENT sid="29089" pm="."><plain>47ChenY.ChenP.de los ReyesB.Differential responses of the cultivated and wild species of soybean to dehydration stressCrop Sci46200620412046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0240"><text><SENT sid="29090" pm="."><plain>48BattagliaM.Olvera-Carrillo GarciarrubioA.CamposF.CovarrubiasA.A.The enigmatic LEA proteins and other hydrophilinsPlant Physiol148200862418772351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0245"><text><SENT sid="29091" pm="."><plain>49MochidaK.YoshidaT.SakuraiT.Yamaguchi-ShinozakiK.ShinozakiK.TranL.S.P.In silico analysis of transcription factor repertoire and prediction of stress responsive transcription factors in soybeanDNA Res16200935336919884168 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0250"><text><SENT sid="29092" pm="."><plain>50VinocurB.AltmanA.Recent advances in engineering plant tolerance to abiotic stress: achievements and limitationsCurr Opin Biotechnol16200512313215831376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0255"><text><SENT sid="29093" pm="."><plain>51LataC.PrasadM.Role of DREBs in regulation of abiotic stress responses in plantsJ Exp Bot6220114731474821737415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="d32e2163"><p><text><SENT sid="29094" pm="."><plain>Peer review under responsibility of Cairo University. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29095" pm="."><plain> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="29096" pm="."><plain>Semi-quantitative RT-PCR of dhn (A), wcor (B) and dreb (C) of two wheat cultivars (Sids and Gmiza) as a result of drought by withholding water. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29097" pm="."><plain>(1) Quantification of expression in terms of band volumes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29098" pm="."><plain>(2) The relative expression in the bands of each treatment after normalization with the internal control 18S rRNA compared to the control treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29099" pm="."><plain>C, control; D, drought; g, Gmiza; s, Sids; R, rehydrating. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f0020"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="29100" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the deduced amino acids of Tadhn with the most closely related DHNs from wheat (T. aesitivum, wcor726, U73213), (T. aestivum wdhn, FN393741), (dhn14, AB272228), (Lophopyrum elongatum dehydrin, AF031250), (T. aestivum rab15B, X62476) and (T. turgidum subsp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29101" pm="."><plain>Durum dhn5, AM180933). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f0025"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="29102" pm="."><plain>Alignment of the deduced amino acids of wcor with the most closely related DHNs from wheat (T. aesitivum, wcor410c, U73211), (T. turgidum subsp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29103" pm="."><plain>Durum dhn11, AJ890140), (T. aesitivum wcor410b, U73210), (T. aesitivum wzy1-2, EU124658), (Hordeum vulgare dehydrin, AF181458) and (Oryza sativa SK3-type dehydrin, EF444534). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag></floats-group></article>
