<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6750</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4570255</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">203</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12896-015-0203-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="32591" pm="."><plain>Construction of polyomavirus-derived pseudotype virus-like particles displaying a functionally active neutralizing antibody against hepatitis B virus surface antigen </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pleckaityte</surname><given-names>Milda</given-names></name><address><email>milda.pleckaityte@bti.vu.lt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>Corinna M.</given-names></name><address><email>Corinna.Bremer@viro.med.uni-giessen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gedvilaite</surname><given-names>Alma</given-names></name><address><email>alma.gedvilaite@bti.vu.lt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kucinskaite-Kodze</surname><given-names>Indre</given-names></name><address><email>indre.kodze@bti.vu.lt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Glebe</surname><given-names>Dieter</given-names></name><address><email>Dieter.Glebe@viro.med.uni-giessen.de</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Zvirbliene</surname><given-names>Aurelija</given-names></name><address><email>azvirb@ibt.lt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Immunology and Cell Biology, Institute of Biotechnology, Vilnius University, Graciuno 8, LT-02241 Vilnius, Lithuania </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Institute of Medical Virology, National Reference Centre for Hepatitis B and D Viruses, German Centre for Infection Research, Justus-Liebig University of Giessen, Schubertstrasse 81, 35392 Giessen, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>85</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>5</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Pleckaityte et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="32592" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="32593" pm="."><plain>Virus-like particles (VLPs) can be efficiently produced by heterologous expression of viral structural proteins in yeast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32594" pm="."><plain>Due to their repetitive structure, VLPs are extensively used for protein engineering and generation of chimeric VLPs with inserted foreign epitopes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32595" pm="."><plain>Hamster polyomavirus VP1 represents a promising epitope carrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32596" pm="."><plain>However, insertion of large sized protein sequences may interfere with its self-assembly competence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32597" pm="."><plain>The co-expression of polyomavirus capsid protein VP1 with minor capsid protein VP2 or its fusion protein may result in pseudotype VLPs where an intact VP1 protein mediates VLP formation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32598" pm="."><plain>In the current study, the capacity of VP1 protein to self-assemble to VLPs and interact with the modified VP2 protein has been exploited to generate pseudotype VLPs displaying large-sized antibody molecules. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="32599" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="32600" pm="."><plain>Polyomavirus-derived pseudotype VLPs harbouring a surface-exposed functionally active neutralizing antibody specific to hepatitis B virus (HBV) surface antigen (HBsAg) have been generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32601" pm="."><plain>The pseudotype VLPs consisting of an intact hamster polyomavirus (HaPyV) major capsid protein VP1 and minor capsid protein VP2 fused with the anti-HBsAg molecule were efficiently produced in yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae and purified by density-gradient centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32602" pm="."><plain>Formation of VLPs was confirmed by electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32603" pm="."><plain>Two types of pseudotype VLPs were generated harbouring either the single-chain fragment variable (scFv) or Fc-engineered scFv on the VLP surface. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32604" pm="."><plain>The antigen-binding activity of the purified pseudotype VLPs was evaluated by ELISA and virus-neutralization assay on HBV-susceptible primary hepatocytes from Tupaia belangeri. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32605" pm="."><plain>Both types of the pseudotype VLPs were functionally active and showed a potent HBV-neutralizing activity comparable to that of the parental monoclonal antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32606" pm="."><plain>The VP2-fused scFv molecules were incorporated into the VLPs with higher efficiency as compared to the VP2-fused Fc-scFv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32607" pm="."><plain>However, the pseudotype VLPs with displayed VP2-fused Fc-scFv molecule showed higher antigen-binding activity and HBV-neutralizing capacity that might be explained by a better accessibility of the Fc-engineered scFv of the VLP surface. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="32608" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="32609" pm="."><plain>Polyomavirus-derived pseudotype VLPs harbouring multiple functionally active antibody molecules with virus-neutralizing capability may represent a novel platform for developing therapeutic tools with a potential application for post-exposure or therapeutic treatment of viral infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="32610" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32611" pm="."><plain>Viral structural proteins produced by heterologous expression may have the intrinsic ability to spontaneously self-assemble into highly organized particles – virus-like particles (VLPs) – that morphologically resemble viral capsid and represent a promising tool for protein engineering. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32612" pm="."><plain>The simplest VLPs are composed of a single viral structural protein, such as the assembly-competent envelope or capsid protein [1–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32613" pm="."><plain>More complex recombinant VLPs can be generated by either genetic fusion or co-expression of the VLPs with an additional target protein or its segment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32614" pm="."><plain>The co-expression of the assembly-competent viral structural protein with another viral structural protein or its fusion protein results in so-called pseudotype VLPs [3, 5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32615" pm="."><plain>Previous studies show that the major capsid protein VP1 of different polyomaviruses can be efficiently produced in yeast expression system in a form of VLPs [6] consisting of 72 pentamers of the VP1 protein [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32616" pm="."><plain>Hamster polyomavirus (HaPyV) VP1 protein has been exploited for the generation of either chimeric VLPs harbouring foreign epitopes, or pseudotype VLPs when co-expressed with the minor capsid protein VP2 that binds within the central 5-fold cavity of each VP1 pentamer [8–11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32617" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it was demonstrated that HaPyV-derived pseudotype VLPs represent an efficient carrier for functionally active complex molecules, such as antibodies [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32618" pm="."><plain>In these pseudotype VLPs, an intact VP1 protein is functioning as a carrier mediating VLP formation of both VP1 and the modified VP2 protein molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32619" pm="."><plain>The C-terminal part of VP2 protein is necessary for its interaction with VP1 pentamer, therefore, the VP2 N-terminus can be shortened and used to join target molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32620" pm="."><plain>The ratio of VP1:VP2 proteins in HaPyV capsid is 360:72 [7], consequently up to 72 chimeric VP2 molecules harbouring target molecules might be incorporated into one VLP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32621" pm="."><plain>Based on the structure of polyomavirus capsids [13, 14], it was predicted that the inserted target sequence can be displayed on the surface of pseudotype VLPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32622" pm="."><plain>In contrast to chimeric VLPs that do not tolerate long inserts, this approach allowed efficient presentation of large-sized foreign protein sequences as demonstrated for the full-length human tumor-associated antigen Her2 [15, 16], prostate-specific antigen [17], green fluorescent protein [18], cellular marker p16INK4A [19] and the antibody molecule [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32623" pm="."><plain>The first example of a successful expression of a large recombinant antibody molecule on the surface of VLPs was generation of HaPyV-derived pseudotype VLPs harbouring the Fc-engineered single-chain antibody (scFv-Fc) specific to bacterial cytolysin vaginolysin (VLY). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32624" pm="."><plain>In this study, the scFv derived from hybridoma cell line producing high-affinity neutralizing antibody against VLY [20] was fused with human IgG1 Fc domain comprising the CH2 and CH3 domains and the hinge region [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32625" pm="."><plain>To join the scFv-Fc molecule, the N-terminus of VP2 protein was deleted and replaced by the scFv-Fc molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32626" pm="."><plain>It was demonstrated that the VLY-specific scFv-Fc fused with HaPyV VP2 protein and co-expressed with VP1 protein in the form of pseudotype VLPs was properly folded and exhibited a strong VLY-binding activity comparable to that of the parental monoclonal antibody (MAb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32627" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the attempts to produce non-tagged, hexahistidine-tagged and alpha factor-tagged scFv-Fc proteins in yeast were unsuccessful due to their low yield, instability and a tendency to form insoluble aggregates [12, 22–24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32628" pm="."><plain>Therefore, an approach to display multiple functionally active antibody molecules on the surface of pseudotype VLPs that can be easily purified by density-gradient centrifugation may provide a promising alternative to other currently available methods for producing recombinant antibodies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32629" pm="."><plain>In the current study, we describe generation of polyomavirus-derived pseudotype VLPs harbouring surface-exposed scFv and scFv-Fc molecules specific to hepatitis B virus surface antigen (HBsAg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32630" pm="."><plain>To our knowledge, this is the first example of pseudotype VLPs with an anti-viral activity. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="32631" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="32632" pm="."><plain>Generation in yeast of recombinant proteins harbouring anti-HBsAg molecule </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32633" pm="."><plain>To generate pseudotype VLPs with surface-exposed HBsAg-specific antibody molecule, the gene encoding anti-HBsAg was fused with gene encoding modified HaPyV minor capsid protein VP2 and co-expressed together with the gene encoding HaPyV major capsid protein VP1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32634" pm="."><plain>To join the anti-HBsAg molecule, the N-terminus of the VP2 protein was truncated by 100 amino acid (aa) residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32635" pm="."><plain>The production of both HaPyV VP1 protein and the modified VP2 protein was induced by adding galactose into yeast growth medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32636" pm="."><plain>Anti-HbsAg scFv comprising variable regions of mouse IgG in the orientation of VL-(G4S)4-VH was derived from the in-house produced hybridoma HB1 secreting neutralizing MAb against HBsAg (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32637" pm="."><plain>The cDNA sequences encoding VH and VL regions of anti-HBsAg MAb were deposited in GenBank under accession numbers KP972453 and KP972454. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32638" pm="."><plain>Two recombinant proteins harbouring HBsAg-specific antibody molecule were produced in yeast S. cerevisiae strain AH22-214p: one carrying the scFv-Fc molecule and one carrying the scFv without the Fc part (Table 1, Fig. 1).Table 1The list of recombinant plasmids for the expression of pseudotype VLPs in yeast S. cerevisiae PlasmidProteinShort namepFGG3-VP1/VP2-Fc-scFvVP1/scFv-Fc-VP2Construct #1pFGG3-VP1/VP2-scFvVP1/scFv-VP2Construct #2Fig. 1Schematic representation of recombinant proteins harbouring anti-HBsAg molecule </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32639" pm="."><plain>After induction of the synthesis of recombinant proteins, the lysates of harvested yeast cells were examined by SDS-PAGE to evaluate the expression of VP1 and the scFv-Fc-VP2 fused proteins and then subjected to ultracentrifugation on sucrose density gradient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32640" pm="."><plain>The analysis of partially purified recombinant proteins VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 and VP1/scFv-VP2 (constructs #1, #2) by SDS-PAGE revealed a protein band of approximately 42 kDa that was identified as an intact VP1 protein (Fig. 2, the position indicated by an asterisk). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32641" pm="."><plain>Protein band of 78.4 kDa corresponding to the molecular mass of scFv-Fc-VP2 fusion protein was detected in the construct #1 (Fig. 2, the position indicated by an arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32642" pm="."><plain>Protein band of 52.5 kDa corresponding to the molecular mass of scFv-VP2 fusion protein was detected in the construct #2 (Fig. 2, the position indicated by an arrow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32643" pm="."><plain>As demonstrated by SDS-PAGE, the yield of recombinant proteins after the first purification step was similar and varied from 0.3 to 0.5 mg from 1 g of wet yeast biomass. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32644" pm="."><plain>The constructs #1 and #2 did not differ significantly in the expression levels of an intact VP1 protein.Fig. 2Analysis of recombinant proteins (constructs #1 and #2) partially purified on sucrose gradient by SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32645" pm="."><plain>The asterisk indicates the position of VP1 protein; the arrow indicates the position of VP2-fused protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32646" pm="."><plain>Prestained protein weight marker (Thermo Fisher Scientific) is presented on the right of each panel </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="32647" pm="."><plain>Purification and electron microscopy analysis of recombinant proteins harbouring anti-HBsAg molecule </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32648" pm="."><plain>HaPyV-derived recombinant proteins VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 (construct #1) and VP1/scFv-VP2 (construct #2) were successfully purified by the method adapted for the purification of VLPs using CsCl density centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32649" pm="."><plain>The analysis of purified recombinant proteins by SDS-PAGE revealed the expected homogenous protein bands of 78.4 kDa and 42 kDa in case of construct #1 (Fig. 3a, lane 1) and homogenous protein bands of 52.5 kDa and 42 kDa in case of construct #2 (Fig. 3a, lane 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32650" pm="."><plain>Western blot with the HaPyV VP1-specific MAb 3D10 immunostained the 42 kDa protein band in both constructs #1 and #2 thus confirming the identity of the VP1 protein (Fig. 3b, lanes 1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32651" pm="."><plain>As a positive control for Western blot with VP1-specific MAb 3D10, the construct consisting of an intact HaPyV VP1 protein and the VP2 fuse with green fluorescent protein (eGFP) was used (VP1/GFP-VP2, Fig. 3b, lane 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32652" pm="."><plain>Western blot with HRP-labelled anti-human IgG antibody immunostained the 78.4 kDa band present in construct #1 thus confirming the identity of scFv-Fc-VP2 fusion protein (Fig. 3c, lane 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32653" pm="."><plain>No specific staining was obtained with construct #2 lacking the Fc part of human IgG (Fig. 3C, lane 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32654" pm="."><plain>As a positive control for Western blot with anti-human IgG, purified human IgG was used (Fig. 3C, lane 4).Fig. 3Analysis of recombinant constructs VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 (construct #1, lane 1) and VP1/scFv-VP2 (construct #2, lane 2) purified on CsCl gradient by SDS-PAGE (a) and Western blot with the MAb 3D10 (b) and anti-human IgG antibody (c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32655" pm="."><plain>Protein band corresponding to MW of 78.4 kDa represents scFv-VP2 fused protein (lane 1), protein band of 52.5 kDa represents scFv-VP2 fused protein (lane 2) and protein band of 42 kDa represents VP1 protein (lanes 1–3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32656" pm="."><plain>The construct VP1/GFP-VP2 (lane 3) and purified human IgG (lane 4) are used as positive controls for Western blot </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32657" pm="."><plain>As calculated from the SDS-PAGE with subsequent densitometry analysis, the VP1: scFv-Fc-VP2 ratio (w/w) in the VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 (construct #1) is approximately 13:1, while the ratio the VP1: scFv-VP2 (w/w) in the VP1/scFv-VP2 (construct #2) is approximately 6:1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32658" pm="."><plain>Based on the molecular weight (MW) of the VP2-fused proteins (78.4 kDa and 52.5 kDa, respectively), the calculated average number of the scFv-Fc-VP2 fused protein per one pseudotype VLP was 14 (construct #1), while the calculated number of the scFv-VP2 fused protein per one pseudotype VLP was 46 (construct #2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32659" pm="."><plain>The purified recombinant proteins were negatively stained and subjected to electron microscopy (EM) analysis that confirmed an efficient self-assembly of both recombinant proteins to VLPs (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32660" pm="."><plain>The pseudotype VLPs were approx. 45–50 nm in diameter, which corresponds to the size of intact HaPyV capsids and the unmodified recombinant HaPyV VP1-derived VLPs [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32662" pm="."><plain>The size and shape of VP1/scFv-Fc- VP2 pseudotype VLPs (A) and VP1/scFv-VP2 pseudotype VLPs (B) were similar to that of VP1/GFP-VP2 pseudotype VLPs used as a positive control (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32663" pm="."><plain>The purified pseudotype VLPs were further analysed for the HBsAg-binding activity and the ability to neutralize HBV.Fig. 4Electron microscopy pictures of CsCl-purified pseudotype VLPs stained with 2 % aqueous uranyl acetate solution and analysed by Morgagni 268 electron microscope. a, VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 pseudotype VLPs (construct #1); b, VP1/scFv-VP2 pseudotype VLPs (construct #2), c, VP1/GFP-VP2 pseudotype VLPs (control). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32664" pm="."><plain>Scale bar – 100 nm </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="32665" pm="."><plain>HBV-neutralizing activity of pseudotype VLPs harbouring anti-HBsAg molecule </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32666" pm="."><plain>Antigen-binding activity of the purified pseudotype VLPs was confirmed by an indirect ELISA using recombinant yeast-derived HBsAg (ayw) coated on the microtiter plate and the HaPyV VP1-specific MAb 3D10 as a detection antibody. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32667" pm="."><plain>Both anti-HBsAg fused proteins displayed on the respective pseudotype VLPs were reactive with the immobilized HBsAg (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32668" pm="."><plain>The scFv-Fc-VP2 fused protein (construct #1) showed antigen-binding activity in a similar concentration range (starting from 1.5 × 10−12 M) as the parental MAb HB1 used as a positive control (starting from 0.7 × 10−12 M). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32669" pm="."><plain>Meanwhile, the scFv-VP2 fused protein (construct #2) was reactive with the plate-bound HBsAg when added at concentrations exceeding 24 × 10−12 M. The VP1/GFP-VP2 pseudotype VLPs used as a negative control did not show any reactivity with the immobilized antigen, which confirms the specificity of the ELISA (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32671" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the ability of the purified pseudotype VLPs to neutralize HBV was assayed in vitro using the HBV infection model of primary Tupaia hepatocytes (PTH) [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32672" pm="."><plain>The neutralizing potency of the pseudotype VLPs was evaluated in comparison to the parental monoclonal antibody HB1 used as a positive control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32673" pm="."><plain>The pseudotype VLPs were used at amounts that correspond to 0.5 μg/mL to 8 μg/mL of the anti-HBsAg fused proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32674" pm="."><plain>The VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 pseudotype VLPs containing the Fc part of human IgG1 (construct #1) showed higher HBV-neutralizing potency as compared to VP1/scFv-VP2 pseudotype VLPs (construct #2): 1 μg/mL (1.27 × 10−10 M) of scFv-Fc-VP2 fused protein displayed on the pseudotype VLPs (construct #1) were sufficient to induce complete HBV neutralization while 1 μg/mL (1.9 × 10−10 M) of the scFv-VP2 fused protein displayed on the pseudotype VLPs (construct #2) induced only partial HBV neutralization (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32675" pm="."><plain>The observed HBV-neutralizing potency of the pseudotype VLPs VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 (construct #1) containing 1 μg/mL (1.27 × 10−10 M) of scFv-Fc-VP2 fused protein was comparable to that obtained with 1 μg /mL (0.67 × 10−10 M) of the full-length parental MAb HB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32676" pm="."><plain>The specificity of the neutralization test was confirmed by the use of HaPyV-derived VP1/GFP-VP2 pseudotype VLPs (negative control) that did not induce HBV neutralization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32677" pm="."><plain>The incomplete HBV neutralization by the construct #2 harbouring the scFv without the Fc part might indicate that the scFv molecule is less accessible on the surface of pseudotype VLPs as compared to the Fc-engineered scFv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32678" pm="."><plain>The results of the HBV-neutralization test are consistent with the results of an indirect ELISA (Fig. 5) where the scFv-Fc-VP2 fused protein displayed on the VLPs showed higher antigen-binding activity as compared to the scFv-VP2 fused protein.Fig. 5HBsAg-binding activity of pseudotype VLPs harbouring anti-HBsAg molecules determined by ELISA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32679" pm="."><plain>Concentrations (pM) of anti-HBsAg fused proteins scFv-Fc-VP2 and scFv-VP2 displayed on the respective pseudotype VLPs are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32680" pm="."><plain>As a positive control, full-length parental MAb HB1 is used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32681" pm="."><plain>As a negative control, VP1/GFP-VP2 pseudotype VLPs are usedFig. 6HBV-neutralizing activity of pseudotype VLPs harbouring anti-HBsAg molecule in comparison to the full length parental antibody (MAb). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32682" pm="."><plain>Concentrations (μg/mL) of anti-HBsAg fused proteins scFv-Fc-VP2 and scFv-VP2 displayed on the respective pseudotype VLPs (construct #1 and construct #2) are indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32683" pm="."><plain>Highly purified HBV was preincubated with the indicated quantities of the respective proteins for 1 h at 16 °C and afterwards added to PTHs for 16 h at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32684" pm="."><plain>As a negative control, VP1/GFP-VP2 at concentration 8 μg/mL is used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32685" pm="."><plain>Newly produced HBsAg of infected PTH cultures was determined on day 11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32686" pm="."><plain>The red line indicates the Cut-off </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="32687" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32688" pm="."><plain>Recombinant VLPs are extensively used for various applications, from basic virus assembly and structure studies to the production of human and animal vaccines [3–5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32689" pm="."><plain>Due to their repetitive structure, VLPs represent an efficient carrier for B and T cell epitopes [4, 8, 10, 11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32690" pm="."><plain>Presentation of large protein sequences on VLPs may broaden the spectrum of potential VLP applications, however the long-sized inserts may interfere with the self-assembly competence of the viral carrier protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32691" pm="."><plain>To overcome this problem, pseudotype VLPs composed of different viral proteins can be generated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32692" pm="."><plain>In the current study, the capacity of HaPyV-derived major capsid protein VP1 to self-assemble to VLPs and interact with the modified minor capsid protein VP2 has been exploited to generate pseudotype VLPs with surface-exposed multiple anti-HBsAg molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32693" pm="."><plain>The pseudotype VLPs expressed in yeast and purified by density-gradient centrifugation were functionally active and showed a potent HBsAg-binding and HBV-neutralizing activity comparable to that of the parental MAb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32694" pm="."><plain>The produced pseudotype VLPs harbouring surface-exposed anti-HBsAg molecules is the first example of anti-viral VLPs with virus-neutralizing capability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32695" pm="."><plain>This approach may be further exploited to develop novel anti-viral tools for a post-exposure treatment of viral infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32696" pm="."><plain>Prevention of clinical disease in individuals already exposed to viral infection is an important issue of modern biomedicine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32697" pm="."><plain>Recent advances in passive immunoprophylaxis of viral infections, such as rabies and human respiratory syncytial virus infection, are based on monoclonal antibody therapies [26, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32698" pm="."><plain>The in vivo studies have demonstrated the efficiency of neutralizing antibodies in established infections of influenza A, HIV, polioviruses, filoviruses and other viral infections [28–30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32699" pm="."><plain>The VLP approach combining the advantages of virus targeting by the surface-exposed antibody molecule and the capability of VLPs to encapsidate and deliver cargo, such as therapeutic nucleic acids or proteins [31, 32] may provide new possibilities for the potential development of effective anti-viral prophylactic and therapeutic strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32700" pm="."><plain>The current study demonstrates that antigen-binding capability of the pseudotype VLPs depends on the structure of the antibody molecule displayed on the VLPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32701" pm="."><plain>The anti-HBsAg molecule was presented on the VP2 protein in two different formats – either scFv alone or Fc-engineered scFv comprising CH2 and CH3 domains and the hinge region of human IgG1 [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32702" pm="."><plain>The calculations based on the SDS-PAGE and densitometry data indicate that the VP2 protein fused with 473 aa-long scFv was incorporated into the pseudotype VLPs with higher efficiency (approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32703" pm="."><plain>46 molecules per VLP in construct #2) as compared to 723 aa–long Fc-scFv (approx. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32704" pm="."><plain>14 molecules per VLP in construct #1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32705" pm="."><plain>However, construct #2 containing 3 times higher amount of anti-HBsAg scFv molecules showed much lower HBsAg-binding activity in ELISA and HBV-neutralizing potency in the in vitro HBV infection assay as compared to construct #1 harbouring Fc-engineered scFv molecules. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32706" pm="."><plain>The observed difference might be explained by a better accessibility of the Fc-engineered scFvs on the surface of VLPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32707" pm="."><plain>The quantity of anti-HBsAg molecules incorporated into the pseudotype VLPs of our study (14 anti-HBsAg Fc-scFv-VP2 molecules per one VLP) is consistent with a previous report where approx. 19 molecules of anti-VLY Fc-scFv-VP2 molecules were found to be displayed the pseudotype VLP [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32709" pm="."><plain>Based on the resolved crystal structures of the virions of SV-40 and murine polyomavirus, a maximum of 72 VP2 molecules could be incorporated into one pseudotype VLPs as this corresponds to the number of VP1 protein pentamers that compose the VLP [7, 13, 14]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32710" pm="."><plain>The current study clearly demonstrates that the number of large fusion proteins to be incorporated into a pseudotype VLP may vary according to the actual size of the modified VP2 molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32711" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the pseudotype VLPs harbouring multiple virus-neutralizing antibody molecules may represent a promising platform for therapeutic vaccines against acute or chronic viral infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32712" pm="."><plain>In case of HBV, construction of pseudotype VLPs combining different neutralizing antibodies directed against both HBsAg and preS1 sequences [33, 34] might provide a potent anti-viral tool with a broad HBV-neutralizing capacity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32713" pm="."><plain>For human use, the scFvs derived from human MAbs would be of special interest [34] to avoid their enhanced immunogenicity after presentation on pseudotype VLPs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion"><title><text><SENT sid="32714" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32715" pm="."><plain>The current study demonstrates that HaPyV-derived pseudotype VLPs are suitable carriers for antibody molecules, both in the format of scFv and Fc-scFv. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32716" pm="."><plain>The pseudotype VLPs harbouring the Fc-scFv-VP2 molecule show higher antigen-binding activity and virus-neutralizing potency as compared to those harbouring the scFv-VP2 molecule. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32717" pm="."><plain>This difference might be explained by a more efficient exposure of the Fc-engineered scFv molecule on the surface of the pseudotype VLPs as compared to the scFv molecule. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32718" pm="."><plain>The produced pseudotype VLPs harbouring surface-exposed anti-HBsAg molecules is the first example of anti-viral VLPs with virus-neutralizing capability. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32719" pm="."><plain>The pseudotype VLPs harbouring multiple functionally active antibody molecules with virus-neutralizing capability represents a novel platform for the construction of therapeutic vaccines with a potential application for post-exposure or therapeutic treatment of viral infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32720" pm="."><plain>The VLP approach combining the advantages of virus targeting by the surface-exposed antibody molecule and the capability of VLPs to encapsidate and deliver cargo, such as therapeutic nucleic acids or proteins, might be further exploited for the development of novel efficient anti-viral strategies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="32721" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="32722" pm="."><plain>Construction of HBsAg-specific single-chain fragment variable (scFv) </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32723" pm="."><plain>All DNA manipulations were carried out according to standard procedures [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32724" pm="."><plain>Enzymes and kits for DNA manipulations were purchased from Thermo Fisher Scientific (Vilnius, Lithuania). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32725" pm="."><plain>The anti-HBsAg scFv comprising variable regions of mouse IgG heavy (VH) [GenBank: KP972453] and light chains (VL) [GenBank: KP972454] in the orientation of VL-linker-VH was cloned and constructed as described previously [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32726" pm="."><plain>Briefly, total mRNA was isolated from 3 × 106 hybridoma cells (clone HB1) using GeneJET RNA Purification Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to manufacturer’s recommendations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32727" pm="."><plain>Hybridoma clone HB1 was produced in-house using spleen cells of BALB/c mouse immunized with recombinant HBsAg (unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32728" pm="."><plain>The first strand of cDNA was prepared using RevertAid™ H Minus First Strand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific) according to manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32729" pm="."><plain>The cDNA corresponding to the variable regions of mouse IgG VH and VL was obtained by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using sets of specific primers described previously [12, 36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32730" pm="."><plain>In the second PCR round, the VL and VH DNA fragments were fused to yield the construction VL-(G4S)4-VH. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="32731" pm="."><plain>Construction of yeast expression plasmids </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32732" pm="."><plain>The anti-HBsAg scFv was displayed on the pseudotype VLPs either alone or fused with the Fc region of human immunoglobulin G1 encoded in pFUSE-hIgG1-Fc2 vector [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32733" pm="."><plain>The resulting construction obtained by fusion of anti-HBsAg scFv to human Fc region was named scFv-Fc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32734" pm="."><plain>Two yeast expression plasmids carrying either the scFv or scFv-Fc DNA fragment were generated (Table 1, constructs #1, #2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32735" pm="."><plain>The recombinants were screened in E. coli DH10B cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32736" pm="."><plain>The plasmid pFGG3-VP1/ VP2-Fc-scFv used for the co-expression of chimeric HaPyV-derived protein scFv-Fc-VP2 and the intact HaPyV VP1 protein (construct #1) were generated as described previously [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32737" pm="."><plain>The construct encodes scFv-Fc molecule that is joined at the N–terminus of the VP2 protein truncated by 100 amino acid (aa) residues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32738" pm="."><plain>The plasmid pFGG3-VP1/VP2-scFv encoding a similar construct without the Fc part (construct #2) was generated by cloning the scFv fragment into pFGG3-VP1/VP2Bg vector as described previously [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32739" pm="."><plain>The plasmid pFGG3-VP1/VP2-eGFP was generated by cloning DNA fragment encoding green-fluorescent protein into the blunted XbaI and BglII sites of pFGG3-VP1/VP2Bg vector for fusion to modified HaPyV VP2-encoding gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="32740" pm="."><plain>Yeast strains, growth media and cultivation conditions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32741" pm="."><plain>The constructed plasmids pFGG3-VP1/VP2-Fc-scFv and pFGG3-VP1/VP2-scFv (Table 1), and pFGG3-VP1/VP2-eGFP were used for the transformation of S. cerevisiae strain AH22-214p (a, leu2-3,112, his4-519, Δpep4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32742" pm="."><plain>Transformed yeast cells were cultivated as described previously [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32743" pm="."><plain>Yeast biomass containing recombinant proteins was harvested by centrifugation and stored at −20 °C until purification. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32744" pm="."><plain>Yeast S. cerevisiae transformed with pFGG3 vector without any insert was used as a negative control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="32745" pm="."><plain>SDS-PAGE </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32746" pm="."><plain>Recombinant proteins were fractionated by electrophoresis on 12.5 % sodium dodecylsulfate-polyacrylamide gels (SDS-PAGE) and then either visualized by staining with Coomassie brilliant blue (Sigma–Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32747" pm="."><plain>The quantities of loaded recombinant proteins were determined by densitometry using the ImageScanner III (GE Healthcare, Little Chalfont, UK) device supplied with the ImageQuantTL software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32748" pm="."><plain>The determination of the quantities of VP1 and VP2-fused antibodies in the preparations of pseudotype VLPs was based on the comparison with the known quantities of VP1 and BSA proteins run in the same SDS-PAGE gel and scanned by the ImageScanner III. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32749" pm="."><plain>The molar quantities of VP1 and VP2-fused proteins in the samples of purified VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 and VP1/scFv-VP2 constructs were calculated in accordance with their molecular weight (MW). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32750" pm="."><plain>The average number of VP2-fused proteins presented on one VLP was calculated as described previously [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32751" pm="."><plain>Briefly, concentrations of purified pseudotype VLPs (mg/mL) were determined by Bradford assay [37] and the known quantities of each construct (1–3 μg per lane) were loaded on the SDS-PAGE gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32752" pm="."><plain>At least three scans of each VLP preparation were obtained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32753" pm="."><plain>The determined quantities of VP1 protein (μg per lane) and VP2-fused proteins (μg per lane) were calculated in pmoles and then the number of protein molecules in both analyzed VLP preparations were determined based on the Avogadro constant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32754" pm="."><plain>Assuming that 360 molecules of VP1 protein are needed for the assembly of one VLP [7] the calculated number of VP1 molecules was divided by 360 to determine the number of VLPs in the respective VLP preparation (VP1/scFv-VP2 VLPs and VP1/scFv-Fc-VP2 VLPs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32755" pm="."><plain>The average number of VP2-fused molecules presented on one VLP was calculated by dividing the number of the respective VP2-fused molecules (scFv-VP2 and scFv-Fc-VP2) by the number of VLPs in the sample. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="32756" pm="."><plain>Western blot </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32757" pm="."><plain>Recombinant proteins fractionated by SDS-PAGE were electrotransferred to Immobilon P membrane (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32758" pm="."><plain>The membranes were blocked with 5 % milk powder in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) for 2 h at room temperature (RT) and rinsed in PBS with 1 % Tween-20 (PBST). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32759" pm="."><plain>For the detection of HaPyV VP1 protein, the membranes were incubated for 1 h at RT with monoclonal antibody (MAb) 3D10 [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32760" pm="."><plain>The MAb was used at working dilution 1:1000 in PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32761" pm="."><plain>The membranes were then incubated with horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-mouse IgG (Bio-Rad) diluted 1:1000 in PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32762" pm="."><plain>For the detection of scFv-Fc-VP2 fused protein, the membranes after blocking were incubated with HRP-conjugated rabbit anti-human IgG (Bio-Rad) diluted 1:2000 in PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32763" pm="."><plain>After rinsing in PBST, the enzymatic reaction was developed using tetramethylbenzidine (TMB) chromogenic substrate (Sigma–Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="32764" pm="."><plain>Purification of pseudotype VLPs harbouring scFv-Fc </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32765" pm="."><plain>S. cerevisiae yeast biomass containing recombinant proteins was suspended and homogenized in DB450 buffer (450 mM NaCl, 1 mM CaCl2, 0.001 % Trition X-100, 0.25 M L-Arginine in 10 mM Tris/HCl-buffer pH 7.2) containing 2 mM PMSF, EDTA-free Complete Protease Inhibitor Cocktail (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and mechanically disrupted using French press. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32766" pm="."><plain>After centrifugation of yeast lysate, the supernatant containing recombinant proteins was collected and subjected to the ultracentrifugation on 30–65 % sucrose gradient and subsequently on CsCl density gradient ranging to buoyant densities from 1.23 to 1.38 g/mL as described previously [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32767" pm="."><plain>The purified recombinant proteins were dialyzed against PBS and analysed by SDS-PAGE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="32768" pm="."><plain>Electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32769" pm="."><plain>The samples of purified recombinant proteins were placed on 400-mesh carbon coated palladium grids, negatively stained with 2 % aqueous uranyl acetate solution and examined by Morgagni 268 electron microscope (FEI Inc., Hillsboro, OR, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="32770" pm="."><plain>Indirect ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32771" pm="."><plain>Polystyrene microtiter plates (Nerbe plus, Winsen/Luhe, Germany) were coated with 100 μL per well of the recombinant HBsAg ayw (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) diluted in coating buffer (0.05 M sodium carbonate, pH 9.6) to a concentration of 5 μg/mL and incubated overnight at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32772" pm="."><plain>The coated plates were blocked with 2 % bovine serum albumin (BSA) for 1 h at RT and rinsed twice with PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32773" pm="."><plain>Recombinant pseudotype VLPs were serially diluted in PBST, added to the wells and incubated for 1 h at RT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32774" pm="."><plain>As a negative control, non-modified HaPyV VP1/VP2 VLPs were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32775" pm="."><plain>The plates were rinsed with PBST and incubated for 1 h with the MAb 3D10 diluted 1:1000 in PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32776" pm="."><plain>The plates were rinsed with PBST and then incubated for 1 h with HRP-conjugated rabbit anti-human IgG (Bio-Rad) diluted 1:1000 in PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32777" pm="."><plain>The plates were rinsed 5–7 times with PBST. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32778" pm="."><plain>Enzymatic reaction was visualized by the addition of 100 μL of ready-to-use TMB substrate (Sigma–Aldrich) to each well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32779" pm="."><plain>After 10 min of incubation at RT, the reaction was stopped by adding 50 μL/well of 10 % sulphuric acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32780" pm="."><plain>The optical density (OD) was measured at 450 nm (reference filter 620 nm) in a microplate reader (Tecan, Groedig, Austria). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="32781" pm="."><plain>HBV-neutralization assay on Tupaia hepatocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="32782" pm="."><plain>Neutralization test was performed as described previously [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32783" pm="."><plain>Briefly, VLPs were preincubated with serum-derived purified HBV (ID326, genotype D) at a ratio of 10 HBV genomes/hepatocyte for 1 h at 16 °C in Tupaia hepatocyte medium (THM) and later incubated on primary Tupaia belangeri hepatocyte cultures (PTHs) for 16 h at 37 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32784" pm="."><plain>As a positive control, the full-length MAb HB1 previously shown to exhibit the HBV-neutralizing activity in the in vitro assay was used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32785" pm="."><plain>As a negative control, irrelevant pseudotype VLPs harbouring green-fluorescent protein (VP1/GFP-VP2) were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32786" pm="."><plain>The HBV-neutralization potency of the pseudotype VLPs was evaluated by measuring the concentration of the newly produced HBsAg in the culture supernatant on day 11th after infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32787" pm="."><plain>Animals were handled in a full accordance with ethical requirements. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32788" pm="."><plain>Permission to use primary hepatocytes from Tupaia belangeri was obtained from the Institutional Review Board of Justus-Liebig University of Giessen. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="32789" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32790" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="32791" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32792" pm="."><plain>MP constructed the plasmids, produced and purified pseudotype VLPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32793" pm="."><plain>IK-K tested the antigen-binding activity of the VLPs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32794" pm="."><plain>CMB tested the neutralizing activity of the VLPs, AG contributed to the expression and purification of recombinant VLPs and DG contributed to the neutralization assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32795" pm="."><plain>AZ conceived of the study, drafted and finalized the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32796" pm="."><plain>All authors read, edited and approved the final version of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="32797" pm="."><plain>This research was funded by the European Social Fund under the Global Grant measure (Grant No. VPI-3.1-SMM-07-K-02-039). </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="32798" pm="."><plain>1.ValenzuelaPMedinaARutterWJAmmererGHallBDSynthesis and assembly of hepatitis B virus surface antigen particles in yeastNature19822983475010.1038/298347a07045698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="32799" pm="."><plain>2.HofmannKJCookJCJoyceJGBrownDRSchultzLDGeorgeHASequence determination of human papillomavirus type 6a and assembly of virus-like particles in Saccharomyces cerevisiaeVirology19952095061810.1006/viro.1995.12837778283 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="32800" pm="."><plain>3.PumpensPGrensEKhudyakovYEFieldsHAArtificial genes for chimeric virus-like particlesArtificial DNA: methods and applications2002Boca RatonCRC Press LLC249327 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="32801" pm="."><plain>4.ZeltinsAConstruction and characterization of virus-like particlesMol Biotechnol2013539210710.1007/s12033-012-9598-423001867 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="32802" pm="."><plain>5.PushkoPPumpensPGrensEDevelopment of virus-like particle technology from small highly symmetric to large complex virus-like particle structuresIntervirology2013561416510.1159/00034677323594863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="32803" pm="."><plain>6.SasnauskasKBuzaiteOVogelFJandrigBRazanskasRStaniulisJYeast cells allow the high-level expression and formation of polyomavirus-like particlesBiol Chem1999380381610.1515/BC.1999.05010223341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="32804" pm="."><plain>7.GriffithJPGriffithDLRaymentIMurakamiWTCasparDLInside polyomavirus at 25-Å resolutionNature1992355652410.1038/355652a01311415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="32805" pm="."><plain>8.GedvilaiteAFrommelCSasnauskasKBurkhardMOzelMBehrsingOFormation of immunogenic virus-like particles by inserting epitopes into surface-exposed regions of hamster major capsid proteinVirology2000273213510.1006/viro.2000.039210891404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="32806" pm="."><plain>9.GedvilaiteAZvirblieneAStaniulisJSasnauskasKKrügerDHUlrichRSegments of puumala hantavirus nucleocapsid protein inserted into chimeric polyomavirus-derived virus-like particles induce a strong immune response in miceViral Immunol200417516810.1089/08828240432287545815018662 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="32807" pm="."><plain>10.ZvirblieneASamonskyteLGedvilaiteAVoronkovaTUlrichRSasnauskasKGeneration of monoclonal antibodies of desired specificity using chimeric polyomavirus-derived virus-like particlesJ Immunol Methods2006311577010.1016/j.jim.2006.01.00716516908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="32808" pm="."><plain>11.DornDCLawatscheckRZvirblieneAAleksaiteEPecherGSasnauskasKCellular and humoral immunogenicity of hamster polyomavirus-derived virus-like particles harboring a mucin 1 cytotoxic T-cell epitopeViral Immunol200821122710.1089/vim.2007.008518355119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="32809" pm="."><plain>12.PleckaityteMZvirblieneASezaiteIGedvilaiteAProduction in yeast of pseudotype virus-like particles harboring functionally active antibody fragments neutralizing the cytolytic activity of vaginolysinMicrob Cell Fact20111010910.1186/1475-2859-10-10922171920 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="32810" pm="."><plain>13.LiddingtonRCYanYMoulaiJSahliRBenjaminTLHarrisonSCStructure of simian virus 40 at 3.8 Å resolutionNature19913542788410.1038/354278a01659663 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="32811" pm="."><plain>14.StehleTYanYBenjaminTLHarrisonSCStructure of murine polyomavirus complexed with an oligosaccharide receptor fragmentNature1994369160310.1038/369160a08177322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="32812" pm="."><plain>15.TegerstedtKFranzenARamqvistTDalianisTDendritic cells loaded with polyomavirus VP1/VP2Her2 virus-like particles efficiently prevent outgrowth of a Her2/neu expressing tumorCancer Immunol Immunother20075613354410.1007/s00262-007-0281-817268793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="32813" pm="."><plain>16.TegerstedtKLindencronaJACurcioCAndreassonKTullusCForniGTA single vaccination with polyomavirus VP1/ VP2 Her2 virus-like particles prevents outgrowth of HER-2/neu-expressing tumorsCancer Res2005655953710.1158/0008-5472.CAN-05-033515994974 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="32814" pm="."><plain>17.ErikssonMAndreassonKWeidmannJLundbergKTegerstedtKDalianisTMurine polyomavirus virus-like particles carrying full-length human PSA protect BALB/c mice from outgrowth of a PSA expressing tumorPLoS One2011610.1371/journal.pone.0023828 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="32815" pm="."><plain>18.FricJMarekMHruskovaVHolanVForstovaJCellular and humoral immune responses to chimeric EGFP-pseudocapsids derived from the mouse polyomavirus after their intranasal administrationVaccine20082632425110.1016/j.vaccine.2008.04.00618468739 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="32816" pm="."><plain>19.LasickienėRGedvilaiteANorkieneMSimanavicieneVSezaiteIDekaminaviciuteDThe use of recombinant pseudotype virus-like particles harbouring inserted target antigen to generate antibodies against cellular marker p16INK4AScientificWorldJournal2012201226373722629125 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="32817" pm="."><plain>20.PleckaityteMMistinieneELasickieneRZvirblisGZvirblieneAGeneration of recombinant single-chain antibodies neutralizing the cytolytic activity of vaginolysin, the main virulence factor of Gardnerella vaginalisBMC Biotechnol20111110010.1186/1472-6750-11-10022047084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="32818" pm="."><plain>21.MoutelSEl MarjouAVielemeyerONizakCBenarochPDübelSA multi-Fc-species system for recombinant antibody productionBMC Biotechnol200991410.1186/1472-6750-9-1419245715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="32819" pm="."><plain>22.BenharIPastanIIdentification of residues that stabilize the single-chain Fv of monoclonal antibodies B3J Biol Chem1995270233738010.1074/jbc.270.40.233737559495 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="32820" pm="."><plain>23.SeoMJJeongKJLeysathCEEllingtonADIversonBLGeorgiouGEngineering antibody fragments to fold in the absence of disulfide bondsProtein Sci2009182596710.1002/pro.3119177559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="32821" pm="."><plain>24.GongRVuBKFengYPrietoDADybaMAWalshJDEngineered human antibody constant domains with increased stabilityJ Biol Chem2009284142031010.1074/jbc.M90076920019307178 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="32822" pm="."><plain>25.GlebeDUrbanSKnoopEÇağNKrassPGrünSMapping of hepatitis B virus attachment site by use of infection-inhibiting preS1 lipopeptides and Tupaia hepatocytesGastroenterology20051292344510.1053/j.gastro.2005.03.09016012950 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="32823" pm="."><plain>26.DyeJMHerbertASKuehneAIBarthJFMuhammadMAZakSEPostexposure antibody prophylaxis protects nonhuman primates from filovirus diseaseProc Natl Acad Sci U S A20121095034910.1073/pnas.120040910922411795 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="32824" pm="."><plain>27.ScottLJLambHMPalivizumabDrugs199953051110.2165/00003495-199958020-0000910473022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="32825" pm="."><plain>28.KouiavskaiaDChenZDragunskyEMirochnitchenkoOPurcellRChumakovKA single chimpanzee-human neutralizing monoclonal antibody provides post-exposure protection against type 1 and type 2 poliovirusesJ Clin Virol20156532710.1016/j.jcv.2015.01.02325766984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="32826" pm="."><plain>29.ClementiNCriscuoloECastelliMClementiMBroad-range neutralizing anti-influenza A human monoclonal antibodies: new perspectives in therapy and prophylaxisNew Microbiol20123539940623109007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="32827" pm="."><plain>30.BothLBanyardACvan DolleweerdCHortonDLMaJKFooksARPassive immunity in the prevention of rabiesLancet Infect Dis20121239740710.1016/S1473-3099(11)70340-122541629 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="32828" pm="."><plain>31.ThomasCEEhrhardtAKayMAProgress and problems with the use of viral vectors for gene therapyNat Rev Genet200343465810.1038/nrg106612728277 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="32829" pm="."><plain>32.KaczmarczykSJSitaramanKYoungHAHughesSHChatterjeeDKProtein delivery using engineered virus-like particlesProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201110816998700310.1073/pnas.110187410821949376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="32830" pm="."><plain>33.BremerCMSominskayaISkrastinaDPumpensPAbd El WahedABeutlingUN-terminal myristoylation-dependent masking of neutralizing epitopes in the preS1 attachment site of hepatitis B virusJ Hepatol201155293710.1016/j.jhep.2010.10.01921145866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="32831" pm="."><plain>34.CerinoABremerCMGlebeDMondelliMUA human monoclonal antibody against hepatitis B surface antigen with potent neutralizing activityPLoS One20151010.1371/journal.pone.0125704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="32832" pm="."><plain>35.SambrookJRussellDWMolecular cloning: a laboratory manual20014Cold Spring HarbourCold Spring Harbor Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="32833" pm="."><plain>36.WangZRaifuMHowardMSmithLHansenDGoldsbyRUniversal PCR amplification of mouse immunoglobulin gene variable regions: the design of degenerate primers and an assessment of the effect of DNA polymerase 3' to 5' exonucleaseJ Immunol Methods2000131677710.1016/S0022-1759(99)00184-210648866 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="32834" pm="."><plain>37.BradfordMMA rapid and sensitive for the quantitation of microgram quantitites of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye bindingAnal Biochem1976722485410.1016/0003-2697(76)90527-3942051 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
