<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4077735</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24983738</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-02490</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0101135</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Biogeography</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Marine Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Evolutionary Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Genetics</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Flow</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Marine Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Marine Conservation</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Ecology and Environmental Sciences</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="24361" pm="."><plain>Genetic Structuring across Marine Biogeographic Boundaries in Rocky Shore Invertebrates </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Genetic Structuring across Biogeographic Barriers</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Villamor</surname><given-names>Adriana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Costantini</surname><given-names>Federica</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abbiati</surname><given-names>Marco</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Department of Biological, Geological and Environmental Sciences, University of Bologna, Ravenna, Emilia-Romagna, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Marine Sciences, National Research Council, Bologna, Emilia-Romagna, Italy</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Simon Fraser University, Canada</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>adriana.villamor@unibo.it</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="24362" pm="."><plain>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="24363" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: AV FC MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24364" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: AV FC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24365" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: AV FC MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24366" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AV FC MA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24367" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: AV FC MA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>7</issue><elocation-id>e101135</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>2</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2014 Villamor et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Villamor et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="24368" pm="."><plain>Biogeography investigates spatial patterns of species distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24369" pm="."><plain>Discontinuities in species distribution are identified as boundaries between biogeographic areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24370" pm="?"><plain>Do these boundaries affect genetic connectivity? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24371" pm="."><plain>To address this question, a multifactorial hierarchical sampling design, across three of the major marine biogeographic boundaries in the central Mediterranean Sea (Ligurian-Tyrrhenian, Tyrrhenian-Ionian and Ionian-Adriatic) was carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24372" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial COI sequence polymorphism of seven species of Mediterranean benthic invertebrates was analysed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24373" pm="."><plain>Two species showed significant genetic structure across the Tyrrhenian-Ionian boundary, as well as two other species across the Ionian Sea, a previously unknown phylogeographic barrier. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24374" pm="."><plain>The hypothesized barrier in the Ligurian-Tyrrhenian cannot be detected in the genetic structure of the investigated species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24375" pm="."><plain>Connectivity patterns across species at distances up to 800 km apart confirmed that estimates of pelagic larval dispersal were poor predictors of the genetic structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24376" pm="."><plain>The detected genetic discontinuities seem more related to the effect of past historical events, though maintained by present day oceanographic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24377" pm="."><plain>Multivariate statistical tools were used to test the consistency of the patterns across species, providing a conceptual framework for across-species barrier locations and strengths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24378" pm="."><plain>Additional sequences retrieved from public databases supported our findings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24379" pm="."><plain>Heterogeneity of phylogeographic patterns shown by the 7 investigated species is relevant to the understanding of the genetic diversity, and carry implications for conservation biology. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by a MIUR project (PRIN 2011 project on “Coastal bioconstructions: structure, function and management”) of the Italian Government. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="24380" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24381" pm="."><plain>Through the study of species distribution as well as patterns of genetic structuring, a link between biogeography and phylogeography can be explored, which aids in the identification of discontinuities in the spatial distribution and genetic diversity of species [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24382" pm="."><plain>The level of connectivity between geographic areas is mainly determined by the interplay between the dispersal capacity of a species (including pre and post-settlement processes [2]), the hydrological regime [3] and the occurrence of geological/topographical boundaries, which may reduce the dispersal potential and hence the gene flow [4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24383" pm="."><plain>Major barriers to gene flow between oceanic basins have previously been identified (for example, Point Conception in California, [5]; the Eastern Pacific barrier, [6]; the Indo-Pacific Barrier, [7]; the South-eastern Australian barrier, [8]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24384" pm="."><plain>These barriers support the occurrence of genetic discontinuities between the world's biogeographical regions [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24385" pm="."><plain>Significant genetic structuring has also been detected at smaller spatial scales in correspondence with the boundaries between biogeographic provinces [10] or sectors [11], [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24386" pm="."><plain>In the Central Mediterranean Sea nine biogeographic sectors have been proposed based on species' distributions [13], but their consistency with phylogeographic sectors has only been investigated in a few cases [14]–[16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24387" pm="."><plain>These studies investigated genetic differentiation between the Mediterranean basins (eastern, western, Adriatic Sea) in a single species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24388" pm="."><plain>However, data from a single species, with specific life history traits, ecology, ethology, etc, cannot be used to generalize phylogeographic barriers or limitations to gene flow across other species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24389" pm="."><plain>In fact, studies on different target species conducted in the same geographical areas often reveal contrasting genetic structures and/or phylogeographical patterns [17]–[19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24390" pm="."><plain>Comparative phylogeography has recently been suggested as a powerful tool to discern general patterns over species-specific traits [20], [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24391" pm="."><plain>It has proven effective in identifying across taxa barriers to gene flow in the Almeria-Oran Front [22], and along the north-eastern Pacific coast [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24392" pm="."><plain>Currently no multispecies studies identifying barriers to gene flow or genetic discontinuities in the Mediterranean Sea exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24393" pm="."><plain>Given the practical implications of defining genetic units for the conservation and management of natural resources, a study of this nature is sorely needed [24]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24394" pm="."><plain>In the present study, the occurrence of phylogeographic boundaries in the Central Mediterranean Sea, and their consistency across species was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24395" pm="."><plain>By means of a multifactorial hierarchical sampling design, three putative long-term barriers to gene flow were tested. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24396" pm="."><plain>These putative barriers were established based on known biogeographic boundaries [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24397" pm="."><plain>Two replicated areas were sampled across each barrier, and within each area the genetic structure of seven common shallow water invertebrate species was analysed using a portion of the COI mitochondrial gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24398" pm="."><plain>In addition to genetic differentiation measures, two types of multivariate analysis were used to test the consistency of the phylogeographical patterns across species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24399" pm="."><plain>The results of this study provide a first contribution towards a comparative phylogeography in the Central Mediterranean Sea, with the aim of fully understanding the main past and present drivers of genetic diversity and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="24400" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="24401" pm="."><plain>Study areas and species </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24402" pm="."><plain>Three major potential biogeographic/phylogeographic boundaries, located in the Central Mediterranean Sea (Figure 1), and hereafter referred to as putative barriers (PB), were investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24403" pm="."><plain>The first putative barrier (PB1, in Location 1) separates the Ligurian Sea and the North Tyrrhenian Sea, corresponding to a virtual line between the coast of Tuscany, and the islands of Elba and Corsica. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24404" pm="."><plain>The two sides of PB1 are characterized by divergent currents [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24405" pm="."><plain>The second putative barrier (PB2, in Location 2) separates the Tyrrhenian and Ionian Seas, and corresponds to a line across the Strait of Messina and Sicily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24406" pm="."><plain>Very strong tidal currents characterize the narrow Strait of Messina, flowing mainly from north to south [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24407" pm="."><plain>The third putative barrier (PB3, in Location 3) separates the Ionian and Adriatic Seas, around the Apulian Cape of Santa Maria di Leuca. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24408" pm="."><plain>Strong currents with different patterns in opposite directions characterize the water circulation along this putative barrier [26]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0101135-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0101135.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="24409" pm="."><plain>Map of the study area, locations defined, sampling areas and putative barriers analyzed. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24410" pm="."><plain>Location 1: A1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24411" pm="."><plain>Castiglioncello, A2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24412" pm="."><plain>Calafuria, B1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24413" pm="."><plain>Talamone, B2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24414" pm="."><plain>Porto Ercole; Location 2: C1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24415" pm="."><plain>Nicotera, C2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24416" pm="."><plain>Vibo Marina, D1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24417" pm="."><plain>Soverato, D2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24418" pm="."><plain>Copanello; and Location 3: E1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24419" pm="."><plain>Gallipoli, E2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24420" pm="."><plain>Porto Cesareo, F1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24421" pm="."><plain>Porto Badisco, and F2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24422" pm="."><plain>Otranto. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24423" pm="."><plain>PB1: putative barrier between Ligurian and Tyrrhenian Seas, PB2: putative barrier between Tyrrhenian and Ionian Seas and, PB3: putative barrier between Ionian and Adriatic Seas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24424" pm="."><plain>Grey arrows represent the direction of the dominant currents in those areas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24425" pm="."><plain>The bottom left image is taken from [65] and shows the most commonly acknowledged biogeographic sectors in the central Mediterranean region. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0101135.g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="24426" pm="."><plain>At each side of the putative barriers two replicate sites 150 km apart from each other were defined (sites A, B, C, D, E, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24427" pm="."><plain>In each site 2 sampling areas about 25 km apart were randomly selected, and named counter-clockwise starting from Location 1 (areas A1, A2; B1, B2; C1, C2; D1, D2; E1, E2; F1, F2; Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24428" pm="."><plain>Seven invertebrate species were selected based on their prevalence in the central Mediterranean as well as to cover a variety of life history traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24429" pm="."><plain>The selected species belong to different taxa: Gastropoda (3), Polyplacophora (1), Ascidiacea (1); Crustacea (1), and Porifera (1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24430" pm="."><plain>Data retrieved on life history traits and larval ecology are summarized in Figure 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24431" pm="."><plain>The longest Pelagic Larval Duration (PLD) estimates correspond to Balanus perforatus, Patella caerulea, and Halocynthia papillosa. Hexaplex trunculus is a brooding species and has no theoretical PLD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24432" pm="."><plain>PLD estimates for Chondrosia reniformis, Chiton olivaceus, and Osilinus turbinatus are of about one week. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="pone-0101135-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0101135.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="24433" pm="."><plain>Pelagic larval dispersal estimates, spawning period, and other reproductive data for the species studied. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24434" pm="."><plain>Data retrieved from [58], [66]–[74]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24435" pm="."><plain>Roman numerals correspond to the months and black bars indicate the extent of the spawning season. * The accepted name of Osilinus turbinatus is Phorcus turbinatus. ** The accepted name of Balanus perforatus is Perforatus perforatus (World Register of Marine Species, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.marinespecies.org">www.marinespecies.org</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0101135.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="24436" pm="."><plain>In each area 30 individuals per species were collected, fixed in 80% ethanol and maintained at 4°C prior to processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24437" pm="."><plain>Only the sponge was sampled as pieces rather than as whole organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24438" pm="."><plain>To minimize the possibility of clonality, samples were collected at least 5 m apart [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24439" pm="."><plain>No specific permits were required for the areas and the species studied. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="24440" pm="."><plain>DNA extraction and COI amplification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24441" pm="."><plain>Total DNA was extracted from a piece of circa 5 g of tissue using a REDExtract-N-Amp kit (Sigma–Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24442" pm="."><plain>The COI gene was chosen for analysis due to its intermediate rate of variation that provides information on genetic structure across a wide range of spatial and temporal scales [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24443" pm="."><plain>Universal primers described in [29] were initially used for the amplification of a fragment of the COI gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24444" pm="."><plain>After the first sequences were retrieved, six pairs of species-specific primers were designed with the software PRIMER v. 3.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fokker.wi.mit.edu/primer3/input.htm">http://www.fokker.wi.mit.edu/primer3/input.htm</ext-link>) in order to increase amplification success and the quality of sequences obtained (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24446" pm="."><plain>PCR amplification reactions were carried out in a 25 µl total volume with 5 µl of 5x GoTaq Flexi Buffer (Promega), 4 µl of MgCl2 25 mM, 0.5 µl of dNTP mix 10 mM, 0.5 µl of each primer, 0.15 µl of GoTaq DNA polymerase (Promega) and 2.5 µl of template DNA (from a 1∶50 dilution of the extracted DNA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24447" pm="."><plain>A hold at 94°C for 3 min was followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 94°C for 45 s, annealing at a primer specific temperature for 45 s and extension at 72°C for 90 s, finishing with a final extension at 72°C for 5 min on a thermal cycler (Applied Biosystems, GeneAmp 2700) (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24448" pm="."><plain>PCR products were purified and sequenced by MACROGEN INC. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24449" pm="."><plain>All sequences were checked and edited manually on Chromas Pro (Technelysium, Pty, Ltd, Australia). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24450" pm="."><plain>Sequence alignments were performed using Mega v. 5 [30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="24452" pm="."><plain>Data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24453" pm="."><plain>Preliminary analysis showed no differentiation in any of the investigated species between the two replicated areas of each site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24454" pm="."><plain>As a result, individuals from the two areas were pooled and hereafter data have been analysed considering only the sites (A, B, C, D, E, F; Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24455" pm="."><plain>We detected no genetic differentiation between Locations 1 and 3 of Balanus perforatus, 1500 km apart, so decided not to analyse Location 2 samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="25128" pm="."><plain>After transforming haplotypes into pseudo-genotypes, we obtained a matrix of 802 individuals with genotypes of 152 loci each (most of them zeros), corresponding to all polymorphic sites across all species (33 of Patella caerulea, 50 of Hexaplex trunculus, 8 of Halocynthia papillosa, 37 of Osilinus turbinatus, 19 of Chiton olivaceus, and 4 of Chondrosia reniformis). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25129" pm="."><plain>The resulting DAPC showed a distribution of the samples (sites) similar to the MDS plot: sites A, B and C grouped together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25130" pm="."><plain>Site D was separated from all the others, and sites E and F clustered together (Figure 4b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="25131" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="25132" pm="."><plain>In the study area two zones of genetic discontinuity have been identified: across the biogeographic boundary between the Tyrrhenian and Ionian Seas, and between the western and eastern coasts of the Ionian Sea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25133" pm="."><plain>The strongest genetic structure detected was across the Tyrrhenian-Ionian biogeographic boundary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25134" pm="."><plain>The presence of this long-term boundary was reflected in the genetic structure of two species out of the seven studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25135" pm="."><plain>It probably corresponds to the boundary between biogeographic sectors 3 and 6 as defined by [13] (see Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25136" pm="."><plain>The genetic structure across these sectors has been described by [47]–[49], but the location of the boundary remained vague. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25137" pm="."><plain>In this area, due to the complex topography of straits and islands, Pleistocene sea level fluctuations have left a signature in the genetic structure of many species [48], subjected to periodic divergences and reconnections of the populations on the two sides of the Messina Strait. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25138" pm="."><plain>Past history events might explain the origin of haplogroups or divergent lineages, whereas present day events, such as the current regimes, aid in maintaining and enhancing the differences due to limited or asymmetric connectivity between sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25139" pm="."><plain>Patella caerulea showed significant genetic structure across this Tyrrhenian-Ionian PB, reflected in the two haplogroups with different frequencies across each side of the boundary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25140" pm="."><plain>In spite of the significant differentiation, a bidirectional but asymmetric migration across the barrier was estimated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25141" pm="."><plain>Other limpet species showed comparable genetic structure in this area [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25142" pm="."><plain>In addition, the sequences retrieved in Genbank gave further support to this structure: western and eastern Mediterranean samples clustered more often with haplotypes of the “northern haplogroup”, and “southern haplogroup”, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25143" pm="."><plain>It is noteworthy that individuals from the Atlantic side of the Almeria-Oran Front (AOF), the best-known barrier to gene flow in the Mediterranean [20], presented common haplotypes, suggesting this barrier had no large effect on P. caerulea genetic structure [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25144" pm="."><plain>Expansion estimates indicate long-term persistence of this species and, in accordance with the older expansion estimates, an older origin of the northwestern haplogroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25145" pm="."><plain>This is in agreement with the widespread distribution and abundance of this species and with the more probable Atlantic origin of this genus [52]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25146" pm="."><plain>The subtidal gastropod Hexaplex trunculus, a brooding species, showed the sharpest genetic structure across the Tyrrhenian-Ionian biogeographic boundary. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25147" pm="."><plain>Despite this fact, several haplotypes were common to sites located up to 1500 km apart, on both sides of the putative barrier, probably indicating high migration rates from the Ligurian-Tyrrhenian towards the Ionian-Adriatic populations, but almost none in the opposite direction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25148" pm="."><plain>This sharp asymmetry has been described in other regions and species, and is suggested to reflect persistent current regimes affecting larval dispersal during the reproductive period [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25149" pm="."><plain>Estimates of expansion of both lineages are consistent with the persistence of this species during the LGM, in more than one glacial refuge, followed by a unidirectional secondary contact [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25150" pm="."><plain>Expansion estimates are older in the southern lineage, which, together with the higher diversity values in this area, indicates a major contribution of the Eastern Mediterranean genetic pool to the total genetic diversity of this species [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25151" pm="."><plain>All sequences retrieved from Genbank belonged to individuals from South Portugal, so no further details on the structure of other Mediterranean sites could be inferred. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25152" pm="."><plain>Most individuals showed haplotypes of the northern haplogroup, reinforcing their Mediterranean origin, but also suggesting no effect of the AOF on the long-term genetic structure of this species, as was the case for Patella caerulea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25153" pm="."><plain>An unexpected area of genetic discontinuity was disclosed between the eastern and western Ionian Sea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25154" pm="."><plain>Two species, presumably not affected by the Tyrrhenian-Ionian boundary previously described, showed significant genetic structure across the Ionian Sea, i.e. between the Adriatic-Ionian sites and the rest of the study area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25155" pm="."><plain>The Ionian Sea has never been considered to host phylogeographic barriers, either related to historical events nor according to present day oceanographic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25156" pm="."><plain>No records referring to genetic structure across this region were found in the literature, despite the fact that the genetic structures of some species support this finding [48], although no explicit tests to identify the barrier had been carried out. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25157" pm="."><plain>The location of the biogeographic boundary separating the eastern and western Mediterranean is controversial [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25158" pm="."><plain>This newly detected phylogeographic boundary provides new insight to understanding the biogeography of the area, although further data on the genetic structure of other species in the area would be needed. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25159" pm="."><plain>Osilinus turbinatus presented a high diversity of haplotypes and significant structure across the Ionian Sea, with bidirectional and symmetric migration estimates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25160" pm="."><plain>Published sequences supported the detected structure and individuals from the eastern Mediterranean and the Adriatic Sea presented haplotypes related to those found exclusively in the Adriatic-Ionian sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25161" pm="."><plain>The estimates of expansion of this species coincide with the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM between 24,000 and 27,000 ya, [20]). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25162" pm="."><plain>The sponge Chondrosia reniformis, in spite of evincing low diversity values, also showed significant genetic structure across the Ionian Sea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25163" pm="."><plain>A similar differentiation has been described in other widespread sponge species in the same geographical area [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25164" pm="."><plain>The only sequence retrieved from Genbank belongs to an eastern Mediterranean individual and shares the more common haplotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25165" pm="."><plain>Although further data from the Ionian Sea and the eastern Mediterranean would be needed to confirm our finding, this study suggests that for Osilinus turbinatus and C. reniformis the phylogeographic barrier between eastern and western Mediterranean is located in the Mid Ionian Sea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25166" pm="."><plain>Significant genetic structure was detected across the northern and southern Tyrrhenian Sea in Hexaplex trunculus and Osilinus turbinatus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25167" pm="."><plain>In both cases significant Fst values were likely due to the occurrence of several private haplotypes, south Tyrrhenian haplotypes in the case of H. trunculus, and Ligurian-North Tyrrhenian private haplotypes in the case of O. turbinatus. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25168" pm="."><plain>Halocynthia papillosa showed several significant pairwise differences between sites across the three locations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25169" pm="."><plain>The positive values of the neutrality tests, the presence of several common haplotypes, the smaller number of private ones, and the flat shape of the BSP, strongly indicate a long-term stability of the population size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25170" pm="."><plain>This species may have persisted in two or more glacial refugia, followed by a secondary contact between them [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25171" pm="."><plain>Although this ascidian has large dispersal capacity estimates [43] our results support larval retention, as has been previously suggested ([58], Figure 2), allowing genetic structuring in the range of 300 and 1500 km. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25172" pm="."><plain>Balanus perforatus, the species with the longest PLD estimates, lacked significant genetic structure across distances of up to 1500 km. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25173" pm="."><plain>Neutrality tests indicated a very old expansion, starting around 60,000 ya. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25174" pm="."><plain>This pattern of persistence is similar to that shown by other widespread and abundant species inhabiting comparable habitats along the northeastern Pacific [59], [60]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25175" pm="."><plain>The genetic structure found among populations of Chiton olivaceus across the whole study area is congruent with a pattern of isolation by distance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25176" pm="."><plain>This species showed the only estimate of expansion time clearly posterior to the LGM, indicating reduced persistence and recent colonization from glacial refugia [60]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25177" pm="."><plain>This would also be in agreement with the low abundances and low molecular diversities detected with respect to the other species studied, and to other polyplacophora species [3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25178" pm="."><plain>As previously shown [61], our results support the weak correlation between PLD and genetic structure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25179" pm="."><plain>The scale of larval dispersal is related to the complex interaction of larval life history traits, oceanographic regimes, habitat quality and distribution, and the variability of each of these factors through time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25180" pm="."><plain>However, it is noteworthy that contrasting dispersal capacity patterns, as those of Hexaplex trunculus and Balanus perforatus, influence connectivity across the boundaries of biogeographic areas, as already detected in fishes [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25181" pm="."><plain>The genetic structure observed is most likely due to the different effects of glacial and interglacial isolations and reconnections on their populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25182" pm="."><plain>Levels of gene flow are not the only factors determining present day genetic structure among populations; divergence times and population size can greatly affect the observed genetic structure [63], however the lack of basic biological data for most of our focus species, does not allow to disentangle the role these different drivers play in the observed genetic structures. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25183" pm="."><plain>The two multivariate analyses allowed a general picture to be provided by merging in a common framework the results obtained for individual species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25184" pm="."><plain>The statistical tests as well as the graphical representation provided a general picture of the phylogeographic structure in the Central Mediterranean, as well as the relative importance of the discontinuity areas detected, according to the number of species affected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25185" pm="."><plain>This approach enables to summarize the available genetic information in a simple, straightforward result, which might be useful for decision-making or management purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25186" pm="."><plain>Species with high haplotype and/or nucleotide diversities could bias these analyses; however the multispecies approach counteracts this effect, so the results are not obscured by the structure of the most variable species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25187" pm="."><plain>According to the results of the present study, the Tyrrhenian-Ionian biogeographical boundary acts as a phylogeographical barrier, as suggested by the genetic structure of two out of seven invertebrate species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25188" pm="."><plain>The hierarchical sampling design adopted allowed the identification of an area of genetic discontinuity in the mid-Ionian Sea, reflected in the genetic structure of two species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25189" pm="."><plain>The data retrieved from public databases reinforced the observed haplotype distributions, and gave further evidence on the variability of the effect of known barriers to gene flow on the genetic structure of different species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25190" pm="."><plain>In the Mediterranean Sea, Pleistocene glaciations had a profound influence on the present day distribution of species and genetic diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25191" pm="."><plain>The estimates of expansion and divergence allowed further understanding of the genetic structure found at present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25192" pm="."><plain>Due to the ecological importance of the Central Mediterranean Sea as a hot spot of marine biodiversity [64], these results are of importance for the better understanding of the ecological functioning of its coastal ecosystem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25193" pm="."><plain>General patterns pertinent to the management and conservation of this important ecosystem have been shown thanks to the comparative phylogeography approach used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25194" pm="."><plain>Further research analyzing the genetic structure of other species, inclusive of additional Putative Boundaries, while also utilizing a larger set of molecular markers, would provide more insight on a multi-species, multi-scale picture of connectivity in the marine realm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="25195" pm="."><plain>Supporting Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0101135.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25196" pm="."><plain>Mismatch distributions at each Location and for the whole data set for each of the seven species. Grey lines represent the expected and black lines the observed distribution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25197" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0101135.s001.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25198" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0101135.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25199" pm="."><plain>Bayesian Skyline Plots for the species showing signs of expansion according to mismatch distribution or neutrality tests. Patella caerulea and Hexaplex trunculus plots are calculated for each haplogroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25200" pm="."><plain>When shown, the black square indicates the date of the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25201" pm="."><plain>The most likely evolutionary model selected by jModelTest is indicated in each plot. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25202" pm="."><plain>(TIF) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0101135.s002.tif"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25203" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0101135.s003"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25204" pm="."><plain>Specific primers. Names, sequence, amplified fragment length, and optimal annealing temperature for each of the seven pairs of primers used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25205" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0101135.s003.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25206" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0101135.s004"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25207" pm="."><plain>Previously published sequences. Accession numbers, geographical origin and identification with the haplotypes found in this study, as named in Figure 3, of sequences retrieved from Genbank. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25208" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0101135.s004.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25209" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0101135.s005"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25210" pm="."><plain>Analyses of Molecular Variance. Results of the Amova on the groups corresponding to the three Locations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25211" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0101135.s005.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25212" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0101135.s006"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25213" pm="."><plain>Demographic history analyses. Fit to sudden expansion model and neutrality tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25214" pm="."><plain>(DOCX) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0101135.s006.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="25215" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="25216" pm="."><plain>Authors are grateful to F. Raffini and S. Tassinari for their involvement in sampling and preliminary analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25219" pm="."><plain>We also thank B. Strain, F. Ferrario, and M. Ponti for field assistance, A. Velonà for suggestions on data analysis and early versions of the manuscript, and G. Beans for language revision. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25225" pm="."><plain>We also thank M. Hart and an anonymous reviewer for constructive criticism that improved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25227" pm="."><plain>Villamor and Costantini were funded by an “Assegno di Ricerca” of the University of Bologna. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0101135-Slatkin1"><text><SENT sid="25228" pm="."><plain>1 SlatkinM (1987) Gene flow and the geographic structure of natural populations. Science 236: 787–792.3576198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Cowen1"><text><SENT sid="25229" pm="."><plain>2 CowenRK, SponaugleS (2009) Larval dispersal and marine population connectivity. Ann Rev Mar Sci 1: 443–466. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Ayre1"><text><SENT sid="25230" pm="."><plain>3 AyreDJ, Minchinton TE, PerrinC (2009) Does life history predict past and current connectivity for rocky intertidal invertebrates across a marine biogeographic barrier?. Mol Ecol 18: 1887–1903.19434808 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-BlancoBercialLAlvarezMarques1"><text><SENT sid="25231" pm="."><plain>4 Blanco-Bercial L Alvarez-MarquesF, BucklinA (2011) Comparative phylogeography and connectivity of sibling species of the marine copepod Clausocalanus (Calanoida). J Exp Mar Biol Ecol 404: 108–115. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Wares1"><text><SENT sid="25232" pm="."><plain>5 WaresJP, CunninghamCW (2001) Phylogeography and historical ecology of the North Atlantic intertidal. Evolution 55: 2455–2469.11831661 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Lessios1"><text><SENT sid="25233" pm="."><plain>6 LessiosHA, RobertsonDR (2006) Crossing the impassable: genetic connections in 20 reef fishes across the eastern Pacific barrier. P Roy Soc B-Biol Sci 273: 2201–2208. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Gaither1"><text><SENT sid="25234" pm="."><plain>7 GaitherMR, ToonenRJ, RobertsonDR, PlanesS, BowenBW (2010) Genetic evaluation of marine biogeographical barriers: perspectives from two widespread Indo-Pacific snappers (Lutjanus kasmira and Lutjanus fulvus). J Biogeogr 37: 133–147. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-ColemanMARoughan1"><text><SENT sid="25235" pm="."><plain>8 Coleman MA RoughanM, MacdonaldHS, ConnellSD, GillandersBM, et al (2011) Variation in the strength of continental boundary currents determines continent-wide connectivity in kelp. J Ecol 99: 1026–1032. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Teske1"><text><SENT sid="25236" pm="."><plain>9 TeskePR, PapadopoulosI, MmonwaKL, MatumbaTG, McQuaidCD, et al (2011) Climate-driven genetic divergence of limpets with different life histories across a southeast African marine biogeographic disjunction: different processes, same outcome. Mol Ecol 20: 5025–5041.22017655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Luttikhuizen1"><text><SENT sid="25237" pm="."><plain>10 LuttikhuizenPC, CamposJ, van BleijswijkJ, PeijnenburgKTC, van der VeerHW (2008) Phylogeography of the common shrimp, Crangon crangon (L.) across its distribution range. Mol Phylogenet Evol 46: 1015–1030.18207428 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Bird1"><text><SENT sid="25238" pm="."><plain>11 BirdCE, HollandBS, BowenBW, ToonenRJ (2007) Contrasting phylogeography in three endemic Hawaiian limpets (Cellana spp.) with similar life histories. Mol Ecol 16: 3173–3186.17651195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Drew1"><text><SENT sid="25239" pm="."><plain>12 DrewJA, BarberPH (2012) Comparative phylogeography in fijian coral reef fishes: a multi-taxa approach towards marine reserve design. PLoS One 7: e47710.23118892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Bianchi1"><text><SENT sid="25240" pm="."><plain>13 BianchiCN, MorriC (2000) Marine biodiversity of the Mediterranean Sea: Situation, problems and prospects for future research. Mar Poll Bull 40: 367–376. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Stefanni1"><text><SENT sid="25241" pm="."><plain>14 StefanniS, ThorleyJL (2003) Mitochondrial DNA phylogeography reveals the existence of an Evolutionarily Significant Unit of the sand goby Pomatoschistus minutus in the Adriatic (Eastern Mediterranean). Mol Phylogenet Evol 28: 601–609.12927142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Domingues1"><text><SENT sid="25242" pm="."><plain>15 DominguesVS, BucciarelliG, AlmadaVC, BernardiG (2005) Historical colonization and demography of the Mediterranean damselfish, Chromis chromis . Mol Ecol 14: 4051–4063.16262858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-MaggioTLoBrutto1"><text><SENT sid="25243" pm="."><plain>16 Maggio T Lo BruttoS, GaroiaF, TintiF, ArculeoM (2009) Microsatellite analysis of red mullet Mullus barbatus (Perciformes, Mullidae) reveals the isolation of the Adriatic Basin in the Mediterranean Sea. ICES J Mar Sci 66: 1883–1891. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-PerezLosada1"><text><SENT sid="25244" pm="."><plain>17 Perez-LosadaM, NolteMJ, CrandallKA, ShawPW (2007) Testing hypotheses of population structuring in the Northeast Atlantic Ocean and Mediterranean Sea using the common cuttlefish Sepia officinalis . Mol Ecol 16: 2667–2679.17594438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Rock1"><text><SENT sid="25245" pm="."><plain>18 RockJ, IronsideJ, PotterT, WhiteleyNM, LuntDH (2007) Phylogeography and environmental diversification of a highly adaptable marine amphipod, Gammarus duebeni . Heredity 99: 102–111.17426729 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Papetti1"><text><SENT sid="25246" pm="."><plain>19 PapettiC, Martin-PujolarJ, MezzavillaM, La MesaM, RockJ, et al (2012) Population genetic structure and gene flow patterns between populations of the Antarctic icefish Chionodraco rastrospinosus . J Biogeogr 39: 1361–1372. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Patarnello1"><text><SENT sid="25247" pm="."><plain>20 PatarnelloT, VolckaertFAMJ, CastilhoR (2007) Pillars of Hercules: is the Atlantic-Mediterranean transition a phylogeographical break? Mol Ecol 16: 4426–4444.17908222 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Marske1"><text><SENT sid="25248" pm="."><plain>21 MarskeKA, RahbekC, Nogues-BravoD (2013) Phylogeography: spanning the ecology-evolution continuum. Ecography 36: 1169–1181. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Galarza1"><text><SENT sid="25249" pm="."><plain>22 GalarzaJA, Carreras-CarbonellJ, MacphersonE, PascualM, RoquesS, et al (2009) The influence of oceanographic fronts and early-life-history traits on connectivity among littoral fish species. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 106: 1473–1478.19164518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Kelly1"><text><SENT sid="25250" pm="."><plain>23 KellyRP, PalumbiSR (2010) Genetic structure among 50 species of the northeastern Pacific rocky intertidal community. PLoS One 5: e8594.20062807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-MartiPuig1"><text><SENT sid="25251" pm="."><plain>24 Marti-PuigP, CostantiniF, RugiuL, PontiM, AbbiatiM (2013) Patterns of genetic connectivity in invertebrates of temperate MPA networks. Adv Oceanogr Limnol 4: 138–149. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Millot1"><text><SENT sid="25252" pm="."><plain>25 MillotC (1999) Circulation in the western Mediterranean Sea. J Marine Syst 20: 423–442. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Astraldi1"><text><SENT sid="25253" pm="."><plain>26 AstraldiM, BalopoulosS, CandelaJ, FontJ, GacicM, et al (1999) The role of straits and channels in understanding the characteristics of Mediterranean circulation. Prog Oceanogr 44: 65–108. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Duran1"><text><SENT sid="25254" pm="."><plain>27 DuranS, GiribetG, TurónX (2004) Phylogeographical history of the sponge Crambe crambe (Porifera, Poecilosclerida): range expansion and recent invasion of the Macaronesian islands from the Mediterranean Sea. Mol Ecol 13: 109–122.14653793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Avise1"><text><SENT sid="25255" pm="."><plain>28Avise JC (2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25256" pm="."><plain>Phylogeography: the history and formation of species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25257" pm="."><plain>Harvard University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Folmer1"><text><SENT sid="25258" pm="."><plain>29 FolmerO, BlackM, HoehW, LutzR, VrijenhoekR (1994) DNA primers for amplification of mitochondrial cytochrome c oxidase subunit I from diverse metazoan invertebrates. Mol Mar Biol Biotech 3: 294–299. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Tamura1"><text><SENT sid="25259" pm="."><plain>30 TamuraK, PetersonD, PetersonN, StecherG, NeiM, KumarS (2011) MEGA5: Molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using Maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Mol Biol Evol 28: 2731–273.21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Rozas1"><text><SENT sid="25260" pm="."><plain>31 RozasJ, Sanchez-DelBarrioJC, MesseguerX, RozasR (2003) DnaSP, DNA polymorphism analyses by the coalescent and other methods. Bioinformatics 19: 2496–2497.14668244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Bandelt1"><text><SENT sid="25261" pm="."><plain>32 BandeltHJ, ForsterP, RohlA (1999) Median-joining networks for inferring intraspecific phylogenies. Mol Biol Evol 16: 37–48.10331250 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Templeton1"><text><SENT sid="25262" pm="."><plain>33 TempletonAR, BoerwinkleE, SingCF (1987) A cladistic analysis of phenotypic associations with haplotypes inferred from restriction endonuclease mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25263" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25264" pm="."><plain>Basic theory and an analysis of alcohol-dehydrogenase activity in Drosophila . Genetics 117: 343–351.2822535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Excoffier1"><text><SENT sid="25265" pm="."><plain>34 ExcoffierL, LischerHEL (2010) Arlequin suite ver 3.5: a new series of programs to perform population genetics analyses under Linux and Windows. Mol Ecol Res 10: 564–567. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Narum1"><text><SENT sid="25266" pm="."><plain>35 NarumSR (2006) Beyond Bonferroni: Less conservative analyses for conservation genetics. Conserv Genet 7: 783–787. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Beerli1"><text><SENT sid="25267" pm="."><plain>36 BeerliP, FelsensteinJ (2001) Maximum likelihood estimation of a migration matrix and effective population sizes in n subpopulations by using a coalescent approach. P Natl Acad Sci USA 98: 4563–4568. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Rogers1"><text><SENT sid="25268" pm="."><plain>37 RogersAR, HarpendingH (1992) Population growth makes waves in the distribution of pairwise genetic differences. Mol Biol Evol 9: 552–569.1316531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Fu1"><text><SENT sid="25269" pm="."><plain>38 FuYX (1997) Statistical tests of neutrality of mutations against population growth, hitchhiking and background selection. Genetics 147: 915–925.9335623 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Drummond1"><text><SENT sid="25270" pm="."><plain>39 DrummondAJ, RambautA (2007) BEAST: Bayesian evolutionary analysis by sampling trees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25271" pm="."><plain>BMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25272" pm="."><plain>Biol. 7: 214. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Posada1"><text><SENT sid="25273" pm="."><plain>40 PosadaD (2008) jModelTest: Phylogenetic model averaging. Mol Biol Evol 25: 1253–1256.18397919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Hellberg1"><text><SENT sid="25274" pm="."><plain>41 HellbergME, BalchDP, RoyK (2001) Climate-driven range expansion and morphological evolution in a marine gastropod. Science 292: 1707–1710.11387473 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Campo1"><text><SENT sid="25275" pm="."><plain>42 CampoD, MolaresJ, GarciaL, Fernandez-RuedaP, Garcia-GonzalezC, Garcia-VazquezE (2010) Phylogeography of the European stalked barnacle (Pollicipes pollicipes): identification of glacial refugia. Mar Biol 157: 147–156. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Kim1"><text><SENT sid="25276" pm="."><plain>43 KimWJ, LeeCI, KimHS, HanHS, JeeYJ, et al (2012) Population genetic structure and phylogeography of the ascidian, Halocynthia roretzi, along the coasts of Korea and Japan, inferred from mitochondrial DNA sequence analysis. Biochem Syst Ecol 44: 128–135. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Rambaut1"><text><SENT sid="25277" pm="."><plain>44Rambaut A, Drummond AJ (2007) Tracer v1.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25278" pm="."><plain>Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer">http://beast.bio.ed.ac.uk/Tracer</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Clarke1"><text><SENT sid="25279" pm="."><plain>45Clarke KR, Warwick RM (2001) Change in marine communities: an approach to statistical analysis and interpretation, 2nd edition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25280" pm="."><plain>PRIMER-E: Plymouth. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Jombart1"><text><SENT sid="25281" pm="."><plain>46 JombartT (2008) Adegenet: a R package for the multivariate analysis of genetic markers. Bioinformatics 24: 1403–1405.18397895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Virgilio1"><text><SENT sid="25282" pm="."><plain>47 VirgilioM, FauvelotC, CostantiniF, AbbiatiM, BackeljauT (2009) Phylogeography of the common ragworm Hediste diversicolor (Polychaeta: Nereididae) reveals cryptic diversity and multiple colonization events across its distribution. Mol Ecol 18: 1980–1994.19344353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Serra1"><text><SENT sid="25283" pm="."><plain>48 SerraIA, InnocentiAM, Di MaidaG, CalvoS, MigliaccioM, et al (2010) Genetic structure in the Mediterranean seagrass Posidonia oceanica: disentangling past vicariance events from contemporary patterns of gene flow. Mol Ecol 19: 557–568.20051010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Gharbi1"><text><SENT sid="25284" pm="."><plain>49 GharbiA, SaidK (2011) Genetic variation and population structure of Holothuria polii from the eastern and western Mediterranean coasts in Tunisia. J Mar Biol Assoc UK 91: 1599–1606. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-SaPinto1"><text><SENT sid="25285" pm="."><plain>50Sa-Pinto A, Branco MS, Alexandrino PB, Fontaine MC, Baird SJE (2012) Barriers to gene flow in the marine environment: insights from two common intertidal limpet species of the Atlantic and Mediterranean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25286" pm="."><plain>PLoS One 7.. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-CrteReal1"><text><SENT sid="25287" pm="."><plain>51 Côrte-RealHBSM, HawkinsSJ, ThorpeJP (1996) Population differentiation and taxonomic status of the exploited limpet Patella candei in the Macaronesian islands (Azores, Madeira, Canaries). Mar Biol 125: 141–152. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-SaPinto2"><text><SENT sid="25288" pm="."><plain>52 Sa-PintoA, BrancoMS, HarrisDJ, AlexandrinoP (2005) Phylogeny and phylogeography of the genus Patella based on mitochondrial DNA sequence data. J Exp Mar Biol Ecol 325: 95–110. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Collins1"><text><SENT sid="25289" pm="."><plain>53 CollinsCJ, FraserCI, AshcroftA, WatersJM (2010) Asymmetric dispersal of southern bull-kelp (Durvillaea antarctica) adults in coastal New Zealand: testing an oceanographic hypothesis. Mol Ecol 19: 4572–4580.20875065 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-PerezPortela1"><text><SENT sid="25290" pm="."><plain>54 Perez-PortelaR, VillamorA, AlmadaV (2010) Phylogeography of the sea star Marthasterias glacialis (Asteroidea, Echinodermata): deep genetic divergence between mitochondrial lineages in the north-western mediterranean. Mar Biol 157: 2015–2028. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Prs1"><text><SENT sid="25291" pm="."><plain>55 PérèsJM, PicardJN (1964) Nouveau manuel de bionomie benthique de la Mer Mediterranee. Recueilles des Travaux de la Station marine Endoume 31: 1–137. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Xavier1"><text><SENT sid="25292" pm="."><plain>56 XavierJR, Rachello-DolmenPG, Parra-VelandiaF, SchoenbergCHL, BreeuwerJAJ, van SoestRWM (2010) Molecular evidence of cryptic speciation in the “cosmopolitan” excavating sponge Cliona celata (Porifera, Clionaidae). Mol Phylogenet Evol 56: 13–20.20363344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Maggs1"><text><SENT sid="25293" pm="."><plain>57 MaggsCA, CastilhoR, FoltzD, HenzlerC, JollyMT, et al (2008) Evaluating signatures of glacial refugia for north Atlantic benthic marine taxa. Ecology 89: S108–S122.19097488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Santic1"><text><SENT sid="25294" pm="."><plain>58 SanticM, RadaB, PaladinA, PleslicG (2010) The influence of some abiotic parameters on growth inclination in ascidian Halocynthia papillosa (Linnaeus, 1767) from the Northern Adriatic Sea (Croatia). Arch Biol Sci 62: 1007–1011. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Sotka1"><text><SENT sid="25295" pm="."><plain>59 SotkaEE, WaresJP, BarthJA, GrosbergRK, PalumbiSR (2004) Strong genetic clines and geographical variation in gene flow in the rocky intertidal barnacle Balanus glandula . Mol Ecol 13: 2143–2156.15245390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Marko1"><text><SENT sid="25296" pm="."><plain>60 MarkoPB, HoffmanJM, EmmeSA, McgovernTM, KeeverCC, et al (2010) The ‘Expansion-Contraction’ model of Pleistocene biogeography: rocky shores suffer a sea change? Mol Ecol 19: 146–169.20092033 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Weersing1"><text><SENT sid="25297" pm="."><plain>61 WeersingK, ToonenRJ (2009) Population genetics, larval dispersal, and connectivity in marine systems. Mar Ecol-Prog Ser 393: 1–12. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Riginos1"><text><SENT sid="25298" pm="."><plain>62 RiginosC, DouglasKE, JinY, ShanahanDF, TremlEA (2011) Effects of geography and life history traits on genetic differentiation in benthic marine fishes. Ecography 34: 566–575. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Marko2"><text><SENT sid="25299" pm="."><plain>63 MarkoPB, HartMW (2011) The complex analytical landscape of gene flow inference. TREE 26: 448–456.21722987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-CollMPiroddi1"><text><SENT sid="25300" pm="."><plain>64 Coll M PiroddiC, SteenbeekJ, KaschnerK, Ben Rais LasramF, et al (2010) The biodiversity of the Mediterranean Sea: estimates, patterns, and threats. PLoS One 5: e11842.20689844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Bianchi2"><text><SENT sid="25301" pm="."><plain>65 BianchiCN (2004) Proposta di suddivisione dei mari italiani in settori biogeografici. Notiziario SIBM 46: 57–59. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Dodd1"><text><SENT sid="25302" pm="."><plain>66 DoddJM (1957) Artificial fertilisation, larval development and metamorphosis in Patella vulgata L. and Patella caerulea L. Mar Ecol PSZN 29: 172–186. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-LahbibYAbidli1"><text><SENT sid="25303" pm="."><plain>67 Lahbib Y AbidliS, ChiffoleauJF, AvertyB, El MenifNT (2010) Imposex and butyltin concentrations in snails from the lagoon of Bizerta (Northern Tunisia). Mar Biol Res 6: 600–607. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Vasconcelos1"><text><SENT sid="25304" pm="."><plain>68 VasconcelosP, GasparMB, JoaquimS, MatiasD, CastroM (2004) Spawning of Hexaplex (Trunculariopsis) trunculus (Gastropoda: Muricidae) in the laboratory: description of spawning behaviour, egg masses, embryonic development, hatchling and juvenile growth rates. Invertebr Reprod Dev 46: 125–138. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Schifano1"><text><SENT sid="25305" pm="."><plain>69 SchifanoG (1983) Allometric growth as influenced by environmental temperature in Monodonta turbinata shells. Palaeogeogr Palaeocl 44: 215–222. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Desai1"><text><SENT sid="25306" pm="."><plain>70 DesaiBN (1966) The biology of Monodonta lineata (Da Costa). J Mollus Stud 37: 1–17. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Riesgo1"><text><SENT sid="25307" pm="."><plain>71 RiesgoA, MaldonadoM (2008) Differences in reproductive timing among sponges sharing habitat and thermal regime. Invertebr Biol 127: 357–367. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Hayward1"><text><SENT sid="25308" pm="."><plain>72Hayward P, Ryland J (1995) Handbook of the marine fauna of North-West Europe Oxford University Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Brown1"><text><SENT sid="25309" pm="."><plain>73 BrownSK, RoughgardenJ (1985) Growth, morphology, and laboratory culture of larvae of Balanus glandula (Cirripedia, Thoracica). J Crustacean Biol 5: 574–590. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="pone.0101135-Crisp1"><text><SENT sid="25310" pm="."><plain>74 CrispDJ, PatelBS (1960) The moulting cycle in Balanus balanoides L. Biol Bull 118: 31–47. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
