<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Lipids Health Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Lipids Health Dis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Lipids in Health and Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1476-511X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4678523</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">162</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12944-015-0162-7</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="34597" pm="."><plain>Krill oil reduces plasma triacylglycerol level and improves related lipoprotein particle concentration, fatty acid composition and redox status in healthy young adults - a pilot study </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Berge</surname><given-names>Rolf K.</given-names></name><address><email>rolf.berge@uib.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ramsvik</surname><given-names>Marie S.</given-names></name><address><email>marie.ramsvik@olympic.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bohov</surname><given-names>Pavol</given-names></name><address><email>pavol.bohov@uib.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Svardal</surname><given-names>Asbjørn</given-names></name><address><email>asbjorn.svardal@uib.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nordrehaug</surname><given-names>Jan E.</given-names></name><address><email>jan.nordrehaug@uib.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rostrup</surname><given-names>Espen</given-names></name><address><email>espen.rostrup@helse-bergen.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bruheim</surname><given-names>Inge</given-names></name><address><email>inge.bruheim@olympic.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9718-5117</contrib-id><name><surname>Bjørndal</surname><given-names>Bodil</given-names></name><address><email>bodil.bjorndal@uib.no</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen, N-5020 Bergen, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Department of Heart Disease, Haukeland University Hospital, N-5021 Bergen, Norway </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Rimfrost AS, N-6099 Fosnavaag, Norway </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>163</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Berge et al. 2015</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34598" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="34599" pm="."><plain>Lipid abnormalities, enhanced inflammation and oxidative stress seem to represent a vicious circle in atherogenesis, and therapeutic options directed against these processes seems like a reasonable approach in the management of atherosclerotic disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34600" pm="."><plain>Krill oil (RIMFROST Sublime®) is a phospholipid-rich oil with eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA): docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) ratio of 1.8:1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34601" pm="."><plain>In this pilot study we determined if krill oil could favourable affect plasma lipid parameters and parameters involved in the initiation and progression of atherosclerosis. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34602" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="34603" pm="."><plain>The study was conducted as a 28 days intervention study examining effect-parameters of dietary supplementation with krill oil (832.5 mg EPA and DHA per day). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34604" pm="."><plain>17 healthy volunteers in the age group 18–36 (mean age 23 ± 4 years) participated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34605" pm="."><plain>Plasma lipids, lipoprotein particle sizes, fatty acid composition in plasma and red blood cells (RBCs), plasma cytokines, antioxidant capacity, acylcarntines, carnitine, choline, betaine, and trimethylamine-N-oxide (TMAO) were measured before and after supplementation. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34606" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="34607" pm="."><plain>Plasma triacylglycerol (TAG) and large very-low density lipoprotein (VLDL) &amp; chylomicron particle concentrations decreased after 28 days of krill oil intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34608" pm="."><plain>A significant reduction in the TAG/HDL cholesterol resulted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34609" pm="."><plain>Krill oil supplementation decreased n-6/n-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) ratio both in plasma and RBCs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34610" pm="."><plain>This was due to increased EPA, DHA and docosapentaenoic acid (DPA) and reduced amount of arachidonic acid (AA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34611" pm="."><plain>The increase of n-3 fatty acids and wt % of EPA and DHA in RBC was of smaller magnitude than found in plasma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34612" pm="."><plain>Krill oil intake increased the antioxidant capacity, double bond index (DBI) and the fatty acid anti-inflammatory index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34613" pm="."><plain>The plasma atherogenicity index remained constant whereas the thrombogenicity index decreased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34614" pm="."><plain>Plasma choline, betaine and the carnitine precursor, γ-butyrobetaine were increased after krill oil supplementation whereas the TMAO and carnitine concentrations remained unchanged. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="34615" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="34616" pm="."><plain>Krill oil consumption is considered health beneficial as it decreases cardiovascular disease risk parameters through effects on plasma TAGs, lipoprotein particles, fatty acid profile, redox status and possible inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34617" pm="."><plain>Noteworthy, no adverse effects on plasma levels of TMAO and carnitine were found. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Krill oil</kwd><kwd>Phospholipids</kwd><kwd>EPA</kwd><kwd>DHA</kwd><kwd>DPA</kwd><kwd>Lipoprotein particle size</kwd><kwd>Choline</kwd><kwd>Carnitine</kwd><kwd>TMAO</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100006475</institution-id><institution>Bergens Forskningsstiftelse</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Rimfrost AS, Fosnavaag, Norway</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2015</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title><text><SENT sid="34618" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34619" pm="."><plain>Cardiovascular disease (CVD) is the leading cause of death worldwide [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34620" pm="."><plain>Plasma lipids, especially cholesterol and triacylglycerol (TAG), are associated with risk for CVD and coronary artery disease [2–4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34621" pm="."><plain>Cholesterol is mostly transported in plasma by specific cholesterol-rich lipoproteins as low-density lipoproteins (LDL) or high-density lipoproteins (HDL). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34622" pm="."><plain>TAG is carried in very low-density lipoproteins (VLDL) and chylomicrons (CMs) Human trials have shown that plasma concentrations of high LDL-cholesterol, low HDL-cholesterol and high TAG are associated with elevated CVD risk [5, 6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34623" pm="."><plain>Recently, it has been found that TAG-rich lipoproteins causally influence risk for coronary artery disease (CAD) [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34624" pm="."><plain>Moreover, small dense LDL particles are shown to be more atherogenic than the larger and less dense LDL particles [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34625" pm="."><plain>Much research has been performed to the study of various interventions for the prevention of CVD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34626" pm="."><plain>Since 1970, regular consumption of fatty fish or fish oils has been stated to have several positive effects on CVD because of the presence of n-3 fatty acids, namely EPA (C20:5n-3) and DHA (C22:6n-3), and lately docosapentanenoic acid (DPA, C22:5n-3) has also become a focus of interest [9, 10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34627" pm="."><plain>Indeed, EPA and DHA supplementations have been shown to consistently lower plasma TAG concentration [11, 12] although the efficacy of EPA and DHA in the prevention of CVD has been challenged in the recent meta-analyses [13–15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34628" pm="."><plain>Thus, clinical cardiovascular benefits of these n-3 fatty acids have been reported in several, but not all human trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34629" pm="."><plain>Most probably EPA and/or DHA do not affect CVD through a single factor, but rather due to several factors such as plasma lipid concentration [11, 12], systemic and local inflammation [16], vascular endothelial function [17, 18], and oxidative stress [17, 18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34630" pm="."><plain>Krill oil from Antarctic krill (Euphausia superba) has in the last years emerged on the market as an alternative source of EPA and DHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34631" pm="."><plain>An increasing number of studies with krill oil demonstrate health benefits in animals as well as in humans [19–22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34632" pm="."><plain>While fish oils have their bioactive n-3 fatty acids incorporated into TAG or ethylesters, krill oil has EPA and DHA esterified in phospholipids (PLs) in particular phosphatidylcholine (PC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34633" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the polar structure of PLs was shown to increase the bioavailability of EPA and DHA from krill oil in comparison to fish oil [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34634" pm="."><plain>In addition to its high content of PLs, krill oil contains the antioxidant astaxanthin, which might enhance stability of n-3 fatty acids and preserve them from lipid oxidation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34635" pm="."><plain>Trimethylamine-N-oxide (TMAO) is a diet and microbiota-dependent proatherogenic metabolite and a proposed cardiovascular risk marker [24–26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34636" pm="."><plain>It´s precursors are betaine, choline and carnitine [24, 27], thus a high intake of PC and choline could potentially influence plasma levels of TMAO. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34637" pm="."><plain>The main objective of this pilot study was to investigate the effect of krill oil on plasma lipids, lipoprotein particle concentrations and fatty acid profile in plasma and red blood cells (RBC). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34638" pm="."><plain>In addition, the effect of krill oil on inflammation, antioxidant capacity (AOC), and changes in plasma levels of TMAO was evaluated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="34639" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="34640" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics of the study participants </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34641" pm="."><plain>The study included 18 healthy volunteers, of which all completed the supplementation period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34642" pm="."><plain>One volunteer had a major protocol deviation, and was excluded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34643" pm="."><plain>Thus, 17 healthy individuals (15 females, 2 males) were included in the final analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34644" pm="."><plain>The mean age was 23 years (range 20–33) and the BMI 20.9 kg/m2 (range 17.6-25.5) (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34645" pm="."><plain>Compliance of the intervention was &gt;95 % for all subjects during the period (mean 100 %; range 96 % to 100 %). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="34646" pm="."><plain>Safety parameters </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34647" pm="."><plain>No significant adverse effects or other complications were reported throughout the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34648" pm="."><plain>All safety parameters remained within normal limits both for males and females, and krill oil supplementation did not change these clinical parameters compared to baseline, with the exception of a small increase in gamma-glutamyltransferase (Table 1).Table 1Effect of krill oil supplementation on safety parametersBaselineEndpoint p-valueCRP, mg/L1.5 ± 2.12.0 ± 4.30.6ALT, U/L19.4 ± 6.420.0 ± 8.40.7AST, U/L25.6 ± 5.426.6 ± 6.70.2ALP, U/L61.7 ± 18.661.8 ± 16.00.8Bilirubin, μmol/L6.9 ± 1.98.4 ± 4.90.2Protein, g/L71.5 ± 4.771.1 ± 4.20.4Albumin, g/L46.9 ± 2.446.6 ± 2.30.5GT, U/L12.9 ± 4.714.0 ± 5.20.04Insulin, μU/mL6.3 ± 2.56.6 ± 3.70.9Glucose, mmol/L4.7 ± 0.44.8 ± 0.40.1Values are given as means ± standard deviation (n = 17). P-values ≤ 0.05 were considered statistically significantAbbreviations: ALT alanine-aminotransferase, ALP alkaline phosphatase, AST asparat aminotransferase, CRP C-reactive protein, GT gamma-glutamyltransferase </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="34649" pm="."><plain>Effect on plasma lipids and lipoprotein particle size </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34650" pm="."><plain>After krill oil supplementation the plasma level of TAG decreased significantly compared to baseline (12 %, p = 0.016; Fig. 1a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34651" pm="."><plain>The total VLDL &amp; CM particle concentration tended to decrease (p = 0.06) and this was due to significantly decreased concentrations of large VLDL &amp; CM particles, and partly due to medium VLDL particle concentration (p = 0.07; Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34652" pm="."><plain>A close positive correlation was observed between plasma TAG and large VLDL &amp; CM and medium VLDL particles (R/rs = 0.532, p = 0.001 and R = 0.559, p = 0.001, respectively; Fig. 1b and c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34653" pm="."><plain>Total plasma level of cholesterol showed a small (4 %) but significant increase by krill oil supplementation (Fig. 1d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34654" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the HDL-cholesterol (Fig. 1e) and LDL-cholesterol (Fig. 1f) were increased by krill oil intake whereas plasma non-HDL-cholesterol was unchanged (p = 0.07; Fig. 1g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34655" pm="."><plain>The ratio of HDL-cholesterol to LDL-cholesterol remained unchanged after krill oil intake (Fig. 1h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34656" pm="."><plain>These findings were accompanied by increased total HDL and LDL particle concentration mediated by large particle size (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34657" pm="."><plain>Noteworthy, the small LDL particle concentration and the IDL particle concentration remained unchanged by krill oil supplementation (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34658" pm="."><plain>Finally, the alterations in plasma lipids resulted in a significant reduction in the TAG/HDL cholesterol ratio (Fig. 1i), while the total cholesterol/HDL cholesterol ratio was unchanged (Fig. 1j). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34659" pm="."><plain>The plasma PL level increased significantly (Fig. 1k), while the plasma non-esterified fatty acid (NEFA) content remained unchanged by krill oil intake (Fig. 1l).Fig. 1Plasma lipid profile after krill oil intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34660" pm="."><plain>Plasma TAG (a), correlation between plasma TAG and large VLDL &amp; CM concentration (b), correlation between plasma TAG and medium VLDL &amp; CM concentration (c), plasma total cholesterol (d), plasma HDL-cholesterol (e), plasma LDL-cholesterol (f), plasma non-HDL-cholesterol (g), plasma HDL-cholesterol/LDL-cholesterol ratio (h), plasma TAG/HDL-cholesterol (i), plasma total cholesterol/HDL-cholesterol (j), plasma PL (k), plasma NEFA (l). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34661" pm="."><plain>Values from all 17 participants are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34662" pm="."><plain>Significant difference was determined by Wilcoxon signed-rank test (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34663" pm="."><plain>Correlation coefficients (R) were determined by Spearman correlation, and linear regressions are shownTable 2Effect of krill oil supplementation on plasma lipoprotein concentrations VLDL particle concentration, nmol/L BaselineEnd of study p-value Total VLDL &amp; Chylomicron32.8 ± 22.428.1 ± 18.80.06 Large VLDL &amp; Chylomicron1.3 ± 1.01.0 ± 0.60.04 Medium11.1 ± 10.48.9 ± 8.70.07 Small20.4 ± 12.918.3 ± 14.00.2 LDL particle concentration, nmol/L  Total873.6 ± 288.9943.4 ± 352.80.04 Large447.8 ± 201.5528.5 ± 218.40.04 Small352.1 ± 230.0348.5 ± 260.80.7 IDL73.7 ± 43.266.4 ± 76.40.4 HDL particle concentration, μmol/L  Total32.1 ± 5.633.4 ± 5.70.03 Large8.7 ± 2.89.8 ± 3.60.04 Medium10.4 ± 5.610.1 ± 5.71.0 Small13.0 ± 3.513.5 ± 4.30.9Values are given as means ± standard deviation (n = 17). P-values ≤ 0.05 were considered statistically significantAbbreviations: HDL high-density lipoprotein, IDL intermediate-density lipoprotein, LDL low-density lipoprotein, VLDL very low-density lipoprotein </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="34664" pm="."><plain>Fatty acid composition in plasma and RBC </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34665" pm="."><plain>When analysing the effects of krill oil on fatty acid composition in plasma and RBC, several findings were revealed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34666" pm="."><plain>First, while the wt % of monounsaturated fatty acids (MUFAs) and n-6 fatty acids was decreased both in plasma and RBC, the wt % of polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFAs) was increased due to increased n-3 fatty acids (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34667" pm="."><plain>Total saturated fatty acids (SFAs) were unchanged by krill oil supplementation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34668" pm="."><plain>Second, the increase of n-3 fatty acids was reflected by an increase of EPA (plasma, 218 fold; RBC, 100 fold), DPA (plasma, 50 fold; RBC, 10 fold) and DHA (plasma, 23 fold; RBC, 5 fold). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34669" pm="."><plain>Alpha linolenic acid (ALA, C18:3n-3) was not changed in plasma and RBC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34670" pm="."><plain>Third, the 5 % reduction in n-6 fatty acids in plasma and RBC was primarily reflected by a decrease in the content of linoleic acid (LA, C18:2n-6) and AA (C20:4n-6; Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34671" pm="."><plain>Finally, krill oil supplementation decreased the n-6 to n-3 ratio (Fig. 2a, b) and increased wt % of EPA and DHA (often called omega-3 index in RBC), the double bond index (DBI), and the fatty acid inflammatory index in both plasma and RBC (Fig. 2c-h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34672" pm="."><plain>Noteworthy, a more pronounced effect was observed on the n-6 to n-3 ratio and the fatty acid inflammatory index in plasma compared to RBC, despite a close correlation between wt % of EPA and DHA in plasma and RBC (R =0.665, p = 0.0001; data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34673" pm="."><plain>It is reported that the EPA level in fish oil is responsible for lowering plasma TAG in animals [28–30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34674" pm="."><plain>However, neither plasma EPA and DHA alone correlated with plasma TAG and VLDL &amp; CM particle concentration (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34675" pm="."><plain>Moreover, no associations between the wt % of EPA and DHA in plasma and RBC were found with plasma TAG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34676" pm="."><plain>It was of interest, however, to observe that krill oil supplementation decreased the plasma thrombogenicity index (Fig. 2i) whereas the atherogenicity index was unchanged (Fig. 2j).Table 3Effect of krill oil on plasma and red blood cell (RBC) fatty acid profilePlasmaRBCFatty acids Wt %BaselineEnd of study p-valueBaselineEnd of study p-value SFA31.8 ± 0.731.6 ± 1.00.240.9 ± 0.640.7 ± 0.60.8 MUFA25.2 ± 2.323.6 ± 2.90.00717.5 ± 0.717.3 ± 0.90.02 PUFA42.8 ± 2.744.6 ± 3.20.00541.4 ± 0.741.8 ± 0.80.003 n-6 PUFAs 37.0 ± 2.735.1 ± 3.70.00829.9 ± 1.828.5 ± 1.7&lt;0.0001 C18:2n-6 (LA)27.7 ± 2.726.8 ± 3.50.79.1 ± 1.08.7 ± 1.00.02 C20:3n-61.5 ± 0.31.3 ± 0.30.00081.5 ± 0.41.4 ± 0.30.002 C20:4n-6 (AA)7.0 ± 1.66.3 ± 1.40.000715.9 ± 1.515.1 ± 1.4&lt;0.0001 C22:5n-60.1 ± 0.030.1 ± 0.02&lt;0.00010.4 ± 0.10.4 ± 0.07&lt;0.0001 n-3 PUFAs 5.7 ± 1.59.4 ± 1.6&lt;0.000111.3 ± 1.713.2 ± 1.5&lt;0.0001 C18:3n-3 (ALA)0.7 ± 0.20.7 ± 0.30.80.2 ± 0.030.2 ± 0.040.8 C20:5n-3 (EPA)1.1 ± 0.63.6 ± 0.80.00021.2 ± 0.42.5 ± 0.4&lt;0.0001 C22:5n-3 (DPA)0.6 ± 0.10.8 ± 0.2&lt;0.00012.8 ± 0.43.1 ± 0.3&lt;0.0001 C22:6n-3 (DHA)3.2 ± 0.83.9 ± 0.70.00027.0 ± 1.27.4 ± 1.0&lt;0.0001Values indicate plasma and RBC content by percent weight (wt %) P-values ≤ 0.05 were considered statistically significantAbbreviations: AA arachidonic acid, ALA alpha linolenic acid, DHA docosahexaenoic acid, DPA docosapentaenoic acid, EPA eicosapentaenoic acid, LA linoleic acid, MUFAs monounsaturated fatty acids, n-3 omega-3, n-6 omega-6, PUFAs polyunsaturated fatty acids, SFAs saturated fatty acidsFig. 2Fatty acid composition in plasma and RBC after krill oil supplementation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34677" pm="."><plain>Plasma n-6/n-3 ratio (a), RBC n-6/n-3 ratio (b), plasma wt % of EPA + DHA (c), RBC wt % of EPA + DHA (omega-3 index)(d), plasma double bond index (e), RBC double bond index (f), plasma anti-inflammatory index (g), RBC anti-inflammatory index (h), plasma trombogenicity index (i), plasma atherogenicity index (j). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34678" pm="."><plain>Values are given as means with standard deviations (n = 17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34679" pm="."><plain>Significant difference was determined by Wilcoxon signed-rank test (***p &lt; 0.001) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="34680" pm="."><plain>Effect on antioxidant status </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34681" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress is associated with decreased fatty acid unsaturation and increased lipid peroxidation [31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34682" pm="."><plain>The plasma total antioxidant capacity (AOC) significantly increased after krill oil intake (Fig. 3a) and it was of interest that AOC positively correlated to plasma EPA concentration (R = 0.395, p = 0.021; Fig. 3b), RBC EPA concentration (R = 0.443, p = 0.009: Fig. 3c) and RBC DBI (R = 0.409, p = 0.016; Fig. 3d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34683" pm="."><plain>No correlation was found between AOC and DHA concentrations in plasma and RBC after krill oil intake, but the wt % of EPA and DHA both in plasma and RBC correlated to AOC (data not shown).Fig. 3Antioxidant capacity (AOC) status after krill oil intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34684" pm="."><plain>Plasma level of AOC (a), correlation between plasma EPA concentration and AOC (b), correlation between EPA concentration in RBC and AOC (c), correlation between DBI and AOC in RBC (d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34685" pm="."><plain>AOC is given as mean with standard deviation (n = 14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34686" pm="."><plain>Significant difference was determined by Wilcoxon signed-rank test (**p &lt; 0.01). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34687" pm="."><plain>Correlation coefficients (R) were determined by Spearman correlation, and linear regressions are shown </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="34688" pm="."><plain>Effect on systemic inflammation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34689" pm="."><plain>Krill oil supplementation in humans could be expected to have anti-inflammatory potential in plasma as the fatty acid anti-inflammatory index increased (Fig. 2g). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34690" pm="."><plain>However, the plasma cytokines IL-1β, IL-10, IL-17, granulocyte colony-stimulating factor (G- CSF) and tumor necrosis factor alpha (TNFα) were unchanged after krill oil intake (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="34691" pm="."><plain>Effect on choline, betaine, carnitine and TMAO </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34692" pm="."><plain>TMAO is a substance formed in the liver from trimethylamine generated by the gut microbiota from dietary PC, choline, betaine and carnitine [24–27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34693" pm="."><plain>Krill contains both PC and TMAO, while krill oil only contains PC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34694" pm="."><plain>The plasma level of TMAO was not affected by krill oil intake (Fig. 4a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34695" pm="."><plain>Both choline and its metabolite betaine increased in plasma after 28 days with krill oil supplementation (Fig. 4b, c), whereas the plasma carnitine level remained constant (Fig. 4d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34696" pm="."><plain>The carnitine precursor, γ-butyrobetaine was significantly increased in plasma by krill oil intake compared to baseline values (Fig. 4e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34697" pm="."><plain>The other carnitine precursor, trimethyllysine, remained unchanged over the intervention period (Fig. 4f).Fig. 4Plasma TMAO, carnitine, and carnitine precursors after krill oil intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34698" pm="."><plain>Plasma levels of TMAO (a), choline (b), betaine (c), carnitine (d), γ-butyrobetaine (e), and trimethyllysine (f). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34699" pm="."><plain>Values are given as means with standard deviation (n = 17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34700" pm="."><plain>Significant difference was determined by Wilcoxon signed-rank test (*p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="34701" pm="."><plain>Effect on plasma acylcarnitine level </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34702" pm="."><plain>It is reported that high serum concentrations of long-and medium plasma acylcarnitines are linked to increased risk of disease progression with CAD, especially in heart failure patients [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34703" pm="."><plain>Moreover, increased plasma concentrations of these acylcarnitines may indicate defects in mitochondria function [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34704" pm="."><plain>In the present study, plasma octanoylcarnitine level was decreased after krill oil intake (Fig. 5a), whereas the palmitoylcarnitine and acetylcarnitine levels remained unchanged (Fig. 5b, c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34705" pm="."><plain>In the current study a 15 to 20% (compared to baseline) reduction resulted for the short-chain acylcarnitines, namely iso-/L-valerylcarnitine and propionylcarnitine (Fig. 5d, e).Fig. 5Plasma acylcarnitines after krill oil intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34706" pm="."><plain>Plasma levels of octanoylcarnitine (a), palmitoylcarnitine (b), acetylcarnitine (c), iso-/L-valerylcarnitine (d), and propionylcarnitine (e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34707" pm="."><plain>Values are given as means with standard deviation (n = 17). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34708" pm="."><plain>Significant difference was determined by Wilcoxon signed-rank test (**p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="34709" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34710" pm="."><plain>The present study has shown that 28 days supplementation of krill oil had significant biological effects in healthy subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34711" pm="."><plain>Moreover, intake of this EPA-and DHA rich PC-oil beneficially affected several parameters linked to CVD-risk, including plasma lipids, lipoprotein particle concentrations, fatty acid composition, redox status and potentially inflammation and thrombogenicity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34712" pm="."><plain>However, a small increase in cholesterol was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34713" pm="."><plain>The krill oil intake did not change the safety parameters (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34714" pm="."><plain>Krill oil intake reduced plasma TAG levels due to decreased concentration of large VLDL &amp; CM particles (Table 2), concomitant with increased concentration of large HDL particles and decreased TAG/HDL ratio (Fig. 1i). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34715" pm="."><plain>Large LDL particles also increased after 28 days krill oil supplementation and this resulted in a modest, but significantly higher plasma total cholesterol level (Fig.1d). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34716" pm="."><plain>However, total cholesterol/HDL, a robust risk parameter in European populations [34], was unaltered (Fig. 1j). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34717" pm="."><plain>The increase in large HDL particles in response to n-3 PUFA supplementation has been demonstrated in several studies [35, 36], and may be explained by a reduced exposure to cholesterol ester transfer protein (CETP)-mediated transfer of cholesterol from HDL particles due to a lower concentration of TAG rich large VLDL and CM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34718" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the increased concentration of large HDL-and LDL particles has mainly been found with DHA, but not EPA supplementation [37, 38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34719" pm="."><plain>Noteworthy, the concentration of the more atherogenic small LDL particles remained constant after krill oil supplementation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34720" pm="."><plain>It has been assumed that EPA or DHA, or both, are responsible for the TAG-lowering effect after supplementation of n-3 PUFA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34721" pm="."><plain>Most studies have used fish oil with various contents of EPA and DHA, and only a few studies have examined the effect of EPA and DHA separately to determine for the effects for each fatty acid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34722" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have demonstrated n-3 PUFA supplementation to lower plasma TAG levels when ingesting 2–4 g EPA and DHA per day for 6 weeks or longer, although the effect seem to be strongest among people with an unfavourable risk profile [11, 12, 39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34723" pm="."><plain>Supplementation with 4 g EPA per day for 6–7 weeks has been shown to reduce TAG by 21 % [40] and 23 % [38] in mildly hyperlipidaemic subjects, and by 12 % in healthy subjects [41]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34724" pm="."><plain>The present study showed a reduction in TAG levels (12 %, p = 0.02) in healthy young adults after 28 days of supplementation with 832.5 mg EPA and DHA from krill oil with an EPA:DHA ratio of approximately 1.8:1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34725" pm="."><plain>This indicates a high bioavailability of krill oil (RIMFROST Sublime®) and a subsequent rapid effect on lipid metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34726" pm="."><plain>Moreover, this is in line with a recent study in adults with high TAG levels where a dose of 0.5-2 g/day krill oil significantly reduced plasma TAG [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34727" pm="."><plain>In humans, supplementation of EPA gives rise to EPA and DPA, but not DHA whereas DHA supplementation gives formation of DPA and EPA [41, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34728" pm="."><plain>In keeping with these findings our present study gave rise in DPA both in RBC (approximately 10 %) and plasma (approximately 23 %) and was greater than would be expected, as krill oil does not contain DPA (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34729" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown similar results, both in RBC [43] and in plasma [21, 44, 45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34730" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in the present study the increase in DPA both in plasma and RBCs was higher than DHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34731" pm="."><plain>We have recently found that PLs from herring roe with a DHA:EPA ratio of about 3:1 decreased plasma TAG in healthy subjects [46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34732" pm="."><plain>Despite a dose of 132 mg DPA/day and the possibility of formation of DPA from EPA, DPA levels were not influenced by herring roe PLs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34733" pm="."><plain>This suggests that DPA is less important in mediating TAG lowering effects both in krill oil and oil from herring.Table 4Composition of the krill oil (wt %)Fatty acida Krill oil capsules∑ SFAs36.5 C14:011.4 C16:024.0 C18:01.3 C20:0&lt;0.1 C22:0&lt;0.1∑ MUFAs26.2 C16:1n-75.5 C18:1 (n-9) + (n-7) + (n-5)19.3 C20:1 (n-9) + (n-7)1.0 C22:1 (n-11) + (n-9) + (n-7)0.6 C24:1n-9&lt;0.1 n-6 PUFAs2.6 C18:2n-6 (LA)2.1 C18:3n-60.2 C20:2n-60.2 C20:3n-6&lt;0.1 C20:4n-6 (AA)0.2 C22:4n-6&lt;0.1 n-3 PUFAs34.1 C18:3n-3 (ALA)1.1 C18:4n-33.7 C20:3n-3&lt;0.1 C20:4n-30.3 C20:5n-3 (EPA)18.0 C21:5n-30.5 C22:5n-3 (DPA)0.5 C22:6n-3 (DHA)10.1Lipidsb   Total polar lipids  47.6   Phosphatidylcholin (PC)44.0  Lyso-PC2.3  Phosphatidylethanolamine (PE)1.4  Free fatty acids3.1  Total neutral lipids  52.4   Triacylglycerol (TAG)44.0  Diacylglycerol2.1  Monoacylglycerol&lt;0.1  Free fatty acids3.1 ag/100 g extracted fatty acids. bg/100 g extracted lipidsAbbreviations: see legend to Table 3  </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34734" pm="."><plain>Studies in cultured rat hepatocytes have shown that EPA increases mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation [30], and as recently reviewed, plasma acylcarnitine levels can give an indication on mitochondrial function [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34735" pm="."><plain>When acyl-CoAs accumulate in the mitochondrial matrix, acylcarnitine formation is favoured, which can exit the mitochondrion and access the peripheral circulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34736" pm="."><plain>The intra-mitochondrial relationship between acyl-CoA and free CoA is reflected by the extra-mitochondrial acylcarnitine to free carnitine ratio, given that any mitochondrial acyl-CoA accumulation leads to a corresponding increase in acylcarnitines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34737" pm="."><plain>In situations of inefficient β-oxidation, intermediates such as octanoyl- and palmitoylcarnitine will be formed, which are considered toxic [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34738" pm="."><plain>Elevated palmitoylcarnitine has been associated with poor prognosis in chronic heart failure (CHF) patients [32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34739" pm="."><plain>In the present study the plasma level of octanoylcarnitine was decreased by krill oil supplementation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34740" pm="."><plain>Altogether, this suggests that the krill oil intervention may be responsible for more efficient fatty acid oxidation of medium-chain length fatty acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34741" pm="."><plain>Noteworthy, this is in consistence with findings in animal studies where krill oil was shown to influence metabolic pathways, including fatty acid oxidation, lipid biosynthesis and acylcarntine turnover [48, 49]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34742" pm="."><plain>Choline is mainly utilized for PC biosynthesis, which is required for membrane formation and can take place through two pathways, namely CDP-choline (Kennedy) pathway and the phospatidylethanolamine N-methyltransferase (PEMT) pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34743" pm="."><plain>Moreover, choline can be oxidized to betaine, which is involved in the remethylation of homocysteine to methionine in the one-carbon cycle [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34744" pm="."><plain>In the present study plasma choline and betaine was increased by krill supplementation, indicating an increased PC degradation and increased choline oxidation, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34745" pm="."><plain>Choline is an important nutrient and is predominantly obtained from the diet [51, 52], although it can be synthesised de novo. In a recent European study, the average choline intake was below the adequate intake (set by the Institute of Medicine in the USA) in most of the population groups considered [53]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34746" pm="."><plain>Thus, krill oil can be a well-suited supplement for populations vulnerable to choline deficiency. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34747" pm="."><plain>TMAO is formed in the liver from trimethylamine, a product generated by the gut microbiota from dietary PC, choline and carnitine. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34748" pm="."><plain>Trimethylamine can also be generated from betaine [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34749" pm="."><plain>Recent studies have shown that TMAO is a diet and microbiota-dependent proatherogenic metabolite and cardiovascular risk marker [24–27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34750" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in the present study the plasma TMAO level remained constant by krill oil supplementation, demonstrating that the extra choline intake did not influence TMAO generation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34751" pm="."><plain>AA is a precursor for prostaglandins [16] and is considered proinflammatory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34752" pm="."><plain>Krill oil supplementation decreased the level of AA and increased amounts of n-3 PUFAs in plasma and RBC resulting in an increased anti-inflammatory fatty acid index. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34753" pm="."><plain>This implies that krill oil intake has anti-inflammatory properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34754" pm="."><plain>The plasma cytokines, however, remained unchanged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34755" pm="."><plain>The plasma total antioxidant status significantly increased after krill oil supplementation (Fig. 3a) and it was of interest that AOC positively correlated with the plasma and RBC levels of EPA and wt % of EPA and DHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34756" pm="."><plain>Moreover, plasma AOC correlated with RBC DBI but no correlation was found between AOC and DHA concentrations in plasma and RBC after krill oil intake (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34757" pm="."><plain>Whether the presence of astaxanthin is responsible for the oxidative protective effect observed, should be considered [54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34758" pm="."><plain>This is an important point, as the removal of protective trace compounds in the generation of highly purified PUFAs has been reported to reduce the beneficial effect of fish oil supplements [55]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="34759" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34760" pm="."><plain>28 days of krill oil supplementation in healthy young adults reduced plasma TAG and large VLDL &amp; CM particle concentration, whereas the concentrations of large HDL and LDL were increased. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34761" pm="."><plain>The changes in fatty acid composition in plasma and RBC were accompanied by increased n-3 PUFAs, decreased level of AA and increased the plasma antioxidant status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34762" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, no adverse effects of krill oil intake on plasma TMAO levels were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34763" pm="."><plain>Thus, a dose of 832.5 mg EPA and DHA from krill oil had beneficial biological effects in persons with a normal lipid profile, and may prevent the development of several risk factors related to CVD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="34764" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec14"><title><text><SENT sid="34765" pm="."><plain>Study population </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34766" pm="."><plain>18 subjects in the age group 18–36, with a body mass index (BMI; in kg/m2) of 17–29.9 and in a generally good health, were recruited to the pilot study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34767" pm="."><plain>Exclusion criteria were disease related to fat metabolism or digestion, acute or chronic inflammatory conditions, liver dysfunctions, pregnancy (all self-reported), obesity (defined as a BMI ≥30), inability to swallow capsules and unwillingness to take blood samples. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title><text><SENT sid="34768" pm="."><plain>Intervention </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34769" pm="."><plain>The intervention used was krill oil capsules (RIMFROST Sublime ®, Rimfrost AS, Fosnavaag, Norway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34770" pm="."><plain>The lipid- and fatty acid composition of the oil is presented in Table 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34771" pm="."><plain>Each capsule (500 mg) contained 210 mg PLs and 120 mg n-3 PUFA, of which 60 mg was EPA and 32.5 mg DHA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34772" pm="."><plain>The participants received 9 capsules per day for 28 days, corresponding to a daily dose of 832.5 mg EPA and DHA Moreover, the oil contained 192 mg astaxanthin per kg. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title><text><SENT sid="34773" pm="."><plain>Study procedures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34774" pm="."><plain>Subjects were recruited through advertisements presented at the University of Bergen and the Bergen University College (Norway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34775" pm="."><plain>After written informed consent to participate was provided, blood samples were drawn, and body weight and height were recorded to calculate body mass index (BMI; kg/m2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34776" pm="."><plain>Study participants were interviewed about their dietary intake of food stuffs rich in n-3 fatty acids and PLs, focusing on the amount and frequency of the last month intake. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34777" pm="."><plain>Participants were advised to maintain a steady intake of these food items during the study period, refrain from the use of all nutritional supplements, and to maintain their body weight. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34778" pm="."><plain>At the end of the study, all participants were asked to answer questionnaires to assess self-reported compliance and product tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34779" pm="."><plain>The 18 subjects included all completed the intervention period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34780" pm="."><plain>However, one subject (male) was excluded from the final analysis due to protocol deviation revealed by the questionnaires. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title><text><SENT sid="34781" pm="."><plain>Blood sample collection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34782" pm="."><plain>Blood samples were collected from subjects fasted overnight and seated for 15 minutes, at the beginning (baseline) and end of the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34783" pm="."><plain>At both time points, blood samples were centrifuged and EDTA-plasma and serum was collected after a minimum of 15 minutes and maximum of 30 minutes at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34784" pm="."><plain>Blood samples for isolation of RBC was drawn in EDTA-tubes, centrifuged at 3000 rpm for 10 minutes, and plasma and interface removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34785" pm="."><plain>RBC was then washed three times in phosphate buffered saline (PBS), with subsequent centrifugation and removal of the buffy coat (white blood cells) between each wash. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34786" pm="."><plain>Finally, the original volume was reconstituted using PBS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34787" pm="."><plain>All samples were aliquoted and stored at −80°C for further analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title><text><SENT sid="34788" pm="."><plain>Total fatty acid composition in the red blood cells (RBC) and in plasma </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34789" pm="."><plain>The total fatty acid composition was analysed in RBC and in EDTA-plasma, as previously described [56]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34790" pm="."><plain>The omega-3 index is defined as the sum of EPA and DHA in RBC, expressed as a percentage of the total fatty acid (TFA) content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34791" pm="."><plain>The anti-inflammatory index is defined as the sum of EPA (C20:5n-3), dihomo-gamma-linolenic acid (DGLA, C20:3n-6), DHA (C22:6n-3) and DPA (C22:5n-3), divided on AA (C20:4n-6), multiplied with 100. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34792" pm="."><plain>The double bound index (DBI) is defined as (MUFA + 2*(C18:2n6 + C20:2n6 + C22:2n6) + 3*(C18:3n6 + C18:3n3 + C20:3n9 + C20:3n6) + 4*(C18:4n3 + C20:4n6 + C20:4n3 + C22:4n6) + 5*(C20:5n3 + C21:5n3 + C22:5n6 + C22:5n3) + 6*(C22:6n3))/TFA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34793" pm="."><plain>The atherogenicity index (AI) and the thrombogenenicity (TI) were determined according to Ulbricht and Southgate [57] equations: AI = (C12:0 + 4*C14:0 + C16:0)/(ΣMUFA + Σ(n-6 PUFA) + Σ(n-3 PUFA)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34794" pm="."><plain>TI = (C14:0 + C16:0 + C18:0)/(0.5*ΣMUFA + 0.5*Σ(n-6 PUFA) + 3*Σ(n-3 PUFA) + (Σ(n-3 PUFA)/Σ(n-6 PUFA)), where ΣMUFA, Σ(n-6 PUFA), and Σ(n-3 PUFA) are the sum of MUFA, n-6 and n-3 PUFA in wt % of total fatty acids, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title><text><SENT sid="34795" pm="."><plain>Lipids and lipoproteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34796" pm="."><plain>Lipids were measured enzymatically in EDTA-plasma on a Hitachi 917 system (Roche Diagnostics GmbH, Mannheim, Germany) using the triacylglycerol (GPO-PAP), cholesterol (CHOD-PAP), HDL-cholesterol plus and LDL-cholesterol plus kit from Roche Diagnostics, the non-esterified fatty acid (NEFA FS) kit and the Phospholipids FS kit 17 from DiaSys Diagnostic Systems GmbH (Holzheim, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34797" pm="."><plain>Lipoprotein size was measured in EDTA-plasma with nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy by LabCorp Inc (Burlington, NC, USA), using the NMR LipoProfile® test (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.liposcience.com">http://www.labcorp.com</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title><text><SENT sid="34798" pm="."><plain>Biochemical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34799" pm="."><plain>Plasma choline, betaine, trimethyllysine (TML), butyrobetaine and trimethylamine N-oxide (TMAO), as well as L-carnitine, acetylcarnitine, proponylcarnitine, octanoylcarnitine, iso-/L-valerylcarnitine and palmitoylcarnitine, were analysed in EDTA-plasma using LC/MS/MS as previously described [58, 59]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34800" pm="."><plain>Clinical laboratory measurements, including safety parameters were measured in EDTA-plasma using routine methods at the central laboratory at Haukeland University Hospital (Bergen, Norway). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34801" pm="."><plain>Total AOC of plasma was measured using the total antioxidant capacity kit (Abcam, Cambridge, UK) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34802" pm="."><plain>The protein mask was not used, enabling the analysis of both small molecule antioxidants and proteins ability to reduce Cu2+ to Cu+. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34803" pm="."><plain>In brief, EDTA-plasma was allowed to reduce Cu2+ for 1.5 hour at room temperature on an orbital shaker. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34804" pm="."><plain>The absorbance was measured at 570 nm using a plate reader. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34805" pm="."><plain>Results were expressed as trolox equivalents according to a trolox standard curve. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34806" pm="."><plain>The levels of IL-1β, IL-10, IL-17, G-CSF and TNF-α were measured in plasma samples using a custom-made multiplex MILLIPLEX MAP kit (Millipore Corp., St. Charles, IL, USA), and the assay solution was read by the Bio-Plex array reader (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA) and determined with the Bio-Plex Manager Software 4.1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title><text><SENT sid="34807" pm="."><plain>Questionnaires </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34808" pm="."><plain>All participants were asked to answer a questionnaire to assess compliance, supplementation regime, product tolerance and to report of possible gastrointestinal (GI) symptoms occurring when ingesting the supplement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34809" pm="."><plain>Compliance was further determined by capsule logs and validated by count of capsules in surplus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34810" pm="."><plain>An authorised clinical nutritionist interviewed the participants into the regime, and general product tolerance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title><text><SENT sid="34811" pm="."><plain>Ethical aspects </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34812" pm="."><plain>All examinations and blood samples were performed at the Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen, Norway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34813" pm="."><plain>The study protocol was approved by the Regional Ethics Committee of Northern Norway (Registration number 2013/2152), and registered on ClinicalTrials.gov (NCT02053415). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34814" pm="."><plain>All procedures were carried out in accordance with the ethical standards of the Helsinki declaration of 1975, revised in 2004, for experiments involving humans (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wma.net/en/30publications/10policies/b3/index.html">http://www.wma.net/en/30publications/10policies/b3/index.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title><text><SENT sid="34815" pm="."><plain>Statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34816" pm="."><plain>Data sets were analysed using Prism Software (Prism Graph-Pad Software, version 6, San Diego, California, USA) to determine statistical significance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34817" pm="."><plain>The results are reported as means per group with their standard deviations (SD), with exception of age, BMI and compliance, which is reported as mean with range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34818" pm="."><plain>Wilcoxon signed-rank test was performed to evaluate statistical differences of matched pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34819" pm="."><plain>Correlation coefficients (R) were determined by Spearman correlation, and linear regressions are shown in selected figures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34820" pm="."><plain>P-values &lt; 0.05 were considered significant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="34821" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34822" pm="."><plain>Rimfrost employs IB and MSR, provided the krill oil capsules (RIMFROST Sublime ®), and partly financed the study, but had no role in collection, analysis and interpretation of the data, in writing of the report or in the decision to submit article for publication. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="34823" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="34824" pm="."><plain>BB performed the intervention study and finalized the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34825" pm="."><plain>RKB drafted the manuscript, and together with BB, MSR and IB conceived and designed the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34826" pm="."><plain>MSR took part in performing the study, analysing the data, and wrote the method section. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34827" pm="."><plain>AS carried out the carnitine, acylcarnitines and TMAO analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34828" pm="."><plain>PB was responsible for the fatty acid composition analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34829" pm="."><plain>IB, ER and JEN participated in the interpretation of data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34830" pm="."><plain>All authors critically revised the manuscript, and read and approved the final version. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="34831" pm="."><plain>The authors would like to thank Kari Williams, Elin Strand, Liv Kristine Øysæd, Kari Mortensen, Torunn Eide and Randi Sandvik for valuable technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34832" pm="."><plain>We also thank all the study participants and the bachelor student Cecilie Larsen in Human Nutrition (University of Bergen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34833" pm="."><plain>The study was financed by Rimfrost AS and the Bergen Research Foundation. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="34834" pm="."><plain>1.The top 10 causes of death - Fact sheet. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs310/en/">http://www.who.int/mediacentre/factsheets/fs310/en. Accessed 4 Dec 2015</ext-link>] </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="34835" pm="."><plain>2.World Health Organization (WHO)Prevention of cardiovascular disease: guidelines for assessment and management of total cardiovascular risk2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="34836" pm="."><plain>3.EmbersonJRWhincupPHMorrisRWWalkerMRe-assessing the contribution of serum total cholesterol, blood pressure and cigarette smoking to the aetiology of coronary heart disease: impact of regression dilution biasEur Heart J2003241719172610.1016/S0195-668X(03)00471-8<?supplied-pmid 14522566?>14522566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="34837" pm="."><plain>4.YusufSHawkenSOunpuuSDansTAvezumALanasFEffects of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with myocardial infarction in the 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): case–control studyLancet200436493795210.1016/S0140-6736(04)17018-9<?supplied-pmid 15364185?>15364185 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="34838" pm="."><plain>5.BarterPGottoAMLaRosaJCMaroniJSzarekMGrundySMHDL cholesterol, very low levels of LDL cholesterol, and cardiovascular eventsN Engl J Med20073571301131010.1056/NEJMoa064278<?supplied-pmid 17898099?>17898099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="34839" pm="."><plain>6.MillerMCannonCPMurphySAQinJRayKKBraunwaldEImpact of triglyceride levels beyond low-density lipoprotein cholesterol after acute coronary syndrome in the PROVE IT-TIMI 22 trialJ Am Coll Cardiol20085172473010.1016/j.jacc.2007.10.038<?supplied-pmid 18279736?>18279736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="34840" pm="."><plain>7.EgelandGMIglandJSuloGNygardOEbbingMTellGSNon-fasting triglycerides predict incident acute myocardial infarction among those with favourable HDL-cholesterol: Cohort NorwayEur J Prev Cardiol20152287288110.1177/2047487314535681<?supplied-pmid 24817696?>24817696 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="34841" pm="."><plain>8.GaleanoNFAl-HaideriMKeysermanFRumseySCDeckelbaumRJSmall dense low density lipoprotein has increased affinity for LDL receptor-independent cell surface binding sites: a potential mechanism for increased atherogenicityJ Lipid Res19983912631273<?supplied-pmid 9643358?>9643358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="34842" pm="."><plain>9.BucherHCHengstlerPSchindlerCMeierGN-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids in coronary heart disease: a meta-analysis of randomized controlled trialsAm J Med200211229830410.1016/S0002-9343(01)01114-7<?supplied-pmid 11893369?>11893369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="34843" pm="."><plain>10.Delgado-ListaJPerez-MartinezPLopez-MirandaJPerez-JimenezFLong chain omega-3 fatty acids and cardiovascular disease: a systematic reviewBr J Nutr2012107Suppl 2S20121310.1017/S0007114512001596<?supplied-pmid 22591894?>22591894 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="34844" pm="."><plain>11.MoriTAWoodmanRJThe independent effects of eicosapentaenoic acid and docosahexaenoic acid on cardiovascular risk factors in humansCurr Opin Clin Nutr Metab Care200699510410.1097/01.mco.0000214566.67439.58<?supplied-pmid 16477172?>16477172 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="34845" pm="."><plain>12.von SchackyCA review of omega-3 ethyl esters for cardiovascular prevention and treatment of increased blood triglyceride levelsVasc Health Risk Manag2006225126210.2147/vhrm.2006.2.3.25117326331 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="34846" pm="."><plain>13.EnnsJEYeganehAZarychanskiRAbou-SettaAMFriesenCZahradkaPThe impact of omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid supplementation on the incidence of cardiovascular events and complications in peripheral arterial disease: a systematic review and meta-analysisBMC Cardiovasc Disord2014147010.1186/1471-2261-14-70<?supplied-pmid 24885361?>24885361 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="34847" pm="."><plain>14.KotwalSJunMSullivanDPerkovicVNealBOmega 3 Fatty acids and cardiovascular outcomes: systematic review and meta-analysisCirc Cardiovasc Qual Outcomes2012580881810.1161/CIRCOUTCOMES.112.966168<?supplied-pmid 23110790?>23110790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="34848" pm="."><plain>15.RizosECNtzaniEEBikaEKostapanosMSElisafMSAssociation between omega-3 fatty acid supplementation and risk of major cardiovascular disease events: a systematic review and meta-analysisJama20123081024103310.1001/2012.jama.11374<?supplied-pmid 22968891?>22968891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="34849" pm="."><plain>16.CalderPCn-3 polyunsaturated fatty acids, inflammation, and inflammatory diseasesAm J Clin Nutr2006831505S1519S<?supplied-pmid 16841861?>16841861 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="34850" pm="."><plain>17.MoriTABeilinLJOmega-3 fatty acids and inflammationCurr Atheroscler Rep2004646146710.1007/s11883-004-0087-5<?supplied-pmid 15485592?>15485592 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="34851" pm="."><plain>18.MassaroMScodittiECarluccioMADe CaterinaRBasic mechanisms behind the effects of n-3 fatty acids on cardiovascular diseaseProstaglandins Leukot Essent Fatty Acids20087910911510.1016/j.plefa.2008.09.009<?supplied-pmid 18951002?>18951002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="34852" pm="."><plain>19.BergeKMusa-VelosoKHarwoodMHoemNBurriLKrill oil supplementation lowers serum triglycerides without increasing low-density lipoprotein cholesterol in adults with borderline high or high triglyceride levelsNutr Res20143412613310.1016/j.nutres.2013.12.003<?supplied-pmid 24461313?>24461313 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="34853" pm="."><plain>20.BurriLJohnsenLKrill products: an overview of animal studiesNutrients201573300332110.3390/nu7053300<?supplied-pmid 25961320?>25961320 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="34854" pm="."><plain>21.UlvenSMKirkhusBLamglaitABasuSElindEHaiderTMetabolic effects of krill oil are essentially similar to those of fish oil but at lower dose of EPA and DHA, in healthy volunteersLipids201146374610.1007/s11745-010-3490-4<?supplied-pmid 21042875?>21042875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="34855" pm="."><plain>22.TillanderVBjorndalBBurriLBohovPSkorveJBergeRKFish oil and krill oil supplementations differentially regulate lipid catabolic and synthetic pathways in miceNutr Metab (Lond)2014112010.1186/1743-7075-11-2024834104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="34856" pm="."><plain>23.KohlerASarkkinenETapolaNNiskanenTBruheimIBioavailability of fatty acids from krill oil, krill meal and fish oil in healthy subjects--a randomized, single-dose, cross-over trialLipids Health Dis2015141910.1186/s12944-015-0015-4<?supplied-pmid 25884846?>25884846 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="34857" pm="."><plain>24.KoethRAWangZLevisonBSBuffaJAOrgESheehyBTIntestinal microbiota metabolism of L-carnitine, a nutrient in red meat, promotes atherosclerosisNat Med20131957658510.1038/nm.3145<?supplied-pmid 23563705?>23563705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="34858" pm="."><plain>25.TangWHWangZLevisonBSKoethRABrittEBFuXIntestinal microbial metabolism of phosphatidylcholine and cardiovascular riskN Engl J Med20133681575158410.1056/NEJMoa1109400<?supplied-pmid 23614584?>23614584 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="34859" pm="."><plain>26.WangZKlipfellEBennettBJKoethRLevisonBSDugarBGut flora metabolism of phosphatidylcholine promotes cardiovascular diseaseNature2011472576310.1038/nature09922<?supplied-pmid 21475195?>21475195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="34860" pm="."><plain>27.ReboucheCJSeimHCarnitine metabolism and its regulation in microorganisms and mammalsAnnu Rev Nutr199818396110.1146/annurev.nutr.18.1.39<?supplied-pmid 9706218?>9706218 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="34861" pm="."><plain>28.IkedaIWakamatsuKInayoshiAImaizumiKSuganoMYazawaKalpha-Linolenic, eicosapentaenoic and docosahexaenoic acids affect lipid metabolism differently in ratsJ Nutr199412418981906<?supplied-pmid 7931698?>7931698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="34862" pm="."><plain>29.WillumsenNHexebergSSkorveJLundquistMBergeRKDocosahexaenoic acid shows no triglyceride-lowering effects but increases the peroxisomal fatty acid oxidation in liver of ratsJ Lipid Res1993341322<?supplied-pmid 8445337?>8445337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="34863" pm="."><plain>30.WillumsenNSkorveJHexebergSRustanACBergeRKThe hypotriglyceridemic effect of eicosapentaenoic acid in rats is reflected in increased mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation followed by diminished lipogenesisLipids19932868369010.1007/BF02535987<?supplied-pmid 8377581?>8377581 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="34864" pm="."><plain>31.AssiesJMockingRJLokARuheHGPouwerFScheneAHEffects of oxidative stress on fatty acid- and one-carbon-metabolism in psychiatric and cardiovascular disease comorbidityActa Psychiatr Scand201413016318010.1111/acps.12265<?supplied-pmid 24649967?>24649967 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="34865" pm="."><plain>32.UelandTSvardalAOieEAskevoldETNymoenSHBjorndalBDisturbed carnitine regulation in chronic heart failure--increased plasma levels of palmitoyl-carnitine are associated with poor prognosisInt J Cardiol20131671892189910.1016/j.ijcard.2012.04.150<?supplied-pmid 22622056?>22622056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="34866" pm="."><plain>33.ReuterSEEvansAMCarnitine and acylcarnitines: pharmacokinetic, pharmacological and clinical aspectsClin Pharmacokinet20125155357210.1007/BF03261931<?supplied-pmid 22804748?>22804748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="34867" pm="."><plain>34.McQueenMJHawkenSWangXOunpuuSSnidermanAProbstfieldJLipids, lipoproteins, and apolipoproteins as risk markers of myocardial infarction in 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): a case–control studyLancet200837222423310.1016/S0140-6736(08)61076-4<?supplied-pmid 18640459?>18640459 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="34868" pm="."><plain>35.CalabresiLVillaBCanavesiMSirtoriCRJamesRWBerniniFAn omega-3 polyunsaturated fatty acid concentrate increases plasma high-density lipoprotein 2 cholesterol and paraoxonase levels in patients with familial combined hyperlipidemiaMetabolism20045315315810.1016/j.metabol.2003.09.007<?supplied-pmid 14767865?>14767865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="34869" pm="."><plain>36.MakiKCLawlessALKelleyKMDicklinMRKadenVNSchildALEffects of prescription omega-3-acid ethyl esters on fasting lipid profile in subjects with primary hypercholesterolemiaJ Cardiovasc Pharmacol20115748949410.1097/FJC.0b013e318210fca5<?supplied-pmid 21297494?>21297494 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="34870" pm="."><plain>37.KelleyDSSiegelDVemuriMMackeyBEDocosahexaenoic acid supplementation improves fasting and postprandial lipid profiles in hypertriglyceridemic menAm J Clin Nutr200786324333<?supplied-pmid 17684201?>17684201 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="34871" pm="."><plain>38.NeffLMCulinerJCunningham-RundlesSSeidmanCMeehanDMaturiJAlgal docosahexaenoic acid affects plasma lipoprotein particle size distribution in overweight and obese adultsJ Nutr201114120721310.3945/jn.110.130021<?supplied-pmid 21178084?>21178084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="34872" pm="."><plain>39.European Food Safety Authority (EFSA) Panel on Dietetic Products NaANScientific Opinion on the substantiation of health claims related to eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA), docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), docosapentaenoic acid (DPA)Book Scientific Opinion on the substantiation of health claims related to eicosapentaenoic acid (EPA), docosahexaenoic acid (DHA), docosapentaenoic acid (DPA)2010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="34873" pm="."><plain>40.NestelPShigeHPomeroySCehunMAbbeyMRaederstorffDThe n-3 fatty acids eicosapentaenoic acid and docosahexaenoic acid increase systemic arterial compliance in humansAm J Clin Nutr200276326330<?supplied-pmid 12145002?>12145002 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="34874" pm="."><plain>41.GrimsgaardSBonaaKHHansenJBNordoyAHighly purified eicosapentaenoic acid and docosahexaenoic acid in humans have similar triacylglycerol-lowering effects but divergent effects on serum fatty acidsAm J Clin Nutr199766649659<?supplied-pmid 9280188?>9280188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="34875" pm="."><plain>42.HansenJ-BGrimsgaardSNilsenHNordøyABønaaKHEffects of highly purified eicosapentaenoic acid and docosahexaenoic acid on fatty acid absorption, incorporation into serum phospholipids and postprandial triglyceridemiaLipids19983313113810.1007/s11745-998-0188-8<?supplied-pmid 9507234?>9507234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="34876" pm="."><plain>43.KatanMBDeslypereJPvan BirgelenAPPendersMZegwaardMKinetics of the incorporation of dietary fatty acids into serum cholesteryl esters, erythrocyte membranes, and adipose tissue: an 18-month controlled studyJ Lipid Res19973820122022<?supplied-pmid 9374124?>9374124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="34877" pm="."><plain>44.RamprasathVREyalIZchutSJonesPJEnhanced increase of omega-3 index in healthy individuals with response to 4-week n-3 fatty acid supplementation from krill oil versus fish oilLipids Health Dis20131217810.1186/1476-511X-12-178<?supplied-pmid 24304605?>24304605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="34878" pm="."><plain>45.Von SchackyCFischerJWeberPCLong- term effects of dietary marine omega-3 fatty acids upon plasma and cellular lipids, platelet function, and eicosanoid formation in humansJ Clin Invest1985761626163110.1172/JCI1121472997286 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="34879" pm="."><plain>46.BjorndalBStrandEGjerdeJBohovPSvardalADiehlBWPhospholipids from herring roe improve plasma lipids and glucose tolerance in healthy, young adultsLipids Health Dis2014138210.1186/1476-511X-13-82<?supplied-pmid 24886291?>24886291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="34880" pm="."><plain>47.YamadaKAKanterEMNewatiaALong-chain acylcarnitine induces Ca2+ efflux from the sarcoplasmic reticulumJ Cardiovasc Pharmacol200036142110.1097/00005344-200007000-00002<?supplied-pmid 10892655?>10892655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="34881" pm="."><plain>48.BjorndalBBrattelidTStrandEVigerustNFSvingenGFSvardalAFish oil and the pan-PPAR agonist tetradecylthioacetic acid affect the amino acid and carnitine metabolism in ratsPLoS One20138e6692610.1371/journal.pone.0066926<?supplied-pmid 23826175?>23826175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="34882" pm="."><plain>49.VigerustNFBjorndalBBohovPBrattelidTSvardalABergeRKKrill oil versus fish oil in modulation of inflammation and lipid metabolism in mice transgenic for TNF-alphaEur J Nutr2012521315132510.1007/s00394-012-0441-2<?supplied-pmid 22923017?>22923017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="34883" pm="."><plain>50.UelandPMHolmPIHustadSBetaine: a key modulator of one-carbon metabolism and homocysteine statusClin Chem Lab Med2005431069107510.1515/CCLM.2005.187<?supplied-pmid 16197300?>16197300 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="34884" pm="."><plain>51. Institute of Medicine (US) Standing Committee on the Scientific Evaluation of Dietary Reference Intakes and its Panel on Folate, Other B Vitamins, and Choline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34885" pm="."><plain>Choline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34886" pm="."><plain>In: Book Dietary Reference Intakes: Thiamin, Riboflavin, Niacin, Vitamin B-6, Vitamin B12, Panthothenic Acid, Biotin, and Choline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34887" pm="."><plain>Washington (National Acedemies Press); 1998. p. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34888" pm="."><plain>390–422. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="34889" pm="."><plain>52.ZeiselSHMarMHHoweJCHoldenJMConcentrations of choline-containing compounds and betaine in common foodsJ Nutr200313313021307<?supplied-pmid 12730414?>12730414 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="34890" pm="."><plain>53.Vennemann FB, Ioannidou S, Valsta LM, Dumas C, Ocke MC, Mensink GB, et al. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34891" pm="."><plain>Dietary intake and food sources of choline in European populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34892" pm="."><plain>Br J Nutrit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34893" pm="."><plain>2015;12:1–10 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="34894" pm="."><plain>54.GammoneMARiccioniGD'OrazioNCarotenoids: potential allies of cardiovascular health?Food Nutr Res2015592676210.3402/fnr.v59.26762<?supplied-pmid 25660385?>25660385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="34895" pm="."><plain>55.ClaytonPRLadiSFrom alga to omega; have we reached peak (fish) oil?J R Soc Med2015108351357<?supplied-pmid 26359136?>26359136 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="34896" pm="."><plain>56.StrandEBjorndalBNygardOBurriLBergeCBohovPLong-term treatment with the pan-PPAR agonist tetradecylthioacetic acid or fish oil is associated with increased cardiac content of n-3 fatty acids in ratLipids Health Dis2012118210.1186/1476-511X-11-82<?supplied-pmid 22738017?>22738017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="34897" pm="."><plain>57.UlbrichtTLSouthgateDACoronary heart disease: seven dietary factorsLancet199133898599210.1016/0140-6736(91)91846-M<?supplied-pmid 1681350?>1681350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="34898" pm="."><plain>58.BjorndalBBurriLWergedahlHSvardalABohovPBergeRKDietary supplementation of herring roe and milt enhances hepatic fatty acid catabolism in female mice transgenic for hTNFalphaEur J Nutr20125174175310.1007/s00394-011-0254-8<?supplied-pmid 21986673?>21986673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="34899" pm="."><plain>59.BjorndalBRamsvikMSLindquistCNordrehaugJEBruheimISvardalAA phospholipid-protein complex from antarctic krill reduced plasma homocysteine levels and increased plasma trimethylamine-N-oxide (TMAO) and carnitine levels in male Wistar ratsMar Drugs2015135706572110.3390/md13095706<?supplied-pmid 26371012?>26371012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
