<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">peerj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">peerj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5068391</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2498</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Environmental Sciences</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Marine Biology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Molecular Biology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="46426" pm="."><plain>Metagenomic survey of methanesulfonic acid (MSA) catabolic genes in an Atlantic Ocean surface water sample and in a partial enrichment </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Henriques</surname><given-names>Ana C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>Rui M.S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>De Marco</surname><given-names>Paolo</given-names></name><email>paolo.marco@iscsn.cespu.pt</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1"/></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><institution>Instituto de Investigação e Formação Avançada em Ciências e Tecnologias da Saúde (IINFACTS), CESPU</institution>, <addr-line>Gandra PRD</addr-line>, <country>Portugal</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Smidt</surname><given-names>Hauke</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2016-10-06"><day>6</day><month>10</month><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><elocation-id>e2498</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2016-02-06"><day>6</day><month>2</month><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2016-08-28"><day>28</day><month>8</month><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>©2016 Henriques et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Henriques et al.</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, reproduction and adaptation in any medium and for any purpose provided that it is properly attributed. For attribution, the original author(s), title, publication source (PeerJ) and either DOI or URL of the article must be cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/2498"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="46427" pm="."><plain>Methanesulfonic acid (MSA) is a relevant intermediate of the biogeochemical cycle of sulfur and environmental microorganisms assume an important role in the mineralization of this compound. Several methylotrophic bacterial strains able to grow on MSA have been isolated from soil or marine water and two conserved operons, msmABCD coding for MSA monooxygenase and msmEFGH coding for a transport system, have been repeatedly encountered in most of these strains. Homologous sequences have also been amplified directly from the environment or observed in marine metagenomic data, but these showed a base composition (G + C content) very different from their counterparts from cultivated bacteria. The aim of this study was to understand which microorganisms within the coastal surface oceanic microflora responded to MSA as a nutrient and how the community evolved in the early phases of an enrichment by means of metagenome and gene-targeted amplicon sequencing. From the phylogenetic point of view, the community shifted significantly with the disappearance of all signals related to the Archaea, the Pelagibacteraceae and phylum SAR406, and the increase in methylotroph-harboring taxa, accompanied by other groups so far not known to comprise methylotrophs such as the Hyphomonadaceae. At the functional level, the abundance of several genes related to sulfur metabolism and methylotrophy increased during the enrichment and the allelic distribution of gene msmA diagnostic for MSA monooxygenase altered considerably. Even more dramatic was the disappearance of MSA import-related gene msmE, which suggests that alternative transporters must be present in the enriched community and illustrate the inadequacy of msmE as an ecofunctional marker for MSA degradation at sea. </p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Methanesulfonic acid</kwd><kwd>Sulfur</kwd><kwd>Biogeochemical cycle</kwd><kwd>Ocean</kwd><kwd>Bacteria</kwd><kwd>Gene</kwd><kwd>Metagenomics</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="fund-1"><funding-source>European Commission’s Regional Development Fund (ERDF)</funding-source><award-id>FCOMP-01-0124-FEDER-028330</award-id></award-group><award-group id="fund-2"><funding-source>Portuguese Science Fund</funding-source><award-id>PTDC/BIA-MIC/3623/2012</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the European Commission’s Regional Development Fund (ERDF) through the Competitiveness Factors Operational Program (COMPETE - project FCOMP-01-0124-FEDER-028330) and by the Portuguese Science Fund (FCT - project PTDC/BIA-MIC/3623/2012). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="46434" pm="."><plain>Introduction <p><text><SENT sid="46435" pm="."><plain>It is known that methanesulfonic acid (MSA) has been produced during millennia in the atmosphere by the oxidation of dimethylsulfide (DMS) that escapes from the seawater surface (Andreae, 1986; Hynes, Wine &amp; Semmes, 1986; Mihalopoulos et al., 1992; Koga &amp; Tanaka, 1993; Kelly &amp; Murrell, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46436" pm="."><plain>DMS is mainly a byproduct of the degradation of marine photosynthetic organisms (Todd et al., 2011) and is the major component of marine emissions of volatile sulfur (Gondwe et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46437" pm="."><plain>Due to the huge scale of this biogeochemical process, very significant amounts (est. 1010 kg) of MSA form annually and deposit back onto the sea or land surfaces (Charlson et al., 1987; Kelly &amp; Murrell, 1999; Gondwe et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46439" pm="."><plain>MSA has not been found accumulating in any environment (apart from perennial ices (Legrand &amp; Feniet-Saigne, 1991; Whung et al., 1994)), which means that this compound is readily degraded in nature. Several methylotrophic bacterial strains have been isolated that can use MSA as sole source of carbon and energy (Kelly &amp; Baker, 1990; Thompson, Owens &amp; Murrell, 1995; De Marco et al., 2000; De Marco et al., 2004; Baxter et al., 2002; Moosvi et al., 2005b) while other microbes are known to use this molecule just as a sulfur supply (Kelly &amp; Murrell, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46441" pm="."><plain>An operon (msmABCD) encoding a heteromeric monooxygenase (MSA monooxygenase, or MSAMO) and another operon (msmEFGH) encoding uptake proteins have been found in several MSA-utilizing strains (De Marco et al., 1999; Baxter et al., 2002; Jamshad et al., 2006; Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015a; Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015b) and in a marine bacterium isolated from Western Pacific surface waters (Oh et al., 2010). <p><text><SENT sid="46442" pm="."><plain>All proteobacterial strains known to use MSA methylotrophically that have been analyzed at the molecular level have shown to possess gene msmA and most of them carry gene msmE (Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015a; Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46443" pm="."><plain>By contrast, the only Actinobacterial strain known to grow on MSA as a carbon source (Rhodococcus str. RD6.2 (De Marco et al., 2004)) harbors an alternative gene, ssuD, coding for an enzyme previously associated solely to non-methylotrophic MSA utilization (Eichhorn, Van Der Ploeg &amp; Leisinger, 1999; Endoh et al., 2003), plus some broad-range alkanesulfonate monooxygenases (Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46445" pm="."><plain>Homologs of the msm genes and operons have also been directly amplified from environmental DNA (Baxter et al., 2002; Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015a), retrieved by metagenomic sequencing projects (Leitão, Moradas-Ferreira &amp; De Marco, 2009) or found highly expressed in metatranscriptomic analyses of surface seawater (Gifford et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46446" pm="."><plain>Dozens of hits for msmA gene can also be recovered from the recently published Tara Oceans project data (Sunagawa et al., 2015) and one apparent msm double operon was found in one of the single-cell genomes (Alphaproteobacterium SCGC AAA536-B06) sequenced from the Mediterranean Sea (Swan et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46447" pm="."><plain>Among the MSAMO enzyme components, the ferrodoxin (MsmC) and the FAD-binding NADH-dependent reductase (MsmD) are very similar to analogous components of unrelated oxygenases while MsmB, like many other examples of hydroxylase beta subunits, shows poor sequence conservation (De Marco et al., 1999; Baxter et al., 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46448" pm="."><plain>On the contrary, alpha subunits of MSAMO hydroxylases (MsmA) show strong conservation and a peculiar 26-amino acid-long spacer within the Rieske-type [2Fe-2S]-binding motif. Among the polypeptides involved in the import of MSA into the cell, MsmE is the one that, in the proposed model, binds MSA in the periplasm. For these reasons, genes msmA and msmE have been selected as promising markers for MSA-utilizing bacteria in the environment. However, most likely owing to lower sequence conservation, designing robust primer pairs for gene E and obtaining bona fide msmE amplicons has been much less successful than with gene A (Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46452" pm="."><plain>In general, most of these genes obtained directly from marine water samples were low or very low in G + C content (36–48%) while cultivated strains obtained from both soil, estuary and seawater had G + C content levels in the 47–66% range. This dichotomy is not unique to MSA-utilizers or msm genes: the single-cell genomes retrieved by Swan et al. (2013) showed clear signs of streamlining and much lower GC% than cultivated marine strains, which may be a reflection of the generalized oligotrophic traits of unculturable bacteria versus the copiotrophic nature of cultivated types. Consistent with all these observations is the idea that laboratory isolates are no proper representatives of natural populations and that the only way to obtain a truthful picture of microbial communities is through in situ physiological observation and/or direct molecular investigation. <p><text><SENT sid="46455" pm="."><plain>In this work, we analyzed phylogenetically and functionally a surface coastal seawater sample from the Atlantic Ocean and repeated the analysis after partial enrichment with MSA as sole added source of carbon, energy and sulfur. Amplicon survey analyses on functional markers for MSA degradation, genes msmA and msmE, were also carried out. </sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46457" pm="."><plain>Material &amp; Methods <sec><title><text><SENT sid="46458" pm="."><plain>Seawater sample collection and metagenomic DNA isolation <p><text><SENT sid="46459" pm="."><plain>Atlantic Ocean surface water was collected on Dec 3rd, 2014 along the coast of Leça da Palmeira, Portugal (approximate coordinates 41.226956, −8.720528). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46460" pm="."><plain>Approximately 15 L of seawater were collected off the rocky shore at rising tide into clean bottles, which were immediately transported to the lab in an isothermal bag with ice packs. Before starting the procedures, the bottles were shaken in order to homogenize the samples. Three fractions of 0.5 L were filtered through 1.2 µm glass fiber filters, which were immediately wrapped in aluminum foil and stored at −80°C for later quantification of chlorophyll. The determination of chlorophyll a concentration was performed through a spectrophotometric method as previously described (Inag, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46464" pm="."><plain>Chlorophyll a concentration was calculated through the Jeffrey and Humphrey equation (Jeffrey &amp; Humphrey, 1975). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46465" pm="."><plain>Measures for pH and conductivity were also performed. Two fractions of 5 L of the seawater sample were filtered in parallel through 1.2 µm, 0.45 µm and 0.2 µm filters in succession. The filters from one 5 L fraction were immediately used for DNA extraction using the PowerWater DNA Isolation Kit (MO BIO Laboratories, Inc.) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46468" pm="."><plain>Marine enrichment with MSA and metagenomic DNA isolation <p><text><SENT sid="46469" pm="."><plain>The biomass retained on the filters from the second 5 L fraction was resuspended in the last 200 mL of the ocean water sample. The filters were removed and 1 mL of alkaline (pH 8) sodium methanesulfonate (MSA) 1 M was added to the suspension (5 mM final concentration). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46471" pm="."><plain>Similar amounts of alkaline MSA were used to spike the enrichment at days 7, 9 and 12. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46472" pm="."><plain>The suspension was incubated aerobically at room temperature (ca. 20 °C) in the dark, continuously mixed by a magnetic stirrer. This schedule was deliberately maintained during 16 days, with no subculturing, in order to produce just a partially enriched culture. The biomass at the end of the enrichment process was collected by centrifugation and DNA was extracted with PowerWater DNA Isolation Kit (MO BIO Laboratories, Inc., with adaptations to accommodate biomass in a pellet rather than on a filter). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46476" pm="."><plain>For convenience, the seawater sample (time 0) and the corresponding enrichment (E) culture will be designated SCD0 and SCDE, respectively. This study was limited to the observation of the evolution of the microbial community of a single sample and as such the following results are to be considered exploratory. </sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46478" pm="."><plain>Whole metagenome sequencing <p><text><SENT sid="46479" pm="."><plain>The metagenomes (from SCD0 and SCDE samples) were sequenced at Molecular Research LP (Shallowater, TX, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46480" pm="."><plain>Paired-end sequencing libraries were prepared (2 × 101 bp) and sequencing was performed using the Illumina HiSeq2500 platform. The libraries were prepared using Nextera DNA Sample preparation kit (Illumina) following the manufacturer’s user guide. The initial concentration of DNA was evaluated using the Qubit® dsDNA HS Assay Kit (Life Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46483" pm="."><plain>The samples were then diluted accordingly to achieve the recommended DNA input of 50 ng at a concentration of 2.5 ng/µL. Subsequently, the samples underwent fragmentation, addition of adapter sequences and PCR amplification (5 cycles) during which a unique index was added to each sample. The average library size was determined using the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46486" pm="."><plain>The libraries were then pooled in equimolar ratios at 2 nM and 5 µL of the library pool was clustered using the cBot (Illumina) and sequenced paired-end for 200 cycles using the HiSeq 2500 system (Illumina). <p><text><SENT sid="46487" pm="."><plain>The quality of the sequencing reads from both libraries was assessed using FastQC on Galaxy web-based platform (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://usegalaxy.org/">https://usegalaxy.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46488" pm="."><plain>The libraries were also checked for human contamination with Kraken Metagenomics (Zaharia et al., 2011; Wood &amp; Salzberg, 2014) at Illumina BaseSpace (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://basespace.illumina.com/home/index">http://basespace.illumina.com/home/index</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46489" pm="."><plain>As the resulting values for the presence of human sequences were very low (0.15% for sample SCD0 and 0.04% for sample SCDE), no filtering was performed before the subsequent steps of analysis (general statistics are described in Table S1). <p><text><SENT sid="46490" pm="."><plain>Sequencing data for the two samples, SCD0 and SCDE, were submitted to the European Nucleotide Archive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena</ext-link>) under project number PRJEB9018 and sample accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS700852">ERS700852</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS700853">ERS700853</ext-link>, respectively. The analyses of the metadata were performed through the EBI Metagenomics service pipeline (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/metagenomics/pipelines/2.0">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/metagenomics/pipelines/2.0</ext-link> (Mitchell et al., 2015a)) that includes a quality control step, a taxonomic analysis step based on 16S rDNA sequences and a functional analysis of predicted protein coding sequences using the InterPro resource (Mitchell et al., 2015b). <p><text><SENT sid="46492" pm="."><plain>BIOM (see http://biom-format.org/) files containing phylogenetic classification information provided by EBI metagenomics were used to construct rarefaction curves using MEGAN (version 5.10.6; Huson, Mitra &amp; Ruscheweyh, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46493" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic data were also used to estimate the alpha diversity of the two samples (Shannon index (Shannon, 1948), evenness (Mulder et al., 2004) and Chao species estimator (Chao, 1984)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46494" pm="."><plain>For beta diversity analysis, Jaccard (Jaccard, 1912), Kulczynski (Faith, Minchin &amp; Belbin, 1987), and Chao (Chao, Chazdon &amp; Shen, 2005) indices were calculated through the Vegan package (Oksanen et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46495" pm="."><plain>Bray-Curtis dissimilarity index (Bray &amp; Curtis, 1957) was calculated starting from relative abundances. Only significant differences in phylogenetic or functional composition were retained (Fisher’s exact / χ2 test with a significance level of 0.05 with a Bonferroni correction on the number of comparisons, in order to minimize false positives; code was adapted from Metastats (White, Nagarajan &amp; Pop, 2009)). <p><text><SENT sid="46497" pm="."><plain>Assembled metagenomic data from both samples were also submitted to the DOE Joint Genome Institute’s Integrated Microbial Genome Metagenomic Expert Review (IMG/MER) annotation pipeline (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://img.jgi.doe.gov/">http://img.jgi.doe.gov/</ext-link>) for functional and taxonomic annotation (Markowitz et al., 2014) (SCD0: GOLD Analysis Project Id <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://gold.jgi.doe.gov/analysis_projects?id=Ga0069134">Ga0069134</ext-link>/biosample ID Gb0111627; SCDE: GOLD Analysis Project Id Ga0069135/biosample ID Gb0111630). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46498" pm="."><plain>Before submission, reads were quality checked (FastQC for quality control at Galaxy for trimming and filtering): only sequences with quality scores equal or higher than 20 over 95% or more of the nucleotides were kept. For each sample, forward and reverse sequence files were merged and assembled using Megahit (Li et al., 2015) (general statistics are reported in Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46500" pm="."><plain>A further analysis was performed at MG-RAST (Meyer et al., 2008) using the subsystems approach (Overbeek et al., 2005): metagenome SCD0 was submitted under sample no 4698364.3 and SCDE under sample no 4698363.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46501" pm="."><plain>Binning was performed using MetaBat v0.25.4 (Kang et al., 2015) and the bins obtained were analyzed by MG-RAST. <p><text><SENT sid="46502" pm="."><plain>A flowchart with the major steps of the analysis is available in Fig. S1. </sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46504" pm="."><plain>msmA and msmE amplicon surveys <p><text><SENT sid="46505" pm="."><plain>In order to obtain DNA amounts sufficient for the subsequent analyses, the REPLI-g® MiniKit (QIAGEN) was used to amplify the DNA from each metagenomic sample, according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Negative controls starting from ultrapure nuclease-free water yielded no product. <p><text><SENT sid="46507" pm="."><plain>The amplified metagenomes were tested with primers directed to genes msmA and msmE. As amplicons with less than 400 bp were needed for Ion Torrent sequencing, primer pairs SarA139fwd/SarA488rev and SarE322fwd/SarE704rev (Table S3) were employed in order to obtain amplicons with 349 bp and 382 bp, respectively. However, when amplification was performed directly with these primers, the signals obtained were too weak or absent. As such, a nested PCR approach was carried out. The first round was performed using primer sets SarA124fwd/SarA1053rev or SarE133fwd/SarE1125rev for msmA and msmE amplicons, respectively (Table S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46512" pm="."><plain>Some parameters had to be adjusted in order optimize the reactions, and the successful conditions are reported in Table S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46513" pm="."><plain>Negative controls received PCR water instead of DNA. Positive controls contained DNA from Sargasso Sea Metagenome clone EF103447 (Leitão, Moradas-Ferreira &amp; De Marco, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46515" pm="."><plain>Only primers directed to the low-GC Sargasso Sea Metagenome msm sequences had previously been successful at amplifying these genes from a seawater metagenomic sample from the same location (Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46516" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, the primers used in this work were based on the known Sargasso Sea Metagenome msm sequences. Amplification products were submitted for sequencing at Stabvida Lda. (Caparica, Portugal). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46519" pm="."><plain>After determining the exact PCR product concentrations with Qubit 2.0 Fluorometer (Invitrogen) and Qubit dsDNA BR Kit (Invitrogen), platform-specific barcoded adapters were added to each sample in the preparation of libraries with KAPA Library Preparation Kit (Kapa Biosystems) and NEXTflex™ DNA Barcodes for Ion PGM (Bioo Scientific). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46520" pm="."><plain>Samples were sequenced on an Ion Torrent Personal Genome Machine (PGM, Life Technologies, Thermo Fisher Scientific) using Ion PGM™ Hi-Q Sequencing Kit reagents. Reads were provided free from barcodes and adapters sequences. <p><text><SENT sid="46522" pm="."><plain>Sequencing data from msmA amplicons, SCD0-A and SCDE-A sets, and msmE amplicons, SCD0-E set, were submitted to the European Nucleotide Archive (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena</ext-link>) under sample accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS954926">ERS954926</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS954925">ERS954925</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS954927">ERS954927</ext-link>, respectively, within the metagenomic study PRJEB9018. <p><text><SENT sid="46523" pm="."><plain>The overall quality scores of the output data from the Ion Torrent sequencing was assessed using FastQC on Galaxy web-based platform. Sequencing reads were then trimmed and filtered based on length and quality. For the msmA amplicon, reads ranging from 300 to 365 bp were selected; for the msmE amplicon, sequences with length between 335 to 420 bp were retained. In the quality filtering step, sequences with quality lower than 20 over more than 15% of the nucleotides were discarded. Chimeric sequences were removed with Chimera Check (Edgar et al., 2011) available in the FunGenePipeline (Fish et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46528" pm="."><plain>The resulting files were submitted to FrameBot (Wang et al., 2013) for translation and frameshift correction (FunGenePipeline). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46529" pm="."><plain>Sequences containing stop and/or undefined codons were discarded (general statistics are reported in Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46530" pm="."><plain>For each dataset, protein sequences were aligned with hmmalign (HMMER3 (Eddy, 2011)) and clustered by complete linkage clustering (mcClust (Loewenstein et al., 2008), FunGenePipeline). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46531" pm="."><plain>Rarefaction (FunGenePipeline (Fish et al., 2013)) was based on data from the clust file at 0.03 distance. Conservation analysis of the MsmA and MsmE predicted protein sequences was performed on alignments generated by hmmalign (HMMER3) and analyzed by Jalview (Waterhouse et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46533" pm="."><plain>Alpha diversity analysis (Shannon index, evenness and Chao species estimator) was performed on clustering values obtained at 0.03 distance for each set of results. Beta diversity (Bray-Curtis, Jaccard, Kulczynski, and Chao indices) between SCD0-A and SCDE-A sequence sets was computed on the clustered (0.03 distance) aligned MsmA predicted sequences. For Bray-Curtis, relative cluster abundances were employed. The representative sequence for each cluster was obtained using Representative Sequences (FunGenePipeline). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46537" pm="."><plain>In this case, distance cutoff values were chosen in order to obtain in the region of 20–30 clusters from each dataset (0.15 for SCD0-A/SCDE-A and 0.10 for SCD0-E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46538" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequences corresponding to these cluster-representative sequences were retrieved and used to infer phylogenetic trees by Maximum Likelihood with 100 bootstrap iterations (as implemented in PhyML (Guindon et al., 2010) at Phylogeny.fr (Dereeper et al., 2008)). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46539" pm="."><plain>A flowchart with the major steps of this analysis is available in Fig. S2. </sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="46541" pm="."><plain>Results <sec><title><text><SENT sid="46542" pm="."><plain>Characterization of the samples <p><text><SENT sid="46543" pm="."><plain>The seawater sample collected for this study was at a temperature of 15.5°C and 3.34% salinity (conductivity 47.9 mS/cm). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46544" pm="."><plain>The pH value was 8.07 and the concentration of chlorophyll a was 1.06 mg/m3. <p><text><SENT sid="46545" pm="."><plain>Optical density (at 600 nm) of the filtered sample was 0.606 at time 0 (SCD0), dropped to 0.415 at day 2 and rose towards the last days of incubation to 0.758 (SCDE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46546" pm="."><plain>During the enrichment process the suspension progressively lost its original greenish hue. </sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46547" pm="."><plain>Analysis of phylogenetic composition <p><text><SENT sid="46548" pm="."><plain>Despite the fact that sample SCDE underwent just a partial enrichment with no dilution or subculturing, this was enough for the G + C content of the community’s metagenome to shift from 43.30% (SCD0) to 53.29% (SCDE). <p><text><SENT sid="46549" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic composition analysis was performed by EBI Metagenomics on the metagenomic data, based on prokaryotic rRNA gene sequences. Rarefaction curves were generated from these results for both metagenomes (Fig. S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46552" pm="."><plain>These curves show that a reasonable coverage of the communities’ composition was achieved: however, neither reaches a definite plateau meaning that deeper sequencing levels would have been desirable. <p><text><SENT sid="46553" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetically, the community before the enrichment was composed primarily by taxa typical of surface seawater, namely Alphaproteobacteria of the Pelagibacteraceae and the Rhodobacteraceae, Gammaproteobacteria of the Halomonadaceae and Piscirickettsiaceae, Archaea of the Crenarchaeota (with prominence for Nitrosopumilus) and the Euryarchaeota (Thermoplasmata Marine group II), Bacteroidetes of the Flavobacteriaceae and the uncultured marine phylum SAR406 (Figs. 1 and 2). <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46555" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic composition (phyla) of the two metagenomes, SCD0 and SCDE (in percentage). <p><text><SENT sid="46556" pm="."><plain>Only phyla with abundance ≥1% in either sample are shown (based on EBI Metagenomics analysis of the data). </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46557" pm="."><plain>Taxonomic composition of the two metagenomes (in percentage). <p><text><SENT sid="46558" pm="."><plain>Only taxa with abundance ≥2% in either sample are shown. Taxonomic classification as provided by the phylogenetic analysis of the EBI Metagenomics pipeline (which explains some apparent taxonomic inconsistency such as “Alpha Rickettsiales Pelagibacteraceae,” referring to sequences that could be classified down to the family level, and further down “Alphaproteobacteria,” referring to sequences that could be classified just at the class level). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46560" pm="."><plain>Alpha, and Gamma are abbreviations for the corresponding classes within the Proteobacteria. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="46561" pm="."><plain>Clearly, some of these groups declined or disappeared during our enrichment program (Figs. 1, 2 and 3): all the Archaea and SAR406, the Pelagibacteraceae, Halomonadaceae, Flavobacteriaceae (a family known to harbor methylotrophic species (De Marco et al., 2004; Moosvi et al., 2005a; Boden et al., 2008; Madhaiyan et al., 2010)) and  Variovorax paradoxus (Comamonadaceae) a known methylotroph (Anesti et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46563" pm="."><plain>Other groups thrived: the Rhodobacteraceae and the Hyphomonadaceae within the Alphaproteobacteria, the Oceanospirillaceae, the Piscirickettsiaceae, two families of Alteromonadales and genus Alcanivorax within the Gammaproteobacteria, the Saprospiraceae within the Bacteroidetes. It is worth noticing that: fam. Rhodobacteraceae includes several methylotrophic species and namely marine MSA-degrader Marinosulfonomonas (Thompson, Owens &amp; Murrell, 1995); fam. Piscirickettsiaceae includes the genus Methylophaga, a known methylotrophic taxon relevant in surface sea waters (Neufeld et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46565" pm="."><plain>Indeed, the signal for Methylophaga itself at the genus level shot up from below detection to 82 hits; genus Alcanivorax, which contains marine representatives that have previously been found in a dimethylsulfide-based enrichment (Schäfer, 2007) and one known potentially methylotrophic species (A. borkumensis strain SK2—<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main/BMID000000083743">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/biomodels-main/BMID000000083743</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46566" pm="."><plain>Despite the fact that to our knowledge no methylotrophic species is known among the Hyphomonadaceae, the considerable increase in its abundance after the enrichment (225x) seem to suggest a possible involvement of members of this group in the turnover of MSA. Other rarer taxa that showed sizeable abundance increases after the enrichment were the Cryomorphaceae (Bacteroidetes), among the Gammaproteobacteria several branches within the Alteromonadales, several groups within the Oceanospirillales like the Oceanospirillaceae (and species Neptuniibacter caesariensis), the Oleiphilaceae, genus Halomonas, and rather surprisingly the Enterobacteriaceae. Notably, known methylotrophic-containing taxa like the Hyphomicrobiaceae (Alphaproteobacteria) and Methylotenera mobilis (Betaproteobacteria) also increased significantly. <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46569" pm="."><plain>Significant shifts in phylogenetic composition observed due to the enrichment. <p><text><SENT sid="46570" pm="."><plain>Shown are percentages of the abundance of each taxon in each sample (SCD0 or SCDE) over the total taxon abundance (SCD0 + SCDE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46571" pm="."><plain>Only statistically significant differences are shown. Taxa are as provided by the phylogenetic analysis of the EBI Metagenomics pipeline (which explains some apparent taxonomic inconsistency, see note in Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46573" pm="."><plain>Alpha, Beta, Gamma, Delta and Epsilon are abbreviations for the corresponding classes within the Proteobacteria. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="46574" pm="."><plain>Metagenomic data binning by MetaBat failed to generate discrete bins with sample SCD0: this is not surprising with a diverse natural community under no definite selective pressure where no single species dominate. However, three bins were obtained with sample SCDE which by and large matched the results obtained by direct metagenomics analysis. Bin 1, assigned to an Alcanivorax sp. strain, contains genes coding for diagnostic enzymes for the assimilation of C1 carbon through the serine cycle (serine hydroxymethyltransferase, serine-glyoxylate aminotransferase and isocitrate lyase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46577" pm="."><plain>Bin 2, tentatively classified as the genome of a Hyphomonas sp. strain, also contains genes for the serine cycle (serine hydroxymethyltransferase) and for the anaplerotic ethylmalonyl-CoA and glyoxylate pathways (propionyl-CoA carboxylase, ethylmalonyl-CoA mutase and isocitrate lyase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46578" pm="."><plain>Bin 3 showed phylogenetic markers mostly associated with genus Methylophaga: it contains genes diagnostic for the ribulose monophosphate (RuMP) cycle (3-hexulose-6-phosphate synthase and 6-phospho-3-hexuloisomerase), an alternative metabolic route for the assimilation of C1 carbon, which is the typical metabolic route found in Methylophaga species. <p><text><SENT sid="46579" pm="."><plain>Alpha and beta diversity estimates were based on the phylogenetic data obtained by the EBI Metagenomics analysis. The values are listed in Tables 1 and 2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46581" pm="."><plain>The effects of the enrichment were an increase in the number of taxa observed, internal diversity (H’), and evenness. This was due to the sharp decline or disappearance of some of the major taxa composing the original metagenome (all Archaeal groups, algal chloroplast sequences, the Pelagibacteraceae, and the SAR406 lineages) accompanied by the appearance of a large number of less representative taxa, which shows that the enrichment process was halted at a very early stage, as intended. <SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/table-1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46583" pm="."><plain>Alpha diversity results for samples SCD0 and SCDE based on phylogenetic data. </caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g009"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46584" pm="."><plain>Alpha diversity indicators </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46585" pm="."><plain>SCD0 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46586" pm="."><plain>SCDE </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46587" pm="."><plain>Shannon index (H’) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46588" pm="."><plain>3.95 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46589" pm="."><plain>4.97 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46590" pm="."><plain>Evenness (E) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46591" pm="."><plain>0.68 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46592" pm="."><plain>0.84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46593" pm="."><plain>Number of observed taxa </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46594" pm="."><plain>329 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46595" pm="."><plain>363 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46596" pm="."><plain>Chao taxa number estimator </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46597" pm="."><plain>460.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46598" pm="."><plain>544.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/table-2</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46599" pm="."><plain>Beta diversity between samples SCD0 and SCDE based on phylogenetic data. </caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g010"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46600" pm="."><plain>Beta diversity indexes </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46601" pm="."><plain>Bray-Curtis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46602" pm="."><plain>0.56 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46603" pm="."><plain>Jaccard </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46604" pm="."><plain>0.76 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46605" pm="."><plain>Kulczynski </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46606" pm="."><plain>0.60 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46607" pm="."><plain>Chao index </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46608" pm="."><plain>0.77 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46609" pm="."><plain>Overall analysis of the functional annotation <p><text><SENT sid="46610" pm="."><plain>Significant shifts between the functional annotation of samples SCD0 and SCDE obtained by EBI Metagenomics were observed. <p><text><SENT sid="46611" pm="."><plain>The analysis revealed somewhat surprising large increases in categories <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0000103">GO:0000103</ext-link> “sulfate assimilation” and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0008272">GO:0008272</ext-link> “sulfate transport.” Among the other categories, significantly rising in hit numbers were <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0016846">GO:0016846</ext-link> “carbon-sulfur lyase activity,” <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0016705">GO:0016705</ext-link> “oxidoreductase activity, acting on paired donors, with incorporation or reduction of molecular oxygen” and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0004497">GO:0004497</ext-link> “monooxygenase activity,” <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0051537">GO:0051537</ext-link> “2 iron, 2 sulfur cluster binding,” <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0006730">GO:0006730</ext-link> “one-carbon metabolic process,” <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0004488">GO:0004488</ext-link> “methylenetetrahydrofolate dehydrogenase (NADP+)” and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0008864">GO:0008864</ext-link> “formyltetrahydrofolate deformylase,” all of which can be associated to the catabolism of MSA. The latter two may suggest that a selection for organisms that metabolize formaldehyde through the condensation with tetrahydrofolate (rather than with tetrahydromethanopterin) may have occurred. Oddly, though, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0046653">GO:0046653</ext-link> “tetrahydrofolate metabolic process” and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0046654">GO:0046654</ext-link> “tetrahydrofolate biosynthetic process” were found among the significantly decreased categories. Fittingly, several category associated with oxygenic photosynthesis and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/GTerm?id=GO:0004329">GO:0004329</ext-link> “formate-tetrahydrofolate ligase activity” (incorporation of formate into biomass in anaerobic conditions) also decreased in abundance. <p><text><SENT sid="46615" pm="."><plain>Among the monooxygenase genes significantly increased in number during the enrichment, 5 hits for gene msuD/ssuD were found in the assembled metagenomic data of the enriched sample (SCDE), while no homolog was present in sample SCD0. <p><text><SENT sid="46616" pm="."><plain>Since no hits for msm genes were observed in the metagenomic results by either EBI Metagenomics or IMG/MER, the sequence data were also screened locally by hmmsearch (HMMER3) and tblastn (McGinnis &amp; Madden, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46617" pm="."><plain>The only hits obtained with protein MsmA (expectation value cutoff 10−5) contained short Rieske-associated motifs (spacers varying from 16 to 18 in SCD0, and from 16 to 23 in SCDE) and were low scoring. As for protein MsmE, no hits were found at E-value ≤10−5. <p><text><SENT sid="46619" pm="."><plain>In order to complement the metagenomic data, msmA and msmE genes were investigated by an amplicon survey experiment. Direct amplification was weak or absent, so a nested PCR approach was adopted for both genes, which witnesses to the overall low concentration of these sequences in the metagenomes. Amplification of gene A was achieved from both samples. On the contrary, despite repeated and insistent efforts, we were unable to amplify gene E from the enrichment sample (SCDE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46623" pm="."><plain>For convenience, the three amplicon sets will be designated as follows: SCD0-A (msmA amplicons from sample SCD0), SCDE-A (msmA amplicons from sample SCDE) and SCD0-E (msmE amplicons from sample SCD0). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46624" pm="."><plain>The three amplicon pools were sequenced by ion Torrent technology. The G + C content of the processed reads was close to 40% in all 3 cases (Table S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46626" pm="."><plain>Namely, while community metagenome grew from 43.30% to 53.29% G + C content, there was almost no difference in base composition between of the msmA reads before and after the enrichment. The reads were then translated and checked for frameshift-generating sequencing errors and all sequences containing an undetermined codon or a stop codon were eliminated. Statistics relative to each case are shown in Table S5. <p><text><SENT sid="46629" pm="."><plain>Rarefaction curves constructed from clustering data at a 0.03 distance are represented in Fig. 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46630" pm="."><plain>Although a definite plateau is not achieved, gene A looks sampled at satisfactory depth in both SCD0-A and SCDE-A sets. On the contrary, the level of amplification and sequencing of gene E in set SCD0-E was clearly insufficient. These results suggest that a deeper sequencing would be needed. However, it is also true that a huge part of the data was deleted at the quality control step (Table S5) so better sequencing quality rather than deeper sequencing might be the solution. <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-4</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46634" pm="."><plain>Comparison of the rarefaction curves constructed with sequencing data from the amplicon survey experiment. <p><text><SENT sid="46635" pm="."><plain>SCD0-A and SCDE-A refer to gene msmA before and after the enrichment with MSA, respectively. SCD0-E refers to gene msmE before the enrichment. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="46637" pm="."><plain>The data from clustering of MsmA and MsmE sequences at 0.03 cutoff were analyzed for alpha and beta diversity. Clearly there was an evolution in MsmA sequences during the enrichment process which lead to the loss of some sequence diversity (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46639" pm="."><plain>The shift in MsmA allele composition is very significant as illustrated by the high values of the beta diversity indexes (Bray Curtis = 0.95; Jaccard = 0.98; Kulczynski = 0.95; Chao index = 0.76). <SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/table-3</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46640" pm="."><plain>Alpha diversity results for msmA and msmE genes in samples SCD0 and SCDE. </caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g011"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46641" pm="."><plain>msmA gene </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46642" pm="."><plain>msmE gene </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46643" pm="."><plain>Indexes </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46644" pm="."><plain>SCD0 </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46645" pm="."><plain>SCDE </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46646" pm="."><plain>SCD0 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46647" pm="."><plain>Shannon </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46648" pm="."><plain>5.08 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46649" pm="."><plain>3.56 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46650" pm="."><plain>5.32 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46651" pm="."><plain>Evenness </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46652" pm="."><plain>0.66 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46653" pm="."><plain>0.49 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46654" pm="."><plain>0.78 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46655" pm="."><plain>Sobs </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46656" pm="."><plain>2,211 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46657" pm="."><plain>1,410 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46658" pm="."><plain>933 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46659" pm="."><plain>Chao estimator </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46660" pm="."><plain>3073.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46661" pm="."><plain>2068.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="46662" pm="."><plain>1331.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="46663" pm="."><plain>Conservation analysis was performed with the predicted MsmA and MsmE sequences (Figs. 5 and 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46665" pm="."><plain>The edges of the sequences, corresponding to the PCR primers, should be 100% conserved. The low conservation levels seen in these regions are artifacts due to the occurrence of a few shorter sequences in the datasets and lower quality at the end of reaction. In the case of MsmA (Fig. 5), the levels of amino acid conservation are generally higher and more constant along the central region of the fragment. If the primers regions are not taken into account, all the conservation values are ≥92.35%, with the exception of a one-amino acid trough (a Serine at position 30) with 58% conservation. Particularly, all the amino acids in the Rieske associated motif and spacer demonstrate conservation levels higher than 99%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46670" pm="."><plain>Regarding MsmE (Fig. 6), it is possible to observe regions with high levels of conservation, which in some cases are greater than 99%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46671" pm="."><plain>However, the overall conservation is much less constant than for MsmA, with 4 positions below 85%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46672" pm="."><plain>The lowest conservation value (61%) was found for a Serine at position 10. <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-5</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46673" pm="."><plain>Conservation analysis of the predicted MsmA sequences from joined samples SCD0-A and SCDE-A. <p><text><SENT sid="46674" pm="."><plain>Displayed on top is the consensus sequence. Amino acids in blue correspond to PCR primers. Amino acids in red correspond to the cysteine and histidine residues typical of the Rieske-associated motif. Amino acids in green represent the characteristic long spacer found in the Rieske motif in MsmA. Low conservation of the beginning and end of the sequence (corresponding to PCR primers) are artifacts explainable by the presence of short reads in the dataset. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-6</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46679" pm="."><plain>Conservation analysis of the predicted MsmE sequences from sample SCD0-E. <p><text><SENT sid="46680" pm="."><plain>Displayed on top is the consensus sequence. Amino acids in blue correspond to the PCR primers. Low conservation of the beginning and end of the sequence can be explained as in Fig. 5. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="46683" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic trees of the predicted MsmA and MsmE sequences <p><text><SENT sid="46684" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic trees were constructed based on the nucleotide data corresponding to the representative protein sequences of clusters obtained with distance cutoff values 0.15 (for MsmA) or 0.10 (for MsmE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46685" pm="."><plain>In the process, sequences from this study were aligned with metagenomic seawater homologs obtained in a previous work (Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015a), with sequences EF103447, EF103448 and EF103448 from SSM clones (Leitão, Moradas-Ferreira &amp; De Marco, 2009), with sequences from the GOS project (Rusch et al., 2007) and with sequences from cultured strains. Phylograms of msmA and msmE sequences are shown in Figs. 7 and 8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46688" pm="."><plain>Although some degree of caution is required in the analysis of these sequences due to the fact that they were produced by three rounds of amplification (whole-genome amplification followed by nested PCR), the results obtained seem to fit logical expectations. In the case of gene msmA, it is possible to observe a clear separation (95% bootstrap value) between two principal branches: one consists only of metagenomic sequences and includes all the msmA reads generated in this study; the other group (omitted as root in Fig. 7) contains the sequences from cultured strains (Alpha, Beta or Gammaproteobacteria) of both marine and soil origin. In a similar way, the phylogram for gene msmE shows an unambiguous split between two major groups (94% bootstrap value): one comprising mainly metagenomic sequences, including all the msmE reads from this study, sequences from the GOS project, and two from cultured marine strains C. Puniceispirillum marinum IMCC1322 and C. Filomicrobium marinum str. Y; plus a second group containing all other sequences from cultured strains (Alpha and Betaproteobacteria). <SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-7</object-id><label>Figure 7</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46693" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of msmA sequences. <p><text><SENT sid="46694" pm="."><plain>Clusters with sequences from this study are in blue: CLA stands for msmA clusters. Between brackets is the total number of sequences in each cluster. Horizontal bars indicate the relative frequency of sequences of each cluster (SCD0 in blue and SCDE in red). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46697" pm="."><plain>The accession numbers of the sequences previously published are between brackets. The omitted branch is constituted mostly by sequences from genomes of cultured strains. The accession numbers of these sequences are the following: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF354805">AF354805</ext-link> (Marinosulfonomonas methylotropha str. TR3), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KJ789392">KJ789392</ext-link> (Methylobacterium sp. str. P1), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KJ789392">KJ789392</ext-link> (Hyphomicrobium sp. str. P2), GOS sequence JCVI_READ_2101946, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KM879220">KM879220</ext-link> (C. Filomicrobium marinum str. Y), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NC_011892">NC_011892</ext-link> (Methylobacterium nodulans ORS 2060), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NC_011894.1">NC_011894.1</ext-link> (Methylobacterium nodulans ORS 2060), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KJ789395">KJ789395</ext-link> (Methylobacterium sp. str. RD41), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_KB375270">NZ_KB375270</ext-link> (Afipia felis str. ATCC 53690), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/EF459501">EF459501</ext-link> (Afipia felis str. 25E1), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF091716">AF091716</ext-link> (Methylosulfonomonas methylovora str. M2), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP001751">CP001751</ext-link> (C. Puniceispirillum marinum str. IMCC1322), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_AKCV01000022">NZ_AKCV01000022</ext-link> (Ralstonia sp. str. PBA), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AP014581">AP014581</ext-link> (Burkholderia sp. str. RPE67), and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CP003775">CP003775</ext-link> (Burkholderia cepacia str. GG4), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CCYE01000041">CCYE01000041</ext-link> (Pseudomonas xanthomarina str. S11). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46715" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide sequences corresponding to cluster-representative MsmA sequences obtained at 0.15 distance cutoff were used to infer the phylogenetic tree by Maximum Likelihood with 100 bootstrap iterations. Bootstrap values &lt;50% are omitted. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g007"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig-8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/fig-8</object-id><label>Figure 8</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46717" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree of msmE sequences. <p><text><SENT sid="46718" pm="."><plain>Clusters with sequences from this study are in blue: CLE stands for msmE clusters. Between brackets is the total number of sequences in each cluster. Sequences from cultured strains are in orange. The accession numbers of the sequences previously published are between brackets. The omitted branch is constituted by sequences from genomes of cultured strains, with the following accession numbers: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_AZUP00000000.1">NZ_AZUP00000000.1</ext-link> (Methyloversatilis discipulorum str. FAM1), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_AFHG01000044">NZ_AFHG01000044</ext-link> (Methyloversatilis universalis str. FAM5), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_ARVV01000001">NZ_ARVV01000001</ext-link> (Methyloversatilis discipulorum str. RZ18-153), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_AKCV01000024">NZ_AKCV01000024</ext-link> (Ralstonia sp. str. PBA), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/CCAZ020000001">CCAZ020000001</ext-link> (Afipia felis genospecies A str. 76713), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_JNIJ01000008">NZ_JNIJ01000008</ext-link> (Bradyrhizobium sp. str. URHD0069), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_KB891326">NZ_KB891326</ext-link> (Thiobacillus thioparus str. DSM 505), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_AQWL01000003">NZ_AQWL01000003</ext-link> (Thiobacillus denitrificans str. DSM 12475), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AZSN01000017">AZSN01000017</ext-link> (Methylibium sp. str. T29-B), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NC_008825">NC_008825</ext-link> (Methylibium petroleiphilum str. PM1), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/NZ_JADL01000017">NZ_JADL01000017</ext-link> (Rhodospirillales bacterium str. URHD0088), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KP025766">KP025766</ext-link> (Methylobacterium sp. str. P1), <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/AF091716">AF091716</ext-link> (Methylosulfonomonas methylovora str. M2), and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/KP025767">KP025767</ext-link> (Marinosulfonomonas methylotropha str. TR3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46737" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide sequences corresponding to cluster-representative MsmE sequences obtained at 0.10 distance cutoff were used to infer the phylogenetic tree by Maximum Likelihood with 100 bootstrap iterations. Bootstrap values &lt;50% are omitted. </caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-g008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="46739" pm="."><plain>Discussion <p><text><SENT sid="46740" pm="."><plain>Genes associated to the degradation of methanesulfonic acid have previously been studied in various bacterial isolates and found in several metagenomic studies. A clear G + C-content discrepancy between the former and the latter sequences shows that MSA-degrading strains isolated in the laboratory are not good representatives of the natural communities, especially for marine water. For this reason, in this study we tried to obtain a more faithful snapshot of the MSA-affected microbiota by keeping enrichment parameters as close as possible to field conditions and observing the community at an early stage of enrichment. We started from a surface seawater biomass sample and compared metagenomic information from before and after 16 days of amendment with MSA as the sole organic nutrient. Despite the fact that there was no subculturing, and that the time of enrichment was not sufficient to isolate culturable methylotrophs to purity, the evolution of the community was notorious in the G + C content of the metagenomic data, from 43% of sample SCD0 to 53% of sample SCDE. <p><text><SENT sid="46745" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetically, the enrichment with MSA shifted the prokaryotic community of our sample from a composition fairly typical of oceanic surface waters (mainly Alphaproteobacteria (particularly Pelagibacteraceae), Gammaproteobacteria, Bacteroidetes, SAR406 phylum and Archaea) to a significantly different community with large increases in methylotroph-harboring taxa such as the Rhodobacteraceae, the Piscirickettsiaceae and suspected methylotrophs such as Alcanivorax, accompanied by other emerging taxa not known to harbor methylotrophs (Alteromonadales, Oceanospirillaceae, Hyphomonadaceae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46746" pm="."><plain>Such a considerable change in phylogenetic profile can be the result of adaptation to using MSA as nutrient, but may also be the sign of a move from an oligotrophic to a more copiotrophic community. <p><text><SENT sid="46747" pm="."><plain>The indications obtained from the analysis of the metagenomic sequences at the functional level showed enrichment in some functions associated with methylotrophic metabolism and in [2Fe-2S] cluster-containing monooxygenases, a category including MSAMO. <p><text><SENT sid="46748" pm="."><plain>Binning of the metagenomic sequence data revealed the presence of three coherent sets of sequences in sample SCDE matching genera whose abundance was seen increasing in the 16S-based phylogenetic analysis: Alcanivorax, a possible methylotroph, Hyphomonas and Methylophaga, a genus of genuine methylotrophic strains. Genus Hyphomonas is not known to be able of methylotrophic growth. However, genes possibly involved in C1 metabolism were found in the three bins. <p><text><SENT sid="46751" pm="."><plain>Interesting data were also obtained on the two genes associated to the catabolism of MSA, msmA and msmE, by a targeted single-gene high-throughput sequencing strategy. Gene msmA could not be detected directly in the metagenomic sequence data probably due to an unsuitable ratio between sequencing depth and community complexity. However, after PCR amplification and sequencing, a multitude of diverse sequences was obtained from both the original and enriched sample: despite the shifts in phylogenetic composition caused by the enrichment process, at the level of gene msmA the G + C content remained practically constant. All these sequences from both samples were shown to belong in a very solid metagenomic branch, clearly separate from all the homologs encountered in cultivated strains of both soil and marine origin and unmistakably some sequence clusters were seen shrinking (or even disappearing) or expanding due to the enrichment regime. Gene E too was not found in the metagenomic sequence data of either sample; however, we could amplify it from the initial seawater sample (SCD0) with a variety of diverse sequences most closely related to other known metagenomic sequences. Also in this case, our msmE sequences together with other metagenomic occurrences formed a group clearly distinct from homologs encountered in soil species, although in this instance clustering with the msmE genes from two marine cultivated strains (C. Puniceispirillum marinum and C. Filomicrobium str. Y) was observed. Rather surprisingly, we were not able to amplify gene E from the enriched sample (SCDE). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46759" pm="."><plain>This fact suggests that two different populations of bacteria may have existed in sample SCD0: one, harboring both genes A and E, which was wiped out during the enrichment, and another carrying just the MSA monooxygenase (gene A) and importing methanesulfonate from the medium using a transporter alternative to MsmE whose gene cannot be amplified by the primers we employed. Scanning through the functional annotation of the two assembled metagenome sequences, we found 31 “ABC-type nitrate/sulfonate/bicarbonate transport system, periplasmic component” hits in SCD0 and 55 in SCDE: this is the description of a family of MsmE paralogs. It was already recognized that gene E showed a lesser level of conservation than gene A and our data corroborate this idea and indicate that regrettably msmE cannot be used as a reliable functional indicator of MSA utilizers. <p><text><SENT sid="46762" pm="."><plain>An alternative enzyme has been found in non-methylotrophs that use MSA as a source of sulfur: SsuD (also MsuD) is an FMNH2-dependent alkanesulfonate monooxygenase which can desulfonate MSA (Eichhorn, Van Der Ploeg &amp; Leisinger, 1999; Endoh et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46763" pm="."><plain>Intriguingly, we recently described a Rhododoccus strain that grows on MSA possibly employing SsuD (Henriques &amp; De Marco, 2015c). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46764" pm="."><plain>The fact that we detected 5 msuD/ssuD homologs in the enriched metagenome (and none in the original sample) suggests that this alternative sulfonate monooxygenase may be another relevant marker gene for MSA utilization in the oceanic environment. <p><text><SENT sid="46765" pm="."><plain>This evidence may also point to two possible alternative scenarios: in the first, at least part of the degradation of methanesulfonate is accomplished by non-methylotrophic bacteria capable of cleaving the MSA molecule and of using the resulting formaldehyde purely as a source of energy: a similar model has been found at work with C1 compounds such as methanol, formaldehyde, methylamine, trimethylamine, trimethylamine N-oxide and the C1 moiety of glycine betaine and dimethylsulfoniopropionate in marine strain C. Pelagibacter ubique HTCC1062 of the SAR11 clade (Sun et al., 2011) which lead the authors to coin the term ‘methylovore’ for this type of metabolism. In that study, MSA was not a tested compound: indeed, genes msmA or ssuD are not present in the published genome sequences within the Pelagibacteraceae and we see this family disappear from our enriched sample. However, it is not implausible that other non-methylotrophic marine species may use MSA co-metabolically as a source of energy in an analogous fashion. A second scenario can be imagined of a syntrophic association between non-methylotrophic microorganisms expressing MsmA or SsuD and methylotrophs incapable of cleaving MSA. This hypothesis is especially relevant for marine water where many of the microorganisms are found in suspended particles or flocks (Azam, 1998). <p><text><SENT sid="46771" pm="."><plain>Due to time and practical constraints, this study reports on the community evolution of a single specific sample. As such, the influence of confounding factors on the outcomes cannot be properly discarded and our results must be considered explorative in nature. However, many of the phylogenetic and metabolic data obtained distinctly suggest that MSA was the factor genuinely causing the differences observed. Gene msmA appears to be a good marker for MSA degraders, although further study into organisms employing alternative MSA-cleaving enzymes is needed in order to assess the relative importance of the different genes. Enrichment-free strategies such as single-cell genome sequencing, which provides joined functional and phylogenetic data, or MSA-induced metatranscriptomic shift analysis or in situ physiological studies are necessary to obtain a more complete and realistic picture less dependent on lab culturing. </sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="supplemental-information"><title><text><SENT sid="46776" pm="."><plain>Supplemental Information <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-1"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-1</object-id><label>Figure S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46777" pm="."><plain>Analysis pipeline for metagenomic data </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s001.png"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46778" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-2"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-2</object-id><label>Figure S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46779" pm="."><plain>Analysis pipeline for amplicon data </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s002.png"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46780" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-3"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-3</object-id><label>Figure S3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46781" pm="."><plain>Metagenomic composition rarefaction curves based on 16S rDNA data </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s003.png"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46782" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-4"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-4</object-id><label>Table S1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46783" pm="."><plain>General statistics of whole metagenome sequencing reads quality control performed by EBI Metagenomics </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s004.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46784" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-5"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-5</object-id><label>Table S2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46785" pm="."><plain>General statistics of whole metagenome sequencing reads quality control and assembly for IMG/MER submission </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s005.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46786" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-6"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-6</object-id><label>Table S3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46787" pm="."><plain>Primers used in the amplification of msmA and msmE gene sequences from SCD0 and SCDE samples </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s006.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46788" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-7"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-7</object-id><label>Table S4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46789" pm="."><plain>Successful PCR conditions for the amplification of msmA and msmE gene sequences from SCD0 and SCDE samples </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s007.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46790" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="supp-8"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.2498/supp-8</object-id><label>Table S5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="46791" pm="."><plain>General statistics of amplicon survey quality control </caption><media xlink:href="peerj-04-2498-s008.docx"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="46792" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="46793" pm="."><plain>We wish to acknowledge the help received from colleagues at CESPU Patrícia Duarte, Nilza Ribeiro, Claudia Ribeiro and Hugo Ribeiro, and Hassan Bousbaa (IINFACTS) for institutional support. We also thank Ana Toribio (ENA), Hubert Denise (EBI Metagenomics), Benli Chai (RDP), Jennifer Jackson (Galaxy), Matthieu Vizuete-Forster (Illumina), Scot Dowd (Molecular Research LP), the NGS team at Stabvida, I-Min Chen (IMG/JGI), Brandon KB Seah (Max Planck Institute for Marine Microbiology, Bremen, Germany), and Inês Cruz (Faculty of Science, U. of Porto, Portugal) for their patient technical advice. Finally, we wish to acknowledge the helpful criticism by the two anonymous reviewers of this work. </p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary content-type="abbreviations" id="glossary-1"><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list id="dl1"><def-item><term> MSA</term><def><p>Methanesulfonic acid</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> MSAMO</term><def><p>MSA monooxygenase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> DMS</term><def><p>Dimethylsulfide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> SSM</term><def><p>Sargasso Sea metagenome</p></def></def-item><def-item><term> GOS</term><def><p>Global Ocean Sampling</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="46796" pm="."><plain>The authors declare there are no competing interests. </fn></fn-group></SecTag><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="46797" pm="."><plain>Ana C. Henriques conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper. </fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="46799" pm="."><plain>Rui M.S. Azevedo conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, wrote the paper, reviewed drafts of the paper. </fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="46801" pm="."><plain>Paolo De Marco conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, wrote the paper, prepared figures and/or tables, reviewed drafts of the paper. </fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>DNA Deposition</title><fn id="addinfo-1"><p><text><SENT sid="46802" pm="."><plain>The following information was supplied regarding the deposition of DNA sequences: <p><text><SENT sid="46803" pm="."><plain>DOE Joint Genome Institute’s Integrated Microbial Genome Metagenomic Expert Review (IMG/MER) GOLD Project ID Gp0111927: (biosamples Gp0111627 and Gp0111630). <p><text><SENT sid="46804" pm="."><plain>European Nucleotide Archive project number PRJEB9018 (sample accession numbers <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS700852">ERS700852</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS700853">ERS700853</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS954926">ERS954926</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS954925">ERS954925</ext-link> and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena/data/view/ERS954927">ERS954927</ext-link>). </fn></fn-group></sec><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><text><SENT sid="46805" pm="."><plain>Andreae (1986)AndreaeMO1986The ocean as a source of atmospheric sulfur compoundsThe role of air-sea exchange in geochemical cyclingNATO ASI series 185Buat-MénardPDordrechtSpringer331362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-2"><text><SENT sid="46806" pm="."><plain>Anesti et al. (2005)AnestiVMcDonaldIRRamaswamyMWadeWGKellyDPWoodAP2005Isolation and molecular detection of methylotrophic bacteria occurring in the human mouthEnvironmental Microbiology71227123810.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00805.x16011760 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-3"><text><SENT sid="46807" pm="."><plain>Azam (1998)AzamF1998Microbial control of oceanic carbon flux: the plot thickensScience28069469610.1126/science.280.5364.694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-4"><text><SENT sid="46808" pm="."><plain>Baxter et al. (2002)BaxterNJScanlanJDe MarcoPWoodAPMurrellJC2002Duplicate copies of genes encoding methanesulfonate monooxygenase in Marinosulfonomonas methylotropha strain TR3 and detection of methanesulfonate utilizers in the environmentApplied and Environmental Microbiology6828929610.1128/AEM.68.1.28911772638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-5"><text><SENT sid="46809" pm="."><plain>Boden et al. (2008)BodenRThomasESavaniPKellyDPWoodAP2008Novel methylotrophic bacteria isolated from the River Thames (London, UK)Environmental Microbiology103225323610.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01711.x18681896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-6"><text><SENT sid="46810" pm="."><plain>Bray &amp; Curtis (1957)BrayJRCurtisJT1957An ordination of the upland forest community of Southern WisconsinEcology Monographs2732534910.2307/1942268 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-7"><text><SENT sid="46811" pm="."><plain>Chao (1984)ChaoA1984Nonparametric estimation of the number of classes in a populationThe Annals of Mathematical Statistics2057257910.1214/aoms/1177729949 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-8"><text><SENT sid="46812" pm="."><plain>Chao, Chazdon &amp; Shen (2005)ChaoAChazdonRLShenTJ2005A new statistical approach for assessing similarity of species composition with incidence and abundance dataEcology Letters814815910.1111/j.1461-0248.2004.00707.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-9"><text><SENT sid="46813" pm="."><plain>Charlson et al. (1987)CharlsonRJLovelockJEAndreaeMOWarrenSG1987Oceanic phytoplankton, atmospheric sulphur, cloud albedo and climateNature32665566110.1038/326655a0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-10"><text><SENT sid="46814" pm="."><plain>De Marco et al. (1999)De MarcoPMoradas-FerreiraPHigginsTPMcDonaldIKennaEMMurrellJC1999Molecular analysis of a novel methanesulfonic acid monooxygenase from the methylotroph Methylosulfonomonas methylovoraJournal of Bacteriology1812244225110094704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-11"><text><SENT sid="46815" pm="."><plain>De Marco et al. (2000)De MarcoPMurrellJCBordaloAAMoradas-FerreiraP2000Isolation and characterization of two new methanesulfonic acid-degrading bacterial isolates from a Portuguese soil sampleArchives of Microbiology17314615310.1007/s00203990012410795686 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-12"><text><SENT sid="46816" pm="."><plain>De Marco et al. (2004)De MarcoPPachecoCCFigueiredoARMoradas-FerreiraP2004Novel pollutant-resistant methylotrophic bacteria for use in bioremediationFEMS Microbiology Letters234758010.1016/j.femsle.2004.03.01015109722 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-13"><text><SENT sid="46817" pm="."><plain>Dereeper et al. (2008)DereeperAGuignonVBlancGAudicSBuffetSChevenetFDufayardJFGuidonSLefortVLescotMClaverieJMGascuelO2008Phylogeny.fr: robust phylogenetic analysis for the non-specialistNucleic Acids Research3646546910.1093/nar/gkn180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-14"><text><SENT sid="46818" pm="."><plain>Eddy (2011)EddySR2011Accelerated profile HMM searchesPLoS Computational Biology7e249810.1371/journal.pcbi.1002195 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-15"><text><SENT sid="46819" pm="."><plain>Edgar et al. (2011)EdgarRCHaasBJClementeJCQuinceCKnightR2011UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detectionBioinformatics272194220010.1093/bioinformatics/btr38121700674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-16"><text><SENT sid="46820" pm="."><plain>Eichhorn, Van Der Ploeg &amp; Leisinger (1999)EichhornEVan Der PloegJRLeisingerT1999Characterization of a two-component alkanesulfonate monooxygenase from Escherichia coliJournal of Biological Chemistry274266392664610.1074/jbc.274.38.2663910480865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-17"><text><SENT sid="46821" pm="."><plain>Endoh et al. (2003)EndohTKasugaKHorinouchiMYoshidaTHabeHNojiriHOmoriT2003Characterization and identification of genes essential for dimethyl sulfide utilization in Pseudomonas putida strain DS1Applied Microbiology and Biotechnology62839110.1007/s00253-003-1233-712835925 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-18"><text><SENT sid="46822" pm="."><plain>Faith, Minchin &amp; Belbin (1987)FaithDPMinchinPRBelbinL1987Compsitional dissimilarity as a robust measure of ecogical distanceVegetatio69576810.1007/BF00038687 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-19"><text><SENT sid="46823" pm="."><plain>Fish et al. (2013)FishJAChaiBWangQSunYBrownCTTiedjeJMColeJR2013FunGene: the functional gene pipeline and repositoryFrontiers in Microbiology411410.3389/fmicb.2013.0029123346082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-20"><text><SENT sid="46824" pm="."><plain>Gifford et al. (2013)GiffordSMSharmaSBoothMMoranMA2013Expression patterns reveal niche diversification in a marine microbial assemblageThe ISME Journal728129810.1038/ismej.2012.9622931830 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-21"><text><SENT sid="46825" pm="."><plain>Gondwe et al. (2003)GondweMKrolMGieskesWKlaassenWDe BaarH2003The contribution of ocean-leaving DMS to the global atmospheric burdens of DMS, MSA, SO2, and NSS SO\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{upgreek} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document} }{}${}_{4}^{=}$\end{document}4=Global Biogeochemical Cycles17105610.1029/2002GB001937 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-22"><text><SENT sid="46826" pm="."><plain>Guindon et al. (2010)GuindonSDufayardJFLefortVAnisimovaMHordijkWGascuelO2010New algorithms and methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of PhyML3.0Systematic Biology5930732110.1093/sysbio/syq01020525638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-23"><text><SENT sid="46827" pm="."><plain>Henriques &amp; De Marco (2015a)HenriquesACDe MarcoP2015aMethanesulfonate (MSA) catabolic genes from marine and estuarine bacteriaPLoS ONE105e249810.1371/journal.pone.0125735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-24"><text><SENT sid="46828" pm="."><plain>Henriques &amp; De Marco (2015b)HenriquesACDe MarcoP2015bComplete genome sequences of two strains of candidatus filomicrobium marinum, a methanesulfonate-degrading speciesGenome Announcements31210.1128/genomeA.00160-15 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-25"><text><SENT sid="46829" pm="."><plain>Henriques &amp; De Marco (2015c)HenriquesACDe MarcoP2015cGenome sequence of Rhodococcus sp. strain RD6.2 DSM 46800, a methanesulfonate-degrading strainGenome Announcements391010.1128/genomeA.00326-15 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-26"><text><SENT sid="46830" pm="."><plain>Huson, Mitra &amp; Ruscheweyh (2011)HusonDMitraSRuscheweyhH2011Integrative analysis of environmental sequences using MEGAN4Genome Research211552156010.1101/gr.120618.11121690186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-27"><text><SENT sid="46831" pm="."><plain>Hynes, Wine &amp; Semmes (1986)HynesAJWinePHSemmesDHKinetics and mechanism of OH reactions with organic sulfidesThe Journal of Physical Chemistry1986904148415610.1021/j100408a062 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-28"><text><SENT sid="46832" pm="."><plain>Inag (2009)InagIP2009Manual para a avaliação da qualidade biológica da água em lagos e albufeiras segundo a Directiva Quadro da Água. Protocolo de amostragem e análise para o FitoplânctonMinistério do Ambiente, do Ordenamento do Território e do Desenvolvimento RegionalInstituto da Água, I.P </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-29"><text><SENT sid="46834" pm="."><plain>Jaccard (1912)JaccardP1912The distribution of the flora inthe alpine zoneNew Phytologist11375010.1111/j.1469-8137.1912.tb05611.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-30"><text><SENT sid="46835" pm="."><plain>Jamshad et al. (2006)JamshadMDe MarcoPPachecoCCHanczarTMurrellJC2006Identification, mutagenesis, and transcriptional analysis of the methanesulfonate transport operon of Methylosulfonomonas methylovoraApplied and Environmental Microbiology7227628310.1128/AEM.72.1.276-283.200616391054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-31"><text><SENT sid="46836" pm="."><plain>Jeffrey &amp; Humphrey (1975)JeffreySWHumphreyGF1975New spectrophotometric equations for determining chlorophylls a, b, c1 and c2 in higher plants, algae and natural phytoplanktonBiochemie und Physiologie der Pflanzen16719119410.1016/0022-2860(75)85046-0 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-32"><text><SENT sid="46837" pm="."><plain>Kang et al. (2015)KangDDFroulaJEganRWangZ2015MetaBAT, an efficient tool for accurately reconstructing single genomes from complex microbial communitiesPeerJ3e249810.7717/peerj.1165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-33"><text><SENT sid="46838" pm="."><plain>Kelly &amp; Baker (1990)KellyDPBakerSC1990The organosulphur cycle: aerobic and anaerobic processes leading to turnover of C1-Sulphur compoundsFEMS Microbiology8724124610.1016/0378-1097(90)90461-X </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-34"><text><SENT sid="46839" pm="."><plain>Kelly &amp; Murrell (1999)KellyDPMurrellJC1999Microbial metabolism of methanesulfonic acidArchives of Microbiology534134810.1007/s002030050770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-35"><text><SENT sid="46840" pm="."><plain>Koga &amp; Tanaka (1993)KogaSTanakaH1993Numerical study of the oxidation process of dimethylsulfide in the marine atmosphereJornal of Atmospheric Chemistry1720122810.1007/BF00694398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-36"><text><SENT sid="46841" pm="."><plain>Legrand &amp; Feniet-Saigne (1991)LegrandMFeniet-SaigneC1991Methanesulfonic acid in soth polar snow layers: a record of strong El Nino?Geophysical Research1818719010.1029/90GL02784 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-37"><text><SENT sid="46842" pm="."><plain>Leitão, Moradas-Ferreira &amp; De Marco (2009)LeitãoEMoradas-FerreiraPDe MarcoP2009Evidence of methanesulfonate utilizers in the Sargasso Sea metagenomeJournal of Basic Microbiology49S243010.1002/jobm.20080022319322831 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-38"><text><SENT sid="46843" pm="."><plain>Li et al. (2015)LiDLiuC-MLuoRSadakaneKLamT-W2015MEGAHIT: an ultra-fast single-node solution for large and complex metagenomics assembly via succinct de Bruijn graphBioinformatics311674167610.1093/bioinformatics/btv03325609793 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-39"><text><SENT sid="46844" pm="."><plain>Loewenstein et al. (2008)LoewensteinYPortugalyEFromerMLinialM2008Efficient algorithms for accurate hierarchical clustering of huge datasets: tackling the entire protein spaceBioinformatics24i41i4910.1093/bioinformatics/btn17418586742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-40"><text><SENT sid="46845" pm="."><plain>Madhaiyan et al. (2010)MadhaiyanMPoonguzhaliSLeeJ-SLeeKCSundaramS2010Flavobacterium glycines sp. nov., a facultative methylotroph isolated from the rhizosphere of soybeanInternational Journal of Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology602187219210.1099/ijs.0.014019-019897620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-41"><text><SENT sid="46846" pm="."><plain>Markowitz et al. (2014)MarkowitzVMChenI-MAChuKSzetoEPalaniappanKPillayMRatnerAHuangJPaganiITringeSHuntemannMBillisKVargheseNTennessenKMavromatisKPatiAIvanovaNNKyrpidesNC2014IMG/M 4 version of the integrated metagenome comparative analysis systemNucleic Acids Research42D568D57310.1093/nar/gkt91924136997 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-42"><text><SENT sid="46847" pm="."><plain>McGinnis &amp; Madden (2004)McGinnisSMaddenTL2004BLAST: At the core of a powerful and diverse set of sequence analysis toolsNucleic Acids Research32202510.1093/nar/gkh435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-43"><text><SENT sid="46848" pm="."><plain>Meyer et al. (2008)MeyerFPaarmannDD’SouzaMOlsonRGlassEMKubalMPaczianTRodriguezAStevensRWilkeAWilkeningJEdwardsRA2008The metagenomics RAST server—a public resource for the automatic phylogenetic and functional analysis of metagenomesBMC Bioinformatics938639410.1186/1471-2105-9-38618803844 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-44"><text><SENT sid="46849" pm="."><plain>Mihalopoulos et al. (1992)MihalopoulosNNguyenBCBoissardCPutaudJPBelvisoS1992Field study of dimethylsulfide oxidation in the boundary layer: variations of dimethylsulfide, methanesulfonic acid, sulfur dioxide, non-sea-salt sulfate and aitken nuclei at a coastal siteJournal of Atmospheric Chemistry1445947710.1007/BF00115251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-45"><text><SENT sid="46850" pm="."><plain>Mitchell et al. (2015a)MitchellABucchiniFCochraneGDeniseHHoopenPTFraserMPesseatSPotterSScheremetjewMSterkPFinnRD2015aEBI metagenomics in 2016—an expanding and evolving resource for the analysis and archiving of metagenomic dataNucleic Acids Research44D59560310.1093/nar/gkv119526582919 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-46"><text><SENT sid="46851" pm="."><plain>Mitchell et al. (2015b)MitchellAChangH-YDaughertyLFraserMHunterSLopezRMcAnullaCMcMenaminCNukaGPesseatSSangrador-VegasAScheremetjewMRatoCYongS-YBatemanAPuntaMAttwoodTKSigristCJARedaschiNRivoireCXenariosIKahnDGuyotDBorkPLetunicIGoughJOatesMHaftDHuangHNataleDAWuCHOrengoCSillitoeIMiHThomasPDFinnRD2015bThe InterPro protein families database: the classification resource after 15 yearsNucleic Acids Research43D213D22110.1093/nar/gku124325428371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-47"><text><SENT sid="46852" pm="."><plain>Moosvi et al. (2005a)MoosviASMcDonaldIRPearceDAKellyDPWoodDPWoodAP2005aMolecular detection and isolation from Antarctica of methylotrophic bacteria able to grow with methylated sulfur compoundsSystematic and Applied Microbiology2854155410.1016/j.syapm.2005.03.00216104352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-48"><text><SENT sid="46853" pm="."><plain>Moosvi et al. (2005b)MoosviSAPachecoCCMcDonaldIRDe MarcoPPearceDAKellyDPWoodAP2005bIsolation and properties of methanesulfonate-degrading Afipia felis from Antarctica and comparison with other strains of A. felisEnvironmental Microbiology7223310.1111/j.1462-2920.2004.00661.x15643932 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-49"><text><SENT sid="46854" pm="."><plain>Mulder et al. (2004)MulderCPHDimitrakopoulosPGHectorASchmidB2004Species evenness and productivity in experimental plant communitiesOIKOS107506310.1111/j.0030-1299.2004.13110.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-50"><text><SENT sid="46855" pm="."><plain>Neufeld et al. (2008)NeufeldJDChenYDumontMGMurrellJC2008Marine methylotrophs revealed by stable-isotope probing, multiple displacement amplification and metagenomicsEnvironmental Microbiology101526153510.1111/j.1462-2920.2008.01568.x18294205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-51"><text><SENT sid="46856" pm="."><plain>Oh et al. (2010)OhH-MKwonKKKangIKangSGLeeJ-HKimS-JChoJ-C2010Complete genome sequence of Candidatus Puniceispirillum marinum IMCC1322, a representative of the SAR116 clade in the AlphaproteobacteriaJournal of Bacteriology1923240324110.1128/JB.00347-1020382761 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-52"><text><SENT sid="46857" pm="."><plain>Oksanen et al. (2015)OksanenAJBlanchetFGKindtRMinchinPRO’HaraRBSimpsonGLSolymosPStevensMHHWagnerH2015vegan: community ecologyR package version 2.3-2http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=vegan </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-53"><text><SENT sid="46858" pm="."><plain>Overbeek et al. (2005)OverbeekRBegleyTButlerRMChoudhuriJVChuangHYCohoonMDe Crécy-LagardVDiazNDiszTEdwardsRFonsteinMFrankEDGerdesSGlassEMGoesmannAHansonAIwata-ReuylDJensenRJamshidiNKrauseLKubalMLarsenNLinkeBMcHardyACMeyerFNeuwegerHOlsenGOlsonROstermanAPortnoyVPuschGDRodionovDARuckertCSteinerJStevensRThieleIVassievaOYeYZagnitkoOVonsteinV2005The subsystems approach to genome annotation and its use in the project to annotate 1,000 genomesNucleic Acids Research335691570210.1093/nar/gki86616214803 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-54"><text><SENT sid="46859" pm="."><plain>Rusch et al. (2007)RuschDBHalpernALSuttonGHeidelbergKBWilliamsonSYoosephSWuDEisenJAHoffmanJMRemingtonKBeesonKTranBSmithHBaden-TillsonHStewartCThorpeJFreemanJAndrews-PfannkochCVenterJELiKKravitzSHeidelbergJFUtterbackTRogersY-HFalcónLISouzaVBonilla-RossoGEguiarteLEKarlDMSathyendranathSPlattTBerminghamEGallardoVTamayo-CastilloGFerrariMRStrausbegRLNealsonKFriedmanRFrazierMVenterJC2007The Sorcerer II global ocean sampling expedition: northwest Atlantic through eastern tropical PacificPLoS Biology5e249810.1371/journal.pbio.0050077 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-55"><text><SENT sid="46860" pm="."><plain>Schäfer (2007)SchäferH2007Isolation of Methylophaga spp. from marine dimethylsulfide-degrading enrichment cultures and identification of polypeptides induced during growth on dimethylsulfideApplied and Environmental Microbiology732580259110.1128/AEM.02074-0617322322 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-56"><text><SENT sid="46861" pm="."><plain>Shannon (1948)ShannonCE1948A mathematical theory of communicationBell System Technical Journal2737942310.1002/j.1538-7305.1948.tb01338.x </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-57"><text><SENT sid="46862" pm="."><plain>Sun et al. (2011)SunJSteindlerLThrashJCHalseyKHSmithDPCarterAELandryZCGiovannoniSJ2011One carbon metabolism in SAR11 pelagic marine bacteriaPLoS ONE6e249810.1371/journal.pone.0023973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-58"><text><SENT sid="46863" pm="."><plain>Sunagawa et al. (2015)SunagawaSCoelhoLPChaffronSKultimaJRLabadieKSalazarGDjahanschiriBZellerGMendeDRAlbertiACornejo-castilloFMCosteaPICruaudCOvidioFEngelenSFerreraIGasolJMGuidiLHildebrandFKokoszkaFLepoivreC2015Structure and function of the global ocean microbiomeScience34811010.1126/science.1261359 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-59"><text><SENT sid="46864" pm="."><plain>Swan et al. (2013)SwanBKTupperBSczyrbaALauroFMMartinez-GarciaMGonzalezJMLuoHWrightJJLandryZCHansonNWThompsonBPPoultonNJSchwientekPAcinasSGGiovannoniSJMoranMAHallamSJCavicchioliRWoykeTStepanauskasR2013Prevalent genome streamlining and latitudinal divergence of planktonic bacteria in the surface oceanProceedings of The National Academy of Sciences110114631146810.1073/pnas.1304246110 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-60"><text><SENT sid="46865" pm="."><plain>Thompson, Owens &amp; Murrell (1995)ThompsonASOwensNJPMurrellJC1995Isolation and characterization of methanesulfonic acid-degrading bacteria from the marine environmentApplied and Environmental Microbiology612388239316535055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-61"><text><SENT sid="46866" pm="."><plain>Todd et al. (2011)ToddJDCursonARJKirkwoodMSullivanMJGreenRTJohnstonAWB2011DddQ, a novel, cupin-containing, dimethylsulfoniopropionate lyase in marine roseobacters and in uncultured marine bacteriaEnvironmental Microbiology1342743810.1111/j.1462-2920.2010.02348.x20880330 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-62"><text><SENT sid="46867" pm="."><plain>Wang et al. (2013)WangQQuensenJFIFishJALeeTKSunYTiedjeJMColeJR2013Ecological patterns of nifH genes in four terrestrial climatic zonesMBio41910.1128/mBio.00592-13 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-63"><text><SENT sid="46868" pm="."><plain>Waterhouse et al. (2009)WaterhouseAMProcterJBMartinDMAClampMBartonGJ2009Jalview Version 2–a multiple sequence alignment editor and analysis workbenchBioinformatics251189119110.1093/bioinformatics/btp03319151095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-64"><text><SENT sid="46869" pm="."><plain>White, Nagarajan &amp; Pop (2009)WhiteJRNagarajanNPopM2009Statistical methods for detecting differentially abundant features in clinical metagenomic samplesPLoS Computational Biology5e249810.1371/journal.pcbi.1000352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-65"><text><SENT sid="46870" pm="."><plain>Whung et al. (1994)WhungPYSaltzmanESSpencerMJMayewskiPA1994Two-hundred-year record of biogenic sulfur in a south greenland ice core (20D)Journal of Geophysical Research991147115610.1029/93JD02732 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-66"><text><SENT sid="46871" pm="."><plain>Wood &amp; Salzberg (2014)WoodDESalzbergSL2014Kraken: ultrafast metagenomic sequence classification using exact alignmentsGenome Biology15R4610.1186/gb-2014-15-3-r4624580807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ref-67"><text><SENT sid="46872" pm="."><plain>Zaharia et al. (2011)ZahariaMBoloskyWJCurtisKFoxAPattersonDShenkerSStoicaIKarpRMSittlerT2011Faster and more accurate sequence alignment with SNAP1111.5572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
