<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">International Journal of COPD</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1176-9106</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1178-2005</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Dove Medical Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5536237</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2147/COPD.S138720</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">copd-12-2179</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="59262" pm="."><plain>The association of tidal EFL with exercise performance, exacerbations, and death in COPD </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aarli</surname><given-names>Bernt Boegvald</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-copd-12-2179">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-copd-12-2179">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1-copd-12-2179"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Calverley</surname><given-names>Peter MA</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af3-copd-12-2179">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>Robert L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af4-copd-12-2179">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dellacà</surname><given-names>Raffaele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af5-copd-12-2179">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eagan</surname><given-names>Tomas ML</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-copd-12-2179">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-copd-12-2179">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bakke</surname><given-names>Per S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-copd-12-2179">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hardie</surname><given-names>Jon A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-copd-12-2179">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-copd-12-2179">
<label>1</label>Department of Clinical Science, University of Bergen</aff><aff id="af2-copd-12-2179">
<label>2</label>Department of Thoracic Medicine, Haukeland University Hospital, Bergen, Norway</aff><aff id="af3-copd-12-2179">
<label>3</label>Clinical Science Centre, University Hospital Aintree, Liverpool, UK</aff><aff id="af4-copd-12-2179">
<label>4</label>LDS Hospital, Pulmonary Division, Salt Lake City, UT, USA</aff><aff id="af5-copd-12-2179">
<label>5</label>TBM-Lab, Dipartimento di Elettronica, Informazione e Bioingegneria, Politecnico di Milano University, Milano, Italy</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-copd-12-2179">Correspondence: Bernt Boegvald Aarli, Department of Thoracic Medicine, Postboks 1400, Haukeland University Hospital, 5021 Bergen, Norway, Tel +47 9203 7838, Email <email>bernt_aarli@me.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><fpage>2179</fpage><lpage>2188</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017 Aarli et al. This work is published and licensed by Dove Medical Press Limited</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license><license-p>The full terms of this license are available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php">https://www.dovepress.com/terms.php</ext-link> and incorporate the Creative Commons Attribution – Non Commercial (unported, v3.0) License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>). By accessing the work you hereby accept the Terms. Non-commercial uses of the work are permitted without any further permission from Dove Medical Press Limited, provided the work is properly attributed.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59263" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="59264" pm="."><plain>Tidal expiratory flow limitation (EFLT) is frequently found in patients with COPD and can be detected by forced oscillations when within-breath reactance of a single-breath is ≥0.28 kPa·s·L−1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59265" pm="."><plain>The present study explored the association of within-breath reactance measured over multiple breaths and EFLT with 6-minute walk distance (6MWD), exacerbations, and mortality. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59266" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="59267" pm="."><plain>In 425 patients, spirometry and forced oscillation technique measurements were obtained on eight occasions over 3 years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59268" pm="."><plain>6MWD was assessed at baseline and at the 3-year visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59269" pm="."><plain>Respiratory symptoms, exacerbations, and hospitalizations were recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59270" pm="."><plain>A total of 5-year mortality statistics were retrieved retrospectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59271" pm="."><plain>We grouped patients according to the mean within-breath reactance (ΔXrs¯), measured over several breaths at baseline, calculated as mean inspiratory–mean expiratory reactance over the sampling period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59272" pm="."><plain>In addition to the established threshold of EFLT, an upper limit of normal (ULN) was defined using the 97.5th percentile of ΔXrs¯, of the healthy controls in the study; 6MWDs were compared according to ΔXrs¯, as normal, ≥ ULN &lt; EFLT, or ≥ EFLT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59273" pm="."><plain>Annual exacerbation rates were analyzed using a negative binomial model in the three groups, supplemented by time to first exacerbation analysis, and dichotomizing patients at the ULN. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59274" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="59275" pm="."><plain>In patients with COPD and baseline ΔXrs¯ below the ULN (0.09 kPa·s·L−1), 6MWD was stable. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59276" pm="."><plain>6MWD declined significantly in patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59277" pm="."><plain>Worse lung function and more exacerbations were found in patients with COPD with ΔXrs¯≥ULN, and patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN had shorter time to first exacerbation and hospitalization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59278" pm="."><plain>A significantly higher mortality was found in patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN and FEV1 &gt;50%. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59279" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="59280" pm="."><plain>Patients with baseline ΔXrs¯≥ULN had a deterioration in exercise performance, more exacerbations, and greater hospitalizations, and, among those with moderate airway obstruction, a higher mortality. ΔXrs¯ is a novel independent marker of outcome in COPD. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Keywords</title><kwd>forced oscillation technique</kwd><kwd>reactance</kwd><kwd>COPD</kwd><kwd>exacerbations</kwd><kwd>6-minute walk test</kwd><kwd>mortality</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="59281" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59282" pm="."><plain>COPD is a major cause of morbidity and mortality, leading to an estimated 3.1 million deaths globally in 2012.1 Although symptoms and exacerbation rate have been added to our assessment system of COPD,2 spirometry remains an important tool in assessing severity and prognosis in this disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59283" pm="."><plain>Changes in the forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) are still the best indicator of disease progression and the risk of dying from COPD.2,3 Yet, on an individual level, FEV1 is an unreliable marker of morbidity, especially in early disease,4–6 and there is a need to identify alternative objective tests that can aid in stratifying the risk of further patient deterioration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59284" pm="."><plain>Patients who exhibit tidal expiratory flow limitation (EFLT) might be such a subgroup. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59285" pm="."><plain>EFLT occurs when increases in driving pressure fail to increase expiratory flow during resting tidal breathing and is most often seen in patients with severe COPD,7,8 although it can occur with only moderate airway obstruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59286" pm="."><plain>Previous studies of EFLT in COPD have focused on its association with operating lung volume, exercise tolerance,9,10 and its relation to breathlessness.11–13 It is not known whether EFLT can provide longer-term prognostic information in COPD. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59287" pm="."><plain>EFLT can be detected by the forced oscillation technique (FOT).14,15 When peripheral airways collapse on expiration, oscillatory pressure signals are prevented from reaching the alveoli. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59288" pm="."><plain>As this happens, the oscillatory compliance is reduced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59289" pm="."><plain>Consequently, expiratory reactance (Xrsexp) becomes more negative than the inspiratory reactance (Xrsinsp), leading to a within-breath reactance difference (ΔXrs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59290" pm="."><plain>In the absence of EFLT, reactance measured in inspiration and in expiration is almost identical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59291" pm="."><plain>The within-breath reactance difference (ΔXrs) cut-off of 0.28 kPa·s·L−1 has been defined and validated to identify flow-limited breaths.14,15 EFLT is not only linked to dyspnea in COPD,11,16 but also to COPD exacerbations, where ΔXrs have been found to increase at the onset of COPD exacerbations and decrease when the exacerbation resolves.17 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59292" pm="."><plain>In this study, we used forced oscillation technique to define EFLT in 425 patients with COPD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59293" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that the presence of EFLT, assessed by increased mean ΔXrs (ΔXrs¯), would relate to changes in 6MWD, the risk of COPD exacerbations, and, possibly, mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59294" pm="."><plain>We explored these hypotheses using baseline ΔXrs¯ as a predictor for future events. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59295" pm="."><plain>Patients with COPD with abnormally high ΔXrs¯, both above the upper limit of normal (ULN) and above the established threshold of EFLT, were investigated to determine whether they differed from those without evidence of tidal expiratory flow limitation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="59296" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="methods|subjects"><title><text><SENT sid="59297" pm="."><plain>Study design and patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59298" pm="."><plain>The current data derive from the Bergen cohort of the Evaluation of COPD Longitudinally to Identify Predictive Surrogate Endpoints (ECLIPSE) study,18 with additional patients enrolled from our clinical catchment area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59299" pm="."><plain>Written informed consent was obtained from all study subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59300" pm="."><plain>The study was approved by the regional ethics committee, REK vest (REK 165.08), and performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and the Good Clinical Practice guidelines (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ClinicalTrials.gov">ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>; No: NTC00292552; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ClinicalTrials.gov">www.ClinicalTrials.gov</ext-link>).39 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59301" pm="."><plain>Inclusion criteria for patients with COPD were: age 40–75 years, FEV1 &lt;80% predicted, FEV1/FVC &lt;0.7, and a smoking history of ≥10 pack-years. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59302" pm="."><plain>Study patients were evaluated every 6 months for 3 years with an additional visit at 3 months after baseline, totaling eight visits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59303" pm="."><plain>The American Thoracic Society-Division of Lung Disease (ATS-DLD-78) questionnaire and the modified Medical Research Council dyspnea scale score (mMRC) were used to record respiratory symptoms.19,20 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59304" pm="."><plain>Post-bronchodilator spirometry and oscillatory lung mechanics during tidal breathing were performed after inhalation of 0.4 mg salbutamol (GlaxoSmithKline, Ventolin, London, UK) according to American Thoracic Society/European Respiratory Society (ATS/ERS) international standards at each visit using a Jaeger MasterScope CT Impulse Oscillation System (Jaeger, Hoechberg, Germany).21,22 Local reference values were used to determine the FEV1% predicted.23 The FOT measurements were performed with the patient seated, cheeks supported, and wearing a nose clip. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59305" pm="."><plain>We performed three continuous measurements of 30 seconds, totaling 90 seconds of tidal volume breathing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59306" pm="."><plain>Acceptability of measurements was determined using the ERS 2003 task force recommendations.22 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59307" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯ reactance was averaged over the 90-second sample, containing several breaths, and was calculated as follows: ΔXrs¯=mean Xrsinsp at 5 Hz – mean Xrsexp at 5 Hz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59308" pm="."><plain>Two cut-offs were investigated: the ULN defined as the 97.5th percentile of healthy controls in the Bergen cohort of the ECLIPSE study (ΔXrs¯=0.09kPa·s·L−1; Figure S1),13 and at the established EFLT defining threshold for within-breath reactance, 0.28 kPa·s·L−1, derived from single-breath analysis.14,15 To illustrate the variability of our multiple-breath measurement, ΔXrs¯ was plotted against time in a subset of the patients defined EFLT at baseline with complete visits (N=20). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="59309" pm="."><plain>Study outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59310" pm="."><plain>Distance walked during the 6-minute walk test (6MWT) was used to assess exercise performance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59311" pm="."><plain>The 6MWT was supervised by a trained technician and performed in a 30-m, straight hospital corridor according to agreed standards at baseline and at the end of the study, at the 3-year visit.24 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59312" pm="."><plain>Exacerbations were defined as a worsening of respiratory symptoms over 2 days or more that required systemic corticosteroids or antibiotics, alone or in combination (“moderate exacerbations”), or exacerbations resulting in hospitalization (“severe exacerbations”). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59313" pm="."><plain>Assessment of exacerbations was performed retrospectively by the study physician at the half-yearly visits, over the 3-year study period. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59314" pm="."><plain>Mortality statistics were retrieved on August 25, 2011, approximately 5 years after the conclusion of the baseline visit by checking vital status in our local patient file system, which is linked to the Norwegian Causes of Death Registry. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59315" pm="."><plain>The Causes of Death Registry includes deaths of all residents, regardless of whether they die in Norway or abroad, and is assumed to have information on &gt;98% of all deaths.25 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59316" pm="."><plain>Statistics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59317" pm="."><plain>IBM SPSS version 22, Stata 13.1, and R 3.2.3 GUI 1.66 were used for different aspects of statistical analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59318" pm="."><plain>Data are presented as mean ± standard deviation, median (quartiles), mean (95% confidence interval), and absolute count or percentage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59319" pm="."><plain>Means were compared using independent samples t-tests, paired samples t-tests, or Mann–Whitney U test when appropriate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59320" pm="."><plain>Patients were categorized into three groups according to ΔXrs¯: normal, ≥ ULN &lt; EFLT, and ≥ EFLT at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59321" pm="."><plain>We report the change in the 6-minute walk distance in these three groups from baseline to the 3-year visit in notched boxplots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59322" pm="."><plain>Differences in walking distance between baseline and the end of the study were compared using paired samples t-test, grouping the patients according to the ΔXrs¯ and the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) grade.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59323" pm="."><plain>The rate of exacerbations in the three groups was analyzed as suggested by Keene et al using a negative binomial regression model, accounting for the yearly variability among test subjects in the exacerbation rate over the 3-year study period, adjusting for FEV1, age, sex, and a binary classifier identifying frequent exacerbators in the year prior to inclusion.26 Parameter effects of the baseline explanatory variables are reported as annual rate ratios (RRs), 95% confidence interval (CI), and P-values. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59324" pm="."><plain>Moderate and severe exacerbations requiring hospitalization were also investigated on the basis of the occurrence of ΔXrs¯≥ULN at baseline by time to first event analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59325" pm="."><plain>Groups were compared using a log-rank test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59326" pm="."><plain>Results are displayed as 1-minus-survival plots. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59327" pm="."><plain>Survival analysis was performed with Kaplan–Meier survival analysis, comparing distributions with the log-rank test, grouping patients by the occurrence of ΔXrs¯≥ULN at baseline, and by dichotomizing FEV1 at 50% of that predicted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="59328" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec sec-type="intro"><title><text><SENT sid="59329" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59330" pm="."><plain>In this population of patients with COPD, 60% were men and had moderate to very severe airway obstruction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59331" pm="."><plain>Women were, on average, 2 years younger and had lower tobacco exposure (Table S1); 50% of patients with COPD had normal ΔXrs¯, 31% were classified as being abnormal with ΔXrs¯≥ULN&lt;EFLT, and 18% had ΔXrs¯ above the threshold of EFLT (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59332" pm="."><plain>From the normal to the abnormal group, lung function worsened with a decline in FEV1 and FVC, and an increase in body mass index (BMI) and mMRC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59333" pm="."><plain>This difference was most marked between the normal and EFLT group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59334" pm="."><plain>For IC, we only found a significant difference between the normal and the EFLT group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59335" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯ was not a stable measurement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59336" pm="."><plain>Many patients defined as EFLT at baseline fell below the EFLT threshold during the course of the study (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59337" pm="."><plain>Six percent of the consequent ΔXrs¯ measurements were found to be normal; 23% of the patients dropped out of the study before the final visit, the main reason being death during the study period (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="59338" pm="."><plain>Relationship of EFLT to study outcomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59339" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯ was as poorly correlated with baseline 6-minute walking distance as FEV1 (Figure 2A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59340" pm="."><plain>On a group level, 6MWD declined with increasing ΔXrs¯, being 455 m in the normal, 410 m in the abnormal, and 363 m in the EFLT group (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59341" pm="."><plain>In patients who completed both the baseline and the final visit, changes in 6MWD were compared. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59342" pm="."><plain>No significant change between the baseline and the final 3-year visit was seen in the 6MWD of patients with normal ΔXrs¯. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59343" pm="."><plain>Patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN declined by a mean of 37 m (95% CI 15–58), P=0.001, and patients with EFLT declined by 63 m (95% CI 31–95), P&lt;0.001 (Figure 2C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59344" pm="."><plain>Grouping by GOLD grade produced similar boxplots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59345" pm="."><plain>GOLD 2 patients remained stable whereas a significant decline was seen in GOLD 3–4 grades (Figure 2D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59346" pm="."><plain>A total of 1,289 moderate to severe exacerbations were recorded throughout the study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59347" pm="."><plain>By negative binomial regression, estimated annual exacerbations rates were 0.7 in patients with normal ΔXrs¯, 1.3 in patients with COPD with ΔXrs¯≥ULN, and 1.6 in patients with EFLT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59348" pm="."><plain>Annual exacerbation RR compared to the normal group was 1.28 for ULN patients and 1.30 for EFLT patients (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59349" pm="."><plain>A time to first exacerbation analysis was performed in patients with COPD with and without evidence of ΔXrs¯≥ULN at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59350" pm="."><plain>Significant differences were found in both time to first exacerbation (P=0.009) and in time to first hospitalization (P=0.017; Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59351" pm="."><plain>Median time to first moderate or severe exacerbation was 76 weeks in patients with COPD with normal ΔXrs¯, compared with only 55 weeks in COPD patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN at baseline (Table 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59352" pm="."><plain>The time until 25% of the patients were hospitalized was 126 weeks in patients with normal ΔXrs¯ and 72 weeks in patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59353" pm="."><plain>Mortality </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59354" pm="."><plain>At the 5-year census, 72 (17%) of the 425 patients with COPD had died. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59355" pm="."><plain>Deaths were significantly more frequent in patients with ≥ ULN than in patients with normal ΔXrs¯, but not significantly different between the ≥ ULN and the EFLT, groups (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59356" pm="."><plain>Mortality was higher in patients with FEV1 &lt;50% (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59357" pm="."><plain>The difference in mortality between patients with ΔXrs¯ in the normal range and ≥ ULN was driven by increased mortality in patients with FEV1 &gt;50% (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59358" pm="."><plain>Mortality was 17% in ΔXrs¯≥ULN patients with FEV1 &gt;50%, compared to 5% in patients with normal ΔXrs (P&lt;0.001; Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59359" pm="."><plain>Mortality in patients with ΔXrs ≥ ULN was similar to what was found in patients with COPD with much more advanced airway obstruction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="59360" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59361" pm="."><plain>Using data from the ECLIPSE study, we investigated associations between increased ΔXrs¯ at the ULN and at the threshold of EFLT with decline in 6MWD, risk of later exacerbations, and all-cause mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59362" pm="."><plain>No change in 6MWD was found in patients with COPD with ΔXrs¯ in the normal range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59363" pm="."><plain>All patients with COPD with ΔXrs¯≥ULN deteriorated significantly in 6MWD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59364" pm="."><plain>Patients with COPD with ΔXrs¯≥ULN had increased risk for both moderate and severe exacerbations, and, in the patients with only moderate airway obstruction, FEV1 &gt;50%, a significantly higher mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59365" pm="."><plain>This study Xrs demonstrates that ΔXrs¯ provides valuable extra information in addition to FEV1 when characterizing the effects of small-airway obstruction on key COPD outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59366" pm="."><plain>We defined the ULN at the 97.5th percentile of healthy controls included in our study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59367" pm="."><plain>Data describing the control group have previously been published.13,18 The FOT threshold identifying a single flow-limited breath has been defined when within-breath reactance was &gt;0.28 kPa·s·L−1.14,15 We interpreted our continuous spectrum measurements performed over several breaths as showing evidence of flow limitation when measurements between the ULN and the threshold of EFLT were found. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59368" pm="."><plain>These borderline measurements are thought to represent a mixture of normal and flow-limited breaths. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59369" pm="."><plain>Exercise limitation is extremely common in COPD, and even small decreases in the 6MWD over time identify patients with increased risks of dying.27 When EFLT is present, patients can only increase their minute ventilation during exercise by increasing breathing frequency or by dynamic hyperinflation, allowing end-expiratory lung volume to rise.28 Dynamic hyperinflation can be induced by self-paced walking exercise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59370" pm="."><plain>This is usually assessed by changes in operating lung volume.12,29 We did not measure lung volume during the 6MWT, but reasoned that patients with COPD showing evidence of flow limitation at baseline, either as having ΔXrs¯≥ULN or the threshold of EFLT, were more likely to have a worse exercise tolerance at the same visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59371" pm="."><plain>This was true on a group level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59372" pm="."><plain>The EFLT group had the lowest 6MWD, but neither FEV1 % predicted nor any cut-off level of ΔXrs¯ could identify patients with COPD with a short walking distance (&lt;350 m), as proposed by Spruit et al.30 No significant decline was seen in patients with ΔXrs¯ in the normal range; in patients with COPD with ΔXrs¯≥ULN it declined 37 m, and in patients with EFLT, it declined by 63 m. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59373" pm="."><plain>The minimal clinically important difference on an individual level has been suggested to be 30 m in an ERS/ATS systematic review;31 consequently, the differences seen over time between our subgroups defined by ΔXrs¯≥ULN and EFLT are likely to be clinically important. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59374" pm="."><plain>Exacerbation and hospitalization rates at our site were similar to those reported in the completed ECLIPSE study and in the TORCH study.32,33 By negative binomial regression, the ΔXrs¯≥cut-offsULN and EFLT were both significant predictors for higher rates of exacerbations with very similar RR, demonstrating that the increased risk of exacerbations by EFLT is identified already at ULN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59375" pm="."><plain>In the time to first event analysis of patients with ΔXrs¯≥ULN, we found a shorter time to first exacerbation and a shorter time to first hospitalization than that of the COPD patients with ΔXrs¯ in the normal range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59376" pm="."><plain>A previous study on hospitalized patients showed that many, but not all, have FOT-defined EFLT during a COPD exacerbation.17 FOT measurements performed during hospitalized COPD exacerbations show that ΔXrs¯ measurements improve during resolution of an exacerbation, although many patients remain EFLT at discharge.17 At present, there is a shortage of readily measurable biomarkers that can predict the risk of future exacerbations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59377" pm="."><plain>Our data suggest that, after adjusting for lung function and exacerbation history, EFLT measurement can identify patients who are more likely to develop exacerbations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59378" pm="."><plain>Further prospective studies to confirm these observations and explore their mechanism are merited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59379" pm="."><plain>Patients with COPD with an FEV1 &gt;50% predicted and evidence of EFLT, defined as baseline ΔXrs ≥ ULN, had significantly higher risk of dying within the 5-year follow-up. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59380" pm="."><plain>Similar associations were not found in the patients with more advanced airway obstruction and FEV1 &lt;50%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59381" pm="."><plain>However, COPD is a complex, heterogeneous disease, and respiratory impairment is associated with higher incidence of comorbidities, such as hypertension, cardiovascular disease, and diabetes.34 If there is an association between ΔXrs¯ and mortality, the higher risk of adverse outcomes associated with comorbid disease could mask such an association with advanced disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59382" pm="."><plain>Although the association between death and ΔXrs¯ was highly significant, this sub-analysis should be interpreted with caution due to the relatively small number of deaths in patients with FEV1 &gt;50% predicted (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59383" pm="."><plain>There are certain limitations of this study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59384" pm="."><plain>The FOT threshold identifying a single flow-limited breath has been defined at ΔXrs¯&gt;0.28kPa⋅s⋅L−1.14,15 It is not known whether the use of this threshold may lead to different results when applied to values measured over a continuous spectrum of several breaths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59385" pm="."><plain>Previously published data show that the end-expiratory lung volume varies from breath-to-breath, affecting the prevalence of EFLT.8,15 Although the prevalence of EFLT increased as the FEV1% predicted declined, not all patients with very severe airway obstruction were found to have EFLT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59386" pm="."><plain>In previous studies on elderly and COPD with the NEP technique, higher prevalence of EFLT have been reported than in the present study.11,35,36 Different inclusion criteria and differences in sensitivity between the NEP and the FOT technique, together with the possibility that in borderline patients the application of a NEP per se could lead to development of EFLT, are likely explanations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59387" pm="."><plain>The wide reference range of FEV1 inevitably may also lead to an overestimation of the suspected lung function decline in many patients.23 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59388" pm="."><plain>As previously noted, EFLT varies between breaths in many patients with COPD and varies with repeat testing, likely reflecting differences in the end-expiratory lung volume on different test days.13 Physiological variability in these measurements might require the repetition of this test in different periods to increase the sensitivity of our test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59389" pm="."><plain>Despite this limitation, important relationships related to the presence of tidal flow limitation were seen, even when the data were controlled for severity of airflow obstruction measured by FEV1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59390" pm="."><plain>The data reflect results from the largest recruiting center in the ECLIPSE study, in which patients were carefully characterized using standardized methodologies including oscillatory mechanics.18,37 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="59391" pm="."><plain>Conclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59392" pm="."><plain>Consistent differences in clinically relevant outcomes were found, such as exercise capability, exacerbations, hospitalizations, and death in COPD patients with baseline ΔXrs¯ beyond the ULN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59393" pm="."><plain>This is below the established threshold for EFLT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59394" pm="."><plain>Our data support previous studies showing that patients with EFLT have worse lung mechanics than is evident from FEV1 measurement alone.11,38 The present study suggests that evidence of EFLT, measured during tidal breathing in an effort-independent fashion, can identify a subgroup of COPD patients with worse clinical outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="59395" pm="."><plain>Supplementary materials </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD1-copd-12-2179"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59396" pm="."><plain>Scatterplot of ΔXrs¯ plotted against FEV1 % predicted in healthy controls (N=229). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59397" pm="."><plain>Mean represented by the solid line. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59398" pm="."><plain>The dashed line represents the 97.5th percentile, the upper limit of normal (ULN). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><media mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tif" xlink:href="copd-12-2179s1.tif" xlink:type="simple" id="d35e1682" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SD2-copd-12-2179"><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ts1-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59399" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics in men and women (N=425) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59400" pm="."><plain>Subject characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59401" pm="."><plain>Total </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59402" pm="."><plain>Men </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59403" pm="."><plain>Women </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59404" pm="."><plain>P-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59405" pm="."><plain>Subjects (n) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59406" pm="."><plain>425 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59407" pm="."><plain>254 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59408" pm="."><plain>171 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59409" pm="."><plain>Age (years) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59410" pm="."><plain>63 (7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59411" pm="."><plain>64 (7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59412" pm="."><plain>62 (7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59413" pm="."><plain>0.014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59414" pm="."><plain>BMI kg/m2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59415" pm="."><plain>25 (5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59416" pm="."><plain>26 (5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59417" pm="."><plain>25 (6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59418" pm="."><plain>ns </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59419" pm="."><plain>Pack-years (years) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59420" pm="."><plain>41 (23) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59421" pm="."><plain>45 (24) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59422" pm="."><plain>33 (18) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59423" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59424" pm="."><plain>mMRC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59425" pm="."><plain>1.6 (1, 2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59426" pm="."><plain>1.6 (1, 2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59427" pm="."><plain>1.7 (1, 2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59428" pm="."><plain>ns </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59429" pm="."><plain>FEV1 (L) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59430" pm="."><plain>1.5 (0.5) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59431" pm="."><plain>1.6 (0.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59432" pm="."><plain>1.3 (0.4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59433" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59434" pm="."><plain>FEV1 (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59435" pm="."><plain>46 (14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59436" pm="."><plain>45 (14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59437" pm="."><plain>48 (13) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59438" pm="."><plain>0.007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59439" pm="."><plain>FVC (L) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59440" pm="."><plain>3.3 (0.9) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59441" pm="."><plain>3.7 (0.8) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59442" pm="."><plain>2.6 (0.6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59443" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59444" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯&gt;(kPa⋅s⋅L−1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59445" pm="."><plain>0.14 (0.17) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59446" pm="."><plain>0.13 (0.14) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59447" pm="."><plain>0.16 (0.20) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59448" pm="."><plain>ns </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn12-copd-12-2179"><p><text><SENT sid="59449" pm="."><plain>Note: Data presented as mean (standard deviation) unless otherwise stated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="tfn13-copd-12-2179"><p><text><SENT sid="59450" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: ULN, upper limit of normal 0.09 kPa·s·L−1; EFLT, tidal expiratory flow limitation; BMI, body mass index; Pack-years, packs of 20 cigarettes smoked per day × years as a smoker; Frequent exacerbators, percentage with ≥2 exacerbations the year the prior to inclusion; mMRC, modified Medical Research Council dyspnea scale score – mean (quartiles); FEV1, forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FEV1 (%), FEV1 percentage of predicted; FVC, forced vital capacity; IC, inspiratory capacity; IC (%), IC percentage of predicted; ΔXrs¯, difference between mean inspiratory and mean expiratory reactance at 5 Hz over multiple breaths; 6MWD, 6-minute walk distance. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="59451" pm="."><plain>The study was sponsored by GlaxoSmithKline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59452" pm="."><plain>The sponsor had no role in the design of the study, collection and analysis of the data, nor in the preparation of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="59453" pm="."><plain>The work was performed at Haukeland University Hospital. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59454" pm="."><plain>The authors thank all participants who took part in the study, all members of the Bergen Respiratory Research Group who contributed to the data collection, and offer special thanks to Lene Svendsen, Rita Oppedal, Tina Endresen-Vinsjevik, and Eli Nordeide who performed/supervised the pulmonary function tests. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="59455" pm="."><plain>Author contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59456" pm="."><plain>The corresponding author BBA wrote the manuscript, had access to all of the data in the study, and takes responsibility for the integrity of the data and the accuracy of the data analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59457" pm="."><plain>PMAC was in the ECLIPSE Scientific Committee and PSB in the ECLIPSE Steering Committee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59458" pm="."><plain>They both contributed to the development of the research design. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59459" pm="."><plain>PSB, JAH, and TMLE also contributed in the data collection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59460" pm="."><plain>All authors, including RLJ and RD, contributed to the data analysis, the clinical interpretation of the data, and to reviewing the final submission. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="59461" pm="."><plain>Disclosure </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="59462" pm="."><plain>The authors report no conflicts of interest in this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59463" pm="."><plain>1LozanoRNaghaviMForemanKGlobal and regional mortality from 235 causes of death for 20 age groups in 1990 and 2010: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2010Lancet201238098592095212823245604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59464" pm="."><plain>2From the Global Strategy for the Diagnosis, Management and Prevention of COPDGlobal Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) 2017Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://goldcopd.org/gold-2017-global-strategy-diagnosis-management-prevention-copd/">http://goldcopd.org/gold-2017-global-strategy-diagnosis-management-prevention-copd/</ext-link>Accessed April 18, 2017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59465" pm="."><plain>3SorianoJBAlfagemeIAlmagroPDistribution and prognostic validity of the new Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease grading classificationChest2013143369470223187891 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59466" pm="."><plain>4FranciosiLGPageCPCelliBRMarkers of disease severity in chronic obstructive pulmonary diseasePulm Pharmacol Ther200619318919916019244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59467" pm="."><plain>5GelbAFHoggJCMüllerNLContribution of emphysema and small airways in COPDChest199610923533598620705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59468" pm="."><plain>6Global Strategy for the Diagnosis, Management and Prevention of COPD, Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease (GOLD) 20112011Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.goldcopd.org">www.goldcopd.org</ext-link>Accessed January 2, 2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59469" pm="."><plain>7HyattREThe interrelationships of pressure, flow, and volume during various respiratory maneuvers in normal and emphysematous subjectsAm Rev Respir Dis19618367668313717137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59470" pm="."><plain>8O’DonnellDEVentilatory limitations in chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseMed Sci Sports Exerc2001337 SupplS647S65511462073 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59471" pm="."><plain>9CalverleyPMKoulourisNGFlow limitation and dynamic hyperinflation: key concepts in modern respiratory physiologyEur Respir J200525118619915640341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59472" pm="."><plain>10DiazOVillafrancaCGhezzoHRole of inspiratory capacity on exercise tolerance in COPD patients with and without tidal expiratory flow limitation at restEur Respir J200016226927510968502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59473" pm="."><plain>11EltayaraLBecklakeMRVoltaCAMilic-EmiliJRelationship between chronic dyspnea and expiratory flow limitation in patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseAm J Respir Crit Care Med19961546 Pt 1172617348970362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59474" pm="."><plain>12O’DonnellDEWebbKAExertional breathlessness in patients with chronic airflow limitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59475" pm="."><plain>The role of lung hyperinflationAm Rev Respir Dis19931485135113578239175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59476" pm="."><plain>13AarliBBCalverleyPMJensenRLEaganTMBakkePSHardieJAVariability of within-breath reactance in COPD patients and its association with dyspnoeaEur Respir J201545362563425359342 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59477" pm="."><plain>14DellacàRLDuffyNPompilioPPExpiratory flow limitation detected by forced oscillation and negative expiratory pressureEur Respir J200729236337417079262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59478" pm="."><plain>15DellacàRLSantusPAlivertiADetection of expiratory flow limitation in COPD using the forced oscillation techniqueEur Respir J200423223224014979497 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59479" pm="."><plain>16O’DonnellDELavenezianaPDyspnea and activity limitation in COPD: mechanical factorsCOPD20074322523617729066 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59480" pm="."><plain>17JetmalaniKTimminsSBrownNJExpiratory flow limitation relates to symptoms during COPD exacerbations requiring hospital admissionInt J Chron Obstruct Pulmon Dis20151093994525999709 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59481" pm="."><plain>18VestboJAndersonWCoxsonHOECLIPSE investigatorsEvaluation of COPD longitudinally to identify predictive surrogate end-points (ECLIPSE)Eur Respir J200831486987318216052 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59482" pm="."><plain>19MahlerDAWellsCKEvaluation of clinical methods for rating dyspneaChest19889335805863342669 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59483" pm="."><plain>20FerrisBGEpidemiology Standardization Project (American Thoracic Society)Am Rev Respir Dis19781186 Pt 21120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59484" pm="."><plain>21Standardization of spirometry, 1994 update. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59485" pm="."><plain>American Thoracic SocietyAm J Respir Crit Care Med19951523110711367663792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59486" pm="."><plain>22OostveenEMacLeodDLorinoHERS Task Force on Respiratory Impedance MeasurementsThe forced oscillation technique in clinical practice: methodology, recommendations and future developmentsEur Respir J20032261026104114680096 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59487" pm="."><plain>23GulsvikATostesonTBakkePHumerfeltSWeissSTSpeizerFEExpiratory and inspiratory forced vital capacity and one-second forced volume in asymptomatic never-smokers in NorwayClin Physiol200121664866011722472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59488" pm="."><plain>24ATS Committee on Proficiency Standards for Clinical Pulmonary Function LaboratoriesATS statement: guidelines for the six-minute walk testAm J Respir Crit Care Med2002166111111712091180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59489" pm="."><plain>25PedersenAGEllingsenCLData quality in the Causes of Death RegistryTidsskr Nor Laegeforen2015135876877025947599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59490" pm="."><plain>26KeeneONCalverleyPMJonesPWVestboJAndersonJAStatistical analysis of exacerbation rates in COPD: TRISTAN and ISOLDE revisitedEur Respir J2008321172418591336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59491" pm="."><plain>27PolkeyMISpruitMAEdwardsLDSix-minute-walk test in chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: minimal clinically important difference for death or hospitalizationAm J Respir Crit Care Med2013187438238623262518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59492" pm="."><plain>28GuenetteJAWebbKAO’DonnellDEDoes dynamic hyperinflation contribute to dyspnoea during exercise in patients with COPD?Eur Respir J201240232232922183485 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59493" pm="."><plain>29MarinJMCarrizoSJGasconMSanchezAGallegoBCelliBRInspiratory capacity, dynamic hyperinflation, breathlessness, and exercise performance during the 6-minute-walk test in chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseAm J Respir Crit Care Med200116361395139911371407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59494" pm="."><plain>30SpruitMAPolkeyMICelliBEvaluation of COPD Longitudinally to Identify Predictive Surrogate Endpoints (ECLIPSE) study investigatorsPredicting outcomes from 6-minute walk distance in chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseJ Am Med Dir Assoc201213329129721778120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59495" pm="."><plain>31SinghSJPuhanMAAndrianopoulosVAn official systematic review of the European Respiratory Society/American Thoracic Society: measurement properties of field walking tests in chronic respiratory diseaseEur Respir J20144461447147825359356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59496" pm="."><plain>32HurstJRVestboJAnzuetoAEvaluation of COPD Longitudinally to Identify Predictive Surrogate Endpoints (ECLIPSE) InvestigatorsSusceptibility to exacerbation in chronic obstructive pulmonary diseaseN Engl J Med2010363121128113820843247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59497" pm="."><plain>33JenkinsCRJonesPWCalverleyPMEfficacy of salmeterol/fluticasone propionate by GOLD stage of chronic obstructive pulmonary disease: analysis from the randomised, placebo-controlled TORCH studyRespir Res2009105919566934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59498" pm="."><plain>34ManninoDMThornDSwensenAHolguinFPrevalence and outcomes of diabetes, hypertension and cardiovascular disease in COPDEur Respir J200832496296918579551 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59499" pm="."><plain>35de BisschopCMartyMLTessierJFBarberger-GateauPDartiguesJFGuénardHExpiratory flow limitation and obstruction in the elderlyEur Respir J200526459460116204588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59500" pm="."><plain>36KoulourisNGValtaPLavoieAA simple method to detect expiratory flow limitation during spontaneous breathingEur Respir J1995823063137758567 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59501" pm="."><plain>37CrimCCelliBEdwardsLDECLIPSE investigatorsRespiratory system impedance with impulse oscillometry in healthy and COPD subjects: ECLIPSE baseline resultsRespir Med201110571069107821481577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59502" pm="."><plain>38O’DonnellDEBertleyJCChauLKWebbKAQualitative aspects of exertional breathlessness in chronic airflow limitation: pathophysiologic mechanismsAm J Respir Crit Care Med199715511091159001298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39-copd-12-2179"><text><SENT sid="59503" pm="."><plain>39GlaxoSmithKlineEvaluation of COPD (Chronic Obstructive Pulmonary Disease) to Longitudinally Identify Predictive Surrogate Endpoints (ECLIPSE)Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00292552?">https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00292552?</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59504" pm="."><plain>NLM identifier: NCT00292552Accessed April 4, 2017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59505" pm="."><plain>Timeplot illustrating the variability of ΔXrs¯ measurements (splines) over the course of the study shown in the first 20 patients with COPD with complete visits, defined as having EFLT at baseline (ΔXrs¯&gt;0.28kPa⋅s⋅L−1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59506" pm="."><plain>The dotted line is set at 0.09 kPa·s·L−1, the upper limit of normal and the solid line at EFLT. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="copd-12-2179Fig1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59507" pm="."><plain>(A) Six-minute walk distance (6MWD) in patients with COPD (N=388) at different levels of FEV1% predicted (A) and ΔXrs¯ (B) at baseline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59508" pm="."><plain>Dotted lines set at 350 m (horizontal) and at ΔXrs¯&gt;0.09kPa⋅s⋅L−1, upper limit of normal (ULN), and ΔXrs¯&gt;0.28kPa⋅s⋅L−1, the threshold for tidal expiratory flow limitation (EFLT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59509" pm="."><plain>The solid lines represent the regression lines. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59510" pm="."><plain>(C) 6MWT at baseline and the 3-year visit presented by notchplots with quartiles, 95% central range and outliers among COPD patients of GOLD II–IV grades and categorized according to ΔXrs¯ (D) as normal (white), below EFLT, but above ULN (light gray), and &gt; EFLT threshold (gray). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59511" pm="."><plain>Non-overlapping notched areas are likely to represent significant differences between groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59512" pm="."><plain>Solid lines are drawn between the mean 6MWD at baseline and the 3-year visit. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="copd-12-2179Fig2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59513" pm="."><plain>Time to first moderate or severe exacerbation (A) and to the first hospitalization (B) in COPD patients with ΔXrs¯ measurements above the upper limit of normal (ULN), 0.9 kPa·s·L−1 (solid line), and below the ULN at the baseline visit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59514" pm="."><plain>Dashed line at 25%. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="copd-12-2179Fig3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59515" pm="."><plain>Kaplan–Meier survival curves in COPD patients with normal ΔXrs¯ and in COPD patients with ΔXrs¯ measurements above the upper limit of normal (ULN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59516" pm="."><plain>Test of equality of survival distributions was performed using log-rank test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="copd-12-2179Fig4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t1-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59517" pm="."><plain>Baseline characteristics in COPD patients with different levels of ΔXrs¯ (N=425) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" valign="top" align="left" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59518" pm="."><plain>Subject characteristics </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59519" pm="."><plain>Normal  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59520" pm="."><plain>Abnormal  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59521" pm="."><plain>EFLT  </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59522" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯&lt;ULN </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59523" pm="."><plain>ULN≥ΔXrs¯&lt;EFLT </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59524" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯&gt;0.28kPa⋅s⋅L−1 </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59525" pm="."><plain>Subjects (n) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59526" pm="."><plain>213 (50%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59527" pm="."><plain>134 (32%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59528" pm="."><plain>78 (18%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59529" pm="."><plain>Women </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59530" pm="."><plain>40% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59531" pm="."><plain>36% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59532" pm="."><plain>49% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59533" pm="."><plain>Age (years) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59534" pm="."><plain>63 (7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59535" pm="."><plain>64 (7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59536" pm="."><plain>63 (6) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59537" pm="."><plain>BMI kg/m2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59538" pm="."><plain>24 (5)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59539" pm="."><plain>26 (5)c,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59540" pm="."><plain>28 (6)d,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59541" pm="."><plain>Pack-years (years) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59542" pm="."><plain>40 (24) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59543" pm="."><plain>43 (22) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59544" pm="."><plain>39 (22) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59545" pm="."><plain>Frequent exacerbators (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59546" pm="."><plain>13% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59547" pm="."><plain>20% </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59548" pm="."><plain>35% </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59549" pm="."><plain>mMRC </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59550" pm="."><plain>1.2 (0, 2)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59551" pm="."><plain>1.8 (0.25, 2)c,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59552" pm="."><plain>2.3 (1, 2)d,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59553" pm="."><plain>FEV1 (L) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59554" pm="."><plain>1.7 (0.5)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59555" pm="."><plain>1.3 (0.5)c,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59556" pm="."><plain>1.1 (0.4)d,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59557" pm="."><plain>FEV1 (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59558" pm="."><plain>52 (11)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59559" pm="."><plain>42 (12)c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59560" pm="."><plain>38 (13)d </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59561" pm="."><plain>FVC (L) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59562" pm="."><plain>3.5 (0.9)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59563" pm="."><plain>3.2 (0.8)c,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59564" pm="."><plain>2.8 (0.9)d,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59565" pm="."><plain>IC (L) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59566" pm="."><plain>2.6 (0.8)d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59567" pm="."><plain>2.5 (0.7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59568" pm="."><plain>2.3 (0.7)d </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59569" pm="."><plain>IC (%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59570" pm="."><plain>88 (19) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59571" pm="."><plain>85 (20) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59572" pm="."><plain>84 (21) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59573" pm="."><plain>6MWD (meters) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59574" pm="."><plain>455 (102)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59575" pm="."><plain>410 (109)c,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59576" pm="."><plain>363 (110)d,e </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59577" pm="."><plain>Estimated exacerbations per yeara </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59578" pm="."><plain>0.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59579" pm="."><plain>1.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59580" pm="."><plain>1.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59581" pm="."><plain>Deathsb </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59582" pm="."><plain>25 (12)c,d </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59583" pm="."><plain>28 (21)c </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59584" pm="."><plain>18 (23)d </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn1-copd-12-2179"><p><bold>Notes:</bold> Data presented as mean ± standard deviation unless otherwise stated.</p></fn><fn id="tfn2-copd-12-2179"><label>a</label><p>Estimated exacerbation rate by negative binomial model.</p></fn><fn id="tfn3-copd-12-2179"><label>b</label><p>Number of deaths at the 5-year census (%). Significant differences at the 5% level are marked as</p></fn><fn id="tfn4-copd-12-2179"><label>c</label><p>between normal and abnormal,</p></fn><fn id="tfn5-copd-12-2179"><label>d</label><p>between normal and EFL<sub>T</sub>, and</p></fn><fn id="tfn6-copd-12-2179"><label>e</label><p>between abnormal and EFL<sub>T</sub>. pack-years: packs of 20 cigarettes smoked per day × years as a smoker; Frequent exacerbators: percentage with ≥2 exacerbations the year the prior to inclusion.</p></fn><fn id="tfn7-copd-12-2179"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> ULN, upper limit of normal 0.09 kPa·s·L<sup>−1</sup>; EFL<sub>T</sub>, tidal expiratory flow limitation; BMI, body mass index; mMRC, modified Medical Research Council dyspnea scale score – mean (quartiles); FEV<sub>1</sub>, forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FEV<sub>1</sub> (%), FEV<sub>1</sub> percentage of predicted; FVC, forced vital capacity; IC, inspiratory capacity; IC (%), IC percentage of predicted; <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm75"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Xrs</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, difference between mean inspiratory and mean expiratory reactance at 5 Hz over multiple breaths; 6MWD, 6-minute walk distance.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t2-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59585" pm="."><plain>Deaths and dropouts during the 3-year study period (N=96) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59586" pm="."><plain>Reason </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59587" pm="."><plain>N </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59588" pm="."><plain>% </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59589" pm="."><plain>Died </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59590" pm="."><plain>41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59591" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59592" pm="."><plain>FOT not performed at the final visit </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59593" pm="."><plain>16 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59594" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59595" pm="."><plain>Refused further participation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59596" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59597" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59598" pm="."><plain>Excluded due to use of oral steroids </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59599" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59600" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59601" pm="."><plain>Excluded after being diagnosed with pulmonary cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59602" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59603" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59604" pm="."><plain>Other causes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59605" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59606" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59607" pm="."><plain>Total </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59608" pm="."><plain>96 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59609" pm="."><plain>23 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn8-copd-12-2179"><p><bold>Abbreviation:</bold> FOT, forced oscillation technique.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t3-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59610" pm="."><plain>Annual rate ratios estimated by negative binomial regression (N=395) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59611" pm="."><plain>Baseline explanatory variables </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59612" pm="."><plain>RR </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59613" pm="."><plain>95% CI </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59614" pm="."><plain>P-value </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59615" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯ </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59616" pm="."><plain> ≥ULN (0.09 kPa·s·L−1) and &lt;EFLT </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59617" pm="."><plain>1.28 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59618" pm="."><plain>1.05, 1.55 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59619" pm="."><plain>0.011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59620" pm="."><plain> ≥EFLT (0.28 kPa·s·L−1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59621" pm="."><plain>1.30 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59622" pm="."><plain>1.05, 1.64 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59623" pm="."><plain>0.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59624" pm="."><plain>FEV1 % predicted </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59625" pm="."><plain>0.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59626" pm="."><plain>0.04, 0.14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59627" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59628" pm="."><plain>Age in decades </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59629" pm="."><plain>1.36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59630" pm="."><plain>1.06, 1.34 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59631" pm="."><plain>0.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59632" pm="."><plain>Sex (male) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59633" pm="."><plain>0.85 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59634" pm="."><plain>0.72, 1.00 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59635" pm="."><plain>0.048 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59636" pm="."><plain>Exacerbation in the year prior to inclusion </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59637" pm="."><plain> ≥2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59638" pm="."><plain>1.99 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59639" pm="."><plain>1.64, 2.41 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59640" pm="."><plain>&lt;0.001 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59641" pm="."><plain>Intercept </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59642" pm="."><plain>0.98 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59643" pm="."><plain>0.42, 2.27 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59644" pm="."><plain>0.965 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn9-copd-12-2179"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> RR, estimated rate ratio; 95% CI, confidence interval; ULN, upper limit of normal 0.09 kPa·s·L<sup>−1</sup>; EFL<sub>T</sub>, tidal expiratory flow limitation; FEV<sub>1</sub>, forced expiratory volume in 1 second; FEV<sub>1</sub> (%), FEV<sub>1</sub> percentage of predicted.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="t4-copd-12-2179" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="59645" pm="."><plain>Exacerbations, hospitalizations, and deaths in COPD patients with and without ΔXrs¯≥ULN at baseline (N=425) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59646" pm="."><plain>Parameter </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59647" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯&lt;ULN </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59648" pm="."><plain>ΔXrs¯≥ULN </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59649" pm="."><plain>Total N </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59650" pm="."><plain>213 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59651" pm="."><plain>212 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59652" pm="."><plain>N patients (%) with exacerbation </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59653" pm="."><plain>144 (68%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59654" pm="."><plain>152 (72%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59655" pm="."><plain> Median time (weeks) to first exacerbation (95% CI) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59656" pm="."><plain>76 (57, 95) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59657" pm="."><plain>55 (42, 68) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59658" pm="."><plain> Log-rank test </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59659" pm="."><plain>P=0.009 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59660" pm="."><plain>N patients (%) hospitalized </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59661" pm="."><plain>62 (29%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59662" pm="."><plain>84 (40%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59663" pm="."><plain> Time (weeks) until 25% of the patients were hospitalized </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59664" pm="."><plain>126 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59665" pm="."><plain>72 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59666" pm="."><plain> Log-rank test </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59667" pm="."><plain>P=0.017 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59668" pm="."><plain>N dead at 5-year follow-up </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59669" pm="."><plain>25 (12%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59670" pm="."><plain>46 (22%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59671" pm="."><plain> Log-rank test </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="59672" pm="."><plain>P=0.011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn10-copd-12-2179"><p><bold>Note:</bold> ULN defined at <inline-formula><mml:math id="mm80"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">Δ</mml:mi><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>Xrs</mml:mtext></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">¯</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo>≥</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.09</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.2em"/><mml:mtext>kPa</mml:mtext><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">s</mml:mi><mml:mo>⋅</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>−</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>.</p></fn><fn id="tfn11-copd-12-2179"><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> ULN, upper limit of normal 0.09 kPa·s·L<sup>−1</sup>; 95% CI, 95% confidence interval.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></floats-group></article>
