<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jis</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Insect Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1536-2442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5443607</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25368078</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jisesa/ieu009</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ieu009</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="56575" pm="."><plain>Presence of Wolbachia in Three Hymenopteran Species: Diprion pini (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae) , Neodiprion sertifer (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae), and Dahlbominus fuscipennis (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pistone</surname><given-names>Dario</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bione</surname><given-names>Alessandro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Epis</surname><given-names>Sara</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pajoro</surname><given-names>Massimo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gaiarsa</surname><given-names>Stefano</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bandi</surname><given-names>Claudio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sassera</surname><given-names>Davide</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ieu009-AFF4">4</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="ieu009-COR5">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ieu009-AFF1">
<label><sup>1</sup></label>
Natural History Collections, University Museum of Bergen, P.O. Box 7800, 5020 Bergen, Norway
</aff><aff id="ieu009-AFF2">
<label><sup>2</sup></label>
Dipartimento di Scienze Agrarie, Università degli Studi di Bologna, Viale Fanin 44, 40127 Bologna, Italy
</aff><aff id="ieu009-AFF3">
<label><sup>3</sup></label>
Dipartimento di Scienze Veterinarie e Sanità Pubblica, Facoltà di Medicina Veterinaria, Università degli Studi di Milano, Via Celoria 10, 20133 Milano, Italy
</aff><aff id="ieu009-AFF4">
<label><sup>4</sup></label>
Current address: Dipartimento di Biologia e Biotecnologie, Università degli Studi di Pavia, via Ferrata 9, 27100, Pavia, Italy
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="ieu009-COR5"><sup>5</sup>
Corresponding author, e-mail:
<email>davide.sassera@unimi.it</email>
,
<email>davide.sassera@unipv.it</email></corresp><fn id="FN1"><p><text><SENT sid="56576" pm="."><plain>Subject Editor: Sara Goodacre </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>01</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>147</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>2</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2014. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Entomological Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="jis14-0147.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="56577" pm="."><plain>Abstract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="56578" pm="."><plain>Sawflies are important pests of various plant species. Diprion pini (L.) and Neodiprion sertifer (Geoffroy) (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae) are two of the most important sawfly pests in Italy, and both species are parasitized by the hymenopteran parasitoid Dahlbominus fuscipennis (Zetterstedt). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56579" pm="."><plain>Bacterial endosymbionts are currently studied for their high potential in strategies of biocontrol in a number of insect species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56580" pm="."><plain>In this study, we investigated the presence of symbiotic bacteria ( Wolbachia and Cardinium ) in the three species of hymenoptera mentioned earlier, both in wild and laboratory populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56581" pm="."><plain>Although all samples were negative for the presence of Cardinium , 100% prevalence for Wolbachia was detected, as all examined individuals resulted to be PCR positive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56582" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, 16S rDNA and ftsZ gene sequencing indicated that all individuals from the three hymenopteran species are infected by a single Wolbachia strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56583" pm="."><plain>Additionally, we report the presence of gynandromorphic individuals in D. pini , both in wild and laboratory-reared populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56584" pm="."><plain>Heat treatments on D. pini colonies removed the Wolbachia symbionts, but they also prevented the development of adults. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>endosymbiont</kwd><kwd>gynandromorphism</kwd><kwd>molecular screening</kwd><kwd>diprionid wasp</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><counts><page-count count="5"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="56585" pm="."><plain>Phytophagous insects represent a major threat for worldwide forests by causing direct damage, consuming leaves or other parts of the host, and also by vectoring micro-organisms that can trigger diseases in plants ( Ayres and Lombardero 2000 , Hulcr and Dunn 2011 ). Adults of Diprion pini (L.) (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae) feed preferentially on leaves of plants of the genus Pinus . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56587" pm="."><plain>The areal of distribution of this species covers the majority of continental Europe, in all areas where the host plants are present. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56588" pm="."><plain>In Italy, D. pini is frequently encountered in alpine environments ( Pornbacher 1992 ), but it has also been reported in the Etna area in Sicily ( Turrisi and Bella 1999 ). The species Neodiprion sertifer (Geoffroy) (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae) also occurs in a variety of habitats, on pine host plants from northern and central Europe, as well as in Asia and North America ( Olofsson 1987 ). The larvae of both sawfly species are massive defoliators that can cause important damage to the plants they feed on, also affecting the esthetic value in ornamental tree plantations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56591" pm="."><plain>In both species, the adult females lay eggs inside the needles of host plants, and the damage is determined by trophic activity of the larva consuming the leaves ( Augustaitis 2007 ). Besides, as the larvae mature, their feeding becomes more extensive and needles are stripped. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56593" pm="."><plain>Complete defoliation of the trees may occur, affecting the growth of the parasitized plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56594" pm="."><plain>The larvae, however, do not feed on new grown leaves, so the trees usually survive ( Kurkela et al. 2005 ). Periodically, sawfly populations may increase to outbreak proportion, and reduction in plant increment and tree mortality can be registered over widespread areas ( Coppel and Benjamin 1965 ). Dahlbominus fuscipennis (Zetterstedt) (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) is a parasitoid of many sawfly species, including D. pini and N. sertifer , and it is largely reared and released for pest control purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56597" pm="."><plain>Females of Da. fuscipennis lay eggs in the larvae of diprionid cocoons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56598" pm="."><plain>Several eggs are laid with a single insertion of the ovipositor, and up to 40 parasitoid larvae can develop in one cocoon. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56599" pm="."><plain>The winter is spent as a full-grown larva or pupa within the host cocoon. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56600" pm="."><plain>Haplodiploid sex determination, in which females develop from fertilized diploid eggs and males develop from unfertilized haploid eggs, is the most frequent and presumably ancestral mechanism of sex determination in the insect order Hymenoptera ( Heimpel and de Boer 2008 ). Such is the case of Diprionidae, including D. pini and N. sertifer , where sexual chromosomes are absent and sex is determined by ploidy of the newborn ( Rousselet et al. 1998 ). Males are aploid (e.g., n  = 14 in D. pini ) while females are diploid (e.g., 2 n  = 28 in D. pini ). Gynandromorphism is an anomaly affecting sexual and somatic characters in different tissues of an individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56605" pm="."><plain>An abnormal chimeric organism presenting a mixture of male and female physical features is defined a gynandromorph ( Narita et al. 2010 ). The occurrence of gynandromorphic individuals was previously reported in D. pini ( Beaudoin et al. 1994 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56609" pm="."><plain>Micro-organisms of the genus Wolbachia are gram-negative α-proteobacteria belonging to the order Rickettsiales, family Anaplasmataceae. Wolbachia is an obligated intracellular bacterium infecting a wide range of hosts, from arthropods to filarial nematodes ( Bandi et al. 2001 ). Vertical maternal inheritance is considered the primary route of Wolbachia transmission from one host generation to another. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56612" pm="."><plain>The role of Wolbachia in the host is also variable; in fact, these bacteria can behave as mutualists, pathogens, or even reproductive parasites. Wolbachia bacteria can exploit all known mechanisms of reproductive parasitism, manipulating the host reproduction with different strategies, including parthenogenesis, male killing, cytoplasmic incompatibility, and feminization of genetic males ( Werren et al. 2008 ). In general, Wolbachia bacteria are strictly associated with the gonads but might also be present in different somatic tissues ( Dobson et al. 1999 ). Cardinium , a recently described bacterial genus of maternally acquired endosymbionts, widespread in spiders, arachnids, and other arthropod groups ( Martin and Goodacre 2009 ), is associated with reproductive manipulations such as cytoplasmic incompatibility, parthenogenesis, and feminization in different arthropod species ( Wu and Hoy 2012 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56616" pm="."><plain>Investigations on the presence of endosymbionts in pests represent the first step in developing a potential strategy for biocontrol purposes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56617" pm="."><plain>For example, a study focused on the agent of Pierce disease in grapevines, the glassy-winged sharpshooter, showed that the spread of the disease could be controlled by an antagonistic bacterium that resides in the same insect vector ( Bextine et al. 2004 , Newman et al. 2004 ). On the other hand, the discovery of Wolbachia in filarial nematodes led to the development of antisymbiotic therapy to cure filarial diseases ( Taylor et al. 2000 ). In general, considering that the wide interactions between the host and the associated microbiota are a fundamental aspect of insect biology ( Weiss et al. 2012 ), investigations on the role of bacterial symbionts are allowing the development of novel strategies to control pest and parasitic arthropods and to reduce their vector competence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56624" pm="."><plain>In this study, we collected and reared individuals of two sawfly species ( D. pini and N. sertifer ) and of their parasitoid Da. fuscipennis (Hymenoptera: Eulophide). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56625" pm="."><plain>We then investigated the presence and the potential role of two important reproductive manipulator bacteria ( Wolbachia and Cardinium ) in these three hymenopteran species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56626" pm="."><plain>Besides, in accordance with a potential implication of endosymbionts in the occurrence of gynandromorphism ( Stouthamer et al. 1997 ), we also investigated the occurrence of this phenotype in D. pini in the new light of the presence of endosymbiotic bacteria. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="56628" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56629" pm="."><plain>Larvae of D. pini and N. sertifer were collected in northern Italy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56630" pm="."><plain>In detail, a total of 300 larvae of D. pini were collected on Pinus sylvestris plants in 2007, in two sampling sites in the municipalities of San Martino in Monte (Bolzano County) and San Dorligo (Trieste county) della Valle (Trento County). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56631" pm="."><plain>These individuals were used to establish a colony that was named Dpini1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56632" pm="."><plain>A further sampling was performed in 2007 in the municipality of Velturno (Bolzano County). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56633" pm="."><plain>In this occasion, 42 larvae of D. pini were sampled and used to establish a colony called Dpini2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56634" pm="."><plain>A third colony of individuals, named Dpini1×2, was created by the mating of two females of the Dpini2 line, one male of Dpini1, and one male of Dpini2; these four individuals derived from the first generation of each population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56635" pm="."><plain>Additionally, 35 N. sertifer cocoons were collected in Ozzano dell’Emilia (Bologna County) in 2007, and four of them resulted to be parasitized by Da. fuscipennis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56636" pm="."><plain>The rearing was performed as follows: D. pini larvae from the third to the last instar (fourth instar for males and fifth for females) and N. sertifer cocoons were placed in an artificial cell at a constant temperature of 20°C, with a relative humidity of 80%, and a photoperiod of 17 h on white neon light (Philips TL-D master 58W/84, Philips, Amsterdam, Netherlands). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56637" pm="."><plain>After measuring the development time of the insects at 20°C, we studied the effects of higher temperatures on development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56638" pm="."><plain>Two heat treatment experiments were performed each on 15 D. pini by increasing the rearing temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56639" pm="."><plain>The first experiment consisted of a stable increase in the rearing temperature to 25°C, while the second consisted of an increase to 30°C for three intervals of 24 h separated by 48 h at 20°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56640" pm="."><plain>The hymenopteran parasitoid Da. fuscipennis was reared only on N. sertifer , at the conditions described earlier. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56641" pm="."><plain>In total, 30 individuals of N. sertifer (17 males and 13 females), 30 of Da. fuscipennis (11 males and 19 females), and 50 individuals of D. pini (20 females, 20 males, and 10 gynandromorphs) were subjected to molecular screening for the presence of symbionts (see Table 1 for details). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56642" pm="."><plain>All individuals were stored in absolute ethanol, then washed in sterile water, homogenized with a sterile pestle, and processed for DNA extraction using a commercial kit (DNeasy Blood &amp; Tissue kit, Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) following manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56643" pm="."><plain>A molecular screening was performed on the extracted DNAs to investigate the presence of endosymbiotic bacteria belonging to the genera Wolbachia and Cardinium . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56644" pm="."><plain>Three specific Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR) protocols, targeting two different Wolbachia genes (16s rDNA and ftsZ ) and one Cardinium gene (16s rDNA), respectively, were applied, using previously published assays ( Casiraghi et al. 2001 , 2005 ; Marzorati et al. 2006 ). A subset of the Wolbachia -related PCR products (1,393 and 735 bp, respectively) was sequenced using Applied Biosystems (ABI) technology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56648" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis was performed on the obtained sequences, using an in-house pipeline comprising MUSCLE ( Edgar 2004 ), Gblocks ( Castresana 2000 ), and PhyML ( Guindon et al. 2010 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="ieu009-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="56650" pm="."><plain>Number of male, female, and gynandromorph D. pini individuals for each of the three laboratory colonies for each generation </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead align="left"><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56651" pm="."><plain>Colony </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56652" pm="."><plain>Laboratory line 1 (Dpini1)  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56653" pm="."><plain>Laboratory line 2 (Dipini2)  </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="center" colspan="3" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56654" pm="."><plain>Laboratory line 3 (1×2) (Dpini3)  </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr><tr><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56655" pm="."><plain>Sex </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56656" pm="."><plain>M </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56657" pm="."><plain>F </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56658" pm="."><plain>Gyn </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56659" pm="."><plain>M </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56660" pm="."><plain>F </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56661" pm="."><plain>Gyn </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56662" pm="."><plain>M </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56663" pm="."><plain>F </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56664" pm="."><plain>Gyn </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody align="left"><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56665" pm="."><plain>Generation 0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56666" pm="."><plain>168 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56667" pm="."><plain>111 (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56668" pm="."><plain>21 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56669" pm="."><plain>19 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56670" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56671" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56672" pm="."><plain>4 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56673" pm="."><plain>11 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56674" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56675" pm="."><plain>Generation I </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56676" pm="."><plain>143 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56677" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56678" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56679" pm="."><plain>68 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56680" pm="."><plain>35 (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56681" pm="."><plain>12 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56682" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56683" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56684" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56685" pm="."><plain>Generation II </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56686" pm="."><plain>13 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56687" pm="."><plain>15 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56688" pm="."><plain>3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56689" pm="."><plain>20 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56690" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56691" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56692" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56693" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56694" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56695" pm="."><plain>Generation III </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56696" pm="."><plain>11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56697" pm="."><plain>9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56698" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56699" pm="."><plain>7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56700" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56701" pm="."><plain>10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56702" pm="."><plain>Generation IV </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56703" pm="."><plain>44 (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56704" pm="."><plain>52 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56705" pm="."><plain>7 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56706" pm="."><plain>19 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56707" pm="."><plain>84 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56708" pm="."><plain>8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56709" pm="."><plain>Generation V </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56710" pm="."><plain>18 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56711" pm="."><plain>45 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56712" pm="."><plain>5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56713" pm="."><plain>31 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56714" pm="."><plain>36 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56715" pm="."><plain>51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56716" pm="."><plain>Generation VI </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56717" pm="."><plain>14 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56718" pm="."><plain>4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56719" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56720" pm="."><plain>1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56721" pm="."><plain>2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56722" pm="."><plain>0 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56723" pm="."><plain>Generation VII </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56724" pm="."><plain>52 (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56725" pm="."><plain>10 (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56726" pm="."><plain>7 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56727" pm="."><plain>83 (4) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56728" pm="."><plain>33 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56729" pm="."><plain>26 (2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56730" pm="."><plain>Total Gyn/total individual </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56731" pm="."><plain>60/779 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56732" pm="."><plain>16/187 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td colspan="1" rowspan="1"/><td align="center" colspan="1" rowspan="1"><text><SENT sid="56733" pm="."><plain>101/426 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ieu009-TF1"><p><text><SENT sid="56734" pm="."><plain>Gyn, gynandromorph; F, female; M, male. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="56735" pm="."><plain>In D. pini , the sexual dimorphism is strong, and the marked differences between males and females allow the identification of gynandromorphic individuals in the population and a detailed description of the distribution of male and female tissues on the soma of abnormal specimens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56736" pm="."><plain>In the laboratory-reared D. pini colonies, gynandromorphic individuals were described and the distribution of male and female tissues in these individuals was reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56737" pm="."><plain>In each individual, the male and female areas can be distributed in a strikingly bilateral way, patchily or uniformly mixed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56738" pm="."><plain>In particular, we annotated the frequency of somatic alterations in each body segment (head, thorax, abdomen, and external genitalia) in these individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56739" pm="."><plain>The distribution of the three tissue types is described with different colors: male (black), female (white), and mosaic (gray; see Fig. 1 for an example pattern). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ieu009-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="56740" pm="."><plain>Dorsal and ventral vision representing the tissue distribution of a gynandromorphic individual: male (black), female (white), and gynandromorph (gray). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56741" pm="."><plain>This specific pattern is an example of an individual belonging to the Dpini1×2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ieu009f1p"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="56742" pm="."><plain>We applied a Pearson’s chi-square test to evaluate any significant differences between the frequencies of gynandromorphic individuals in the three different D. pini populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56743" pm="."><plain>The test was applied between the frequency of gynandromorphs and normal individuals, respectively, in Dpini1 and Dpini2 and between each of the two populations and the inbreed line Dpini1×2 (2 × 2 contingency table, 1 df). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="56744" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56745" pm="."><plain>We investigated the presence of two insect symbionts, Wolbachia and Cardinium , in the three different D. pini populations. Cardinium was never detected in any of the sampled individuals, whereas all D. pini samples investigated resulted positive to Wolbachia . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56746" pm="."><plain>DNA samples from a population of N. sertifer and Da. fuscipennis were also tested for the presence of two endosymbionts, and both resulted positive to Wolbachia with 100% prevalence and negative to Cardinium. See Table 1 for a detailed description of the examined individuals, sexes, and rearing generations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56747" pm="."><plain>Partial 16s rDNA and fts Z Wolbachia gene sequences were generated from individuals belonging to the three species investigated in this study ( D. pini , N. sertifer , and Da. fuscipennis ). For each gene, all the obtained sequences showed 100% identity between them, excluding artifacts, indicating that we detected a single Wolbachia strain that presents a high capacity of colonizing the three examined hymenopteran species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56749" pm="."><plain>Gene sequences were submitted to the National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) database under the accession numbers HE814622 (978 bp) and HE814623 (690 bp), respectively, for 16S rDNA and ftsZ . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56750" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analyses were performed aligning the obtained ftsZ gene sequence with the homologous sequences of 21 Wolbachia strains retrieved from the database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56751" pm="."><plain>The resulting tree ( Fig. 2 ) shows that the novel strain belongs to the A Wolbachia supergroup ( Casiraghi et al. 2005 ) and that it is most closely related with two other Wolbachia strains, one infecting a member of Diptera ( Drosophila borealis ) and one infecting a member of Hymenoptera ( Technomyrex albipes ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ieu009-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="56753" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis based on a 437-bp portion of the ftsZ Wolbachia gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56754" pm="."><plain>The alignment was analyzed with PhyML. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56755" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap support values above 50 are indicated above each node. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56756" pm="."><plain>The name of the host species and the sequence accession number are indicated on each branch. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ieu009f2p"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="56757" pm="."><plain>We performed two heat treatments on the colony of D. pini to investigate the effect of temperature increase on the presence of Wolbachia . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56758" pm="."><plain>In fact, it has been shown in the literature that an increase in temperature can be an effective way to “cure” Wolbachia infection ( van Opijnen and Breeuwer 1999 , Sakamoto et al. 2008 ). Additionally, it must be considered that to complete the D. pini biological cycle under standard laboratory experimental conditions ( Bombosch and Ramakers 1976 , Eichhorn et al. 1976 , Köpke et al. 2010 ), an average time of 60 d is required (16-d embryonic, 28-d larval, and 16-d pupal developments). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56763" pm="."><plain>We hypothesized that a temperature increase could reduce this period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56764" pm="."><plain>For the first treatment, the temperature was set up at 25°C, resulting in a complete biological cycle of 48 d instead of 60 d, but with a great reduction of success in egg hatching. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56765" pm="."><plain>The second heat treatment (30°C) led to interruption of development of the D. pini larvae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56766" pm="."><plain>In fact, none of the larvae subjected to the treatment were able to molt into adults. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56767" pm="."><plain>Molecular screening on these larvae revealed that Wolbachia had been eliminated (all 11 tested larvae were negative to both Wolbachia -specific PCRs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56768" pm="."><plain>Further studies should be carried out to establish whether these effects are due to the absence of Wolbachia symbionts or simply to the temperature increase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56769" pm="."><plain>To study the effects of inbreeding on production of gynandromorphs, three different populations of D. pini were followed under controlled laboratory conditions for up to seven generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56770" pm="."><plain>We succeeded in maintaining the two field-derived colonies (Dpini1 and Dpini2), respectively, for seven and three generations, whereas the third colony (Dpini1×2), obtained from a cross between individuals of the two colonies, was more successful and was interrupted after seven generations, while still actively reproducing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56771" pm="."><plain>In all experimental populations, we observed the appearance of gynandromorphic individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56772" pm="."><plain>The total number of gynandromorphs was 177 of 1,392 individuals (mean frequency, 0.12): 60/719 in Dpini1 (mean frequency, 0.08), 16/187 in Dpini2 (mean frequency, 0.08), and 101/426 in Dpini1×2 (mean frequency, 0.23). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56773" pm="."><plain>In the laboratory-interbred population of D. pini (Dpini1×2), we report an increase in the frequency of gynandromorphism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56774" pm="."><plain>Indeed, we registered a statistically significant difference in the frequency of gynandromorphs within the population of the line Dpini1×2 compared with both Dpini1 (χ 2  = 60.956; 2 × 2 contingency table; 1 df; two-tailed P  &lt; 0.0001) and Dpini2 (χ 2  = 19.321; 2 × 2 contingency table; 1 df; two-tailed P  &lt; 0.0001), whereas there is no significant difference in the frequencies of gynandromorphs between the lines Dpini1 and Dpini2 (χ 2  = 0.152, 1 df, two-tailed P  = 0.6969). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56775" pm="."><plain>In the majority of gynandromorphic individuals (90.3%), we reported a complex pattern of external male, female, or gynandromorphic tissues distributed in more than one body district (see Fig. 1 for an example pattern). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56776" pm="."><plain>Worthy of note, external genitalia were frequently affected by gynandromorphism (61/177 = 34.5%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion"><title><text><SENT sid="56777" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56778" pm="."><plain>We investigated the presence of Wolbachia and Cardinium symbionts in D. pini , N. sertifer , and Da. fuscipennis by molecular methods. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56779" pm="."><plain>Our results indicate the presence of Wolbachia in all examined individuals of all three hymenopteran species, whereas Cardinium was not found in any of the examined samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56780" pm="."><plain>Although 100% prevalence of Wolbachia in individuals collected in the wild suggests a complete pervasiveness of the symbiont in the examined species, additional sampling from different geographical sites would be required to allow a definitive conclusion on this issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56781" pm="."><plain>The second part of the study was focused on D. pini to investigate the occurrence of gynandromorphism in wild and laboratory populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56782" pm="."><plain>Finally, heat treatments were performed in D. pini to try to evaluate whether removal of the Wolbachia symbionts was possible and whether this would have an effect on the host, particularly in terms of frequency of occurrence of gynandromorph individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56783" pm="."><plain>We were not able to link the presence of gynandromorphic individuals in D. pini to the presence of Wolbachia because these bacteria are always present in all investigated individuals (i.e., males, females, and gynandromorphs). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56784" pm="."><plain>The lack of genetic variability between bacteria of the genus Wolbachia recorded in D. pini , N. sertifer , and Da. fuscipennis suggests a horizontal transfer event between these three species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56785" pm="."><plain>Because Da. fuscipennis were reared on N. sertifer in our laboratory, the acquisition of Wolbachia in the parasitoid could also be explained through an event of symbiont transfer between these two species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56786" pm="."><plain>We highlight that both N. sertifer and Da. fuscipennis were reared separately from D. pini populations, so we can exclude the occurrence of horizontal transfer between the laboratory populations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56787" pm="."><plain>Nevertheless, horizontal Wolbachia transmission from infected to uninfected individuals within (intraspecific) and between (interspecific) host species has been previously observed both in the laboratory and over evolutionary timescales ( Cordaux et al. 2001 , 2012 ; Huigens et al. 2004 ; Viljakainen et al. 2008 ). Horizontal transmission allows Wolbachia to infect several host species and contributes to its vast host range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56792" pm="."><plain>Interspecific horizontal transmission has been reported, e.g., in wasps of the genus Trichogramma ( Huigens et al. 2004 ) and in the parasitoid wasp Nasonia ( Raychoudhury et al. 2009 ). We can hypothesize that the Wolbachia strain detected in this study was horizontally transferred between the three analyzed hymenopteran species in the wild. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56796" pm="."><plain>It seems reasonable to hypothesize that the parasitoid behavior is involved in this pattern of transmission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56797" pm="."><plain>The parasitoid wasp Da. fuscipennis could have acquired the bacteria while feeding on the caterpillar of diprionid wasps, and it could also have transmitted it to additional hosts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56798" pm="."><plain>For this model to be acceptable, the efficiency of infestation of the parasitoid must be &lt;100%; otherwise, all infected host individuals would be killed by the infestation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56799" pm="."><plain>A study on 16 caterpillar species highlighted the existence of immune response mechanisms that allow the host to survive parasitoid infestations ( Smilanich et al. 2009 ). We currently cannot conclude which was the original host of the detected Wolbachia strain or whether the symbiont exerts specific effects on the three hosts. Wolbachia infection in a parasitoid was previously reported in the uzifly, Exorista sorbillans (Wiedemann) (Diptera: Tachinidae), which parasitizes the silkworm, Bombyx mori (L.) (Lepidoptera: Bombycidae). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56802" pm="."><plain>Administration of tetracycline to the adult uziflies removed Wolbachia endosymbionts and resulted in several reproductive disorders. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56803" pm="."><plain>However, tetracycline treatment did not show marked effects on the life expectancy of the uzifly ( Puttaraju and Prakash 2005 ). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56804" pm="."><plain>Developmental defects, which occur at low frequencies under natural conditions, can lead to morphologically anomalous individuals with both male and female traits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56805" pm="."><plain>Even though gynandromorphic individuals are described in many insect taxa ( Sassaman and Fugate 1997 , Narita et al. 2010 ), the specific mechanisms and driving forces causing this peculiar developmental abnormality are not known. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56807" pm="."><plain>In the examined populations of D. pini , the phenomenon of gynandromorphism occurred with a high frequency in the three populations (8% in Dpini1 and Dpini2 and 23% in Dpini1×2, respectively) with marked variability throughout different generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56808" pm="."><plain>Hence, random events, such as the occurrence of binucleate eggs, dispermy/polyspermy, reduction/duplication of the chromosome number, and loss of part of the genetic material, implicated in cases of gynandromorphism in natural and laboratory populations of other arthropods ( Kamping et al. 2007 , Narita et al. 2010 , Ford 2012 ), unlikely explain the recurrence of this condition in D. pini . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56811" pm="."><plain>Environmental temperature is considered another key factor involved in gynandromorphism occurrence in arthropods ( Narita et al. 2010 ). In fact, increase in temperature has been demonstrated as an important factor for the production of gynandromorphic individuals in Ooencyrtus submetallicus ( Wilson 1962 ). In the parasitic wasp Nasonia vitripennis , the proportion of gynandromorphic individuals can also be increased by exposing the mother or early-stage embryos to high temperature ( Kamping et al. 2007 ). In our work, the three different D. pini populations were kept for the whole duration of the main experiment at a constant temperature (20°C) inside the rearing cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56817" pm="."><plain>Under these persistent conditions, we could appreciate a high variability in the number of gynandromorphic individuals between the different generations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56818" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, our studies on the experimental increase in rearing temperature of D. pini were not sufficient to elucidate the role of this factor in D. pini because these experiments highly decreased the hatching success of the eggs and increased the larval mortality rate (25°C), and they also blocked the development of adults (30°C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56819" pm="."><plain>The association between the presence of Wolbachia and the occurrence of gynandromorphism and other developmental abnormalities has been proposed in diverse arthropod groups ( Pereira et al. 2003 ). Intriguingly, a partial Wolbachia reduction using antibiotics led to the appearance of Ostrinia scapulalis (Walker) intersexes having exclusively male genotype ( Kageyama and Traut 2004 ). In Zyginidia pullula (Hemiptera: Cicadellidae), the infection by Wolbachia induces feminization of genetic males. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56823" pm="."><plain>These feminized males are characterized by intersexual phenotypes, females presenting upper pygofer appendages, a typical male secondary sexual feature ( Negri et al. 2008 ). Another example can be found in the isopod Armadillidium vulgare , where a conflict between feminizing sex ratio distorters and autosomal masculinizing genes can be traced to the origin of intersexes ( Rigaud and Juchault 1993 ). In the case of D. pini , a possible link between the presence of Wolbachia and the occurrence of gynandromorphism remains an issue to be clarified with specific experiments, such as the use of antibiotics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56827" pm="."><plain>Besides, the possible discovery of Wolbachia -free populations of D. pini could also shed light on the mechanisms leading to gynandromorphism in this species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56828" pm="."><plain>The findings presented here spring a number of intriguing questions to be answered before a full picture of the many genetically ecological and evolutionary aspects of gynandromorphism in D. pini will be clarified. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="56829" pm="."><plain>The transinfection of different host species with Wolbachia also suggests a promising biocontrol approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56830" pm="."><plain>Fruit fly Wolbachia strains were demonstrated to be able to invade and prosper in mosquito populations, also reducing adult host lifespan, affecting host reproduction, and interfering with pathogen replication ( Iturbe-Ormaetxe et al. 2011 ). Our work on the presence of Wolbachia endosymbionts in the three hymenopteran species represents an initial step for potential biocontrol applications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References Cited</title><ref id="ieu009-B1"><text><SENT sid="56833" pm="."><plain> AugustaitisA . 2007 .  Pine sawfly ( Diprion pini L.) – related changes in Scots pine crown defoliation and possibilities of recovery  . Pol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56834" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56835" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56836" pm="."><plain>Study16 : 363 – 369 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B2"><text><SENT sid="56837" pm="."><plain> AyresM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56838" pm="."><plain>P.LombarderoM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56839" pm="."><plain>J. . 2000 . Assessing the consequences of global change for forest disturbance from herbivores and pathogens . Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56840" pm="."><plain>Total Environ.262 : 263 – 286 . 11087032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B3"><text><SENT sid="56841" pm="."><plain> BandiC.DunnA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56842" pm="."><plain>M.HurstG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56843" pm="."><plain>D.RigaudT. . 2001 . Inherited microorganisms, sex-specific virulence and reproductive parasitism . Trends Parasitol.2 : 88 – 94 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B4"><text><SENT sid="56844" pm="."><plain> BeaudoinL.GeriC.AllaisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56845" pm="."><plain>P.GoussardF. . 1994 .  Influence of consanguinity on the sex-ratio and diapause of Diprion pini L. (Hym., Diprionidae) populations  . J. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56848" pm="."><plain>Entomol.118 : 267 – 280 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B5"><text><SENT sid="56849" pm="."><plain> BextineB.LauzonC.PotterS.LampeD.MillerT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56850" pm="."><plain>A. . 2004 .  Delivery of a genetically marked Alcaligenes sp. to the glassy-winged sharpshooter for use in a paratransgenic control strategy  . Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56851" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.48 : 327 – 331 . 15060727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B6"><text><SENT sid="56852" pm="."><plain> BomboschS.RamakersP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56853" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56854" pm="."><plain>J. . 1976 .  Zur Dauerzucht von Gilpinia hercyniae . Pflanzenkrankheiten und Pflanzenschutz83 : 40 – 44 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B7"><text><SENT sid="56855" pm="."><plain> CasiraghiM.FaviaG.CancriniG.BartoloniA.BandiC. . 2001 .  Molecular identification of Wolbachia from the filarial nematode Mansonella ozzardi. Parasitol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56856" pm="."><plain>Res.87 : 417 – 420 . 11403387 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B8"><text><SENT sid="56857" pm="."><plain> CasiraghiM.BordensteinS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56858" pm="."><plain>R.BaldoL.LoN.BeninatiT.WernegreenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56859" pm="."><plain>J.WerrenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56860" pm="."><plain>H.BandiC. . 2005 .  Phylogeny of Wolbachia pipientis based on glt A, gro EL and fts Z gene sequences: clustering of arthropod and nematode symbionts in the F supergroup, and evidence for further diversity in the Wolbachia tree  . Microbiology151 : 4015 – 4022 . 16339946 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B9"><text><SENT sid="56861" pm="."><plain> CastresanaJ . 2000 . Selection of conserved blocks from multiple alignments for their use in phylogenetic analysis . Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56862" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56863" pm="."><plain>Evol.17 :  540 – 552 . 10742046 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B10"><text><SENT sid="56864" pm="."><plain> CoppelH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56865" pm="."><plain>C.BenjaminD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56866" pm="."><plain>M. . 1965 . Bionomics of the nearctic pine-feeding diprionids . Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56867" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56868" pm="."><plain>Entomol.10 : 69 – 96 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B11"><text><SENT sid="56869" pm="."><plain> CordauxR.Michel-SalzatA.BouchonD. . 2001 . Wolbachia infection in crustaceans: novel hosts and potential routes for horizontal transmission  . J. Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56871" pm="."><plain>Biol.14 :  237 – 243 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B12"><text><SENT sid="56872" pm="."><plain> CordauxR.PichonS.HatiraH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56873" pm="."><plain>B.DoubletV.GrèveP.MarcadéI.Braquart-VarnierC.Souty-GrossetC.Charfi-CheikhrouhaF.BouchonD. . 2012 .  Widespread Wolbachia infection in terrestrial isopods and other crustaceans  . Zookeys176 : 123 – 131 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B13"><text><SENT sid="56874" pm="."><plain> DobsonS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56875" pm="."><plain>L.BourtzisK.BraigH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56876" pm="."><plain>R.JonesB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56877" pm="."><plain>F.ZhouW.RoussetF.O'NeillS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56878" pm="."><plain>L. . 1999 . Wolbachia infections are distributed throughout insect somatic and germ line tissues  . Insect Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56879" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56880" pm="."><plain>Biol.29 : 153 – 160 . 10196738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B14"><text><SENT sid="56881" pm="."><plain> EdgarR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56882" pm="."><plain>C . 2004 . MUSCLE: multiple sequence alignment with high accuracy and high throughput . Nucleic Acids Res.32 : 1792 – 1797 . 15034147 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B15"><text><SENT sid="56883" pm="."><plain> EichhornO . 1976 .  Dauerzucht von D. pini (L.) (Hym. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56884" pm="."><plain>Diprionidae) im Laboratorium unter Berücksichtigung der Fotoperiode  . Anz. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56885" pm="."><plain>Schaedlingskd. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56886" pm="."><plain>Pfl.49 : 38 – 41 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B16"><text><SENT sid="56887" pm="."><plain> FordA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56888" pm="."><plain>T . 2012 . Intersexuality in Crustacea: an environmental issue?Aquat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56889" pm="."><plain>Toxicol.108 : 125 – 129 . 22265612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B17"><text><SENT sid="56890" pm="."><plain> HeimpelG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56891" pm="."><plain>E.de BoerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56892" pm="."><plain>G. . 2008 . Sex determination in the hymenoptera . Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56893" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56894" pm="."><plain>Entomol.53 : 209 – 230 . 17803453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B18"><text><SENT sid="56895" pm="."><plain> GuindonS.DufayardJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56896" pm="."><plain>F.LefortV.AnisimovaM.HordijkW.GascuelO. . 2010 . New algorithms and methods to estimate maximum-likelihood phylogenies: assessing the performance of phyML 3.0 . Syst. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56897" pm="."><plain>Biol.59 : 307 – 321 . 20525638 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B19"><text><SENT sid="56898" pm="."><plain> HuigensM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56899" pm="."><plain>E.de AlmeidaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56900" pm="."><plain>P.BoonsP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56901" pm="."><plain>A.LuckR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56902" pm="."><plain>F.StouthamerR. . 2004 .  Natural interspecific and intraspecific horizontal transfer of parthenogenesis-inducing Wolbachia in Trichogramma wasps  . Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56903" pm="."><plain>Roy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56904" pm="."><plain>Sci.271 : 509 – 515 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B20"><text><SENT sid="56905" pm="."><plain> HulcrJ.DunnR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56906" pm="."><plain>R. . 2011 . The sudden emergence of pathogenicity in insect-fungus symbioses threatens naive forest ecosystems . Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56907" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56908" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56909" pm="."><plain>B278 : 2866 – 2873 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B21"><text><SENT sid="56910" pm="."><plain> Iturbe-OrmaetxeI.WalkerT.O' NeillS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56911" pm="."><plain>L. . 2011 . Wolbachia and the biological control of mosquito-borne disease  . EMBO Rep.12 : 508 – 518 . 21546911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B22"><text><SENT sid="56912" pm="."><plain> KageyamaD.TrautW. . 2004 .  Opposite sex-specific effects of Wolbachia and interference with the sex determination of its host Ostrinia scapulalis . Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56913" pm="."><plain>R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56914" pm="."><plain>Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56915" pm="."><plain>B271 : 251 – 258 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B23"><text><SENT sid="56916" pm="."><plain> KampingA.KatjuV.BeukeboomL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56917" pm="."><plain>W.WerrenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56918" pm="."><plain>H. . 2007 .  Inheritance of gynandromorphism in the parasitic wasp Nasonia vitripennis . Genetics175 : 1321 – 1333 . 17179086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B24"><text><SENT sid="56919" pm="."><plain> KöpkeD.BeyaertI.GershenzonJ.HilkerM.SchmidtA. . 2010 . Species-specific responses of pine sesquiterpene synthases to sawfly oviposition . Phytochemistry71 : 909 – 917 . 20394954 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B25"><text><SENT sid="56920" pm="."><plain> KurkelaT.AaltoT.VaramaM.JalkanenR. . 2005 .  Defoliation by the common pine sawfly ( Diprion pini ) and subsequent growth reduction in Scots pine: a retrospective approach  . Silva Fenn.39 : 467 – 480 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B26"><text><SENT sid="56921" pm="."><plain> MartinO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56922" pm="."><plain>Y.GoodacreS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56923" pm="."><plain>L. . 2009 .  Widespread infections with the bacterial endosymbiont Cardinium in arachnids  . J. Arachnol.37 : 106 – 108 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B27"><text><SENT sid="56925" pm="."><plain> MarzoratiM.AlmaA.SacchiL.PajoroM.PalermoS.BrusettiL.RaddadiN.BalloiA.TedeschiR.ClementiE. . 2006 .  A novel Bacteroidetes symbiont is localized in Scaphoideus titanus , the insect vector of Flavescence dorée in Vitis vinifera . Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56926" pm="."><plain>Environ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56927" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.72 : 1467 – 1475 . 16461701 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B28"><text><SENT sid="56928" pm="."><plain> NaritaS.PereiraR.KjellbergF.KageyamaD. . 2010 . Gynandromorphs and intersexes: potential to understand the mechanism of sex determination in arthropods . Terrest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56929" pm="."><plain>Arthropod Rev.3 : 63 – 96 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B29"><text><SENT sid="56930" pm="."><plain> NegriI.FranchiniA.MandrioliM.MazzoglioP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56931" pm="."><plain>J.AlmaA. . 2008 .  The gonads of Zyginidia pullula males feminized by Wolbachia pipientis . Bull. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56932" pm="."><plain>Insectol.61 : 213 – 214 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B30"><text><SENT sid="56933" pm="."><plain> NewmanK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56934" pm="."><plain>L.AlmeidaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56935" pm="."><plain>P.PurcellA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56936" pm="."><plain>H.LindowS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56937" pm="."><plain>E. . 2004 .  Cell-cell signaling controls Xylella fastidiosa interactions with both insects and plants  . Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56938" pm="."><plain>Natl Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56939" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56940" pm="."><plain>U S A.101 : 1737 – 1742 . 14755059 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B31"><text><SENT sid="56941" pm="."><plain> OlofssonE . 1987 .  Mortality factors in a population of Neodiprion sertifer (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae)  . Oikos48 : 297 – 303 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B32"><text><SENT sid="56942" pm="."><plain> PereiraR.A.S.PradoA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56943" pm="."><plain>P.KjellbergF. . 2003 . Gynandromorphism in pollinating fig wasps (Hymenoptera: Agaonidae) . Entomol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56944" pm="."><plain>News114 : 152 – 155 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B33"><text><SENT sid="56945" pm="."><plain> PornbacherD. 1992 .  Studio biologico e demoecologico su infestazioni di Diprion pini (Linnaeus) (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae) in Val Venosta, tesi di laurea  . Facoltà di Agraria Università degli Studi di Padova , Padova .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B34"><text><SENT sid="56946" pm="."><plain> PuttarajuH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56947" pm="."><plain>P.PrakashB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56948" pm="."><plain>M. . 2005 .  Effects of Wolbachia in the uzifly, Exorista sorbillans , a parasitoid of the silkworm, Bombyx mori . J. Insect Sci5 : 30 . 17119612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B35"><text><SENT sid="56950" pm="."><plain> RaychoudhuryR.BaldoL.OliveiraD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56951" pm="."><plain>C.WerrenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56952" pm="."><plain>H. . 2009 .  Modes of acquisition of Wolbachia : horizontal transfer, hybrid introgression, and co-divergence in the Nasonia species complex  . Evolution63 : 165 – 183 . 18826448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B36"><text><SENT sid="56953" pm="."><plain> RigaudT.JuchaultP. . 1993 .  Conflict between feminizing sex ratio distorters and an autosomal masculinizing gene in the terrestrial isopod Armadillidium vulgare Latr  . Genetics133 : 247 – 252 . 8436273 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B37"><text><SENT sid="56954" pm="."><plain> RousseletJ.GériC.HewittsG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56955" pm="."><plain>M.LemeunierF. . 1998 .  The chromosomes of Diprion pini and D. similis (Hymenoptera: Diprionidae): implications for karyotype evolution  . Heredity81 : 573 – 578 . 9881453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B38"><text><SENT sid="56956" pm="."><plain> SakamotoH.KageyamaD.HoshizakiS.IshikawaY. . 2008 .  Heat treatment of the Adzuki bean borer, Ostrinia scapulalis infected with Wolbachia gives rise to sexually mosaic offspring  . J. Insect Sci.8 : 1 – 5 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B39"><text><SENT sid="56958" pm="."><plain> SassamanC.FugateM. . 1997 .  Gynandromorphism in Anostraca : multiple mechanisms of origin? Hydrobiologia359 : 163 – 169 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B40"><text><SENT sid="56959" pm="."><plain> SmilanichA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56960" pm="."><plain>M.DyerL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56961" pm="."><plain>A.GentryG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56962" pm="."><plain>L. . 2009 . The insect immune response and other putative defenses as effective predictors of parasitism . Ecology90 : 1434 – 1440 . 19569356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B41"><text><SENT sid="56963" pm="."><plain> StouthamerR. 1997 . Gynandromorphs, pp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56964" pm="."><plain>113-114 . InO'NeillS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56965" pm="."><plain>L.HoffmannA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56966" pm="."><plain>A.WerrenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56967" pm="."><plain>H. (eds.), Influential passengers—inherited microorganisms and arthropod reproduction . Oxford University Press , New York .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B42"><text><SENT sid="56968" pm="."><plain> TaylorM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56969" pm="."><plain>J.BandiC.HoeraufA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56970" pm="?"><plain>M.LazdinsJ. . 2000 . Wolbachia bacteria of filarial nematodes: a target for control? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56971" pm="."><plain>Parasitol .Today16 : 179 – 180 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B43"><text><SENT sid="56972" pm="."><plain> TurrisiG.BellaS. . 1999 . Prima segnalazione di Diprionidae per la fauna siciliana (Hymenoptera: Synphyta) . B. Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56974" pm="."><plain>Entomol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56975" pm="."><plain>Ital.131 : 179 – 182 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B44"><text><SENT sid="56976" pm="."><plain> van OpijnenT.BreeuwerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56977" pm="."><plain>A. . 1999 .  High temperatures eliminate Wolbachia , a cytoplasmic incompatibility inducing endosymbiont, from the two-spotted spider mite  . Exp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56978" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56979" pm="."><plain>Acarol.23 : 871 – 881 . 10668862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B45"><text><SENT sid="56980" pm="."><plain> ViljakainenL.ReuterM.PamiloP. . 2008 . Wolbachia transmission dynamics in Formica wood ants  . BMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56981" pm="."><plain>Biol.8 : 55 . 18291041 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B46"><text><SENT sid="56982" pm="."><plain> WeissB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56983" pm="."><plain>L.MaltzM.AksoyS. . 2012 . Obligate symbionts activate immune system development in the tsetse fly . J. Immunol.188 : 3395 – 3403 . 22368278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B47"><text><SENT sid="56985" pm="."><plain> WerrenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56986" pm="."><plain>R.BaldoL.ClarkM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56987" pm="."><plain>E. . 2008 . Wolbachia : master manipulators of invertebrate biology  . Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56988" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56989" pm="."><plain>Microbiol.6 : 741 – 751 . 18794912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B48"><text><SENT sid="56990" pm="."><plain> WilsonF . 1962 .  Sex determination and gynandromoph production in aberrant and normal strains of Ooencyrtus submetallicus (Hymenoptera: Encyridae)  . Aust. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56991" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56992" pm="."><plain>Zool.10 : 349 – 359 .  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ieu009-B49"><text><SENT sid="56993" pm="."><plain> WuK.HoyM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56994" pm="."><plain>A. . 2012 . Cardinium is associated with reproductive incompatibility in the predatory mite Metaseiulus occidentalis (Acari: Phytoseiidae)  . J. Invertebr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56996" pm="."><plain>Pathol.110 : 359 – 365 . 22504433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
