<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5986900</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01108</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="76508" pm="."><plain>Dermatophyte Resistance to Antifungal Drugs: Mechanisms and Prospectus </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Rossi</surname><given-names>Nilce M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/220635/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bitencourt</surname><given-names>Tamires A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/564648/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>Nalu T. A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/285290/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>Elza A. S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/289093/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>Eriston V.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/243119/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quaresemin</surname><given-names>Natalia R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/539805/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>Maíra P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/289534/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>Lucia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>Antonio</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/289402/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Genetics, Ribeirão Preto Medical School, University of São Paulo</institution>, <addr-line>Ribeirão Preto</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Morphology, Federal University of Sergipe</institution>, <addr-line>Aracaju</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="76509" pm="."><plain>Edited by: Edvaldo Antonio Ribeiro Rosa, Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Paraná, Brazil </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p><text><SENT sid="76510" pm="."><plain>Reviewed by: Lívia Kmetzsch, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil; Slawomir Milewski, Gdańsk University of Technology, Poland </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Nilce M. Martinez-Rossi, <email>nmmrossi@usp.br</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p><text><SENT sid="76511" pm="."><plain>This article was submitted to Antimicrobials, Resistance and Chemotherapy, a section of the journal Frontiers in Microbiology </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>29</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>1108</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2018 Martinez-Rossi, Bitencourt, Peres, Lang, Gomes, Quaresemin, Martins, Lopes and Rossi.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Martinez-Rossi, Bitencourt, Peres, Lang, Gomes, Quaresemin, Martins, Lopes and Rossi</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="76512" pm="."><plain>Dermatophytes comprise pathogenic fungi that have a high affinity for the keratinized structures present in nails, skin, and hair, causing superficial infections known as dermatophytosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76513" pm="."><plain>A reasonable number of antifungal drugs currently exist on the pharmaceutical market to control mycoses; however, their cellular targets are restricted, and fungi may exhibit tolerance or resistance to these agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76514" pm="."><plain>For example, the stress caused by antifungal and cytotoxic drugs in sub-inhibitory concentrations promotes compensatory stress responses, with the over-expression of genes involved in cellular detoxification, drug efflux, and signaling pathways being among the various mechanisms that may contribute to drug tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76515" pm="."><plain>In addition, the ATP-binding cassette transporters in dermatophytes that are responsible for cellular efflux can act synergistically, allowing one to compensate for the absence of the other, revealing the complexity of drug tolerance phenomena. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76516" pm="."><plain>Moreover, mutations in genes coding for target enzymes could lead to substitutions in amino acids involved in the binding of antifungal agents, hindering their performance and leading to treatment failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76517" pm="."><plain>The relevance of each one of these mechanisms of resistance to fungal survival is hard to define, mainly because they can act simultaneously in the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76518" pm="."><plain>However, an understanding of the molecular mechanisms involved in the resistance/tolerance processes, the identification of new antifungal targets, as well as the prospective of new antifungal compounds among natural or synthetic products, are expected to bring advances and new insights that facilitate the improvement or development of novel strategies for antifungal therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>dermatophyte</kwd><kwd>stress response</kwd><kwd>drug target</kwd><kwd>drug resistance</kwd><kwd>natural compounds</kwd><kwd>kinase</kwd><kwd>Hsp</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001">Fundação de Amparo à Pesquisa do Estado de São Paulo<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100001807</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn001">2014/03847-7</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">2015/23435-8</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">2016/04274-6</award-id><award-id rid="cn001">2011/08424-9</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002">Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Científico e Tecnológico<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100008353</named-content></funding-source><award-id rid="cn002">305797/2017-4</award-id><award-id rid="cn002">304989/2017-7</award-id></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003">Coordenação de Aperfeiçoamento de Pessoal de Nível Superior<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100002322</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn004">Fundação de Apoio ao Ensino, Pesquisa e Assistência do Hospital das Clínicas da Faculdade de Medicina de Ribeirão Preto da Universidade de São Paulo<named-content content-type="fundref-id">10.13039/501100008353</named-content></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="3"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="181"/><page-count count="18"/><word-count count="0"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76519" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76520" pm="."><plain>The growing prevalence of human fungal infections, especially in immunocompromised patients, has resulted in these diseases becoming a worldwide public health issue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76521" pm="."><plain>The immune status of the host determines the outcome of the disease, which may range from limited cutaneous or subcutaneous to invasive, disseminated, and life-threatening infections (Kohler et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76522" pm="."><plain>The most common fungal infections comprise the dermatomycoses, which constitute fungal infections in the skin that affect both immunocompetent and immunocompromised individuals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76523" pm="."><plain>Yeasts from the genera Candida and Malassezia, and molds such as the dermatophytes, serve as the most prevalent etiologic agents of these infections (Havlickova et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76524" pm="."><plain>Dermatophytes comprise a class of primary pathogenic fungi; i.e., not opportunistic, that requires the cleavage of keratin found in the skin, hair, and nails to acquire nutrients for their survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76525" pm="."><plain>The secretion of a broad spectrum of lytic enzymes, such as lipases and proteases, especially keratinases, by the fungal hyphae represents their most studied virulence factor, allowing fungal colonization and maintenance in the host tissue (Monod, 2008; Peres et al., 2010a). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76526" pm="."><plain>Dermatophytes can be classified as zoophilic or anthropophilic depending on their host prevalence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76527" pm="."><plain>Whereas zoophilic species are able to cause infections in both animals and humans, the anthropophilic dermatophytes are only able to infect humans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76528" pm="."><plain>This classification is important as the clinical manifestation is highly influenced by the fungal species along with the immune response they trigger during infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76529" pm="."><plain>In humans, zoophilic species are responsible for acute infections, mostly owing to the intense induction of the inflammatory response in the infected tissue. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76530" pm="."><plain>In comparison, anthropophilic species are associated with chronic infections, with a lower cellular infiltration in the skin (Hube et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76531" pm="."><plain>In the first stages of infection, dermatophytes colonize the skin and stimulate keratinocytes to produce different patterns of cytokines that mediate the inflammatory response and accumulation of leukocytes, mainly neutrophils, in the infected tissue (Peres et al., 2010b; Hube et al., 2015; Martinez-Rossi et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76532" pm="."><plain>Dermatophytes are initially recognized by receptors in the host innate immune cells, such as macrophages, neutrophils, and dendritic cells, which induce the activation of an adaptive response to control infection. In vitro and in vivo models of infection have shown that anthropophilic species (including Trichophyton tonsurans) induce keratinocytes to secrete a limited spectrum of cytokines, mainly IL-8, IL-6, and IL-1β. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76533" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, the zoophilic species Arthroderma benhamiae induces a broader spectrum of cytokines, such as IL-8, Il-6, IL-1β, IL-10, IL-2, IL-15, TGF-β, contributing to the higher amount of inflammatory cells in the infection site, which is responsible for fungal clearance, healing, and tissue remodeling (Hau et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76534" pm="."><plain>Induction of the adaptive immunity by innate cells triggers both Th1 and Th17 responses, which are important to control dermatophyte infection, by stimulating cellular-mediated immunity (Hau et al., 2015; Heinen et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76535" pm="."><plain>Th17 response increases the infiltration of neutrophils in the infection site, in turn promoting the activation of epithelial cells to produce chemotactic molecules and antimicrobial peptides (Heinen et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76536" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the production of antibodies and complement activation is also important to control dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76537" pm="."><plain>Serum analysis of patients with dermatophytosis shows high levels of Th2 cytokines, such as IL-4, IL-5, and IgE (Woodfolk and Platts-Mills, 2001; Hau et al., 2015; Gupta C. et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76538" pm="."><plain>The Th1, Th2, and Th17 immune responses observed in dermatophytosis is believed to reflect the different immunological status of the hosts (Hau et al., 2015) and may also be due to the infecting species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76539" pm="."><plain>Moreover, genetic factors play a further role in the susceptibility to invasive dermatophytosis (Garcia-Romero and Arenas, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76540" pm="."><plain>In particular, mutations in the card9 gene render a more invasive lesion in patients with dermatophytosis, together with a concomitant lower level of IL17 (Lanternier et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76541" pm="."><plain>Despite the availability of several antifungal drugs for clinical use, these act on a limited number of cellular targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76542" pm="."><plain>Commercially available drugs act on the plasma membrane, cell wall, nucleic acids, and the process of cell division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76543" pm="."><plain>In particular, three classes of antifungal drugs interfere with the plasma membrane. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76544" pm="."><plain>Azoles and triazoles inhibit the enzyme sterol 14 α-demethylase, and the allylamines inhibit squalene epoxidase, both leading to inhibition of ergosterol biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76545" pm="."><plain>Allylamines also lead to the accumulation of lanosterol, a toxic intermediary compound of the ergosterol biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76546" pm="."><plain>Polyenes bind to ergosterol, thus reducing plasma membrane integrity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76547" pm="."><plain>Echinocandins comprise a class of cell wall interfering agents that inhibit β-glucan synthase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76548" pm="."><plain>The pyrimidine analog 5-fluorocytosine inhibits DNA and RNA synthesis, leading to cell division and protein synthesis defects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76549" pm="."><plain>Griseofulvin (GRS) interferes with microtubule formation, impairing fungal growth and cell division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76550" pm="."><plain>Finally, ciclopirox oleamine functions as a protein synthesis inhibitor, which is often used against dermatophytes (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76551" pm="."><plain>The overlapping mechanisms of action of the commonly used drugs may contribute to the multidrug resistance (MDR) phenotypes observed for several pathogenic fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76552" pm="."><plain>Moreover, is common for patients to neglect and abandon treatment, owing to its requirement for long term use and the associated side effects (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008; Peres et al., 2010a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76553" pm="."><plain>In turn, clinical and/or microbiological resistance may result in treatment failure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76554" pm="."><plain>Specifically, clinical resistance is defined as the failure of infection clearance even with the administration of drugs that display in vitro activity, whereas microbial resistance relies on different molecular mechanisms used by the fungus to overcome the inhibitory effects of the antifungal drugs (Kanafani and Perfect, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76555" pm="."><plain>Several such mechanisms may be triggered by the fungus, which can act alone or in combination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76556" pm="."><plain>These mechanisms involve the overexpression of efflux pumps or detoxification enzymes, along with target and drug modification (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008; Cowen et al., 2015; Pianalto and Alspaugh, 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76557" pm="."><plain>In this review, we provide a special emphasis on the mechanisms of stress response and antifungal resistance in dermatophytes, and the prospective for the use of novel drugs to treat cutaneous fungal infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76558" pm="."><plain>Natural and Synthetic Compounds with Antifungal Activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76559" pm="."><plain>Fungal infections are increasing owing to various factors, whereas the current antifungal arsenal shows considerable drawbacks mainly related to their side effects and the emergence of drug resistance (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76560" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is imperative to develop new agents with effective and specific modes of action. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76561" pm="."><plain>Currently, synthetic drugs acting on novel cellular targets are under investigation, or in preclinical or clinical trials. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76562" pm="."><plain>These drugs include inhibitors of metabolic pathways, such as the glyoxylate cycle, pyrimidine biosynthesis, cytochrome P450 pathway, iron metabolism, acetate metabolism, and heme biosynthesis, along with signal transduction pathways, such as mitogen-activated protein (MAP) kinase and calcium signaling pathways, as well as transcription factor and DNA-binding and histone deacetylase inhibitors, with the latter representing epigenetic therapy (McCarthy et al., 2017) (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="76563" pm="."><plain>Novel antifungal drugs currently under evaluation, preclinical or clinical trial. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76564" pm="."><plain>Target </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76565" pm="."><plain>Drugs (phase of development) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76566" pm="."><plain>Proposed mechanism of action </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76567" pm="."><plain>Fungi tested </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76568" pm="."><plain>Reference </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76569" pm="."><plain>Cell membrane </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76570" pm="."><plain>BHBM D0 (preclinical) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76571" pm="."><plain>Interferes with fungal vesicles, and synthesis of sphingolipids </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76572" pm="."><plain>Cryptococcus spp. Candida spp. Aspergillus fumigatus Rhizopus oryzae Blastomyces dermatitidis Histoplasma capsulatum Coccidioides Paecilomyces variotii Pneumocystis jirovecii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76573" pm="."><plain>Mor et al., 2015 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76574" pm="."><plain>VT-1129 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76575" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of Cyp51 (lanosterol 14-α-demethylase) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76576" pm="."><plain>Cryptococcus Candida sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76577" pm="."><plain>Lockhart et al., 2016; Schell et al., 2017b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76578" pm="."><plain>VT-1598 (investigational) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76579" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of Cyp51 (lanosterol 14-α-demethylase) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76580" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Aspergillus sp. Cryptococcus sp. Rhizopus sp. Coccidioides sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76581" pm="."><plain>Wiederhold et al., 2018a,b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76582" pm="."><plain>VT-1161 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76583" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of Cyp51 (lanosterol 14-α-demethylase) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76584" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Trichophyton mentagrophytes Trichophyton rubrum Epidermophyton floccosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76585" pm="."><plain>Warrilow et al., 2014; Garvey et al., 2015; Schell et al., 2017b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76586" pm="."><plain>Nucleic acid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76587" pm="."><plain>F901318 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76588" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of dihydroorotate dehydrogenase (pyrimidine biosynthesis pathway) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76589" pm="."><plain>Aspergillus sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76590" pm="."><plain>Oliver et al., 2016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76591" pm="."><plain>MGCD290 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76592" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of the Hos2 histone deacetylase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76593" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Aspergillus sp. Cryptococcus sp. Rhodotorula sp. Fusarium sp. Trichosporon sp. Scedosporium sp. Zygomycetes sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76594" pm="."><plain>Pfaller et al., 2009 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76595" pm="."><plain>Mitochondria </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76596" pm="."><plain>T-23073 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76597" pm="."><plain>Disruption of the fungal mitochondrial membrane potential </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76598" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Cryptococcus sp. Aspergillus sp. Fusarium solani Malassezia furfur Mucor racemosus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76599" pm="."><plain>Mitsuyama et al., 2008; Nishikawa et al., 2017 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76600" pm="."><plain>Ilicicolin H (investigational) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76601" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of the cytochrome bc1 reductase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76602" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Aspergillus sp. C. neoformans </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76603" pm="."><plain>Singh et al., 2012 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76604" pm="."><plain>Heme biosynthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76605" pm="."><plain>Sampangine (investigational) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76606" pm="."><plain>Interferes with heme metabolism </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76607" pm="."><plain>C. neoformans C. albicans C. glabrata C. krusei A. fumigatus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76608" pm="."><plain>Agarwal et al., 2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76609" pm="."><plain>Hemofungin (investigational) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76610" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of ferrochelatase, an enzyme from the heme biosynthesis pathway </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76611" pm="."><plain>Aspergillus sp. Candida sp. Fusarium sp. Rhizopus sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76612" pm="."><plain>Ben Yaakov et al., 2016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76613" pm="."><plain>Metabolism </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76614" pm="."><plain>AR-12 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76615" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of acetyl coenzyme A (acetyl-CoA) synthetase (acetate metabolism) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76616" pm="."><plain>C. neoformans Candida sp. Fusarium sp. Mucor sp. Blastomyces sp. Histoplasma sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76617" pm="."><plain>Koselny et al., 2016; Kushwaha et al., 2017 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76618" pm="."><plain>Coccidioides sp. Trichophyton rubrum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76619" pm="."><plain>Mohangamides (investigational) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76620" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of the isocitrate lyase (glyoxylate pathway) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76621" pm="."><plain>Candida albicans </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76622" pm="."><plain>Bae et al., 2015; McCarthy et al., 2017 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76623" pm="."><plain>ASP2037 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76624" pm="."><plain>Unknown (iron metabolism) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76625" pm="."><plain>Aspergillus sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76626" pm="."><plain>Arendrup et al., 2016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76627" pm="."><plain>Cell wall </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76628" pm="."><plain>Biafungin (CD101) (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76629" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of glucan synthase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76630" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Aspergillus sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76631" pm="."><plain>Pfaller et al., 2016 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76632" pm="."><plain>Scy-078 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76633" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of glucan synthase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76634" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Aspergillus sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76635" pm="."><plain>Schell et al., 2017a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76636" pm="."><plain>Nikkomycin Z (completed clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76637" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of chitin synthase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76638" pm="."><plain>Blastomyces dermatitidis Coccidioides sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76639" pm="."><plain>Clemons and Stevens, 1997; Shubitz et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76640" pm="."><plain>GPI anchor biosynthesis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76641" pm="."><plain>E-1210/APX001 (clinical trial) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76642" pm="."><plain>Inhibition of inositol acyltransferase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76643" pm="."><plain>Candida sp. Aspergillus fumigatus Scedosporium prolificans Fusarium solani Paecilomyces lilacinus </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76644" pm="."><plain>Miyazaki et al., 2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>Drugs: <italic>N</italic>’-(3-bromo-4-hydroxybenzylidene)-2-methylbenzohydrazide, BHBM; 3-bromo-N0-(3-bromo-4-hydroxybenzylidene) benzohydrazide, D0; 4-{3-[1-(3-{4-[amino(imino)methyl]phenoxy}propyl)piperidin-4-yl]propoxy}benzamidine, T-2307. Clinical trials were accessed at the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://clinicaltrials.gov">https://clinicaltrials.gov</ext-link>.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="76645" pm="."><plain>The majority of these molecules had been evaluated for their efficacy against fungi responsible for systemic and life-threatening diseases, such as Candida sp., Cryptococcus sp., and Aspergillus fumigatus (Pianalto and Alspaugh, 2016; McCarthy et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76646" pm="."><plain>However, few studies have evaluated the effect of these drugs in dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76647" pm="."><plain>In particular, VT-1161 is currently under phase I clinical trial for onychomycosis NCT02267356 (Garvey et al., 2015; Schell et al., 2017a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76648" pm="."><plain>This drug inhibits the fungal cytochrome P-450 enzyme lanosterol 14-α-demethylase (Cyp51), being effective against several fungi including the dermatophytes Trichophyton rubrum, Trichophyton mentagrophytes, and Epidermophyton floccosum (Garvey et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76649" pm="."><plain>Moreover, VT-1161 has shown efficacy in a guinea pig infection model of dermatophytosis caused by T. mentagrophytes (Garvey et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76650" pm="."><plain>AR-12 constitutes an anti-tumor drug that inhibits acetyl coenzyme A (acetyl-CoA) synthetase, which is currently in clinical trial for lymphoma and solid tumors (NCT00978523). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76651" pm="."><plain>This drug also exhibits antifungal activity against several life-threatening fungi (Table 1) as well as the dermatophyte T. rubrum (Koselny et al., 2016; Kushwaha et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76652" pm="."><plain>In addition, AR-12 is able to reach the human nail plate and is thus considered a promising drug to treat onychomycosis (Kushwaha et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76653" pm="."><plain>Moreover, plant kingdom diversity is widely unexplored and can serve as a source for almost limitless compounds. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76654" pm="."><plain>In particular, many plant secondary metabolites have drawn attention as being endowed with antifungal properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76655" pm="."><plain>In addition, these natural sources lead to novel structural entities, which can be used directly or function as a precursor for the development of better and more effective molecules (Arif et al., 2009; Negri et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76656" pm="."><plain>The identification of promising molecules with antifungal properties can be streamlined through the screening of crude plant extract to aid the discovery process as the first step of investigation, followed by assays geared toward the identification of molecules responsible for the antifungal activity (Liu et al., 2009; Medeiros et al., 2011; Negri et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76657" pm="."><plain>Notably, this process has provided some evidence of the biological properties of plant extracts and their phytochemical compounds against dermatophytes (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="76658" pm="."><plain>Antifungal compounds derived from plants extracts showing activity against dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76659" pm="."><plain>Plant </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76660" pm="."><plain>Phytochemical </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76661" pm="."><plain>Dermatophyte </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76662" pm="."><plain>MIC values </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76663" pm="."><plain>Reference </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76664" pm="."><plain>Thymbra capitata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76665" pm="."><plain>EO, carvacrol (&gt;65%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76666" pm="."><plain>5 dermatophyte strains </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76667" pm="."><plain>0.08–0.32 μL/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76668" pm="."><plain>Salgueiro et al., 2004 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76669" pm="."><plain>Juniperus sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76670" pm="."><plain>EO, α-pinene (&gt;48%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76671" pm="."><plain>E. floccosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76672" pm="."><plain>0.08–2.5 μL/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76673" pm="."><plain>Cavaleiro et al., 2006 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76674" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76675" pm="."><plain>Microsporum sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76676" pm="."><plain>Lippia gracilis LGRA-106 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76677" pm="."><plain>EO, thymol (&gt;61%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76678" pm="."><plain>T. rubrum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76679" pm="."><plain>23.44–46.87 μL/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76680" pm="."><plain>de Melo et al., 2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76681" pm="."><plain>Lippia gracilis LGRA-109 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76682" pm="."><plain>EO, carvacrol (&gt;54%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76683" pm="."><plain>T. rubrum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76684" pm="."><plain>46.87–93.75 μL/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76685" pm="."><plain>de Melo et al., 2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76686" pm="."><plain>Thymus vulgaris </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76687" pm="."><plain>EO thymol (&gt;48%) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76688" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76689" pm="."><plain>NT∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76690" pm="."><plain>Sokovic et al., 2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76691" pm="."><plain>Vernonanthura tweedieana </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76692" pm="."><plain>sesquiterpene (6-cinnamoyloxy-1-hydroxyeudesm-4-en-3-one) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76693" pm="."><plain>T. mentagrophytesM. gypseum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76694" pm="."><plain>4–8 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76695" pm="."><plain>Portillo et al., 2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76696" pm="."><plain>Zuccagnia punctata </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76697" pm="."><plain>Chalcones </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76698" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76699" pm="."><plain>8–16 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76700" pm="."><plain>Svetaz et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76701" pm="."><plain>M. gypseum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76702" pm="."><plain>Glaucium oxylobum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76703" pm="."><plain>Alkaloids </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76704" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76705" pm="."><plain>300 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76706" pm="."><plain>Morteza-Semnani et al., 2003 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76707" pm="."><plain>Microsporum sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76708" pm="."><plain>E. floccosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76709" pm="."><plain>Tabernaemontana catharinensis </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76710" pm="."><plain>MMV alkaloid </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76711" pm="."><plain>T. rubrum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76712" pm="."><plain>0.16 mg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76713" pm="."><plain>Medeiros et al., 2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76714" pm="."><plain>Baccharis darwinii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76715" pm="."><plain>Diversinin (coumarin) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76716" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76717" pm="."><plain>15.6 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76718" pm="."><plain>Kurdelas et al., 2010 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76719" pm="."><plain>M. gypseum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76720" pm="."><plain>Baccharis darwinii </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76721" pm="."><plain>Anisocoumarin H </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76722" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76723" pm="."><plain>62.5 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76724" pm="."><plain>Kurdelas et al., 2010 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76725" pm="."><plain>M. gypseum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76726" pm="."><plain>Lavandula viridis L’He′r </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76727" pm="."><plain>Monoterpenes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76728" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76729" pm="."><plain>0.32–0.64 μL/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76730" pm="."><plain>Zuzarte et al., 2011 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76731" pm="."><plain>Microsporum sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76732" pm="."><plain>E. floccosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76733" pm="."><plain>Piper ecuadorense </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76734" pm="."><plain>Pinocembrin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76735" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76736" pm="."><plain>125 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76737" pm="."><plain>Ramirez et al., 2013 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76738" pm="."><plain>Dorstenia barteri </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76739" pm="."><plain>Isobavachalcone </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76740" pm="."><plain>T. rubrum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76741" pm="."><plain>1.2 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76742" pm="."><plain>Mbaveng et al., 2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76743" pm="."><plain>M. audorium </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76744" pm="."><plain>Dorstenia barteri </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76745" pm="."><plain>Amentoflavone </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76746" pm="."><plain>T. rubrum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76747" pm="."><plain>39.1 μg/mL </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76748" pm="."><plain>Mbaveng et al., 2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76749" pm="."><plain>Terminalia chebula </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76750" pm="."><plain>Apigenin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76751" pm="."><plain>T. mentagrophytes </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76752" pm="."><plain>NT∗ </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76753" pm="."><plain>Singh et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76754" pm="."><plain>Piper solmsianum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76755" pm="."><plain>Orientin </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76756" pm="."><plain>Microsporum sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76757" pm="."><plain>≤9 μg/mL) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76758" pm="."><plain>De Campos et al., 2005 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76759" pm="."><plain>Trichophyton sp. </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76760" pm="."><plain>E. floccosum </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic><sup>∗</sup>NT, MIC values non-tested, but antifungal activity evaluated through <italic>in vivo</italic> assays.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="76761" pm="."><plain>In particular, plant metabolites possess diverse anti-infective activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76762" pm="."><plain>Coumarins exhibit immunoregulatory effects toward macrophages, whereas quinones bind with adhesins and cell wall polypeptides, impairing their function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76763" pm="."><plain>Saponines are grouped into three main categories: triterpenoid, steroid, or steroidal glycoalkaloid, and act by disrupting sterol-containing membranes, leading to a breakdown and loss of cellular integrity (Keukens et al., 1995; Arif et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76764" pm="."><plain>Moreover, phenolic compounds exert activity on different biological pathways and cellular targets, as previously reported against Candida sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76765" pm="."><plain>For example, cinnamic acid has an immunoregulatory effect on the activation of monocytes (Conti et al., 2013), curcumin and isoquercitrin cause cellular membrane damage (Lee and Lee, 2014; Yun et al., 2015), licochalcone A leads to the impairment of hyphae development (Teodoro et al., 2015), and caffeic acid inhibits isocitrate lyase (Cheah et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76766" pm="."><plain>In addition, the blocking of drug transporters pumps by curcumin (Sharma et al., 2009), thymol, carvacrol, and baicalein has also been reported (Teodoro et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76767" pm="."><plain>The phytochemical effects on different cellular targets have also prompted investigation of the actions of these compounds toward dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76768" pm="."><plain>Studies have demonstrated fungitoxicity of the monoterpene linalool toward T. rubrum (de Oliveira Lima et al., 2017), as well as that of thymol and carvacrol; moreover, the essential oils from two Lippia gracilis genotypes (LGRA-106 and LGRA-109) presented antidermatophytic activity similar to that of FLC (de Melo et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76769" pm="."><plain>In addition, the MMV alkaloid (12-methoxy-4-methylvoachalotine) showed antifungal activity against T. rubrum (Medeiros et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76770" pm="."><plain>Finally, the chalcones, which comprise open-chain flavonoids, exhibit antifungal activity toward dermatophytes through the inhibition of cell wall biosynthesis (Boeck et al., 2005), and the blockage of FAS (Bitencourt et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76771" pm="."><plain>Other studies have also attempted to assess the detailed modes of action of biomolecules against T. rubrum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76772" pm="."><plain>For example, the glycoalkaloid α solanine showed antifungal activity toward T. rubrum, causing the down-regulation of the erg1, erg11, mep4, and mdr2 genes, which were evaluated in a co-culture of T. rubrum with a keratinocyte cell line (Komoto et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76773" pm="."><plain>Caffeic acid also demonstrated antifungal activity against T. rubrum, with its mode of action appearing to be related to a decrease in ergosterol content, impairing the cellular membrane, along with a moderate inhibition of isocitrate lyase activity (Cantelli et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76774" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the flavonoids quercetin and luteolin showed activity against T. rubrum as well. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76775" pm="."><plain>Quercetin was assayed more comprehensively; the data hinted that its mode of action was related to ergosterol reduction, membrane damage, and the inhibition of FAS activity (Bitencourt et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76776" pm="."><plain>In this context, a trans-chalcone compound also simultaneously inhibited the synthesis of fatty acid and ergosterol, and showed marked inhibitory activity against strains of T. rubrum (Bitencourt et al., 2013; Komoto et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76777" pm="."><plain>Moreover, licochalcone A presented marked antifungal activity toward T. rubrum, causing the down-regulation of genes encoding putative virulence factors such as isocitrate lyase, citrate synthase, and malate synthase as well as of genes involved in cell wall synthesis and ergosterol biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76778" pm="."><plain>In addition, this compound impaired hyphal development during the interaction of T. rubrum with a keratinocyte cell line, and markedly inhibited the isocitrate lyase activity (Cantelli et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76779" pm="."><plain>Finally, chalcone treatment led to a down-regulation of a gene coding for a drug efflux pump during the co-culture of T. rubrum conidia with a keratinocyte cell line (Komoto et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76780" pm="."><plain>Chalcones constitute widespread natural molecules that are a subject of increasing interest owing to their numerous pharmacological activities (Nowakowska, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76781" pm="."><plain>These compounds are considered interesting and promising molecules, and their simple chemical structures allow their synthesis in a secure, inexpensive, and straightforward manner (Narender and Reddy, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76782" pm="."><plain>They exhibit antifungal activity against both different and specific fungal targets, and also play a role as MDR modulators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76783" pm="."><plain>For example, the inhibition of an MDR efflux pump (P-glycoprotein – P-gp) by chalcones was previously assessed through testing distinct methoxy-chalcones B-ring derivatives in a human mdr1 gene transfected into a mouse lymphoma cell line, which showed a high binding affinity to P-gp, exceeding that of a known MDR blocking agent (Ivanova et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76784" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the use of chalcone analogs also promoted the sensitization of a fluconazole-resistant C. albicans strain mediated by the inhibition of efflux pumps (Lacka et al., 2015; Wang et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76785" pm="."><plain>Taking into account the features of natural compounds together with the increasing need for new drugs, which has been mainly forestalled owing to the challenges afforded by similarities shared between mammalian and fungal cells, these molecules, and their derivatives appear as promising alternative sources for the development of new antifungal agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76786" pm="."><plain>Additionally, their combinatory effects with synthetic and the commercial drugs may represent new strategies for antifungal therapies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76787" pm="."><plain>Mechanisms of Resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76788" pm="."><plain>Drug Exposure, Stress Responses, and Adaptation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76789" pm="."><plain>Fungi must sense and respond appropriately to environmental changes to survive cellular stresses, such as those caused by drug exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76790" pm="."><plain>They have evolved diverse mechanisms for adaptation with complex circuitries involving cellular responses, including the interplay among signaling molecules, stress responses, and drug resistance (Cowen, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76791" pm="."><plain>Following drug exposure, cell wall instability, changes in osmolarity, and production of reactive oxygen species are among the stimuli that can activate signaling pathways, such as the cell wall integrity pathway, calcineurin signaling, and high osmolarity glycerol (HOG) pathway to counteract the effects of drug-induced stress (Hayes et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76792" pm="."><plain>Critical signaling pathways involved in the tolerance to antifungal agents are modulated by stress responses governed by the molecular chaperone Hsp90, a global cellular regulator that controls the stability and activation of key regulators of stress responses, such as calcineurin and the MAP kinase in the Pkc1 cell wall integrity pathway, Mkc1 (Robbins et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76793" pm="."><plain>Among pathogenic fungi, most of the known molecular mechanisms underlying drug stress response, drug tolerance, or resistance were initially elucidated in Candida sp., Aspergillus sp., and Cryptococcus sp., and they are still poorly understood in dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76794" pm="."><plain>In particular, it is still challenging to utilize gene targeting to study gene function in most species of this group of fungi; thus, transcriptomics have been applied to better understand the molecular mechanisms involved in drug-stress responses and adaptation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76795" pm="."><plain>For example, T. interdigitale and T. rubrum respond to sub-lethal doses of several antifungal compounds by modulating the expression of genes related to various processes, such as protein transport, drug efflux, lipid metabolism, signal transduction, translation, post-translational modifications, and oxidative stress, depending on the drug and time of exposure (Paião et al., 2007; Yu et al., 2007a; Zhang et al., 2007, 2009; Peres et al., 2010b; Persinoti et al., 2014; Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76796" pm="."><plain>Specifically, a gene encoding a transposable element was shown to be up-regulated in T. interdigitale after exposure to several drugs (Paião et al., 2007; Peres et al., 2010b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76797" pm="."><plain>In turn, transposable elements can influence gene expression; in Schizosaccharomyces pombe, the preferential integration of the retrotransposon Tf1 into promoters of stress response genes has been reported, thereby enhancing their expression (Feng et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76798" pm="."><plain>However, the regulatory mechanisms involved in stress responses are complex. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76799" pm="."><plain>Recently, a refined use of pre-mRNA processing events has been reported in T. rubrum in response to undecanoic acid (UDA), regulating the expression of genes encoding phosphoglucomutase, which is involved in gluconeogenesis and in cell wall biosynthesis, along with inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase, a key enzyme supplying guanine nucleotides to cells (Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76800" pm="."><plain>These mechanisms, along with others, collectively help the cells to counteract the toxicity of drugs and cope with stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76801" pm="."><plain>It has been reported that the repeated exposure of T. rubrum to sub-lethal doses of antifungal drugs in vitro can lead to the selection of strains able to survive higher minimal inhibitory concentrations (MICs) following drug pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76802" pm="."><plain>However, in the absence of such pressure, a fraction of the strains regained susceptibility (Ghelardi et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76803" pm="."><plain>The strains that survive higher MICs can be classified either as tolerant, being able to survive transient exposure, or resistant, having acquired mutations that confer the stable ability to survive higher MICs (Delarze and Sanglard, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76804" pm="."><plain>In particular, in Candida sp. and Aspergillus sp., Hsp90 promotes drug tolerance by stabilizing key regulators of cellular stress responses (Robbins et al., 2017), thus controlling the downstream signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76805" pm="."><plain>Therefore, fungal survival in inhospitable environments, as in the presence of antifungal agents, relies on the stress responses and involves a global modulation of gene expression, resulting in the synthesis of specific proteins that are fundamental to counteract stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76806" pm="."><plain>The relevance of these genes in the survival of fungi suggests that they may be considered as potential therapeutic targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76807" pm="."><plain>Here, we focus mainly on the drug stress response related to drug efflux, drug detoxification, and the modulation of kinase and heat shock (hsp) genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76808" pm="."><plain>Drug Efflux </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76809" pm="."><plain>Efflux cell membrane transporters are proteins capable of binding to different compounds including antifungal drugs, and subsequently extruding them from the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76810" pm="."><plain>The expression of these molecular pumps represents one of the main reasons for treatment failure, acting as a protective mechanism against the cytotoxic effects of the drug by reducing the accumulation of harmful compounds (Putman et al., 2000; Cervelatti et al., 2006; El-Awady et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76811" pm="."><plain>The efflux cell activity leads to a gradual and non-specific increase in drug resistance by diminishing the expected effect in vivo. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76812" pm="."><plain>In turn, enhanced drug export represents a critical strategy among the mechanisms used by fungi to gain resistance toward antifungal therapy (Sharma and Prasad, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76813" pm="."><plain>The modification of efflux transporters in fungal resistance contributes to the pathogenicity, favoring the occurrence of cases of dermatophytosis by providing a colonization advantage to the fungus (Coleman and Mylonakis, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76814" pm="."><plain>In particular, MDR results to a large degree from the overexpression of genes belonging to the ATP-binding cassette superfamily (ABC), which is evolutionarily conserved in both prokaryotes and eukaryotes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76815" pm="."><plain>These proteins contain two distinct regions: a highly conserved nucleotide-binding domain and a quite variable transmembrane domain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76816" pm="."><plain>Through the binding and hydrolization of ATP, ABC transporters actively move a wide variety of structurally and chemically unrelated compounds across membranes, thereby reducing drug accumulation even in cancer cells (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008; Housman et al., 2014; Xiong et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76817" pm="."><plain>This superfamily encompasses three well-studied families involved in the efflux of toxic compounds: MDR, MDR-associated protein (MRP), and the pleiotropic drug resistance (PDR) families (Coleman and Mylonakis, 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76818" pm="."><plain>The availability of the genome sequence of different dermatophytes has revealed a homogeneous group of these transporters, which exhibits very low genetic diversity with only a few exclusive genes in each analyzed species (Burmester et al., 2011; Martinez et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76819" pm="."><plain>The analysis of seven of these dermatophyte genomes identified a large number of encoded ABC transporter domains with many of the associated genes having counterparts in all studied species, suggesting that ABC transporter genes act equivalently, despite the phenotypic and adaptive uniqueness of each species (Gadzalski et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76820" pm="."><plain>Evidence implicating drug efflux as a mechanism of resistance has been extensively evaluated in the T. interdigitale H6 strain (previously identified as T. rubrum). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76821" pm="."><plain>Initially, the occurrence of a drug efflux phenomenon was hypothesized consequent to an observed resistance to both GRS and tioconazole in vitro (Fachin et al., 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76822" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, mdr1 and mdr2 genes were identified, which presented an increased level of transcription after exposure to different classes of antifungal agents (Cervelatti et al., 2006; Fachin et al., 2006; Paião et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76823" pm="."><plain>The disruption of the mdr2 gene rendered a mutant more sensitive to terbinafine (TRB) but not to other tested drugs, precluding the suggestion of a modulatory role of the mdr2 gene in drug susceptibility (Fachin et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76824" pm="."><plain>Gene expression analysis later demonstrated that the mdr4 gene somehow depends on the MDR2 transporter when challenged with antifungal agents, suggesting the existence of network interaction with regard to MDR activity as well as the interdependence of different ABC transporters in drug efflux (Yibmantasiri et al., 2014; Martins et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76825" pm="."><plain>Different ABC transporters with overlapping substrate profiles may present broad ranges of substrate affinity and capacity of transport, and may respond differently to cellular drug-concentrations, thereby determining the actual fate of the substrates (Glavinas et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76826" pm="."><plain>For example, the transcriptional profiling of the pdr1, mdr2, and mdr4 genes of four species of Trichophyton: T. equinum, T. interdigitale, T. rubrum, and T. tonsurans, did not reflect the intrinsic phylogenetic relationship among these fungi, nor was a functional correlation revealed between species and the efflux modulation under the tested conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76827" pm="."><plain>However, the evaluated genes appear to work synergistically, leading to the understanding that one mdr gene may be compensated by others as related to extrusion activity (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008; Gadzalski et al., 2016; Martins et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76828" pm="."><plain>Owing to the relevant contribution of drug efflux resistance mechanisms to the pathogenesis of dermatophytes, the use of inhibitors or modulators of ABC transporters to block and reverse MDR response represents a potential alternative method to thwart multidrug transporter activity, thus preventing the occurrence of drug efflux (Glavinas et al., 2004; Sharma and Prasad, 2011; Holmes et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76829" pm="."><plain>An assortment of such compounds present MDR modulatory properties by synergistically enhancing fungicidal activity, although these still require a definitive demonstration of clinical efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76830" pm="."><plain>The identified inhibitors include isonitrile, enniatins, milbemycins, ibuprofen, and the calcineurin inhibitor FK506. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76831" pm="."><plain>These compounds present effective efflux blocking activity in a terbinafine-resistant strain of the dermatophyte Microsporum canis as well as in multiple types of eukaryotic cells including malignant cells (Kawahara et al., 2015; Holmes et al., 2016; Kano et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76832" pm="."><plain>However, it is relevant to consider that cells can heterogeneously express ABC transporters, varying the responses between fungal species, patients, as well as within tumors, potentially impairing their activity (Holmes et al., 2016; Martins et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76833" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the many similarities between fungal and human cells represent a challenge for host treatments in regard to the currently limited antifungal choices (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76834" pm="."><plain>As multidrug transporter genes are also relatively conserved from microorganisms to humans, an ideal MDR- interfering drug must therefore be capable of chemosensitizing cells to existing effective antifungal agents while also shielding human orthologs (Glavinas et al., 2004; Holmes et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76835" pm="."><plain>This approach represents a hopeful option for effective chemotherapy and a pivotal strategy to overwhelm clinical MDR outcomes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76836" pm="."><plain>Drug Detoxification </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76837" pm="."><plain>A substantial group of genes involved in cellular detoxification is activated when fungi are challenged with cytotoxic drugs at sub-inhibitory concentrations, which contributes to increasing the tolerance to these drugs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76838" pm="."><plain>RNA-sequencing (RNA-Seq) analysis of the effect of acriflavine (ACR) on T. rubrum showed that genes involved in cellular detoxification were highly up-regulated, including those encoding catalases that protect the cell against oxidative stress and reactive oxygen species (Persinoti et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76839" pm="."><plain>The increased expression of catalase genes may constitute a compensatory mechanism to maintain the intracellular level of this enzyme, thus protecting the cells from apoptotic effects elicited by the drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76840" pm="."><plain>Conversely, catalase activity is inhibited by acriflavine in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76841" pm="."><plain>Moreover, RNA-Seq analysis of the differential gene expression of T. rubrum challenged with UDA also revealed the up-regulation of several genes coding for antioxidant enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76842" pm="."><plain>In addition to catalases, superoxide dismutase, peroxidases, glutathione transferases, and glutathione peroxidases were identified as being stimulated in response to UDA, leading to enzymatic oxidative detoxification of the fungal cells (Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76843" pm="."><plain>Consistent with these findings, a previous report also suggested that Candida resistance to amphotericin B (AMB) might be mediated by increased catalase activity as well (Peman et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76844" pm="."><plain>The ability of a fungus to secrete enzymes is related to its pathogenicity and stress response as well as its mechanisms of detoxification. T. rubrum secretes esterases and other enzymes depending on the nutrients supplied (Brasch et al., 1991). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76845" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the electrophoretic pattern of esterases secreted from T. rubrum revealed new isoforms when this dermatophyte was grown in sub-inhibitory concentrations of GRS and tioconazole (Fachin et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76846" pm="."><plain>These additional forms of esterase may participate in the cellular detoxification directly or may comprise a non-specific cellular response to stress leading to drug tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76847" pm="."><plain>The participation of esterase in detoxification leading to drug resistance has already been described in other organisms (Harms et al., 1996; Rooker et al., 1996). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76848" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of target enzymes is also found in several azole-resistant strains, which is a compensatory mechanism for ergosterol depletion. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76849" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of erg11 occurs in C. albicans through duplication of the left arm of chromosome 5, which harbors the erg11 gene (Cowen et al., 2015; Sanglard, 2016). Cryptococcus neoformans adapts to high concentrations of FLC by the formation of chromosome 1 disomies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76850" pm="."><plain>This resistance is a consequence of the duplication of two genes that are located on this chromosome: ERG11, the target of FLC and AFR1, a transporter of azoles in C. neoformans (Sionov et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76851" pm="."><plain>Also, extra copies of the A. fumigatus squalene epoxidase gene confer resistance to terbinafine (Liu et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76852" pm="."><plain>However, extra copies of the salicylate 1-monooxygenase (salA) gene were suggested to be the cause of terbinafine resistance in Aspergillus nidulans, although this enzyme does not represent the target of this drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76853" pm="."><plain>Instead, the authors hypothesized that the cleavage of the naphthalene nucleus present in the molecular structure of terbinafine is responsible for its degradation and consequently the resistance phenotype (Graminha et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76854" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, a strain of T. rubrum was rendered resistant to terbinafine by transformation with multiple copies of the salA gene (Santos et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76855" pm="."><plain>This strain exhibited elevated expression of the salA gene and simultaneously increased resistance to terbinafine, compared to the original strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76856" pm="."><plain>Thus, these results showed that this gene plays a role in the resistance and response to terbinafine in dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76857" pm="."><plain>However, the resistant phenotype was reversed after the strain was cultured in the absence of terbinafine for several generations, thereby losing plasmids containing the salA gene, which confirmed that extra copies of this gene provoked resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76858" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the original strain without any plasmid responded to the challenge with terbinafine by increasing the expression of the endogenous salA gene (Santos et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76859" pm="."><plain>Unlike bacteria, which exhibit several examples of antibiotic resistance through the degradation of these compounds, the resistance of fungi to antifungal agents by inactivation or degradation is a not well known (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76860" pm="."><plain>Taking into account that fungi secrete a large number of enzymes (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2017), it is probable that similar mechanisms resulting in resistance or tolerance to antifungal may be frequent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76861" pm="."><plain>The disclosure of fungal enzymes having this role may thus be useful for the development of enzyme inhibitors, which could be applied alone or in association with conventional therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="76862" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional Modulation of Kinase Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="76863" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide expression profiling has provided new targets for the development of novel drugs by the pharmaceutical industries and increased the general understanding regarding the mechanisms of action of different drugs and their therapeutic effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76864" pm="."><plain>Several studies have revealed the existence of various regulatory and metabolic circuits necessary to develop resistance to antifungal agents (Sanglard et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76865" pm="."><plain>Considering the nature of the pathogen stress-response systems and that some cellular proteins related to these mechanisms are phosphorylated, protein kinases may represent a potential target for antifungal drug therapy (Garaizar et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76866" pm="."><plain>In particular, protein phosphorylation is known to trigger several signaling transduction pathways involved in cell stimuli propagation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76867" pm="."><plain>Thus, several groups have been exploring different genetic approaches to investigate the expression of kinases responsive to different drugs, with the purpose of obtaining a better understanding of dermatophyte resistance to antifungal agents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76868" pm="."><plain>For example, a microarray hybridization approach was applied in the analysis of gene expression responses of dermatophytes exposed to several antifungal agents. T. rubrum was exposed to sub-inhibitory concentrations of the antifungal agents ketoconazole and AMB (Yu et al., 2007b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76869" pm="."><plain>The authors reported the down-regulation of four kinase genes in response to AMB, highlighting two genes coding for MAP kinases (MpkA and STE7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76870" pm="."><plain>Notably, these proteins belong to different stress-responsive pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76871" pm="."><plain>The authors also reported a down-regulated kinase gene in response to AMB, coding for a serine/threonine protein kinase (sps1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76872" pm="."><plain>This protein is important for transcriptional, biochemical, and morphological events during the later events of fungal sporulation (Friesen et al., 1994; Widmann et al., 1999; Yu et al., 2007b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76873" pm="."><plain>Conversely, T. rubrum cultivated in the presence of terbinafine showed an up-regulation of the kinase gene sps1 (Zhang et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76874" pm="."><plain>These authors have also reported a significant down-regulation of two-phosphorylated-intermediary-components involved in regulating a MAP kinase cascade, as well as a predicted unusual protein kinase (Yu et al., 2007b; Zhang et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76875" pm="."><plain>In addition, the same group analyzed the transcription of T. rubrum genes in response to PHS11A and PH11B, inhibitors of synthesized fatty acid synthase (FAS), which was chosen as an interesting antifungal target owing to architectural differences between the mammalian and fungal protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76876" pm="."><plain>Four kinase genes were negatively modulated in response to PHS11A: pkaC, ssp1, and sln1, which are related to signal transduction pathways, and a putative dihydroxyacetone kinase (DAK2), related to carbohydrate transport and metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76877" pm="."><plain>Only one kinase gene (bck1) showed up-regulation in the presence of PHS11A. Bck1 was also responsive to TRB (Zhang et al., 2007, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76878" pm="."><plain>In turn, PH11B up-regulated two kinase genes, the pyrophosphate-dependent phosphofructo-1-kinase gene (pfk1) and a hexokinase gene (glk1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76879" pm="."><plain>Both genes are related to carbohydrate transport and metabolism (Yu et al., 2007a). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76880" pm="."><plain>Up-regulation of the MAP kinase gene (mpka) in the presence of itraconazole has also been reported (Diao et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76881" pm="."><plain>This gene was also down-regulated in response to AMB, being related to cell wall integrity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76882" pm="."><plain>Thus, the authors argued that the stress caused by this antifungal agent in the ergosterol pathway, and consequently in the plasma membrane, can be compensated by the activation of the cell wall integrity pathway, altering the structure and composition of the fungal cell wall (Jung and Levin, 1999; Yu et al., 2007b; Diao et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76883" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a suppressive subtractive hybridization approach was used to identify genes differentially expressed after the exposure of T. rubrum to the cytotoxic drugs ACR, fluconazole (FLC), GRS, TRB, and UDA (Paião et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76884" pm="."><plain>The authors described the up-regulation of the never in mitosis A (nima) gene in response to FLC, GRS, and TRB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76885" pm="."><plain>This gene was also up-regulated in T. rubrum under acidic pH and growth in keratin as the only carbon source (Paião et al., 2007; Peres et al., 2010b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76886" pm="."><plain>The NIMA kinase family, initially isolated from A. nidulans, is required for the G2/M transition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76887" pm="."><plain>Mammalian NIMA-related kinase 11, long and short isoform (nek11L and nek11S) genes are related to DNA replication/damage stress response, being also expressed in response to unspecific cellular stresses (Osmani et al., 1988; Noguchi et al., 2002; Paião et al., 2007; Peres et al., 2010b). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76888" pm="."><plain>Differential display RT-PCR and northern blot techniques have been used to analyze T. rubrum molecular responses to acriflavine as well, showing increased transcription levels of a gene coding for a putative riboflavin kinase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76889" pm="."><plain>This enzyme is essential in the flavin biosynthetic pathway, catalyzing the first step of this process yielding flavin mononucleotide (FMN) and flavin adenine dinucleotide (FAD). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76890" pm="."><plain>This pathway is crucial for several biological processes including lipid, protein, and carbohydrate metabolism (Santos et al., 2000; Segato et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76891" pm="."><plain>In turn, a high-throughput RNA-Seq approach was applied to evaluate the time-dependent effects of acriflavine on the T. rubrum transcriptome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76892" pm="."><plain>In 3 h of drug exposure, four kinase genes responded to acriflavine, two being up- (adenosine 5′-phosphosulfate kinase and homoserine kinase) and two down-regulated (protein kinase subdomain-containing protein, and pyridoxine kinase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76893" pm="."><plain>In 12 h of exposure, only one kinase gene was up-regulated (cmgc/srpk protein kinase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76894" pm="."><plain>In 24 h of exposure, four kinase genes were up-regulated, highlighting the genes coding for a calcium-calmodulin-dependent pathway, indicating that acriflavine probably affects this signaling route in T. rubrum, which is reported to be involved in cell survival under stressful conditions (Persinoti et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76895" pm="."><plain>Moreover, in 24 h of exposure, five kinase genes were down-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76896" pm="."><plain>Notably, acriflavine repressed an unusual kinase gene (coding for an atypical/ABC1/ABC1-B protein kinase) that does not display most of the typical eukaryotic protein kinase features, being reported as a chloroplast or mitochondria-related protein that regulates quinone synthesis (Huang et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76897" pm="."><plain>In addition, a gene coding for a kinase subdomain-containing protein was strongly up-regulated upon acriflavine exposure (Persinoti et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="76898" pm="."><plain>Recently, RNA-Seq analysis also revealed interesting data related to the response of T. rubrum to sub-lethal doses of UDA (Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76899" pm="."><plain>In this study, three kinase genes were up-regulated including the uridine/cytidine kinase (uck), ste/ste7 (ste7) protein kinase, and dephospho-CoA kinase (dpck). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76900" pm="."><plain>UCK is involved in the conversion of both cytidine and uridine to nucleoside monophosphate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76901" pm="."><plain>STE7 is associated with the MAPK pathway, and DPCK is involved with the final steps of the pathway for CoA biosynthesis (Wadler and Cronan, 2007; Tomoike et al., 2017; Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76902" pm="."><plain>One gene was down-regulated (nucleoside diphosphate kinase) in the early response to UDA (3 h). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76903" pm="."><plain>At 12 h of exposure to UDA, two distinct serine/threonine protein kinase coding genes were down-regulated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76904" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the authors reported two kinase genes responding to UDA in both 3 and 12 h of drug exposure; one was another distinct serine/threonine protein kinase coding gene, showing a strong down-regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76905" pm="."><plain>The other was AGC/RSK protein kinase, which was also down-regulated in response to acriflavine (Persinoti et al., 2014; Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76906" pm="."><plain>AGC protein kinase (a subgroup of the Ser/Thr protein kinases) was named based on sequence alignments of the catalytic domain with the cAMP-dependent protein kinase 1 (PKA), cGMP-dependent protein kinase (PKG), and protein kinase C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76907" pm="."><plain>Notably, ribosomal S6 kinase (RSK), a member of the AGC family, contains two kinase catalytic domains in the same polypeptide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76908" pm="."><plain>Thus, in addition to the AGC kinase domain at the N-terminal portion, the C-terminus displays a calcium/calmodulin dependent kinase domain that is activated by the extracellular signal-regulated kinase (eRK) pathway and plays an important role in protein synthesis (Pearce et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76909" pm="."><plain>All of these kinase genes/proteins described above are listed in Table 3. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="76910" pm="."><plain>Relation of T. rubrum kinase genes modulated by antifungal agents. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" cellspacing="5" cellpadding="5"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76911" pm="."><plain>Gene product name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76912" pm="."><plain>ID </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76913" pm="."><plain>Antifungals </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76914" pm="."><plain>Modulation </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76915" pm="."><plain>Reference </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76916" pm="."><plain>Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MpkA) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76917" pm="."><plain>TERG_00832 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76918" pm="."><plain>AMB, ITRA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76919" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated, Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76920" pm="."><plain>Yu et al., 2007b, Diao et al., 2009 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76921" pm="."><plain>Mitogen-activated protein kinase (STE7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76922" pm="."><plain>TERG_02515 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76923" pm="."><plain>AMB </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76924" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76925" pm="."><plain>Yu et al., 2007b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76926" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase (SPS1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76927" pm="."><plain>TERG_00281 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76928" pm="."><plain>AMB </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76929" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76930" pm="."><plain>Yu et al., 2007b </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76931" pm="."><plain>cAMP-dependent protein kinase catalytic subunit (PKaC) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76932" pm="."><plain>TERG_03685 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76933" pm="."><plain>PHS11A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76934" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76935" pm="."><plain>Zhang et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76936" pm="."><plain>Suppressor of sensor kinase (SLN1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76937" pm="."><plain>TERG_06080 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76938" pm="."><plain>PHS11A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76939" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76940" pm="."><plain>Zhang et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76941" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase (SSP1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76942" pm="."><plain>TERG_05979 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76943" pm="."><plain>PHS11A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76944" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76945" pm="."><plain>Zhang et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76946" pm="."><plain>Dihydroxyacetone kinase (DAK2) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76947" pm="."><plain>TERG_08455 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76948" pm="."><plain>PHS11A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76949" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76950" pm="."><plain>Zhang et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76951" pm="."><plain>Mitogen-activated protein kinase (BCK1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76952" pm="."><plain>TERG_00207 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76953" pm="."><plain>PHS11A </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76954" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76955" pm="."><plain>Zhang et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76956" pm="."><plain>Pyrophosphate-dependent phosphofructo-1-kinase (PFK1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76957" pm="."><plain>TERG_05437 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76958" pm="."><plain>PH11B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76959" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76960" pm="."><plain>Yu et al., 2007a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76961" pm="."><plain>Hexokinase (GLK1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76962" pm="."><plain>TERG_08933 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76963" pm="."><plain>PH11B </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76964" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76965" pm="."><plain>Yu et al., 2007a </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76966" pm="."><plain>Never in mitosis A kinase (NIMA) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76967" pm="."><plain>TERG_06149 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76968" pm="."><plain>FLC, GRS or TRB </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76969" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76970" pm="."><plain>Paião et al., 2007 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76971" pm="."><plain>Riboflavin kinase (FMN1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76972" pm="."><plain>TERG_03281 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76973" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76974" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76975" pm="."><plain>Segato et al., 2008 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76976" pm="."><plain>Pyridoxine kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76977" pm="."><plain>TERG_06151 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76978" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76979" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76980" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76981" pm="."><plain>Adenosine 5’-phosphosulfate kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76982" pm="."><plain>TERG_07921 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76983" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76984" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76985" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76986" pm="."><plain>Kinase subdomain-containing protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76987" pm="."><plain>TERG_07159 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76988" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76989" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76990" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76991" pm="."><plain>Kinase subdomain-containing protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76992" pm="."><plain>TERG_02787 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76993" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76994" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76995" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76996" pm="."><plain>Kinase subdomain-containing protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76997" pm="."><plain>TERG_01497 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76998" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="76999" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77000" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77001" pm="."><plain>Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAF1) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77002" pm="."><plain>TERG_00595 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77003" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77004" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77005" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77006" pm="."><plain>CMGC/SRPK protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77007" pm="."><plain>TERG_08979 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77008" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77009" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77010" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77011" pm="."><plain>Calcium-calmodulin-dependent protein kinase (CamK) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77012" pm="."><plain>TERG_02198 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77013" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77014" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77015" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77016" pm="."><plain>CAMKK protein kinase (CamKK) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77017" pm="."><plain>TERG_07555 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77018" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77019" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77020" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77021" pm="."><plain>Stress activated MAP kinase interacting protein </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77022" pm="."><plain>TERG_03684 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77023" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77024" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77025" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77026" pm="."><plain>Atypical/ABC1/ABC1-B protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77027" pm="."><plain>TERG_07639 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77028" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77029" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77030" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77031" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77032" pm="."><plain>TERG_04042 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77033" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77034" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77035" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77036" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77037" pm="."><plain>TERG_07140 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77038" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77039" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77040" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77041" pm="."><plain>Thiamine pyrophosphokinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77042" pm="."><plain>TERG_05058 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77043" pm="."><plain>ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77044" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77045" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77046" pm="."><plain>Uridine/cytidine kinase (UCK) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77047" pm="."><plain>TERG_05622 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77048" pm="."><plain>UDA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77049" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77050" pm="."><plain>Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77051" pm="."><plain>STE/STE7 protein kinase (STE7) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77052" pm="."><plain>TERG_08066 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77053" pm="."><plain>UDA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77054" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77055" pm="."><plain>Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77056" pm="."><plain>Dephospho-CoA kinase (DPCK) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77057" pm="."><plain>TERG_04392 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77058" pm="."><plain>UDA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77059" pm="."><plain>Up-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77060" pm="."><plain>Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77061" pm="."><plain>Nucleoside diphosphate kinase (NDK) </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77062" pm="."><plain>TERG_04558 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77063" pm="."><plain>UDA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77064" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77065" pm="."><plain>Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77066" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77067" pm="."><plain>TERG_08278 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77068" pm="."><plain>UDA/ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77069" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77070" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014; Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77071" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77072" pm="."><plain>TERG_00199 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77073" pm="."><plain>UDA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77074" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77075" pm="."><plain>Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77076" pm="."><plain>Serine/threonine protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77077" pm="."><plain>TERG_03851 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77078" pm="."><plain>UDA </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77079" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77080" pm="."><plain>Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77081" pm="."><plain>AGC/RSK protein kinase </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77082" pm="."><plain>TERG_00281 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77083" pm="."><plain>UDA/ACR </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77084" pm="."><plain>Down-regulated </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="77085" pm="."><plain>Persinoti et al., 2014; Mendes et al., 2018 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><attrib><italic>Drugs: ACR, acriflavine; AMB, amphotericin B; FLC, fluconazole; GRS, griseofulvin; ITRA, itraconazole; TRB, terbinafine; UDA, undecanoic acid, and PHS11A and PH11B.</italic></attrib></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77086" pm="."><plain>Fungal Heat Shock Proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77087" pm="."><plain>Initially discovered in Drosophila (De Maio et al., 2012), the heat shock proteins (Hsps) comprise chaperones present in all organisms studied to date that participate in diverse cellular processes such as transcription, translation, post-translational modifications, protein folding, and protein aggregation and disaggregation (Tiwari et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77088" pm="."><plain>Some Hsps may be induced when cells undergo stressful conditions, such as the exposure to antifungal agents, and extremes of temperature or pH (Singh et al., 2009; Leach et al., 2012a; Tamayo et al., 2013; Tiwari et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77089" pm="."><plain>These proteins are classified according to their functions and molecular mass into six families: Hsp40, Hsp60, Hsp70, Hsp90, Hsp100, and small Hsps (Tiwari et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77090" pm="."><plain>In fungi, Hsp20-40, Hsp70, and Hsp90 are predominant and participate in several cellular events, with some Hsps acting as co-chaperones (Fink, 1999; Tiwari et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77091" pm="."><plain>In C. albicans, low molecular mass Hsps are ATP independent, whereas those with higher molecular mass are ATP dependent (Gong et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77092" pm="."><plain>Usually, the hsp genes are activated by a heat shock transcription factor (HSF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77093" pm="."><plain>This protein under stress conditions is phosphorylated and trimerized, binding to the promoter regions of the hsp genes and inducing their transcription (Akerfelt et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77094" pm="."><plain>The relationship between the gene expression of hsp genes and the stress induced by antifungal drugs has been evidenced in different pathogenic agents including yeasts and filamentous fungi (Tiwari et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77095" pm="."><plain>In dermatophytes, the exposure to sub-lethal doses of diverse cytotoxic drugs results in the modulation of several hsp genes (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77096" pm="."><plain>Drug stress induces the up-regulation of genes encoding proteins belonging mainly to the Hsp70 family, such as in response to TRB, PHS11A, and ACR, or belonging to the small Hsp family, such as in response to TRB, AMB, ITR, and ACR (Jacob et al., 2015; Martinez-Rossi et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77097" pm="."><plain>Hsp70 proteins are monomeric and collaborate with the Hsp40 family of co-chaperones to bind to linear segments of unfolded proteins, whereas small Hsps form oligomeric complexes that bind to denatured proteins (Schopf et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77098" pm="."><plain>The genes encoding Hsp90 (Jacob et al., 2015), Cdc37, and the transcription factor Hsf1 (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2016) are up-regulated in T. rubrum in response to TRB and ACR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77099" pm="."><plain>Cdc37 is one of the co-chaperones that regulates Hsp90 function, playing roles in the maturation of kinases (Schopf et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77100" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the genes encoding the transcriptional regulator Hsf1 and PacC are upregulated when T. rubrum and T. interdigitale are submitted to temperature shifts in keratin cultures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77101" pm="."><plain>In a pacC- strain of T. interdigitale the transcription of the hsf1 gene was tightly reduced compared to the other hsp genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77102" pm="."><plain>The authors suggested that the collaboration between PacC and Hsf1 proteins modulates the level of hsp transcripts in response to cellular stress (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77103" pm="."><plain>In contrast, T. rubrum challenged with sub-inhibitory concentrations of UDA for 3 and 12 h did not significantly increase the expression of any hsp gene (Mendes et al., 2018), indicating that the cell used another strategy to cope with the stress provoked by this drug. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77104" pm="."><plain>In support of this, other pathways were also highlighted during UDA detoxification in T. rubrum such as those involved in lipid metabolism, cellular membrane composition, pathogenesis, and oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77105" pm="."><plain>Moreover, events of alternative splicing, including intron retention and exon skipping, were described in response to UDA as well (Mendes et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77106" pm="."><plain>Hsp90, one of the most conserved Hsps, associates with a wide range of client proteins, controlling their activities by folding them to their active conformations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77107" pm="."><plain>Clients are enriched in signal transducers including kinases and transcription factors (Taipale et al., 2010; Leach et al., 2012a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77108" pm="."><plain>In S. cerevisiae, Hsp90 interacts with approximately 10% of the yeast proteome (Zhao et al., 2005; Leach et al., 2012b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77109" pm="."><plain>By controlling the activation of key molecules, Hsp90 plays roles in diverse processes including morphogenetic changes, stress adaptation, and antifungal resistance (Cowen, 2009; Singh et al., 2009; Lamoth et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77110" pm="."><plain>In yeast, it was established that Hsp90 potentiates azole resistance in C. albicans and Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Cowen and Lindquist, 2005; Cowen, 2009), in addition to governing the cellular circuits required for resistance to echinocandins in C. albicans (Singh et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77111" pm="."><plain>This biological response occurs through the activation of calcineurin phosphatase by Hsp90 under stress conditions (Cowen, 2008; Singh et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77112" pm="."><plain>In A. fumigatus, the genetic repression of Hsp90 showed that this chaperone appears to be essential for the development of this fungus, causing a decrease in spore viability, reduction in hyphae growth, and defects in germination (Lamoth et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77113" pm="."><plain>Some information about the cellular location of Hsp90 in different pathogenic fungi may help to understand the biological functionality of this protein against toxic agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77114" pm="."><plain>In C. neoformans, Hsp90 is located on the cell surface, so that the inhibition of this protein confers the natural resistance to cell wall inhibitors (Chatterjee and Tatu, 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77115" pm="."><plain>However, in A. fumigatus, Hsp90 is predominantly found in the cytosol, although in the presence of cell wall stressors it accumulates in the cell wall and the septa regions of the hypha, indicating an activity in compensatory stress mechanisms (Lamoth et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77116" pm="."><plain>However, despite the well-established data regarding Hsp90 in drug-induced responses in several fungi, few studies have addressed protein interactions and their biological role in dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77117" pm="."><plain>For example, the chemical inhibition of Hsp90 of T. rubrum caused increased susceptibility to micafungin and itraconazole, and improved the efficacy of these antifungal agents. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77118" pm="."><plain>Additionally, Hsp90 inhibition impaired fungal growth in human nail fragments and altered the modulation of other hsp genes as well as the pacC gene, which encodes a transcription factor involved in fungal pathogenicity (Bignell et al., 2005; Ferreira-Nozawa et al., 2006), suggesting that Hsp90 is involved in both pathogenicity and drug susceptibility in T. rubrum (Jacob et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77119" pm="."><plain>In this case, the synergism observed between the inhibition of Hsp90 and the increased susceptibility to some antifungal in T. rubrum revealed Hsp90 as a novel target and its inhibition as a potential strategy to treat dermatophytosis (Jacob et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77120" pm="."><plain>Although they present a high degree of homology, the differences between Hsp90 orthologs may be explained owing to the occurrence of post-translational modifications that can interfere in the differential regulation of these proteins (Lamoth et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77121" pm="."><plain>Considering the participation of Hsp90 in the development of drug resistance, drugs targeting this chaperone have been recognized as new therapeutic alternatives against pathogenic fungi. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77122" pm="."><plain>Currently, inhibitors and anti-Hsp90 antibodies have been shown to interfere with the activity of Hsp90 (Gong et al., 2017) by binding to the N-terminal region in the ATP binding site (Li et al., 2015); these agents include radicicol (RAD), geldanamycin (GdA), GdA analogs, and non-GdA Hsp90 inhibitors (Gong et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77123" pm="."><plain>However, for pharmacological application in clinical therapy, the toxicity of these drugs must be carefully evaluated in humans (Uehara, 2003) to avoid any potential for harm to patient health. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77124" pm="."><plain>Mutations Affecting Drug Target Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77125" pm="."><plain>Several mutations in genes encoding enzymes targeted by antifungal agents, mostly enzymes involved in ergosterol biosynthesis and cell wall synthesis, have been described in different fungal pathogens. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77126" pm="."><plain>Azoles inhibits lanosterol alfa-14-demethylase (Cyp51) by binding the nitrogen in the azoles ring to the iron atom of the heme group of the protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77127" pm="."><plain>This class of drugs is used for the treatment of several mycoses, including dermatophytosis, owing to its broad spectrum of activity; however, an increasing number of resistant isolates have arisen (Campoy and Adrio, 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77128" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the erg11 gene, which encodes the lanosterol alfa-14-demethylase, are often found in C. albicans azole-resistant clinical isolates, resulting in non-synonymous amino acid substitutions in regions close to the active site of the enzyme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77129" pm="."><plain>Although inducing post-translational modifications that affect its three-dimensional structure (Morio et al., 2010), these mutations do not affect the enzyme function and are often followed by loss of heterozygosity, which increases azole resistance (Selmecki et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77130" pm="."><plain>Moreover, erg11 mutations have different effects on the affinity of distinct azole drugs, which interact with specific Erg11 residues (Morio et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77131" pm="."><plain>Accordingly, a recent study demonstrated that some mutations alter the hydrogen bond between the drug and target protein, reducing the affinity of short-tailed but not of long-tailed triazoles (Sagatova et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77132" pm="."><plain>Another target enzyme of antifungal agents is squalene epoxidase (SE), which participates in the ergosterol biosynthesis pathway by catalyzing the epoxidation of squalene to 2-3-oxidosqualene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77133" pm="."><plain>Terbinafine, the drug of choice for dermatophytes, is an antifungal agent that inhibits SE fungal activity in a non-competitive way, leading to depletion of ergosterol and accumulation of squalene (Favre and Ryder, 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77134" pm="."><plain>Mutations in the gene for SE that give rise to amino acid substitutions lead to structural changes and decreased binding of terbinafine to the protein without causing dysfunction in ergosterol biosynthesis (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77135" pm="."><plain>Until recently, few T. rubrum clinical isolates resistant to terbinafine have been described, and only two clinical isolates were investigated and associated with SE mutations, which resulted in the amino acid substitutions L393F and F397L. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77136" pm="."><plain>Both isolates were cross-resistant to all tested SE inhibitors, with these mutations being in the same region as several mutations identified previously in terbinafine-resistant S. cerevisiae strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77137" pm="."><plain>In addition, the expression of C. albicans SE harboring mutations with corresponding amino acid substitutions was shown to decrease inhibitor susceptibility in S. cerevisiae; furthermore, single point mutations in A. nidulans and A. fumigatus in amino acids corresponding to the F397L substitution were associated with terbinafine resistance (Osborne et al., 2005; Rocha et al., 2006; Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008) These data therefore suggested that this region may contain the high-affinity site for TRB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77138" pm="."><plain>Recently, 2,056 isolates of T. rubrum and T. interdigitale were evaluated regarding to their susceptibility to TRB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77139" pm="."><plain>The authors found that only 17 isolates, representing less than 1%, were resistant to TRB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77140" pm="."><plain>By analyzing the gene sequence of the SE, they found point mutations in four positions responsible for the resistant phenotype, which are represented in Figure 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77141" pm="."><plain>In addition to L393F and F397L, seven new mutations were identified including one in residue L393 and two in residue F397. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77142" pm="."><plain>These mutations were investigated through expression of the corresponding amino acid substitutions using Arthoderma vanbreuseghemii (T. mentagrophytes) as a recipient organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77143" pm="."><plain>The strains harboring mutated genes were less susceptible to TRB, with global gene expression analysis revealing no other significant differences between the mutated and control strains, indicating that the increased TRB resistance was due to the mutations (Yamada et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>FIGURE 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="77144" pm="."><plain>Alignment of amino acid sequences of squalene epoxidase (SE) of T. mentagrophytes, T. rubrum, A. fumigatus, and S. cerevisiae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77145" pm="."><plain>The six residues with point mutations associated with terbinafine resistance are indicated by red contour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77146" pm="."><plain>The boxes represent point mutations in SE from T. mentagrophytes and T. rubrum (blue), A. fumigatus (red), and S. cerevisiae (green). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77147" pm="."><plain>Asterisks are related to identical residues in the four species, whereas two dots or one dot represent a higher and lower degree of conservation, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-09-01108-g001"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="77148" pm="."><plain>The substitution in the amino acid corresponding to F415 in S. cerevisiae (F420) has been previously associated with TRB resistance (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2008), being the first mutation found in residue His440. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77149" pm="."><plain>A valine is located in the equivalent position (Figure 1), which was not identified in a previous screening of critical amino acids by 3D modeling of S. cerevisiae SE (Nowosielski et al., 2011), owing to subtle conformational differences between the enzymes from S. cerevisiae and Trichophyton spp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77150" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the high frequency of TRB resistant isolates in this study are considered to be related to the prolonged exposure during treatment, as eight among 17 patients had been previously treated with TRB (Yamada et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77151" pm="."><plain>Currently, the increasing resistance to azoles in some Candida species has rendered echinocandins as the first line therapy for invasive candidiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77152" pm="."><plain>This class of drugs inhibits the fks subunit of glucan synthases; accordingly, clinical resistance has been associated with mutations in fks-encoding genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77153" pm="."><plain>In C. glabrata, the majority of mutations are located in one of the two hot spot regions of fks1 and fks2, whereas in other Candida spp., these substitutions are encountered only in fks1, in two hot spot regions comprising residues Phe641–Pro649 and Arg1361. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77154" pm="."><plain>The most abundant mutations that give rise to the most pronounced phenotypes in C. albicans are substitutions in Ser645 and Phe641 (Perlin, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77155" pm="."><plain>This mechanism of resistance to echinocandins has also been described for A. fumigatus, through S678P substitution in the Fks1 subunit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77156" pm="."><plain>In addition, the reduced intrinsic susceptibility of the C. parapsilosis complex and C. guilliermondii involve the occurrence of polymorphisms in hot spot 1 of the Fks1 subunit, although the clinical significance is uncertain as these species are often successfully treated with echinocandins (Perlin, 2015; Dudiuk et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77157" pm="."><plain>It is known that fks1 mutations can result in different therapeutic responses to different echinocandins and may or may not be associated with reduced virulence and fitness (Lackner et al., 2014; Perlin, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77158" pm="."><plain>Reduced virulence was previously related to altered kinetics of glucan synthase, resulting in changes in cell wall composition and decreased transmission between patients of strains harboring these mutations (Perlin, 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77159" pm="."><plain>However, fitness may depend not only on the nature and position of the substitution but also on host immunity, as significant differences were found between immunocompetent and neutropenic hosts (Lackner et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77160" pm="."><plain>Aside from the known consequences of fks1 mutations in echinocandin resistance, the functions of the Fks2 and Fks3 subunits are not yet entirely elucidated and may differ among species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77161" pm="."><plain>Although echinocandin resistance in S. cerevisiae is conferred by fks2 mutations, both fks2 and fks3 deletion in this species resulted in better growth under exposure to caspofungin (Suwunnakorn et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77162" pm="."><plain>Moreover, a recent study demonstrated that Fks2 and Fks3 are not functionally redundant in C. albicans and suggested the action of both subunits as negative regulators of Fks1 (Suwunnakorn et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77163" pm="."><plain>The in vitro efficacy of echinocandin drugs against dermatophytes was firstly evaluated by Bao et al. (2013), who demonstrated that caspofungin and micafungin did not entirely inhibit growth, but exhibit good in vitro antifungal activity to dermatophytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77164" pm="."><plain>Recent studies also showed that anidulafungin has potent in vitro activity against dermatophytes although the relevance for clinical efficacy has not yet been established (Badali et al., 2015; Baghi et al., 2016; Deng et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77165" pm="."><plain>The absence of in vivo studies of echinocandins efficacy limits its use for treatment of dermatophytosis, which may underlie the absence of resistant dermatophyte strains described to date. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77166" pm="."><plain>Structural Elements Influencing Drug Resistance </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77167" pm="."><plain>In addition to mechanisms involving stress and alteration of the target drug, other factors such as the fungal structure and cellular organization can also interfere with drug resistance/tolerance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77168" pm="."><plain>For example, biofilms are comprised of complex, surface-associated cell populations embedded in an extracellular matrix and are considered the most prevalent forms of microbial growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77169" pm="."><plain>They are responsible for a broad spectrum of microbial infections in humans and are associated with increased resistance to antifungal therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77170" pm="."><plain>Factors that contribute to biofilm drug resistance include structural complexity, presence of extracellular matrix, metabolic heterogeneity, and up-regulation of efflux pump genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77171" pm="."><plain>The matrix that surrounds the microbial population acts as a physical barrier, protecting the microbial community against drugs and host immune response and contributing to the emergence of persistent cells, a subpopulation able to tolerate higher concentrations of drugs and considered to enable recalcitrance (Fanning and Mitchell, 2012; Robbins et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77172" pm="."><plain>As recalcitrance is often associated with dermatophytosis, it has been proposed that biofilms may act as a source of persistent infection and antifungal resistance in onychomycosis (Burkhart et al., 2002; Gupta A.K. et al., 2016). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77173" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this concept, dermatophytes have been shown to form biofilms in vitro (Costa-Orlandi et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77174" pm="."><plain>Recently, the formation of biofilms in nail fragments has also been demonstrated in an in vitro model of onychomycosis (Brilhante et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77175" pm="."><plain>The production of arthroconidia by dermatophytes has also been proposed to contribute to drug resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77176" pm="."><plain>Arthroconidia are produced by the fragmentation of hyphae and are considered as the main mode of transmission of dermatophytosis (Gupta and Kohli, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77177" pm="."><plain>Arthroconidia are more resistant to antifungal drugs than hyphae (Arrese et al., 2001) and, in general, are more resistant than microconidia as well (Coelho et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec><SecTag type="DISCUSS,CONCL"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77178" pm="."><plain>Conclusion and Perspectives </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77179" pm="."><plain>The ideal antifungal agent has been postulated as the compound that inhibits potential virulence factors, affects fungi physiology, and also acts on specific fungal cellular targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77180" pm="."><plain>Recently, the genomes of about twenty dermatophyte strains were sequenced through the Broad Institute initiative, and the databases are available at Broad Fungal FTP Site1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77181" pm="."><plain>Consequently, advances in dermatophyte research have been reported, improving the understanding of their pathophysiology, niche and host preferences, and general aspects of gene structure and regulation, which together strongly contribute to the development of strategies for more effective therapies (Martinez-Rossi et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77182" pm="."><plain>Additionally, the comparative genome analysis highlighted the kinases as an enriched class in dermatophyte genomes, reemphasizing the interplay between signal transduction and regulation with dermatophyte–host interaction (Martinez et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77183" pm="."><plain>Some such kinases, with unknown specificities, may be associated with intrinsic abilities of dermatophytes to cause disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77184" pm="."><plain>Here, we discussed the modulation of kinase-encoding genes in response to antifungal drugs along with their putative roles in drug-stress responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77185" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the current studies shed light on potential novel antifungal targets such as the glyoxylate cycle, which is absent in mammalian cells and plays an adaptive role during infection (Lorenz and Fink, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77186" pm="."><plain>Another interesting target is FAS, owing to the marked architectural differences between fungal and mammalian FAS proteins, and to the importance of fatty acid biosynthesis for fungal physiology (Maier et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77187" pm="."><plain>Additionally, Hsp90 has been considered as a therapeutic target to treat fungal infections, as it is essential for cell physiology and participates in the response to several stresses including the exposure to antifungals as well as in fungal–host interactions (Jacob et al., 2015; Martinez-Rossi et al., 2016, 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77188" pm="."><plain>Together, these potential targets play important roles in fungal adaptation, physiology, and the infection process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77189" pm="."><plain>In this respect, both synthetic and natural compounds constitute promising sources of new structural entities with antifungal properties that exhibit potentially novel mechanisms of action. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77190" pm="."><plain>Moreover, these natural compounds may be administrated in association with conventional antifungal agents, synergistically enhancing their antifungal activity and acting as chemosensitizers to overcome fungal resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77191" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the natural sources may expand the possibilities to improve or develop new and effective antifungal therapies. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77192" pm="."><plain>Author Contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77193" pm="."><plain>All authors reviewed literature and wrote sections of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77194" pm="."><plain>NM-R, TB, NP, EL, and AR edited the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77195" pm="."><plain>TB and NQ designed the figure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77196" pm="."><plain>TB, NP, and EG prepared the tables. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77197" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the submitted version. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="77198" pm="."><plain>Conflict of Interest Statement </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="77199" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="77200" pm="."><plain>We thank the Brazilian Agencies for the continuous support to our projects: FAPESP (proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77201" pm="."><plain>Nos. 2014/03847-7, 2015/23435-8, 2016/04274-6, 2011/08424-9, and others), CNPq (proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77202" pm="."><plain>Nos. 305797/2017-4 and 304989/2017-7), CAPES, and FAEPA. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn id="fn01"><label>1</label><p><text><SENT sid="77203" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://ftp.broadinstitute.org/pub/annotation/fungi">ftp://ftp.broadinstitute.org/pub/annotation/fungi</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="77204" pm="."><plain>AgarwalA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77205" pm="."><plain>K.XuT.JacobM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77206" pm="."><plain>R.FengQ.LorenzM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77207" pm="."><plain>C.WalkerL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77208" pm="."><plain>A. (2008). Role of heme in the antifungal activity of the azaoxoaporphine alkaloid sampangine. Eukaryot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77209" pm="."><plain>Cell 7 387–400. 10.1128/EC.00323-07 <?supplied-pmid 18156292?>18156292 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="77210" pm="."><plain>AkerfeltM.MorimotoR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77211" pm="."><plain>I.SistonenL. (2010). Heat shock factors: integrators of cell stress, development and lifespan. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77212" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77213" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77214" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 11 545–555. 10.1038/nrm2938 <?supplied-pmid 20628411?>20628411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="77215" pm="."><plain>ArendrupM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77216" pm="."><plain>C.JensenR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77217" pm="."><plain>H.Cuenca-EstrellaM. (2016). In vitro activity of ASP2397 against Aspergillus isolates with or without acquired azole resistance mechanisms. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77218" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 60 532–536. 10.1128/AAC.02336-15 <?supplied-pmid 26552973?>26552973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="77219" pm="."><plain>ArifT.BhosaleJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77220" pm="."><plain>D.KumarN.MandalT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77221" pm="."><plain>K.BendreR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77222" pm="."><plain>S.LavekarG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77223" pm="."><plain>S. (2009). Natural products–antifungal agents derived from plants. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77224" pm="."><plain>Asian Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77225" pm="."><plain>Prod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77226" pm="."><plain>Res. 11 621–638. 10.1080/10286020902942350 <?supplied-pmid 20183299?>20183299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="77227" pm="."><plain>ArreseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77228" pm="."><plain>E.Pierard-FranchimontC.PierardG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77229" pm="."><plain>E. (2001). A plea to bridge the gap between antifungals and the management of onychomycosis. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77230" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77231" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77232" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 2 281–284. 10.2165/00128071-200102050-00002 <?supplied-pmid 11721646?>11721646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="77233" pm="."><plain>BadaliH.MohammadiR.MashediO.De HoogG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77234" pm="."><plain>S.MeisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77235" pm="."><plain>F. (2015). In vitro susceptibility patterns of clinically important Trichophyton and Epidermophyton species against nine antifungal drugs. Mycoses 58 303–307. 10.1111/myc.12315 <?supplied-pmid 25757042?>25757042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="77236" pm="."><plain>BaeM.KimH.MoonK.NamS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77237" pm="."><plain>J.ShinJ.OhK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77238" pm="."><plain>B. (2015). Mohangamides A and B, new dilactone-tethered pseudo-dimeric peptides inhibiting Candida albicans isocitrate lyase. Org. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77239" pm="."><plain>Lett. 17 712–715. 10.1021/ol5037248 <?supplied-pmid 25622093?>25622093 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="77240" pm="."><plain>BaghiN.ShokohiT.BadaliH.MakimuraK.Rezaei-MatehkolaeiA.AbdollahiM. (2016). In vitro activity of new azoles luliconazole and lanoconazole compared with ten other antifungal drugs against clinical dermatophyte isolates. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77241" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 54 757–763. 10.1093/mmy/myw016 <?supplied-pmid 27118804?>27118804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="77242" pm="."><plain>BaoY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77243" pm="."><plain>Q.WanZ.LiR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77244" pm="."><plain>Y. (2013). In vitro antifungal activity of micafungin and caspofungin against dermatophytes isolated from China. Mycopathologia 175 141–145. 10.1007/s11046-012-9571-6 <?supplied-pmid 22983900?>22983900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="77245" pm="."><plain>Ben YaakovD.RivkinA.MircusG.AlbertN.DietlA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77246" pm="."><plain>M.KovalerchickD. (2016). Identification and characterization of haemofungin, a novel antifungal compound that inhibits the final step of haem biosynthesis. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77247" pm="."><plain>Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77248" pm="."><plain>Chemother. 71 946–952. 10.1093/jac/dkv446 <?supplied-pmid 26747101?>26747101 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="77249" pm="."><plain>BignellE.Negrete-UrtasunS.CalcagnoA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77250" pm="."><plain>M.HaynesK.ArstH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77251" pm="."><plain>N.RogersT. (2005). The Aspergillus pH-responsive transcription factor PacC regulates virulence. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77252" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 55 1072–1084. 10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04472.x <?supplied-pmid 15686555?>15686555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="77253" pm="."><plain>BitencourtT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77254" pm="."><plain>A.KomotoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77255" pm="."><plain>T.MassarotoB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77256" pm="."><plain>G.MirandaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77257" pm="."><plain>E.BeleboniR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77258" pm="."><plain>O.MarinsM. (2013). Trans-chalcone and quercetin down-regulate fatty acid synthase gene expression and reduce ergosterol content in the human pathogenic dermatophyte Trichophyton rubrum. BMC Complement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77259" pm="."><plain>Altern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77260" pm="."><plain>Med. 13:229. 10.1186/1472-6882-13-229 <?supplied-pmid 24044691?>24044691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="77261" pm="."><plain>BoeckP.LealP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77262" pm="."><plain>C.YunesR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77263" pm="."><plain>A.FilhoV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77264" pm="."><plain>C.LopezS.SortinoM. (2005). Antifungal activity and studies on mode of action of novel xanthoxyline-derived chalcones. Arch. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77265" pm="."><plain>Pharm. 338 87–95. 10.1002/ardp.200400929 <?supplied-pmid 15799012?>15799012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="77266" pm="."><plain>BraschJ.MartinsB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77267" pm="."><plain>S.ChristophersE. (1991). Enzyme release by Trichophyton rubrum depends on nutritional conditions. Mycoses 34 365–368. 10.1111/j.1439-0507.1991.tb00795.x <?supplied-pmid 1726475?>1726475 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="77268" pm="."><plain>BrilhanteR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77269" pm="."><plain>S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77270" pm="."><plain>N.CorreiaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77271" pm="."><plain>E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77272" pm="."><plain>M.GuedesG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77273" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77274" pm="."><plain>M.PereiraV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77275" pm="."><plain>S.OliveiraJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77276" pm="."><plain>S.BandeiraS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77277" pm="."><plain>P. (2017). Quantitative and structural analyses of the in vitro and ex vivo biofilm-forming ability of dermatophytes. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77278" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77279" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 66 1045–1052. 10.1099/jmm.0.000528 <?supplied-pmid 28708048?>28708048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="77280" pm="."><plain>BurkhartC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77281" pm="."><plain>N.BurkhartC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77282" pm="."><plain>G.GuptaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77283" pm="."><plain>K. (2002). Dermatophytoma: recalcitrance to treatment because of existence of fungal biofilm. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77284" pm="."><plain>Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77285" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77286" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 47 629–631. 10.1067/mjd.2002.124699 <?supplied-pmid 12271316?>12271316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="77287" pm="."><plain>BurmesterA.ShelestE.GlocknerG.HeddergottC.SchindlerS.StaibP. (2011). Comparative and functional genomics provide insights into the pathogenicity of dermatophytic fungi. Genome Biol. 12:R7. 10.1186/gb-2011-12-1-r7 <?supplied-pmid 21247460?>21247460 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="77288" pm="."><plain>CampoyS.AdrioJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77289" pm="."><plain>L. (2017). Antifungals. Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77290" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol. 133 86–96. 10.1016/j.bcp.2016.11.019 <?supplied-pmid 27884742?>27884742 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="77291" pm="."><plain>CantelliB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77292" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77293" pm="."><plain>M.BitencourtT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77294" pm="."><plain>A.KomotoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77295" pm="."><plain>T.BeleboniR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77296" pm="."><plain>O.MarinsM.FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77297" pm="."><plain>L. (2017). Caffeic acid and licochalcone A interfere with the glyoxylate cycle of Trichophyton rubrum. Biomed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77298" pm="."><plain>Pharmacother. 96 1389–1394. 10.1016/j.biopha.2017.11.051 <?supplied-pmid 29174577?>29174577 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="77299" pm="."><plain>CavaleiroC.PintoE.GoncalvesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77300" pm="."><plain>J.SalgueiroL. (2006). Antifungal activity of Juniperus essential oils against dermatophyte, Aspergillus and Candida strains. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77301" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77302" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 100 1333–1338. 10.1111/j.1365-2672.2006.02862.x <?supplied-pmid 16696681?>16696681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="77303" pm="."><plain>CervelattiE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77304" pm="."><plain>P.FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77305" pm="."><plain>L.Ferreira-NozawaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77306" pm="."><plain>S.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77307" pm="."><plain>M. (2006). Molecular cloning and characterization of a novel ABC transporter gene in the human pathogen Trichophyton rubrum. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77308" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 44 141–147. 10.1080/13693780500220449 <?supplied-pmid 16519017?>16519017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="77309" pm="."><plain>ChatterjeeS.TatuU. (2017). Heat shock protein 90 localizes to the surface and augments virulence factors of Cryptococcus neoformans. PLoS Negl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77310" pm="."><plain>Trop. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77311" pm="."><plain>Dis. 11:e0005836. 10.1371/journal.pntd.0005836 <?supplied-pmid 28783748?>28783748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="77312" pm="."><plain>CheahH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77313" pm="."><plain>L.LimV.SandaiD. (2014). Inhibitors of the glyoxylate cycle enzyme ICL1 in Candida albicans for potential use as antifungal agents. PLoS One 9:e95951. 10.1371/journal.pone.0095951 <?supplied-pmid 24781056?>24781056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="77314" pm="."><plain>ClemonsK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77315" pm="."><plain>V.StevensD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77316" pm="."><plain>A. (1997). Efficacy of nikkomycin Z against experimental pulmonary blastomycosis. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77317" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 41 2026–2028. <?supplied-pmid 9303408?>9303408 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="77318" pm="."><plain>CoelhoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77319" pm="."><plain>M.Aquino-FerreiraR.MaffeiC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77320" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77321" pm="."><plain>L.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77322" pm="."><plain>M. (2008). In vitro antifungal drug susceptibilities of dermatophytes microconidia and arthroconidia. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77323" pm="."><plain>Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77324" pm="."><plain>Chemother. 62 758–761. 10.1093/jac/dkn245 <?supplied-pmid 18552341?>18552341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="77325" pm="."><plain>ColemanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77326" pm="."><plain>J.MylonakisE. (2009). Efflux in fungi: la piece de resistance. PLoS Pathog. 5:e1000486. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1000486 <?supplied-pmid 19557154?>19557154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="77327" pm="."><plain>ContiB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77328" pm="."><plain>J.BufaloM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77329" pm="."><plain>C.Golim MdeA.BankovaV.SforcinJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77330" pm="."><plain>M. (2013). Cinnamic acid is partially involved in propolis immunomodulatory action on human monocytes. Evid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77331" pm="."><plain>Based Complement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77332" pm="."><plain>Alternat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77333" pm="."><plain>Med. 2013:109864. 10.1155/2013/109864 <?supplied-pmid 23762102?>23762102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="77334" pm="."><plain>Costa-OrlandiC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77335" pm="."><plain>B.SardiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77336" pm="."><plain>C.SantosC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77337" pm="."><plain>T.Fusco-AlmeidaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77338" pm="."><plain>M.Mendes-GianniniM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77339" pm="."><plain>J. (2014). In vitro characterization of Trichophyton rubrum and T. mentagrophytes biofilms. Biofouling 30 719–727. 10.1080/08927014.2014.919282 <?supplied-pmid 24856309?>24856309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="77340" pm="."><plain>CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77341" pm="."><plain>E. (2008). The evolution of fungal drug resistance: modulating the trajectory from genotype to phenotype. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77342" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77343" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 6 187–198. 10.1038/nrmicro1835 <?supplied-pmid 18246082?>18246082 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="77344" pm="."><plain>CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77345" pm="."><plain>E. (2009). Hsp90 orchestrates stress response signaling governing fungal drug resistance. PLoS Pathog. 5:e1000471. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1000471 <?supplied-pmid 19714223?>19714223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="77346" pm="."><plain>CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77347" pm="."><plain>E.LindquistS. (2005). Hsp90 potentiates the rapid evolution of new traits: drug resistance in diverse fungi. Science 309 2185–2189. 10.1126/science.1118370 <?supplied-pmid 16195452?>16195452 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="77348" pm="."><plain>CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77349" pm="."><plain>E.SanglardD.HowardS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77350" pm="."><plain>J.RogersP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77351" pm="."><plain>D.PerlinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77352" pm="."><plain>S. (2015). Mechanisms of antifungal drug resistance. Cold Spring Harb. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77353" pm="."><plain>Perspect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77354" pm="."><plain>Med. 5:a019752. 10.1101/cshperspect.a019752 <?supplied-pmid 25384768?>25384768 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="77355" pm="."><plain>De CamposM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77356" pm="."><plain>P.CechinelV.Da SilvaR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77357" pm="."><plain>Z.YunesR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77358" pm="."><plain>A.ZacchinoS.JuarezS. (2005). Evaluation of antifungal activity of Piper solmsianum C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77359" pm="."><plain>DC. var. solmsianum (Piperaceae). Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77360" pm="."><plain>Pharm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77361" pm="."><plain>Bull. 28 1527–1530. 10.1248/bpb.28.1527 <?supplied-pmid 16079508?>16079508 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="77362" pm="."><plain>De MaioA.SantoroM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77363" pm="."><plain>G.TanguayR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77364" pm="."><plain>M.HightowerL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77365" pm="."><plain>E. (2012). Ferruccio Ritossa’s scientific legacy 50 years after his discovery of the heat shock response: a new view of biology, a new society, and a new journal. Cell Stress Chaperones 17 139–143. 10.1007/s12192-012-0320-z <?supplied-pmid 22252402?>22252402 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="77366" pm="."><plain>de MeloJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77367" pm="."><plain>O.BitencourtT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77368" pm="."><plain>A.FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77369" pm="."><plain>L.CruzE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77370" pm="."><plain>M.De JesusH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77371" pm="."><plain>C.AlvesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77372" pm="."><plain>B. (2013). Antidermatophytic and antileishmanial activities of essential oils from Lippia gracilis Schauer genotypes. Acta Trop. 128 110–115. 10.1016/j.actatropica.2013.06.024 <?supplied-pmid 23850505?>23850505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="77373" pm="."><plain>de Oliveira LimaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77374" pm="."><plain>I.Araujo de MedeirosA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77375" pm="."><plain>C.Souza SilvaK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77376" pm="."><plain>V.CardosoG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77377" pm="."><plain>N.De Oliveira LimaE.De Oliveira PereiraF. (2017). Investigation of the antifungal potential of linalool against clinical isolates of fluconazole resistant Trichophyton rubrum. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77378" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77379" pm="."><plain>Med. 27 195–202. 10.1016/j.mycmed.2017.01.011 <?supplied-pmid 28189377?>28189377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="77380" pm="."><plain>DelarzeE.SanglardD. (2015). Defining the frontiers between antifungal resistance, tolerance and the concept of persistence. Drug Resist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77381" pm="."><plain>Updat. 23 12–19. 10.1016/j.drup.2015.10.001 <?supplied-pmid 26690338?>26690338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="77382" pm="."><plain>DengS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77383" pm="."><plain>W.AnsariS.IlkitM.RafatiH.HedayatiM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77384" pm="."><plain>T.Taghizadeh-ArmakiM. (2017). In vitro antifungal susceptibility profiles of 12 antifungal drugs against 55 Trichophyton schoenleinii isolates from tinea capitis favosa patients in Iran, Turkey, and China. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77385" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 61:e01753-16. <?supplied-pmid 27956429?>27956429 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="77386" pm="."><plain>DiaoY.ZhaoR.DengX.LengW.PengJ.JinQ. (2009). Transcriptional profiles of Trichophyton rubrum in response to itraconazole. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77387" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 47 237–247. 10.1080/13693780802227308 <?supplied-pmid 18663659?>18663659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="77388" pm="."><plain>DudiukC.MacedoD.LeonardelliF.TheillL.CabezaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77389" pm="."><plain>S.GamarraS. (2017). Molecular confirmation of the relationship between Candida guilliermondii Fks1p naturally occurring amino acid substitutions and its intrinsic reduced echinocandin susceptibility. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77390" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 61:e02644-16. 10.1128/AAC.02644-16 <?supplied-pmid 28242659?>28242659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="77391" pm="."><plain>El-AwadyR.SalehE.HashimA.SolimanN.DallahA.ElrasheedA. (2016). The role of eukaryotic and prokaryotic ABC transporter family in failure of chemotherapy. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77392" pm="."><plain>Pharmacol. 7:535. 10.3389/fphar.2016.00535 <?supplied-pmid 28119610?>28119610 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="77393" pm="."><plain>FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77394" pm="."><plain>L.ContelE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77395" pm="."><plain>P.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77396" pm="."><plain>M. (2001). Effect of sub-MICs of antimycotics on expression of intracellular esterase of Trichophyton rubrum. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77397" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 39 129–133. 10.1080/mmy.39.1.129.133 <?supplied-pmid 11270400?>11270400 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="77398" pm="."><plain>FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77399" pm="."><plain>L.Ferreira-NozawaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77400" pm="."><plain>S.MaccheroniW.Jr.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77401" pm="."><plain>M. (2006). Role of the ABC transporter TruMDR2 in terbinafine, 4-nitroquinoline N-oxide and ethidium bromide susceptibility in Trichophyton rubrum. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77402" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77403" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 55 1093–1099. 10.1099/jmm.0.46522-0 <?supplied-pmid 16849730?>16849730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="77404" pm="."><plain>FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77405" pm="."><plain>L.MaffeiC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77406" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77407" pm="."><plain>L.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77408" pm="."><plain>M. (1996). In vitro susceptibility of Trichophyton rubrum isolates to griseofulvin and tioconazole. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77409" pm="."><plain>Induction and isolation of a resistant mutant to both antimycotic drugs. Mycopathologia 135 141–143. 10.1007/BF00632334 <?supplied-pmid 9066154?>9066154 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="77410" pm="."><plain>FanningS.MitchellA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77411" pm="."><plain>P. (2012). Fungal biofilms. PLoS Pathog. 8:e1002585. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1002585 <?supplied-pmid 22496639?>22496639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="77412" pm="."><plain>FavreB.RyderN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77413" pm="."><plain>S. (1996). Characterization of squalene epoxidase activity from the dermatophyte Trichophyton rubrum and its inhibition by terbinafine and other antimycotic agents. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77414" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 40 443–447. <?supplied-pmid 8834895?>8834895 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="77415" pm="."><plain>FengG.LeemY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77416" pm="."><plain>E.LevinH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77417" pm="."><plain>L. (2013). Transposon integration enhances expression of stress response genes. Nucleic Acids Res. 41 775–789. 10.1093/nar/gks1185 <?supplied-pmid 23193295?>23193295 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="77418" pm="."><plain>Ferreira-NozawaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77419" pm="."><plain>S.SilveiraH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77420" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77421" pm="."><plain>S.OnoC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77422" pm="."><plain>J.FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77423" pm="."><plain>L.RossiA.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77424" pm="."><plain>M. (2006). The pH signaling transcription factor PacC mediates the growth of Trichophyton rubrum on human nail in vitro. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77425" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 44 641–645. 10.1080/13693780600876553 <?supplied-pmid 17071558?>17071558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="77426" pm="."><plain>FinkA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77427" pm="."><plain>L. (1999). Chaperone-mediated protein folding. Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77428" pm="."><plain>Rev. 79 425–449. 10.1152/physrev.1999.79.2.425 <?supplied-pmid 10221986?>10221986 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="77429" pm="."><plain>FriesenH.LunzR.DoyleS.SegallJ. (1994). Mutation of the SPS1-encoded protein kinase of Saccharomyces cerevisiae leads to defects in transcription and morphology during spore formation. Genes Dev. 8 2162–2175. 10.1101/gad.8.18.2162 <?supplied-pmid 7958886?>7958886 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="77430" pm="."><plain>GadzalskiM.CiesielskaA.StaczekP. (2016). Bioinformatic survey of ABC transporters in dermatophytes. Gene 576 466–475. 10.1016/j.gene.2015.10.064 <?supplied-pmid 26524502?>26524502 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="77431" pm="."><plain>GaraizarJ.BrenaS.BikandiJ.RementeriaA.PontonJ. (2006). Use of DNA microarray technology and gene expression profiles to investigate the pathogenesis, cell biology, antifungal susceptibility and diagnosis of Candida albicans. FEMS Yeast Res. 6 987–998. 10.1111/j.1567-1364.2006.00108.x <?supplied-pmid 17042748?>17042748 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="77432" pm="."><plain>Garcia-RomeroM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77433" pm="."><plain>T.ArenasR. (2015). New insights into genes, immunity, and the occurrence of dermatophytosis. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77434" pm="."><plain>Invest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77435" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 135 655–657. 10.1038/jid.2014.498 <?supplied-pmid 25666672?>25666672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="77436" pm="."><plain>GarveyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77437" pm="."><plain>P.HoekstraW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77438" pm="."><plain>J.MooreW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77439" pm="."><plain>R.SchotzingerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77440" pm="."><plain>J.LongL.GhannoumM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77441" pm="."><plain>A. (2015). VT-1161 dosed once daily or once weekly exhibits potent efficacy in treatment of dermatophytosis in a guinea pig model. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77442" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 59 1992–1997. 10.1128/AAC.04902-14 <?supplied-pmid 25605358?>25605358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="77443" pm="."><plain>GhelardiE.CelandroniF.GueyeS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77444" pm="."><plain>A.SalvettiS.SenesiS.BulgheroniA. (2014). Potential of ergosterol synthesis inhibitors to cause resistance or cross-resistance in Trichophyton rubrum. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77445" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 58 2825–2829. 10.1128/AAC.02382-13 <?supplied-pmid 24614379?>24614379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="77446" pm="."><plain>GlavinasH.KrajcsiP.CserepesJ.SarkadiB. (2004). The role of ABC transporters in drug resistance, metabolism and toxicity. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77447" pm="."><plain>Drug Deliv. 1 27–42. 10.2174/156720104348003616305368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="77448" pm="."><plain>GongY.LiT.YuC.SunS. (2017). Candida albicans heat shock proteins and Hsps-associated signaling pathways as potential antifungal targets. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77449" pm="."><plain>Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77450" pm="."><plain>Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77451" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 7:520. 10.3389/fcimb.2017.00520 <?supplied-pmid 29312897?>29312897 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="77452" pm="."><plain>GraminhaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77453" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77454" pm="."><plain>S.RochaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77455" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77456" pm="."><plain>F.PradeR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77457" pm="."><plain>A.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77458" pm="."><plain>M. (2004). Terbinafine resistance mediated by salicylate 1-monooxygenase in Aspergillus nidulans. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77459" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 48 3530–3535. 10.1128/AAC.48.9.3530-3535.2004 <?supplied-pmid 15328121?>15328121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="77460" pm="."><plain>GuptaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77461" pm="."><plain>K.DaigleD.CarvielJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77462" pm="."><plain>L. (2016). The role of biofilms in onychomycosis. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77463" pm="."><plain>Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77464" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77465" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 74 1241–1246. 10.1016/j.jaad.2016.01.008 <?supplied-pmid 27012826?>27012826 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="77466" pm="."><plain>GuptaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77467" pm="."><plain>K.KohliY. (2003). In vitro susceptibility testing of ciclopirox, terbinafine, ketoconazole and itraconazole against dermatophytes and nondermatophytes, and in vitro evaluation of combination antifungal activity. Br. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77468" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77469" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 149 296–305. 10.1046/j.1365-2133.2003.05418.x <?supplied-pmid 12932235?>12932235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="77470" pm="."><plain>GuptaC.DasS.RamachandranV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77471" pm="."><plain>G.SahaR.BhattacharyaS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77472" pm="."><plain>N.DarS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77473" pm="."><plain>A. (2016). Possible role of trichophytin antigen in inducing impaired immunological clearance of fungus in onychomycosis. Mycopathologia 181 247–251. 10.1007/s11046-015-9973-3 <?supplied-pmid 26614362?>26614362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="77474" pm="."><plain>HarmsN.RasJ.ReijndersW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77475" pm="."><plain>N.Van SpanningR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77476" pm="."><plain>J.StouthamerA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77477" pm="."><plain>H. (1996). S-formylglutathione hydrolase of Paracoccus denitrificans is homologous to human esterase D: a universal pathway for formaldehyde detoxification? J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77478" pm="."><plain>Bacteriol. 178 6296–6299. 10.1128/jb.178.21.6296-6299.19968892832 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="77479" pm="."><plain>HauC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77480" pm="."><plain>S.TadaY.KandaN.WatanabeS. (2015). Immunoresponses in dermatomycoses. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77481" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 42 236–244. 10.1111/1346-8138.12718 <?supplied-pmid 25736316?>25736316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="77482" pm="."><plain>HavlickovaB.CzaikaV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77483" pm="."><plain>A.FriedrichM. (2008). Epidemiological trends in skin mycoses worldwide. Mycoses 51(Suppl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77484" pm="."><plain>4) 2–15. 10.1111/j.1439-0507.2008.01606.x <?supplied-pmid 18783559?>18783559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="77485" pm="."><plain>HayesB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77486" pm="."><plain>M.AndersonM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77487" pm="."><plain>A.TravenA.Van Der WeerdenN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77488" pm="."><plain>L.BleackleyM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77489" pm="."><plain>R. (2014). Activation of stress signalling pathways enhances tolerance of fungi to chemical fungicides and antifungal proteins. Cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77490" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77491" pm="."><plain>Life Sci. 71 2651–2666. 10.1007/s00018-014-1573-8 <?supplied-pmid 24526056?>24526056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="77492" pm="."><plain>HeinenM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77493" pm="."><plain>P.CambierL.FievezL.MignonB. (2016). Are Th17 cells playing a role in immunity to dermatophytosis? Mycopathologia 182 251–261. 10.1007/s11046-016-0093-5 <?supplied-pmid 27878642?>27878642 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="77494" pm="."><plain>HolmesA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77495" pm="."><plain>R.CardnoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77496" pm="."><plain>S.StrouseJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77497" pm="."><plain>J.Ivnitski-SteeleI.KeniyaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77498" pm="."><plain>V.LackovicK. (2016). Targeting efflux pumps to overcome antifungal drug resistance. Future Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77499" pm="."><plain>Chem. 8 1485–1501. 10.4155/fmc-2016-0050 <?supplied-pmid 27463566?>27463566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="77500" pm="."><plain>HolmesA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77501" pm="."><plain>R.KeniyaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77502" pm="."><plain>V.Ivnitski-SteeleI.MonkB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77503" pm="."><plain>C.LampingE.SklarL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77504" pm="."><plain>A. (2012). The monoamine oxidase A inhibitor clorgyline is a broad-spectrum inhibitor of fungal ABC and MFS transporter efflux pump activities which reverses the azole resistance of Candida albicans and Candida glabrata clinical isolates. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77505" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 56 1508–1515. 10.1128/AAC.05706-11 <?supplied-pmid 22203607?>22203607 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="77506" pm="."><plain>HousmanG.BylerS.HeerbothS.LapinskaK.LongacreM.SnyderN. (2014). Drug resistance in cancer: an overview. Cancers 6 1769–1792. 10.3390/cancers6031769 <?supplied-pmid 25198391?>25198391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="77507" pm="."><plain>HuangH.YangM.SuY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77508" pm="."><plain>E.QuL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77509" pm="."><plain>J.DengX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77510" pm="."><plain>W. (2015). Arabidopsis atypical kinases ABC1K1 and ABC1K3 act oppositely to cope with photodamage under red light. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77511" pm="."><plain>Plant 8 1122–1124. 10.1016/j.molp.2015.04.003 <?supplied-pmid 25882344?>25882344 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="77512" pm="."><plain>HubeB.HayR.BraschJ.VeraldiS.SchallerM. (2015). Dermatomycoses and inflammation: the adaptive balance between growth, damage, and survival. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77513" pm="."><plain>Mycol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77514" pm="."><plain>Med. 25 e44–e58. 10.1016/j.mycmed.2014.11.002 <?supplied-pmid 25662199?>25662199 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="77515" pm="."><plain>IvanovaA.BatovskaD.EngiH.ParushevS.OcsovszkiI.KostovaI. (2008). MDR-reversal activity of chalcones. In Vivo 22 379–384.18610751 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="77516" pm="."><plain>JacobT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77517" pm="."><plain>R.PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77518" pm="."><plain>T.MartinsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77519" pm="."><plain>P.LangE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77520" pm="."><plain>A.SanchesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77521" pm="."><plain>R.RossiA. (2015). Heat shock protein 90 (Hsp90) as a molecular target for the development of novel drugs against the dermatophyte Trichophyton rubrum. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77522" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 6:1241. 10.3389/fmicb.2015.01241 <?supplied-pmid 26617583?>26617583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="77523" pm="."><plain>JungU. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77524" pm="."><plain>S.LevinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77525" pm="."><plain>E. (1999). Genome-wide analysis of gene expression regulated by the yeast cell wall integrity signalling pathway. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77526" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 34 1049–1057. 10.1046/j.1365-2958.1999.01667.x10594829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75"><text><SENT sid="77527" pm="."><plain>KanafaniZ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77528" pm="."><plain>A.PerfectJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77529" pm="."><plain>R. (2008). Antimicrobial resistance: resistance to antifungal agents: mechanisms and clinical impact. Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77530" pm="."><plain>Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77531" pm="."><plain>Dis. 46 120–128. 10.1086/524071 <?supplied-pmid 18171227?>18171227 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76"><text><SENT sid="77532" pm="."><plain>KanoR.HsiaoY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77533" pm="."><plain>H.HanH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77534" pm="."><plain>S.ChenC.HasegawaA.KamataH. (2018). Resistance mechanism in a terbinafine-resistant strain of Microsporum canis. Mycopathologia 10.1007/s11046-018-0242-0 [Epub ahead of print]. <?supplied-pmid 29340910?>29340910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77"><text><SENT sid="77535" pm="."><plain>KawaharaT.KashiwagiE.IdeH.LiY.ZhengY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77536" pm="."><plain>C.MiyamotoY. (2015). Cyclosporine A and tacrolimus inhibit bladder cancer growth through down-regulation of NFATc1. Oncotarget 6 1582–1593. 10.18632/oncotarget.2750 <?supplied-pmid 25638160?>25638160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B78"><text><SENT sid="77537" pm="."><plain>KeukensE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77538" pm="."><plain>A.De VrijeT.Van Den BoomC.De WaardP.PlasmanH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77539" pm="."><plain>H.ThielF. (1995). Molecular basis of glycoalkaloid induced membrane disruption. Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77540" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77541" pm="."><plain>Acta 1240 216–228. 10.1016/0005-2736(95)00186-7 <?supplied-pmid 8541293?>8541293 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B79"><text><SENT sid="77542" pm="."><plain>KohlerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77543" pm="."><plain>R.HubeB.PucciaR.CasadevallA.PerfectJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77544" pm="."><plain>R. (2017). Fungi that infect humans. Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77545" pm="."><plain>Spectr. 5:FUNK-0014-2016. 10.1128/microbiolspec.FUNK-0014-2016 <?supplied-pmid 28597822?>28597822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B80"><text><SENT sid="77546" pm="."><plain>KomotoT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77547" pm="."><plain>T.BitencourtT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77548" pm="."><plain>A.SilvaG.BeleboniR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77549" pm="."><plain>O.MarinsM.FachinA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77550" pm="."><plain>L. (2015). Gene expression response of Trichophyton rubrum during coculture on keratinocytes exposed to antifungal agents. Evid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77551" pm="."><plain>Based Complement. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77552" pm="."><plain>Alternat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77553" pm="."><plain>Med. 2015:180535. 10.1155/2015/180535 <?supplied-pmid 26257814?>26257814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B81"><text><SENT sid="77554" pm="."><plain>KoselnyK.GreenJ.DidoneL.HaltermanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77555" pm="."><plain>P.FothergillA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77556" pm="."><plain>W.WiederholdN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77557" pm="."><plain>P. (2016). The celecoxib derivative AR-12 has broad-spectrum antifungal activity in vitro and improves the activity of fluconazole in a murine model of cryptococcosis. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77558" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 60 7115–7127. 10.1128/AAC.01061-16 <?supplied-pmid 27645246?>27645246 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B82"><text><SENT sid="77559" pm="."><plain>KurdelasR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77560" pm="."><plain>R.LimaB.TapiaA.FeresinG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77561" pm="."><plain>E.Gonzalez SierraM.RodriguezM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77562" pm="."><plain>V. (2010). Antifungal activity of extracts and prenylated coumarins isolated from Baccharis darwinii Hook &amp; Arn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77563" pm="."><plain>(Asteraceae). Molecules 15 4898–4907. 10.3390/molecules15074898 <?supplied-pmid 20657398?>20657398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B83"><text><SENT sid="77564" pm="."><plain>KushwahaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77565" pm="."><plain>S.SharmaP.ShivakumarH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77566" pm="."><plain>N.RappleyeC.ZukiwskiA.ProniukS. (2017). Trans-ungual delivery of AR-12, a novel antifungal drug. AAPS PharmSciTech 18 2702–2705. 10.1208/s12249-017-0752-y <?supplied-pmid 28289970?>28289970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B84"><text><SENT sid="77567" pm="."><plain>LackaI.KoniecznyM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77568" pm="."><plain>T.BulakowskaA.KodedovaM.GaskovaD.MauryaI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77569" pm="."><plain>K. (2015). Chemosensitization of multidrug resistant Candida albicans by the oxathiolone fused chalcone derivatives. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77570" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 6:783. 10.3389/fmicb.2015.00783 <?supplied-pmid 26300857?>26300857 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B85"><text><SENT sid="77571" pm="."><plain>LacknerM.TschernerM.SchallerM.KuchlerK.MairC.SartoriB. (2014). Positions and numbers of FKS mutations in Candida albicans selectively influence in vitro and in vivo susceptibilities to echinocandin treatment. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77572" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 58 3626–3635. 10.1128/AAC.00123-14 <?supplied-pmid 24733467?>24733467 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B86"><text><SENT sid="77573" pm="."><plain>LamothF.JuvvadiP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77574" pm="."><plain>R.FortwendelJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77575" pm="."><plain>R.SteinbachW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77576" pm="."><plain>J. (2012). Heat shock protein 90 is required for conidiation and cell wall integrity in Aspergillus fumigatus. Eukaryot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77577" pm="."><plain>Cell 11 1324–1332. 10.1128/EC.00032-12 <?supplied-pmid 22822234?>22822234 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B87"><text><SENT sid="77578" pm="."><plain>LamothF.JuvvadiP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77579" pm="."><plain>R.SteinbachW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77580" pm="."><plain>J. (2016). Heat shock protein 90 (Hsp90): a novel antifungal target against Aspergillus fumigatus. Crit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77581" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77582" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 42 310–321. 10.3109/1040841X.2014.947239 <?supplied-pmid 25243616?>25243616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B88"><text><SENT sid="77583" pm="."><plain>LanternierF.PathanS.VincentQ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77584" pm="."><plain>B.LiuL.CypowyjS.PrandoC. (2013). Deep dermatophytosis and inherited CARD9 deficiency. N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77585" pm="."><plain>Engl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77586" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77587" pm="."><plain>Med. 369 1704–1714. 10.1056/NEJMoa1208487 <?supplied-pmid 24131138?>24131138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B89"><text><SENT sid="77588" pm="."><plain>LeachM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77589" pm="."><plain>D.BudgeS.WalkerL.MunroC.CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77590" pm="."><plain>E.BrownA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77591" pm="."><plain>J. (2012a). Hsp90 orchestrates transcriptional regulation by Hsf1 and cell wall remodelling by MAPK signalling during thermal adaptation in a pathogenic yeast. PLoS Pathog. 8:e1003069. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1003069 <?supplied-pmid 23300438?>23300438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B90"><text><SENT sid="77592" pm="."><plain>LeachM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77593" pm="."><plain>D.KlippE.CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77594" pm="."><plain>E.BrownA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77595" pm="."><plain>J. (2012b). Fungal Hsp90: a biological transistor that tunes cellular outputs to thermal inputs. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77596" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77597" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 10 693–704. 10.1038/nrmicro2875 <?supplied-pmid 22976491?>22976491 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B91"><text><SENT sid="77598" pm="."><plain>LeeW.LeeD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77599" pm="."><plain>G. (2014). An antifungal mechanism of curcumin lies in membrane-targeted action within Candida albicans. IUBMB Life 66 780–785. 10.1002/iub.1326 <?supplied-pmid 25380239?>25380239 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B92"><text><SENT sid="77600" pm="."><plain>LiL.AnM.ShenH.HuangX.YaoX.LiuJ. (2015). The non-Geldanamycin Hsp90 inhibitors enhanced the antifungal activity of fluconazole. Am. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77601" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77602" pm="."><plain>Transl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77603" pm="."><plain>Res. 7 2589–2602. <?supplied-pmid 26885259?>26885259 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B93"><text><SENT sid="77604" pm="."><plain>LiuH.LiJ.ZhaoW.BaoL.SongX.XiaY. (2009). Fatty acid synthase inhibitors from Geum japonicum Thunb. var. chinense. Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77605" pm="."><plain>Biodivers. 6 402–410. 10.1002/cbdv.200700462 <?supplied-pmid 19319862?>19319862 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B94"><text><SENT sid="77606" pm="."><plain>LiuW.MayG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77607" pm="."><plain>S.LionakisM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77608" pm="."><plain>S.LewisR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77609" pm="."><plain>E.KontoyiannisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77610" pm="."><plain>P. (2004). Extra copies of the Aspergillus fumigatus squalene epoxidase gene confer resistance to terbinafine: genetic approach to studying gene dose-dependent resistance to antifungals in A. fumigatus. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77611" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 48 2490–2496. 10.1128/AAC.48.7.2490-2496.2004 <?supplied-pmid 15215099?>15215099 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B95"><text><SENT sid="77612" pm="."><plain>LockhartS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77613" pm="."><plain>R.FothergillA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77614" pm="."><plain>W.IqbalN.BoldenC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77615" pm="."><plain>B.GrossmanN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77616" pm="."><plain>T.GarveyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77617" pm="."><plain>P. (2016). The investigational fungal Cyp51 inhibitor VT-1129 demonstrates potent in vitro activity against Cryptococcus neoformans and Cryptococcus gattii. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77618" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 60 2528–2531. 10.1128/AAC.02770-15 <?supplied-pmid 26787697?>26787697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B96"><text><SENT sid="77619" pm="."><plain>LorenzM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77620" pm="."><plain>C.FinkG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77621" pm="."><plain>R. (2001). The glyoxylate cycle is required for fungal virulence. Nature 412 83–86. 10.1038/35083594 <?supplied-pmid 11452311?>11452311 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B97"><text><SENT sid="77622" pm="."><plain>MaierT.LeibundgutM.BoehringerD.BanN. (2010). Structure and function of eukaryotic fatty acid synthases. Q. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77623" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77624" pm="."><plain>Biophys. 43 373–422. 10.1017/S0033583510000156 <?supplied-pmid 20731893?>20731893 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B98"><text><SENT sid="77625" pm="."><plain>MartinezD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77626" pm="."><plain>A.OliverB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77627" pm="."><plain>G.GraserY.GoldbergJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77628" pm="."><plain>M.LiW.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77629" pm="."><plain>M. (2012). Comparative genome analysis of Trichophyton rubrum and related dermatophytes reveals candidate genes involved in infection. mBio 3:e00259-12. 10.1128/mBio.00259-12 <?supplied-pmid 22951933?>22951933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B99"><text><SENT sid="77630" pm="."><plain>Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77631" pm="."><plain>M.JacobT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77632" pm="."><plain>R.SanchesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77633" pm="."><plain>R.PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77634" pm="."><plain>T.LangE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77635" pm="."><plain>A.MartinsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77636" pm="."><plain>P. (2016). Heat shock proteins in dermatophytes: current advances and perspectives. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77637" pm="."><plain>Genomics 17 99–111. 10.2174/1389202917666151116212437 <?supplied-pmid 27226766?>27226766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B100"><text><SENT sid="77638" pm="."><plain>Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77639" pm="."><plain>M.PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77640" pm="."><plain>T.RossiA. (2017). Pathogenesis of dermatophytosis: sensing the host tissue. Mycopathologia 182 215–227. 10.1007/s11046-016-0057-9 <?supplied-pmid 27590362?>27590362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B101"><text><SENT sid="77641" pm="."><plain>Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77642" pm="."><plain>M.PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77643" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77644" pm="."><plain>A.RossiA. (2008). Antifungal resistance mechanisms in dermatophytes. Mycopathologia 166 369–383. 10.1007/s11046-008-9110-7 <?supplied-pmid 18478356?>18478356 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B102"><text><SENT sid="77645" pm="."><plain>MartinsM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77646" pm="."><plain>P.FranceschiniA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77647" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77648" pm="."><plain>C.JacobT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77649" pm="."><plain>R.RossiA.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77650" pm="."><plain>M. (2016). Compensatory expression of multidrug-resistance genes encoding ABC transporters in dermatophytes. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77651" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77652" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 65 605–610. 10.1099/jmm.0.000268 <?supplied-pmid 27121717?>27121717 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B103"><text><SENT sid="77653" pm="."><plain>MbavengA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77654" pm="."><plain>T.NgameniB.KueteV.SimoI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77655" pm="."><plain>K.AmbassaP.RoyR. (2008). Antimicrobial activity of the crude extracts and five flavonoids from the twigs of Dorstenia barteri (Moraceae). J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77656" pm="."><plain>Ethnopharmacol. 116 483–489. 10.1016/j.jep.2007.12.017 <?supplied-pmid 18280679?>18280679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B104"><text><SENT sid="77657" pm="."><plain>McCarthyM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77658" pm="."><plain>W.KontoyiannisD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77659" pm="."><plain>P.CornelyO. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77660" pm="."><plain>A.PerfectJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77661" pm="."><plain>R.WalshT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77662" pm="."><plain>J. (2017). Novel agents and drug targets to meet the challenges of resistant fungi. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77663" pm="."><plain>Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77664" pm="."><plain>Dis. 216 S474–S483. 10.1093/infdis/jix130 <?supplied-pmid 28911042?>28911042 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B105"><text><SENT sid="77665" pm="."><plain>MedeirosM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77666" pm="."><plain>R.PradoL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77667" pm="."><plain>A.FernandesV. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77668" pm="."><plain>C.FigueiredoS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77669" pm="."><plain>S.CoppedeJ.MartinsJ. (2011). Antimicrobial activities of indole alkaloids from Tabernaemontana catharinensis. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77670" pm="."><plain>Prod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77671" pm="."><plain>Commun. 6 193–196. <?supplied-pmid 21425672?>21425672 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B106"><text><SENT sid="77672" pm="."><plain>MendesN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77673" pm="."><plain>S.BitencourtT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77674" pm="."><plain>A.SanchesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77675" pm="."><plain>R.Silva-RochaR.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77676" pm="."><plain>M.RossiA. (2018). Transcriptome-wide survey of gene expression changes and alternative splicing in Trichophyton rubrum in response to undecanoic acid. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77677" pm="."><plain>Rep. 8:2520. 10.1038/s41598-018-20738-x <?supplied-pmid 29410524?>29410524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B107"><text><SENT sid="77678" pm="."><plain>MitsuyamaJ.NomuraN.HashimotoK.YamadaE.NishikawaH.KaeriyamaM. (2008). In vitro and in vivo antifungal activities of T-2307, a novel arylamidine. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77679" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 52 1318–1324. 10.1128/AAC.01159-07 <?supplied-pmid 18227186?>18227186 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B108"><text><SENT sid="77680" pm="."><plain>MiyazakiM.HoriiT.HataK.WatanabeN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77681" pm="."><plain>A.NakamotoK.TanakaK. (2011). In vitro activity of E1210, a novel antifungal, against clinically important yeasts and molds. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77682" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 55 4652–4658. 10.1128/AAC.00291-11 <?supplied-pmid 21825291?>21825291 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B109"><text><SENT sid="77683" pm="."><plain>MonodM. (2008). Secreted proteases from dermatophytes. Mycopathologia 166 285–294. 10.1007/s11046-008-9105-4 <?supplied-pmid 18478360?>18478360 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B110"><text><SENT sid="77684" pm="."><plain>MorV.RellaA.FarnoudA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77685" pm="."><plain>M.SinghA.MunshiM.BryanA. (2015). Identification of a new class of antifungals targeting the synthesis of fungal sphingolipids. mBio 6:e00647-15. 10.1128/mBio.00647-15 <?supplied-pmid 26106079?>26106079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B111"><text><SENT sid="77686" pm="."><plain>MorioF.LogeC.BesseB.HennequinC.Le PapeP. (2010). Screening for amino acid substitutions in the Candida albicans Erg11 protein of azole-susceptible and azole-resistant clinical isolates: new substitutions and a review of the literature. Diagn. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77687" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77688" pm="."><plain>Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77689" pm="."><plain>Dis. 66 373–384. 10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2009.11.006 <?supplied-pmid 20226328?>20226328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B112"><text><SENT sid="77690" pm="."><plain>Morteza-SemnaniK.AminG.ShidfarM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77691" pm="."><plain>R.HadizadehH.ShafieeA. (2003). Antifungal activity of the methanolic extract and alkaloids of Glaucium oxylobum. Fitoterapia 74 493–496. 10.1016/S0367-326X(03)00113-8 <?supplied-pmid 12837370?>12837370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B113"><text><SENT sid="77692" pm="."><plain>NarenderT.ReddyK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77693" pm="."><plain>P. (2007). A simple and highly efficient method for the synthesis of chalcones by using borontrifluoride-etherate. Tetrahedron Lett. 48 3177–3180. 10.1016/j.tetlet.2007.03.054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B114"><text><SENT sid="77694" pm="."><plain>NegriM.SalciT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77695" pm="."><plain>P.Shinobu-MesquitaC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77696" pm="."><plain>S.CapociI. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77697" pm="."><plain>R.SvidzinskiT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77698" pm="."><plain>I.KioshimaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77699" pm="."><plain>S. (2014). Early state research on antifungal natural products. Molecules 19 2925–2956. 10.3390/molecules19032925 <?supplied-pmid 24609016?>24609016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B115"><text><SENT sid="77700" pm="."><plain>NishikawaH.FukudaY.MitsuyamaJ.TashiroM.TanakaA.TakazonoT. (2017). In vitro and in vivo antifungal activities of T-2307, a novel arylamidine, against Cryptococcus gattii: an emerging fungal pathogen. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77701" pm="."><plain>Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77702" pm="."><plain>Chemother. 72 1709–1713. 10.1093/jac/dkx020 <?supplied-pmid 28201509?>28201509 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B116"><text><SENT sid="77703" pm="."><plain>NoguchiK.FukazawaH.MurakamiY.UeharaY. (2002). Nek11, a new member of the NIMA family of kinases, involved in DNA replication and genotoxic stress responses. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77704" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77705" pm="."><plain>Chem. 277 39655–39665. 10.1074/jbc.M204599200 <?supplied-pmid 12154088?>12154088 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B117"><text><SENT sid="77706" pm="."><plain>NowakowskaZ. (2007). A review of anti-infective and anti-inflammatory chalcones. Eur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77707" pm="."><plain>J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77708" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77709" pm="."><plain>Chem. 42 125–137. 10.1016/j.ejmech.2006.09.019 <?supplied-pmid 17112640?>17112640 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B118"><text><SENT sid="77710" pm="."><plain>NowosielskiM.HoffmannM.WyrwiczL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77711" pm="."><plain>S.StepniakP.PlewczynskiD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77712" pm="."><plain>M.LazniewskiM. (2011). Detailed mechanism of squalene epoxidase inhibition by terbinafine. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77713" pm="."><plain>Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77714" pm="."><plain>Inf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77715" pm="."><plain>Model. 51 455–462. 10.1021/ci100403b <?supplied-pmid 21229992?>21229992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B119"><text><SENT sid="77716" pm="."><plain>OliverJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77717" pm="."><plain>D.SibleyG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77718" pm="."><plain>E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77719" pm="."><plain>M.BeckmannN.DobbK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77720" pm="."><plain>S.SlaterM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77721" pm="."><plain>J.McenteeL. (2016). F901318 represents a novel class of antifungal drug that inhibits dihydroorotate dehydrogenase. Proc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77722" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77723" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77724" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77725" pm="."><plain>U.S.A. 113 12809–12814. 10.1073/pnas.1608304113 <?supplied-pmid 27791100?>27791100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B120"><text><SENT sid="77726" pm="."><plain>OsborneC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77727" pm="."><plain>S.LeitnerI.FavreB.RyderN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77728" pm="."><plain>S. (2005). Amino acid substitution in Trichophyton rubrum squalene epoxidase associated with resistance to terbinafine. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77729" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 49 2840–2844. 10.1128/AAC.49.7.2840-2844.2005 <?supplied-pmid 15980358?>15980358 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B121"><text><SENT sid="77730" pm="."><plain>OsmaniS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77731" pm="."><plain>A.PuR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77732" pm="."><plain>T.MorrisN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77733" pm="."><plain>R. (1988). Mitotic induction and maintenance by overexpression of a G2-specific gene that encodes a potential protein kinase. Cell 53 237–244. 10.1016/0092-8674(88)90385-6 <?supplied-pmid 3359487?>3359487 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B122"><text><SENT sid="77734" pm="."><plain>PaiãoF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77735" pm="."><plain>G.SegatoF.Cursino-SantosJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77736" pm="."><plain>R.PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77737" pm="."><plain>T.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77738" pm="."><plain>M. (2007). Analysis of Trichophyton rubrum gene expression in response to cytotoxic drugs. FEMS Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77739" pm="."><plain>Lett. 271 180–186. 10.1111/j.1574-6968.2007.00710.x <?supplied-pmid 17425668?>17425668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B123"><text><SENT sid="77740" pm="."><plain>PearceL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77741" pm="."><plain>R.KomanderD.AlessiD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77742" pm="."><plain>R. (2010). The nuts and bolts of AGC protein kinases. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77743" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77744" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77745" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 11 9–22. 10.1038/nrm2822 <?supplied-pmid 20027184?>20027184 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B124"><text><SENT sid="77746" pm="."><plain>PemanJ.CantonE.Espinel-IngroffA. (2009). Antifungal drug resistance mechanisms. Expert Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77747" pm="."><plain>Anti Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77748" pm="."><plain>Ther. 7 453–460. 10.1586/eri.09.18 <?supplied-pmid 19400764?>19400764 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B125"><text><SENT sid="77749" pm="."><plain>PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77750" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77751" pm="."><plain>A.MaranhãoF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77752" pm="."><plain>C.RossiA.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77753" pm="."><plain>M. (2010a). Dermatophytes: host-pathogen interaction and antifungal resistance. An. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77754" pm="."><plain>Bras. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77755" pm="."><plain>Dermatol. 85 657–667.21152790 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B126"><text><SENT sid="77756" pm="."><plain>PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77757" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77758" pm="."><plain>A.SanchesP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77759" pm="."><plain>R.FalcãoJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77760" pm="."><plain>P.SilveiraH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77761" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77762" pm="."><plain>S.PaiãoF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77763" pm="."><plain>G.MaranhãoF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77764" pm="."><plain>C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77765" pm="."><plain>A. (2010b). Transcriptional profiling reveals the expression of novel genes in response to various stimuli in the human dermatophyte Trichophyton rubrum. BMC Microbiol. 10:39. 10.1186/1471-2180-10-39 <?supplied-pmid 20144196?>20144196 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B127"><text><SENT sid="77766" pm="."><plain>PerlinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77767" pm="."><plain>S. (2015). Mechanisms of echinocandin antifungal drug resistance. Ann. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77768" pm="."><plain>N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77769" pm="."><plain>Y. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77770" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77771" pm="."><plain>Sci. 1354 1–11. 10.1111/nyas.12831 <?supplied-pmid 26190298?>26190298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B128"><text><SENT sid="77772" pm="."><plain>PersinotiG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77773" pm="."><plain>F.PeresN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77774" pm="."><plain>T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77775" pm="."><plain>A.JacobT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77776" pm="."><plain>R.RossiA.VencioR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77777" pm="."><plain>Z.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77778" pm="."><plain>M. (2014). RNA-seq Trichophyton rubrum transcriptome analysis in response to the cytotoxic drug acriflavine. BMC Genomics 15:S1. 10.1186/1471-2164-15-S7-S1 <?supplied-pmid 25573029?>25573029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B129"><text><SENT sid="77779" pm="."><plain>PfallerM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77780" pm="."><plain>A.MesserS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77781" pm="."><plain>A.GeorgopapadakouN.MartellL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77782" pm="."><plain>A.BestermanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77783" pm="."><plain>M.DiekemaD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77784" pm="."><plain>J. (2009). Activity of MGCD290, a Hos2 histone deacetylase inhibitor, in combination with azole antifungals against opportunistic fungal pathogens. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77785" pm="."><plain>Clin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77786" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 47 3797–3804. 10.1128/JCM.00618-09 <?supplied-pmid 19794038?>19794038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B130"><text><SENT sid="77787" pm="."><plain>PfallerM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77788" pm="."><plain>A.MesserS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77789" pm="."><plain>A.RhombergP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77790" pm="."><plain>R.JonesR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77791" pm="."><plain>N.CastanheiraM. (2016). Activity of a long-acting echinocandin, CD101, determined using CLSI and EUCAST reference methods, against Candida and Aspergillus spp., including echinocandin- and azole-resistant isolates. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77792" pm="."><plain>Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77793" pm="."><plain>Chemother. 71 2868–2873. 10.1093/jac/dkw214 <?supplied-pmid 27287236?>27287236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B131"><text><SENT sid="77794" pm="."><plain>PianaltoK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77795" pm="."><plain>M.AlspaughJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77796" pm="."><plain>A. (2016). New horizons in antifungal therapy. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77797" pm="."><plain>Fungi 2:E26. 10.3390/jof2040026 <?supplied-pmid 29376943?>29376943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B132"><text><SENT sid="77798" pm="."><plain>PortilloA.VilaR.FreixaB.FerroE.ParellaT.CasanovaJ. (2005). Antifungal sesquiterpene from the root of Vernonanthura tweedieana. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77799" pm="."><plain>Ethnopharmacol. 97 49–52. 10.1016/j.jep.2004.09.052 <?supplied-pmid 15652274?>15652274 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B133"><text><SENT sid="77800" pm="."><plain>PutmanM.Van VeenH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77801" pm="."><plain>W.KoningsW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77802" pm="."><plain>N. (2000). Molecular properties of bacterial multidrug transporters. Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77803" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77804" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77805" pm="."><plain>Rev. 64 672–693. 10.1128/MMBR.64.4.672-693.200011104814 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B134"><text><SENT sid="77806" pm="."><plain>RamirezJ.CartucheL.MorochoV.AguilarS.MalagonO. (2013). Antifungal activity of raw extract and flavanons isolated from Piper ecuadorense from Ecuador. Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77807" pm="."><plain>Bras. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77808" pm="."><plain>Farmacogn. 23 370–373. 10.1590/S0102-695X2013005000012 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B135"><text><SENT sid="77809" pm="."><plain>RobbinsN.CaplanT.CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77810" pm="."><plain>E. (2017). Molecular evolution of antifungal drug resistance. Annu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77811" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77812" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 71 753–775. 10.1146/annurev-micro-030117-020345 <?supplied-pmid 28886681?>28886681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B136"><text><SENT sid="77813" pm="."><plain>RochaE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77814" pm="."><plain>M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77815" pm="."><plain>F.GardinerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77816" pm="."><plain>E.ParkS.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77817" pm="."><plain>M.PerlinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77818" pm="."><plain>S. (2006). A Phe389Leu substitution in ErgA confers terbinafine resistance in Aspergillus fumigatus. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77819" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 50 2533–2536. 10.1128/AAC.00187-06 <?supplied-pmid 16801438?>16801438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B137"><text><SENT sid="77820" pm="."><plain>RookerS.GuillemaudT.BergeJ.PasteurN.RaymondM. (1996). Coamplification of esterase A and B genes as a single unit in Culex pipiens mosquitoes. Heredity 77 555–561. <?supplied-pmid 8939022?>8939022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B138"><text><SENT sid="77821" pm="."><plain>SagatovaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77822" pm="."><plain>A.KeniyaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77823" pm="."><plain>V.WilsonR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77824" pm="."><plain>K.SabherwalM.TyndallJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77825" pm="."><plain>D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77826" pm="."><plain>A.MonkB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77827" pm="."><plain>C. (2016). Triazole resistance mediated by mutations of a conserved active site tyrosine in fungal lanosterol 14 alpha-demethylase. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77828" pm="."><plain>Rep. 6:26213. 10.1038/srep26213 <?supplied-pmid 27188873?>27188873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B139"><text><SENT sid="77829" pm="."><plain>SalgueiroL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77830" pm="."><plain>R.PintoE.GoncalvesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77831" pm="."><plain>J.Pina-VazC.CavaleiroC.RodriguesA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77832" pm="."><plain>G. (2004). Chemical composition and antifungal activity of the essential oil of Thymbra capitata. Planta Med. 70 572–575. 10.1055/s-2004-827162 <?supplied-pmid 15229809?>15229809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B140"><text><SENT sid="77833" pm="."><plain>SanglardD. (2016). Emerging threats in antifungal-resistant fungal pathogens. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77834" pm="."><plain>Med. 3:11. 10.3389/fmed.2016.00011 <?supplied-pmid 27014694?>27014694 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B141"><text><SENT sid="77835" pm="."><plain>SanglardD.CosteA.FerrariS. (2009). Antifungal drug resistance mechanisms in fungal pathogens from the perspective of transcriptional gene regulation. FEMS Yeast Res. 9 1029–1050. 10.1111/j.1567-1364.2009.00578.x <?supplied-pmid 19799636?>19799636 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B142"><text><SENT sid="77836" pm="."><plain>SantosH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77837" pm="."><plain>L.LangE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77838" pm="."><plain>A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77839" pm="."><plain>S.SegatoF.RossiA.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77840" pm="."><plain>M. (2018). Terbinafine resistance conferred by multiple copies of the salicylate 1-monooxygenase gene in Trichophyton rubrum. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77841" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 56 378–381. 10.1093/mmy/myx044 <?supplied-pmid 28582544?>28582544 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B143"><text><SENT sid="77842" pm="."><plain>SantosM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77843" pm="."><plain>A.JimenezA.RevueltaJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77844" pm="."><plain>L. (2000). Molecular characterization of FMN1, the structural gene for the monofunctional flavokinase of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77845" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77846" pm="."><plain>Chem. 275 28618–28624. 10.1074/jbc.M004621200 <?supplied-pmid 10887197?>10887197 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B144"><text><SENT sid="77847" pm="."><plain>SchellW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77848" pm="."><plain>A.JonesA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77849" pm="."><plain>M.Borroto-EsodaK.AlexanderB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77850" pm="."><plain>D. (2017a). Antifungal activity of SCY-078 and standard antifungal agents against 178 clinical iisolates of resistant and susceptible Candida species. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77851" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 61:e01102-17. 10.1128/AAC.01102-17 <?supplied-pmid 28827419?>28827419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B145"><text><SENT sid="77852" pm="."><plain>SchellW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77853" pm="."><plain>A.JonesA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77854" pm="."><plain>M.GarveyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77855" pm="."><plain>P.HoekstraW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77856" pm="."><plain>J.SchotzingerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77857" pm="."><plain>J.AlexanderB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77858" pm="."><plain>D. (2017b). Fungal CYP51 inhibitors VT-1161 and VT-1129 exhibit strong in vitro activity against Candida glabrata and C. krusei isolates clinically resistant to azole and echinocandin antifungal compounds. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77859" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 61:e01817-16. 10.1128/AAC.01817-16 <?supplied-pmid 27956419?>27956419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B146"><text><SENT sid="77860" pm="."><plain>SchopfF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77861" pm="."><plain>H.BieblM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77862" pm="."><plain>M.BuchnerJ. (2017). The Hsp90 chaperone machinery. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77863" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77864" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77865" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 18 345–360. 10.1038/nrm.2017.20 <?supplied-pmid 28429788?>28429788 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B147"><text><SENT sid="77866" pm="."><plain>SegatoF.NozawaS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77867" pm="."><plain>R.RossiA.Martinez-RossiN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77868" pm="."><plain>M. (2008). Over-expression of genes coding for proline oxidase, riboflavin kinase, cytochrome c oxidase and an MFS transporter induced by acriflavin in Trichophyton rubrum. Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77869" pm="."><plain>Mycol. 46 135–139. 10.1080/13693780701742381 <?supplied-pmid 18324492?>18324492 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B148"><text><SENT sid="77870" pm="."><plain>SelmeckiA.ForcheA.BermanJ. (2010). Genomic plasticity of the human fungal pathogen Candida albicans. Eukaryot. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77871" pm="."><plain>Cell 9 991–1008. 10.1128/EC.00060-10 <?supplied-pmid 20495058?>20495058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B149"><text><SENT sid="77872" pm="."><plain>SharmaM.ManoharlalR.ShuklaS.PuriN.PrasadT.AmbudkarS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77873" pm="."><plain>V. (2009). Curcumin modulates efflux mediated by yeast ABC multidrug transporters and is synergistic with antifungals. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77874" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 53 3256–3265. 10.1128/AAC.01497-08 <?supplied-pmid 19470507?>19470507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B150"><text><SENT sid="77875" pm="."><plain>SharmaM.PrasadR. (2011). The quorum-sensing molecule farnesol is a modulator of drug efflux mediated by ABC multidrug transporters and synergizes with drugs in Candida albicans. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77876" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 55 4834–4843. 10.1128/AAC.00344-11 <?supplied-pmid 21768514?>21768514 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B151"><text><SENT sid="77877" pm="."><plain>ShubitzL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77878" pm="."><plain>F.TrinhH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77879" pm="."><plain>T.PerrillR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77880" pm="."><plain>H.ThompsonC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77881" pm="."><plain>M.HananN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77882" pm="."><plain>J.GalgianiJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77883" pm="."><plain>N. (2014). Modeling nikkomycin Z dosing and pharmacology in murine pulmonary coccidioidomycosis preparatory to phase 2 clinical trials. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77884" pm="."><plain>Infect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77885" pm="."><plain>Dis. 209 1949–1954. 10.1093/infdis/jiu029 <?supplied-pmid 24421256?>24421256 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B152"><text><SENT sid="77886" pm="."><plain>SinghG.KumarP.JoshiS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77887" pm="."><plain>C. (2014). Treatment of dermatophytosis by a new antifungal agent ’apigenin’. Mycoses 57 497–506. 10.1111/myc.12188 <?supplied-pmid 24708558?>24708558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B153"><text><SENT sid="77888" pm="."><plain>SinghS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77889" pm="."><plain>B.LiuW.LiX.ChenT.ShafieeA.CardD. (2012). Antifungal spectrum, in vivo efficacy, and structure-activity relationship of ilicicolin h. ACS Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77890" pm="."><plain>Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77891" pm="."><plain>Lett. 3 814–817. 10.1021/ml300173e <?supplied-pmid 24900384?>24900384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B154"><text><SENT sid="77892" pm="."><plain>SinghS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77893" pm="."><plain>D.RobbinsN.ZaasA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77894" pm="."><plain>K.SchellW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77895" pm="."><plain>A.PerfectJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77896" pm="."><plain>R.CowenL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77897" pm="."><plain>E. (2009). Hsp90 governs echinocandin resistance in the pathogenic yeast Candida albicans via calcineurin. PLoS Pathog. 5:e1000532. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1000532 <?supplied-pmid 19649312?>19649312 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B155"><text><SENT sid="77898" pm="."><plain>SionovE.LeeH.ChangY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77899" pm="."><plain>C.Kwon-ChungK. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77900" pm="."><plain>J. (2010). Cryptococcus neoformans overcomes stress of azole drugs by formation of disomy in specific multiple chromosomes. PLoS Pathog. 6:e1000848. 10.1371/journal.ppat.1000848 <?supplied-pmid 20368972?>20368972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B156"><text><SENT sid="77901" pm="."><plain>SokovicM.GlamoclijaJ.CiricA.KataranovskiD.MarinP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77902" pm="."><plain>D.VukojevicJ. (2008). Antifungal activity of the essential oil of Thymus vulgaris L. and thymol on experimentally induced dermatomycoses. Drug Dev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77903" pm="."><plain>Ind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77904" pm="."><plain>Pharm. 34 1388–1393. 10.1080/03639040802130053 <?supplied-pmid 18651285?>18651285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B157"><text><SENT sid="77905" pm="."><plain>SuwunnakornS.WakabayashiH.KordalewskaM.PerlinD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77906" pm="."><plain>S.RustchenkoE. (2018). FKS2 and FKS3 genes of opportunistic human pathogen Candida albicans influence echinocandin susceptibility. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77907" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 62:e02299-17. 10.1128/AAC.02299-17 <?supplied-pmid 29358288?>29358288 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B158"><text><SENT sid="77908" pm="."><plain>SvetazL.AgueroM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77909" pm="."><plain>B.AlvarezS.LunaL.FeresinG.DeritaM. (2007). Antifungal activity of Zuccagnia punctata Cav.: evidence for the mechanism of action. Planta Med. 73 1074–1080. 10.1055/s-2007-981561 <?supplied-pmid 17628836?>17628836 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B159"><text><SENT sid="77910" pm="."><plain>TaipaleM.JaroszD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77911" pm="."><plain>F.LindquistS. (2010). Hsp90 at the hub of protein homeostasis: emerging mechanistic insights. Nat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77912" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77913" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77914" pm="."><plain>Cell Biol. 11 515–528. 10.1038/nrm2918 <?supplied-pmid 20531426?>20531426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B160"><text><SENT sid="77915" pm="."><plain>TamayoD.MunozJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77916" pm="."><plain>F.TorresI.AlmeidaA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77917" pm="."><plain>J.RestrepoA.McewenJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77918" pm="."><plain>G. (2013). Involvement of the 90 kDa heat shock protein during adaptation of Paracoccidioides brasiliensis to different environmental conditions. Fungal Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77919" pm="."><plain>Biol. 51 34–41. 10.1016/j.fgb.2012.11.005 <?supplied-pmid 23207691?>23207691 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B161"><text><SENT sid="77920" pm="."><plain>TeodoroG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77921" pm="."><plain>R.EllepolaK.SeneviratneC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77922" pm="."><plain>J.Koga-ItoC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77923" pm="."><plain>Y. (2015). Potential use of phenolic acids as anti-Candida agents: a review. Front. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77924" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 6:1420 10.3389/fmicb.2015.01420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B162"><text><SENT sid="77925" pm="."><plain>TiwariS.ThakurR.ShankarJ. (2015). Role of heat-shock proteins in cellular function and in the biology of fungi. Biotechnol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77926" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77927" pm="."><plain>Int. 2015:132635. 10.1155/2015/132635 <?supplied-pmid 26881084?>26881084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B163"><text><SENT sid="77928" pm="."><plain>TomoikeF.NakagawaN.FukuiK.YanoT.KuramitsuS.MasuiR. (2017). Indispensable residue for uridine binding in the uridine-cytidine kinase family. Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77929" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77930" pm="."><plain>Rep. 11 93–98. 10.1016/j.bbrep.2017.07.002 <?supplied-pmid 28955773?>28955773 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B164"><text><SENT sid="77931" pm="."><plain>UeharaY. (2003). Natural product origins of Hsp90 inhibitors. Curr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77932" pm="."><plain>Cancer Drug Targets 3 325–330. 10.2174/1568009033481796 <?supplied-pmid 14529384?>14529384 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B165"><text><SENT sid="77933" pm="."><plain>WadlerC.CronanJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77934" pm="."><plain>E. (2007). Dephospho-CoA kinase provides a rapid and sensitive radiochemical assay for coenzyme A and its thioesters. Anal. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77935" pm="."><plain>Biochem. 368 17–23. 10.1016/j.ab.2007.05.031 <?supplied-pmid 17603993?>17603993 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B166"><text><SENT sid="77936" pm="."><plain>WangY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77937" pm="."><plain>H.DongH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77938" pm="."><plain>H.ZhaoF.WangJ.YanF.JiangY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77939" pm="."><plain>Y. (2016). The synthesis and synergistic antifungal effects of chalcones against drug resistant Candida albicans. Bioorg. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77940" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77941" pm="."><plain>Chem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77942" pm="."><plain>Lett. 26 3098–3102. 10.1016/j.bmcl.2016.05.013 <?supplied-pmid 27210436?>27210436 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B167"><text><SENT sid="77943" pm="."><plain>WarrilowA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77944" pm="."><plain>G. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77945" pm="."><plain>S.HullC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77946" pm="."><plain>M.ParkerJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77947" pm="."><plain>E.GarveyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77948" pm="."><plain>P.HoekstraW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77949" pm="."><plain>J.MooreW. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77950" pm="."><plain>R. (2014). The clinical candidate VT-1161 is a highly potent inhibitor of Candida albicans CYP51 but fails to bind the human enzyme. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77951" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 58 7121–7127. 10.1128/AAC.03707-14 <?supplied-pmid 25224009?>25224009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B168"><text><SENT sid="77952" pm="."><plain>WidmannC.GibsonS.JarpeM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77953" pm="."><plain>B.JohnsonG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77954" pm="."><plain>L. (1999). Mitogen-activated protein kinase: conservation of a three-kinase module from yeast to human. Physiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77955" pm="."><plain>Rev. 79 143–180. 10.1152/physrev.1999.79.1.143 <?supplied-pmid 9922370?>9922370 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B169"><text><SENT sid="77956" pm="."><plain>WiederholdN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77957" pm="."><plain>P.PattersonH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77958" pm="."><plain>P.TranB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77959" pm="."><plain>H.YatesC. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77960" pm="."><plain>M.SchotzingerR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77961" pm="."><plain>J.GarveyE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77962" pm="."><plain>P. (2018a). Fungal-specific Cyp51 inhibitor VT-1598 demonstrates in vitro activity against Candida and Cryptococcus species, endemic fungi, including Coccidioides species, Aspergillus species and Rhizopus arrhizus. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77963" pm="."><plain>Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77964" pm="."><plain>Chemother. 73 404–408. 10.1093/jac/dkx410 <?supplied-pmid 29190379?>29190379 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B170"><text><SENT sid="77965" pm="."><plain>WiederholdN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77966" pm="."><plain>P.ShubitzL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77967" pm="."><plain>F.NajvarL. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77968" pm="."><plain>K.JaramilloR.OlivoM.CatanoG. (2018b). The novel fungal Cyp51 inhibitor VT-1598 is efficacious in experimental models of central nervous system coccidioidomycosis caused by Coccidioides posadasii and Coccidioides immitis. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77969" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 62:e02258-17. 10.1128/AAC.02258-17 <?supplied-pmid 29437615?>29437615 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B171"><text><SENT sid="77970" pm="."><plain>WoodfolkJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77971" pm="."><plain>A.Platts-MillsT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77972" pm="."><plain>A. (2001). Diversity of the human allergen-specific T cell repertoire associated with distinct skin test reactions: delayed-type hypersensitivity-associated major epitopes induce Th1- and Th2-dominated responses. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77973" pm="."><plain>Immunol. 167 5412–5419. 10.4049/jimmunol.167.9.5412 <?supplied-pmid 11673560?>11673560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B172"><text><SENT sid="77974" pm="."><plain>XiongJ.FengJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77975" pm="."><plain>M.YuanD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77976" pm="."><plain>X.ZhouJ.MiaoW. (2015). Tracing the structural evolution of eukaryotic ATP binding cassette transporter superfamily. Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77977" pm="."><plain>Rep. 5:16724. 10.1038/srep16724 <?supplied-pmid 26577702?>26577702 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B173"><text><SENT sid="77978" pm="."><plain>YamadaT.MaedaM.AlshahniM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77979" pm="."><plain>M.TanakaR.YaguchiT.BontemsO. (2017). Terbinafine resistance of Trichophyton clinical isolates caused by specific point mutations in the squalene epoxidase gene. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77980" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 61:e00115-17. 10.1128/AAC.00115-17 <?supplied-pmid 28416557?>28416557 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B174"><text><SENT sid="77981" pm="."><plain>YibmantasiriP.BirchamP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77982" pm="."><plain>W.MaassD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77983" pm="."><plain>R.BellowsD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77984" pm="."><plain>S.AtkinsonP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77985" pm="."><plain>H. (2014). Networks of genes modulating the pleiotropic drug response in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77986" pm="."><plain>Biosyst. 10 128–137. 10.1039/c3mb70351g <?supplied-pmid 24201294?>24201294 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B175"><text><SENT sid="77987" pm="."><plain>YuL.ZhangW.LiuT.WangX.PengJ.LiS. (2007a). Global gene expression of Trichophyton rubrum in response to PH11B, a novel fatty acid synthase inhibitor. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77988" pm="."><plain>Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77989" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 103 2346–2352. <?supplied-pmid 18045420?>18045420 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B176"><text><SENT sid="77990" pm="."><plain>YuL.ZhangW.WangL.YangJ.LiuT.PengJ. (2007b). Transcriptional profiles of the response to ketoconazole and amphotericin B in Trichophyton rubrum. Antimicrob. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77991" pm="."><plain>Agents Chemother. 51 144–153. <?supplied-pmid 17060531?>17060531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B177"><text><SENT sid="77992" pm="."><plain>YunJ.LeeH.KoH. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77993" pm="."><plain>J.WooE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77994" pm="."><plain>R.LeeD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77995" pm="."><plain>G. (2015). Fungicidal effect of isoquercitrin via inducing membrane disturbance. Biochim. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77996" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77997" pm="."><plain>Acta 1848 695–701. 10.1016/j.bbamem.2014.11.019 <?supplied-pmid 25445674?>25445674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B178"><text><SENT sid="77998" pm="."><plain>ZhangW.YuL.LengW.WangX.WangL.DengX. (2007). cDNA microarray analysis of the expression profiles of Trichophyton rubrum in response to novel synthetic fatty acid synthase inhibitor PHS11A. Fungal Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77999" pm="."><plain>Biol. 44 1252–1261. 10.1016/j.fgb.2007.03.002 <?supplied-pmid 17442600?>17442600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B179"><text><SENT sid="78000" pm="."><plain>ZhangW.YuL.YangJ.WangL.PengJ.JinQ. (2009). Transcriptional profiles of response to terbinafine in Trichophyton rubrum. Appl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78001" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78002" pm="."><plain>Biotechnol. 82 1123–1130. 10.1007/s00253-009-1908-9 <?supplied-pmid 19234875?>19234875 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B180"><text><SENT sid="78003" pm="."><plain>ZhaoR.DaveyM.HsuY. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78004" pm="."><plain>C.KaplanekP.TongA.ParsonsA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78005" pm="."><plain>B. (2005). Navigating the chaperone network: an integrative map of physical and genetic interactions mediated by the Hsp90 chaperone. Cell 120 715–727. 10.1016/j.cell.2004.12.024 <?supplied-pmid 15766533?>15766533 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B181"><text><SENT sid="78006" pm="."><plain>ZuzarteM.GoncalvesM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78007" pm="."><plain>J.CavaleiroC.CanhotoJ.Vale-SilvaL.SilvaM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78008" pm="."><plain>J. (2011). Chemical composition and antifungal activity of the essential oils of Lavandula viridis L’Her. J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78009" pm="."><plain>Med. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78010" pm="."><plain>Microbiol. 60 612–618. 10.1099/jmm.0.027748-0 <?supplied-pmid 21321363?>21321363 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
