<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jexbot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5014156</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/erw273</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="44953" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide identification and characterization of TCP genes involved in ovule development of Phalaenopsis equestris </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Yu-Fu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>You-Yi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>Yu-Yun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>Ching-Yu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>Jui-Ling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yeh</surname><given-names>Chuan-Ming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mitsuda</surname><given-names>Nobutaka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0006">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ohme-Takagi</surname><given-names>Masaru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0005">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0006">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Zhong-Jian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0007">
<sup>7</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0008">
<sup>8</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Wen-Chieh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="AF0001"><sup>1</sup><institution>Institute of Tropical Plant Sciences, National Cheng Kung University</institution>, <addr-line>Tainan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="AF0002"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Life Sciences</institution>, <institution>National Cheng Kung University</institution>, <addr-line>Tainan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="AF0003"><sup>3</sup><institution>Orchid Research and Development Center, National Cheng Kung University</institution>, <addr-line>Tainan</addr-line>, <country>Taiwan</country></aff><aff id="AF0004"><sup>4</sup><institution>Shenzhen Key Laboratory for Orchid Conservation and Utilization, The National Orchid Conservation Center of China and The Orchid Conservation and Research Center of Shenzhen</institution>, <addr-line>Shenzhen</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="AF0005"><sup>5</sup><institution>Division of Strategic Research and Development, Graduate School of Science and Engineering, Satitama University</institution>, <addr-line>Saitama</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AF0006"><sup>6</sup><institution>Research Institute of Bioproduction, National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology</institution>, <addr-line>Tsukuba</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="AF0007"><sup>7</sup><institution>The Center for Biotechnology and BioMedicine, Graduate School at Shenzhen, Tsinghua University</institution>, <addr-line>Shenzhen</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="AF0008"><sup>8</sup><institution>College of Forestry, South China Agricultural University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">* Correspondence: <email>tsaiwc@mail.ncku.edu.tw</email></corresp><fn id="fn-100"><p><text><SENT sid="44954" pm="."><plain>Editor: Peter Bozhkov, Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>9</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>67</volume><issue>17</issue><fpage>5051</fpage><lpage>5066</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2016. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="precis"><title><text><SENT sid="44955" pm="."><plain>Highlight </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="44956" pm="."><plain>Of twenty-three TCP genes identified from the genome of Phalaenopsis orchid, PePCF10 and PeCIN8 play important roles in orchid ovule development by modulating cell division. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="44957" pm="."><plain>TEOSINTE-BRANCHED/CYCLOIDEA/PCF (TCP) proteins are plant-specific transcription factors known to have a role in multiple aspects of plant growth and development at the cellular, organ and tissue levels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44958" pm="."><plain>However, there has been no related study of TCPs in orchids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44959" pm="."><plain>Here we identified 23 TCP genes from the genome sequence of Phalaenopsis equestris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44960" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis distinguished two homology classes of PeTCP transcription factor families: classes I and II. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44961" pm="."><plain>Class II was further divided into two subclasses, CIN and CYC/TB1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44962" pm="."><plain>Spatial and temporal expression analysis showed that PePCF10 was predominantly expressed in ovules at early developmental stages and PeCIN8 had high expression at late developmental stages in ovules, with overlapping expression at day 16 after pollination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44963" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization and protein–protein interaction analyses revealed that PePCF10 and PeCIN8 could form homodimers and localize in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44964" pm="."><plain>However, PePCF10 and PeCIN8 could not form heterodimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44965" pm="."><plain>In transgenic Arabidopsis thaliana plants (overexpression and SRDX, a super repression motif derived from the EAR-motif of the repression domain of tobacco ETHYLENE-RESPONSIVE ELEMENT-BINDING FACTOR 3 and SUPERMAN, dominantly repressed), the two genes helped regulate cell proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44966" pm="."><plain>Together, these results suggest that PePCF10 and PeCIN8 play important roles in orchid ovule development by modulating cell division. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>Key words:</title><kwd>Cell proliferation</kwd><kwd>functional characterization</kwd><kwd>genome-wide identification</kwd><kwd>ovule development</kwd><kwd><italic>Phalaenopsis equestris</italic></kwd><kwd>TEOSINTE-BRANCHED/CYCLOIDEA/PCF (TCP) proteins.</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source>Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan
<named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100004663</named-content></funding-source><award-id>NSC 99-2311-B-006-004-MY3</award-id><award-id>103-2313-B-006-001-MY3</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="44967" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44968" pm="."><plain>Plant architecture and organ shape depends on complex coordination of cell proliferation and cell differentiation in response to genetic and environmental cues (Ingram and Waite, 2006; Kieffer et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44969" pm="."><plain>The final shape of shoot lateral organs, leaves and flowers is determined by coordinated growth after the initiation of primordia from shoot meristems in seed plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44970" pm="."><plain>This coordination involves the complex behavior of many transcription factors (TFs). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="44971" pm="."><plain>The TCP gene family was first described in 1999 and named after the first three characterized members, TEOSINTE BRANCHED1 (TB1) in maize, CYCLOIDEA (CYC) in snapdragon, and Proliferating Cell Factor (PCF) in rice (Cubas et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44972" pm="."><plain>They are ancient plant-specific TFs that originated near the base of streptophytes about 650–800 million years ago (Mondragon-Palomino and Trontin, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44973" pm="."><plain>From amino acid sequence similarity of the TCP domain, TCP proteins can be divided into two major classes: class I (also known as the PCF or TCP-P class) and class II (also known as the TCP-C class) (Martín-Trillo and Cubas, 2010; Manassero et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44974" pm="."><plain>TCP class II is further subdivided into the CINCINNATA (CIN) and CYC/TB1 subclades. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44975" pm="."><plain>In addition, several class II TCP members share an arginine-rich R domain and an ECE motif (a glutamic acid–cysteine–glutamic acid stretch), both of unknown biological function (Martín-Trillo and Cubas, 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="44976" pm="."><plain>The TCP family of plant-specific TFs controls multiple traits in diverse plant species by controlling cell proliferation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44977" pm="."><plain>This control includes regulation of lateral branching, leaf development and senescence, flower development, gametophyte development, embryo growth, seed germination, circadian rhythm, hormone pathways and mitochondrial biogenesis (Aguilar-Martinez et al., 2007; Koyama et al., 2007; Martín-Trillo and Cubas, 2010; Aguilar-Martinez and Sinha, 2013; Balsemão-Pires et al., 2013; Manassero et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44978" pm="."><plain>Class I genes are suggested to promote plant growth and proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44979" pm="."><plain>The Arabidopsis multiple mutants (AtTCP8, 15, 21, 22, and 23) have fewer but larger leaves (Aguilar-Martinez and Sinha, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44980" pm="."><plain>However, most class I single mutants analysed have mild or no phenotypic defects, probably due to genetic redundancy (Martín-Trillo and Cubas, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44981" pm="."><plain>Class II genes are involved in lateral organ development, including CIN in snapdragon and CYC/TB1 clade genes controlling axillary meristem development, such as TB1 in maize (Lopez et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44982" pm="."><plain>In Arabidospsis, a group of CIN-type genes (AtTCP3, 4, 5, 10, and 13) functions redundantly to control shoot lateral organ morphology by negative regulation of boundary-specific genes (Koyama et al., 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="44983" pm="."><plain>Orchidaceae is one of the largest families among the angiosperms, consisting of about 850 genera with 25 000 species (Dressler, 1993). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44984" pm="."><plain>They are well known for their broad geographic distribution, tremendous diversity in plant forms and growth habits, extraordinary diversity in flower morphology within the framework of a relatively conserved structure, initiation of ovule development precisely regulated by pollination, and high value of hybrids as a floricultural commodity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44985" pm="."><plain>Despite the economic and biological significance of orchids, and the importance of TCP TFs in controlling floral architecture, the relationship between the function of TCP genes, flower morphology and reproductive development remains poorly understood in this family. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="44986" pm="."><plain>Recently, the whole genome of the orchid Phalaenopsis equestris was sequenced (Cai et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44987" pm="."><plain>The information provides a great opportunity to identify and characterize TCP TFs in orchid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44988" pm="."><plain>In this study, we identified 23 non-redundant genes encoding TCP TFs in the genome of P. equestris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44989" pm="."><plain>Systematic analysis including phylogenetic analysis and expression profiling was performed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44990" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, a class I PCF-like gene, PePCF10, and a class II CIN-like gene, PeCIN8, were functionally characterized by cellular localization, protein–protein interaction and, in transgenic Arabidopsis, by gain-of-function and loss-of-function constructs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44991" pm="."><plain>Our findings indicate that the two genes play important roles in orchid ovule development by modulating cell division. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="44992" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="44993" pm="."><plain>Accession numbers </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44994" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide sequences reported in this paper have been submitted to GenBank under the following accession numbers: PePCF1, KT258871; PePCF2, KT258872; PePCF3, KT258873; PePCF4, KT258874; PePCF5, KT258875; PePCF6, KT258876; PePCF7, KT258877; PePCF8, KT228878; PePCF9, KT258879; PePCF10, KT258880; PePCF11, KT258881; PeCIN1, KT258882; PeCIN2, KT258883; PeCIN3, KT258884; PeCIN4, KT258885; PeCIN5, KT258886; PeCIN6, KT258887; PeCIN7, KT258888; PeCIN8, KT258889; PeCIN9, KT258890; PeCYC1, KT258891; PeCYC2, KT258892; PeCYC3, KT258893. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="44995" pm="."><plain>Plant material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44996" pm="."><plain>Phalaenopsis plants were grown in a greenhouse at National Cheng Kung University (NCKU) under natural light (photosynthetic photon-flux density 90 μmol m–2 s–1) and controlled temperature (23–27 °C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="44997" pm="."><plain>RNA preparation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44998" pm="."><plain>The flower of Phalaenopsis equestris has two main petals with three sepals behind them. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44999" pm="."><plain>The median petal is highly modified into an enlarged petal, called a lip or labellum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45000" pm="."><plain>The male and female reproductive parts are fused in a structure, the gynostemium or column, located at the center of the flower (see Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45001" pm="."><plain>Definition of the developing flower bud stage (stage 1: 0–1mm; stage 2: 1–2mm; stage 3: 2–5mm; stage 4: 5–10mm; Fig. 3B) is based on the description by Tsai et al. (2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45002" pm="."><plain>Morphological changes in the ovary and ovule development at various days after pollination (DAP) is based on the description by Chen et al. (2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45003" pm="."><plain>For RNA extraction, samples were collected, immersed in liquid nitrogen, and stored at –80 °C as described (Tsai et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="45004" pm="."><plain>Sequence retrieval for TCP proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45005" pm="."><plain>The conserved TCP DNA-binding domain based on the hidden Markov model (HMM) (PF03634) was obtained from the Pfam protein family database (http://pfam.sanger.ac.uk). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45006" pm="."><plain>To identify the TCP TF coding genes of P. equestris, the HHM profile of the TCP domain was used as a query for an HMMER search (http://hmmer.janelia.org/) of the P. equestris genome sequence (Cai et al., 2015) (E-value=0.00001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45007" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, to verify the reliability of the results, all candidate TCP sequences were analysed to confirm the presence of the conserved TCP domain by using InterproScan (Quevillon et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45008" pm="."><plain>The sequences of TCP family members in the genome of Arabidopsis and Oryza sativa were retrieved from the PlantTFDB TF database (http://planttfdb.cbi.pku.edu.cn/, v3.0). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><text><SENT sid="45009" pm="."><plain>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45010" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment of the amino acid sequences of TCP proteins in P. equestris, Arabidopsis and rice genomes involved use of Clustal W (Thompson et al., 1994) with default settings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45011" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, MEGA 4.0 (Tamura et al., 2007) was used to construct an unrooted phylogenetic tree based on alignments with the neighbor-joining method and the parameters JTTmodel, pairwise gap deletion and 1000 bootstraps. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s8"><title><text><SENT sid="45012" pm="."><plain>Real-time quantitative RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45013" pm="."><plain>RNA samples were treated with RNase-free DNase (New England Biolabs, Hitchin, UK) to remove remnant DNA, then underwent synthesis of first-strand cDNA by the use of the SuperScript III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45014" pm="."><plain>Gene-specific primers for PeTCP genes were designed with the use of Primer Express (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) and are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link> at JXB online. PeActin4 (5′-TTGTGAGCAACTGGGATG-3′ and 5′-GCCACGCGAAGTTCATTG-3′) and 18S rRNA (5′-TTAGGCCACGGAAGTTTGAG-3′ and 5′-ACACTTCACCG GACCATTCAA-3′) (Lin et al., 2014) were used as internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45015" pm="."><plain>Each real-time RT-PCR contained 5ng of cDNA, 20mM primers and 12.5ml of SYBR GREEN PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems), and water was added to 25ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45016" pm="."><plain>Real-time PCR involved use of the ABI 7 500 Real-Time PCR Instrument (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45017" pm="."><plain>For each real-time RT-PCR, each sample was analysed in triplicate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45018" pm="."><plain>Data were analysed by the use of the Sequencing Detection System v1.2.3 (Applied Biosystems). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45019" pm="."><plain>The software MultiExperiment Viewer was used to construct heatmap representations for expression patterns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s9"><title><text><SENT sid="45020" pm="."><plain>Whole-mount in situ hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45021" pm="."><plain>Phalaenopsis equestris inflorescences were fixed in 4% (v/v) paraformaldehyde and 0.5% (v/v) glutaraldehyde for 24h at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45022" pm="."><plain>They were dehydrated through a graded ethanol series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45023" pm="."><plain>Digoxigenin-labeled sense and antisense RNA probes containing a partial C-terminal region and 3′-UTR were synthesized following the manufacturer’s instructions (Roche Applied Science). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45024" pm="."><plain>Hybridization and immunological detection of the signals with alkaline phosphatase were as described by Traas (2008). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s10"><title><text><SENT sid="45025" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45026" pm="."><plain>Template-specific primers were designed by addition of attB1 adapter primer (5′-GGGGACAAGTTTGTACAA AAA AGCAGGCTCCACC-3′) to the 5′ end of the first 18–25 nt of each open reading frame (ORF), and attB2 adapter primer (5′-GGGGACCA CTTTGTACAAGAAAGCTGGGTT-3′) to the 3′ end of the first 18–25 nt of each ORF, which generated the full-length attB1 and attB2 sites flanking the ORFs (S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45027" pm="."><plain>Gateway-compatible amplified ORFs were recombined into the pDONR 221 vector (Invitrogen) by BP cloning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45028" pm="."><plain>BP reactions were used directly for bacterial transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45029" pm="."><plain>Entry clones were used for transformation of E. coli DH5α cells, and bacteria were plated on LB medium containing kanamycin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45030" pm="."><plain>These entry clones were set up in LR reactions for recombining target genes into the destination vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45031" pm="."><plain>The 35S promoter-driven green fluorescent protein (GFP)-fusion construct for protoplast transfection was created by use of the high-copy plasmid p2GWF7, with C-terminal fusion (Karimi et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45032" pm="."><plain>Entry clones were used for generation of GFP-tagged clones. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45033" pm="."><plain>Then, the LR reactions were used for transformation of E. coli DH5α. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45034" pm="."><plain>Transformants were selected on plates containing ampicillin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45035" pm="."><plain>The plasmids were transfected into Phalaenopsis protoplasts by PEG transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45036" pm="."><plain>Signals were visualized by confocal laser microscopy (Carl Zeiss LSM780, Jena, Germany). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s11"><title><text><SENT sid="45037" pm="."><plain>Bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) assay </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45038" pm="."><plain>Gateway-compatible vectors [pSAT5(A)-DEST-cEYFP-N1 and pSAT5-DEST-cEYFP-C1(B) (Lin et al., 2014)] were used to generate expression vectors by a Gateway cloning strategy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45039" pm="."><plain>The N-terminus of yellow florescent protein (YFP) (YN) was cloned upstream of PePCF10 and PeCIN8 in the pE-SPYNE vector, and the C-terminus of yellow florescent protein (YC), was fused upstream of PePCF10 and PeCIN8 in the pE-SPYCE vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45040" pm="."><plain>The signals were visualized by confocal laser microscopy (Carl Zeiss LSM780). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s12"><title><text><SENT sid="45041" pm="."><plain>Yeast two-hybrid analysis and Quantification of β-galactosidase activity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45042" pm="."><plain>For the yeast two-hybrid, the full-length coding sequences of PePCF10 and PeCIN8 were cloned into either pGBKT7 bait vector (fused with Gal4 DNA-binding domain; BD) or pGADT7 prey vector (fused with GAL4 activation domain (AD), Clontech, http://clontech.com). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45043" pm="."><plain>The constructs were verified by sequencing and co-transformed into yeast strain Y187. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45044" pm="."><plain>To test for interactions, the bait and prey constructs were co-expressed in yeast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45045" pm="."><plain>The yeast cells were plated on selection medium containing SD/–Trp–Leu and then incubated in a growth chamber at 30 °C for 2–5 d (Li et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45046" pm="."><plain>All primers used for cloning are listed in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>. β-Galactosidase activity from cotransformed yeast was measured using the o-nitrophenyl β-D-galactopyranoside assay, where o-nitrophenyl produced from cleavage of o-nitrophenyl β-D-galactopyranoside by β-galactosidase was detected by spectrophotometry (Li et al., 2011, Li &amp; Zachgo, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45047" pm="."><plain>For systematically analysing interaction behavior of PePCF10, PePCF10 was cloned into pDEST_GBKT7 bait vector, which was retrieved from Arabidopsis Biological Resource Center (ABRC) from the Gateway entry clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45048" pm="."><plain>The Y2H Gold yeast strain (Takara Bio Inc.) was employed for the assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45049" pm="."><plain>After selecting the yeast harboring bait plasmid, prey plasmids constructed on pDEST_GAD424 vector (Mitsuda et al., 2010) were additionally transformed and spotted onto positive control medium, which lacks leucine and tryptophan, and test medium, which lacks histidine, leucine, and tryptophan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45050" pm="."><plain>Yeast growth was observed daily for several days. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s13"><title><text><SENT sid="45051" pm="."><plain>Construction of transformed fusions and Arabidopsis transformation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45052" pm="."><plain>cDNA fragments containing the coding regions of PePCF10 and PeCIN8 were cloned into the pBI121 vector (primers are in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45053" pm="."><plain>The constructs were then introduced into Agrobacterium tumefaciens (strain GV3101). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45054" pm="."><plain>To construct the transgene for the chimeric repressor, the coding sequences of PePCF10 and PeCIN8, except for the stop codon (primers are in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Table S1</ext-link>), were cloned into the SmaI site of p35SSRDXG in-frame to the region that encodes the SRDX repression domain (LDLDLELRLGFA) from SUPERMAN (Hiratsu et al., 2002, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45055" pm="."><plain>p35SSRDXG contains a CaMV 35S promoter followed by an Ω translation enhancer sequence, the SRDX repression domain sequence, Nos terminator and the attL1 and attL2 Gateway recombination sites (Invitrogen) outside the regions of the 35S promoter and the Nos terminator in the pUC119 vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45056" pm="."><plain>The transgene cassette was transferred into the destination vector pBCKK by the Gateway LR clonase reaction (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45057" pm="."><plain>Each gene was used to transform Arabidopsis thaliana Col-0 by the floral dip method, as described previously (Clough and Bent, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45058" pm="."><plain>To select transformed Arabidopsis, seeds (T0) were screened on media supplemented with 50 µg ml–1 kanamycin (Sigma-Aldrich). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45059" pm="."><plain>After a 2-week selection, the kanamycin-resistant seedlings (T1) were transferred to soil and grown under the conditions described previously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45060" pm="."><plain>Kanamycin segregation in the T1 generation was analysed by use of chi-square test. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45061" pm="."><plain>The homozygous, kanamycin-resistant T2 generation was used to confirm the integration fragment by PCR for each construct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45062" pm="."><plain>Transformed lines with segregation ratio 3:1 were collected for analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s14"><title><text><SENT sid="45063" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45064" pm="."><plain>Leaves and flowers were frozen by liquid nitrogen and observed by scanning electron microscopy (Hitachi TM3000, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45065" pm="."><plain>The data were analysed by using ImageJ (http://rsb.info.nih.gov/ij/). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s15"><title><text><SENT sid="45066" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s16"><title><text><SENT sid="45067" pm="."><plain>Identification and sequence analyses of TCP genes from P. equestris </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45068" pm="."><plain>To identify TCP TF coding genes, the HMM profile of the TCP domain (PF03634) was blast searched in the P. equestris genome (Cai et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45069" pm="."><plain>Full-length sequences of 23 TCP family genes were identified from the genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45070" pm="."><plain>All candidate TCP genes were confirmed to encode the conserved TCP domain with the use of InterproScan (Quevillon et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45071" pm="."><plain>The mean length of the 23 TCP TFs was 307 amino acids (range 220–425 amino acids). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45072" pm="."><plain>Other characteristics, including isoelectric point, molecular mass, and location at Phalaenopsis scaffolds are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="TABLE"><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45073" pm="."><plain>TCP gene family in Phalaenopsis equestris </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45074" pm="."><plain>Gene Name </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45075" pm="."><plain>Length (a.a.) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45076" pm="."><plain>Molecular mass (Da) </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45077" pm="."><plain>pI </plain></SENT>
</text></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45078" pm="."><plain>Scaffold location </plain></SENT>
</text></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45079" pm="."><plain>PePCF1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45080" pm="."><plain>253 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45081" pm="."><plain>26 846.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45082" pm="."><plain>5.71 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45083" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000123:1543921~1544682 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45084" pm="."><plain>PePCF2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45085" pm="."><plain>289 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45086" pm="."><plain>30 740.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45087" pm="."><plain>7.96 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45088" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000865:254675~255534 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45089" pm="."><plain>PePCF3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45090" pm="."><plain>333 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45091" pm="."><plain>34 736.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45092" pm="."><plain>9.51 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45093" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000927:176~1177 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45094" pm="."><plain>PePCF4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45095" pm="."><plain>301 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45096" pm="."><plain>31 308.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45097" pm="."><plain>9.09 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45098" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000053:108817~109722 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45099" pm="."><plain>PePCF5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45100" pm="."><plain>303 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45101" pm="."><plain>32 070.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45102" pm="."><plain>6.26 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45103" pm="."><plain>Scaffold001019:11294~12205 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45104" pm="."><plain>PePCF6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45105" pm="."><plain>251 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45106" pm="."><plain>27 085.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45107" pm="."><plain>6.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45108" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000382:232040~232795 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45109" pm="."><plain>PePCF7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45110" pm="."><plain>257 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45111" pm="."><plain>27 559.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45112" pm="."><plain>6.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45113" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000552:2647726~2648558 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45114" pm="."><plain>PePCF8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45115" pm="."><plain>230 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45116" pm="."><plain>24 376.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45117" pm="."><plain>9.24 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45118" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000002:70407263~70407955 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45119" pm="."><plain>PePCF9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45120" pm="."><plain>274 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45121" pm="."><plain>27 428.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45122" pm="."><plain>9.74 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45123" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000002:66457383~66457997 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45124" pm="."><plain>PePCF10 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45125" pm="."><plain>370 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45126" pm="."><plain>38 951.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45127" pm="."><plain>7.93 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45128" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000058: 217817~218940 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45129" pm="."><plain>PePCF11 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45130" pm="."><plain>274 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45131" pm="."><plain>29 655.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45132" pm="."><plain>8.75 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45133" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000349:250533~251358 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45134" pm="."><plain>PeCIN1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45135" pm="."><plain>392 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45136" pm="."><plain>42 192 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45137" pm="."><plain>6.65 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45138" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000552:3228304~3229491 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45139" pm="."><plain>PeCIN2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45140" pm="."><plain>372 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45141" pm="."><plain>40 543.5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45142" pm="."><plain>9.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45143" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000272:914770~915888 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45144" pm="."><plain>PeCIN3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45145" pm="."><plain>363 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45146" pm="."><plain>40 087.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45147" pm="."><plain>8.79 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45148" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000113:35591~36682 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45149" pm="."><plain>PeCIN4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45150" pm="."><plain>277 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45151" pm="."><plain>30 765.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45152" pm="."><plain>7.79 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45153" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000404:25049~25882 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45154" pm="."><plain>PeCIN5 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45155" pm="."><plain>292 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45156" pm="."><plain>32 589.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45157" pm="."><plain>6.38 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45158" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000873:1549183~1550061 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45159" pm="."><plain>PeCIN6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45160" pm="."><plain>425 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45161" pm="."><plain>44 992.4 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45162" pm="."><plain>9.89 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45163" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000428:5478841~5480211 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45164" pm="."><plain>PeCIN7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45165" pm="."><plain>324 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45166" pm="."><plain>35 144.8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45167" pm="."><plain>6.7 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45168" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000198:252605~253579 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45169" pm="."><plain>PeCIN8 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45170" pm="."><plain>220 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45171" pm="."><plain>24 505.2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45172" pm="."><plain>6.21 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45173" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000180:1361454~1362116 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45174" pm="."><plain>PeCIN9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45175" pm="."><plain>310 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45176" pm="."><plain>34 721.9 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45177" pm="."><plain>7.84 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45178" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000408:191611~192543 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45179" pm="."><plain>PeCYC1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45180" pm="."><plain>288 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45181" pm="."><plain>32 774.3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45182" pm="."><plain>8.94 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45183" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000878:1078313~1079179 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45184" pm="."><plain>PeCYC2 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45185" pm="."><plain>334 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45186" pm="."><plain>37 454.1 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45187" pm="."><plain>9.07 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45188" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000428:1243571~1244575 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45189" pm="."><plain>PeCYC3 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45190" pm="."><plain>326 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45191" pm="."><plain>36 663.6 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45192" pm="."><plain>9.06 </plain></SENT>
</text></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><text><SENT sid="45193" pm="."><plain>Scaffold000428:1253199~1254179 </plain></SENT>
</text></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></SecTag></sec><sec id="s17"><title><text><SENT sid="45194" pm="."><plain>Sequence comparison and phylogenetic analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45195" pm="."><plain>On multiple sequence alignment of the 23 PeTCP proteins, the sequences were found to encode a putative TCP-domain protein that contains a basic helix–loop–helix-type motif at the N-terminus (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45196" pm="."><plain>Orchid TCP proteins could be divided into two subfamilies, as for all species so far (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45197" pm="."><plain>The PCF or class I subfamily members showed an extended homology C-terminus from the TCP domain, and the class II subfamily had, as reported earlier, an extended four amino acids in the basic region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45198" pm="."><plain>In addition, both subfamilies showed internally conserved but distinct loop region sequences (Cubas et al., 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45199" pm="."><plain>According to this division, 11 genes belonged to the class I subfamily and 12 to the class II subfamily in the Phalaenopsis orchid genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45200" pm="."><plain>The result is also supported by the phylogenetic analysis (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45201" pm="."><plain>In addition, the class II subfamily could be further divided into two subclades, class IIa or CYC/TB1 and class IIb or CIN (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45202" pm="."><plain>The CYC/TB1 subclade contains the three orchid genes PeCYC1, PeCYC2, and PeCYC3 and CIN includes nine members, PeCIN1– PeCIN9 (Figs 1A and 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45203" pm="."><plain>Multiple alignment of TCP protein sequences for Phalaenopsis equestris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45204" pm="."><plain>(A) Alignment of the TCP domain and adjoining sequence for the predicted orchid TCP proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45205" pm="."><plain>Overall conserved amino acids are in black. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45206" pm="."><plain>(B) Alignment of the R-domain of class II subfamily members. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45207" pm="."><plain>(C) Alignment of putative areas for miR319. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0001"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45208" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic relationships of TCP transcription factors from P. equestris, Arabidopsis and rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45209" pm="."><plain>The unrooted phylogenetic tree was created with MEGA 4.0 by the neighbor-joining method and the bootstrap test involved 1000 iterations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45210" pm="."><plain>Blue, red and green lines indicate the PCF, CIN and CYC/TB1clades, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0002"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45211" pm="."><plain>Previous reports showed that Arabidopsis class II CYC/TB1 genes AtTCP1, AtTCP12, and AtTCP18 as well as CIN genes AtTCP2 and AtTCP24 contain the R-domain at the C-terminus of the TCP domain (Yao et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45212" pm="."><plain>In Phalaenopsis, all three genes PeCYC1, PeCYC2, and PeCYC3 in CYC/TB1 and one gene, PeCIN3, in the CIN subclade encode proteins with the R-domain (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45213" pm="."><plain>In addition, in Arabidopsis, five of the CIN members are post-transcriptionally regulated by miRNA319 (AtTCP2, 3, 4, 10, and 24) (Palatnik et al., 2003, 2007; Ori et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45214" pm="."><plain>Six orchid TCP genes in the CIN subclade were identified to have a putative binding site for Phalaenopsis miR319 (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45215" pm="."><plain>This finding suggests the regulation of leaf development by a redundant set of miRNA-regulated homologous TCP genes in orchid. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45216" pm="."><plain>To determine the phylogenetic relationships of PeTCP and other TCP genes, we reconstructed the phylogeny for the known TCP family using the conceptual amino acid sequences of the respective genes as input data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45217" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic analysis of the putative protein with TCP proteins from Arabidopsis (Arabidopsis thaliana), rice (Oryza sativa), and Phalaenopsis (P. equestris) distinguished two types of TCP proteins based on differences within their TCP domains: class I and class II (Figs 1A and 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45218" pm="."><plain>In addition, PeCIN5 and PeCIN9 as well as PeCYC1, PeCYC2, and PeCYC3 may be duplicated genes in orchid (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45219" pm="."><plain>Pairwise alignment analysis showed that PeCIN5 and PeCIN9 obtain the lowest E-value, 2e–51, compared with those of PeCIN5 or PeCIN9 to other PeCIN proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45220" pm="."><plain>Indeed, PeCYC2 and PeCYC3 are located in the same assembled scaffold (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s18"><title><text><SENT sid="45221" pm="."><plain>Expression profiles of TCP genes in P. equestris </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45222" pm="."><plain>We determined the spatial and temporal expression profiles of TCP genes in P. equestris of different floral organs (sepal, petal, labellum/lip, and gynostemium/column) (Fig. 3A), various developmental stages of floral buds (B1, 2, 3, and 4) (Fig. 3B; Tsai et al., 2004), pedicel, leaf, floral stalk and root, and different developmental stages of ovule after pollination (Fig. 3C; Chen et al., 2012) by real-time RT-PCR analysis (Fig. 4 and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Figs S1–S8</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45223" pm="."><plain>The expression patterns of 11 PePCF-like and nine PeCIN-like genes are shown in Fig. 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45224" pm="."><plain>The expression in different tissues varied widely among orchid TCP genes and among different organs for individual TCP genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45225" pm="."><plain>The results suggested the functional divergence of orchid genes during plant developmental processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45226" pm="."><plain>Heat map representation for the expression profiles of PeTCP genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45227" pm="."><plain>(A) Structure of a P. equestris flower. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45228" pm="."><plain>(B) Floral bud development stages from B1 to B4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45229" pm="."><plain>(C) Morphological changes in the ovary at various days after pollination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45230" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns of (D) 11 PePCF genes and nine PeCIN genes in various organs and developmental stages of floral bud; (E) 11 PePCF genes and nine PeCIN genes in various developmental stages of ovule. PeActin4 was used as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45231" pm="."><plain>The expression levels are represented by the color bar. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45232" pm="."><plain>B1: stage 1 flower bud (0~1mm); B2: stage 2 flower bud (1~2mm); B3: stage 3 flower bud (2~5mm); B4: stage 4 flower bud (5~10mm); Co: column; DAP, days after pollination; F: floral stalk; L: leaf; Li: lip; P: pedicel; Pe: petals; R: root; Se: sepals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45233" pm="."><plain>Scale bar: 1cm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0003"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45234" pm="."><plain>Spatial and temporal expression patterns of PeCYCs genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45235" pm="."><plain>(A) Real-time quantitative RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis of the mRNA expression of PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 in various tissues and developmental stages of floral bud. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45236" pm="."><plain>(B) qRT-PCR analysis of the mRNA expression of PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 in different floral organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45237" pm="."><plain>(C) Whole mount in situ hybridization of PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 in early floral development stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45238" pm="."><plain>Upper left: antisense probe of PeCYC1; upper right: sense probe of PeCYC1; lower left: antisense probe of PeCYC2; lower right: sense probe of PeCYC2. co: column primordium; ds: dorsal sepal primordium; ls: lateral sepal primordium; p: petal primordium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45239" pm="."><plain>Scale bar: 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0004"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45240" pm="."><plain>Most of the transcripts of PePCF-like genes could be detected in vegetative and reproductive tissues. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45241" pm="."><plain>However, PePCF6 was not expressed in any tissues, and the expression of PePCF11 was not detected in developing ovules (Fig. 3D, E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45242" pm="."><plain>Many PeCIN-like genes showed wide expression in floral organs, developing floral bud, pedicel, leaf, floral stalk, and root (Fig. 3D and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9A</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45243" pm="."><plain>Four genes (PeCIN2, 5, 7, and 8) expressed in developing ovule, especially in the late developmental stage of ovule (40–64 days after pollination [DAP]) (Fig. 3E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9B</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45244" pm="."><plain>However, the expression of PeCIN6 was not detected in any tissue (Fig. 3D, E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9</ext-link>), but PeCIN9 specifically expressed in leaf (Fig. 3D and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9A</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45245" pm="."><plain>As compared with the four PeCIN-like genes, nine PePCF genes were expressed in developing ovule (Fig. 3E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9B</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45246" pm="."><plain>This may imply that PePCF-like genes play more important roles in ovule differentiation and growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45247" pm="."><plain>Of note, PePCF10 predominantly expressed in ovules at early developmental stages (0–16 DAP) and PeCIN8 showed high expression at late developmental stages in ovule (16–64 DAP) (Fig. 3E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9B</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45248" pm="."><plain>Transcripts of PePCF6 and PeCIN6 were not detected in any organs, so they may be primarily expressed in other organs not tested or under special conditions (Fig. 3D, E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s19"><title><text><SENT sid="45249" pm="."><plain>PeCYC genes were predominantly expressed in developing floral buds </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45250" pm="."><plain>Expression profiles of three PeCYCs (PeCYC1, PeCYC2, and PeCYC3) were also analysed by real-time RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45251" pm="."><plain>Results showed that both PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 were predominantly expressed in developing floral buds (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45252" pm="."><plain>However, the expression of PeCYC3 was not detected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45253" pm="."><plain>Expression analysis of PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 was further conducted in dissected floral organs (including the dorsal/lateral sepal, petal, lip, and column). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45254" pm="."><plain>Both PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 were strongly expressed in the lateral sepal, lip, and column (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45255" pm="."><plain>The detailed spatial expression patterns of PeCYC1 and PeCYC2 at the early stage of floral development were further investigated by whole mount in situ hybridization by antisense RNA probes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45256" pm="."><plain>Results showed transcripts of PeCYC1 were detected at the primordia of lateral sepal and lip (Fig. 4C, upper left panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45257" pm="."><plain>However, transcripts of PeCYC2 were concentrated at the dorsal parts of the lateral sepal and lip primordia (Fig. 4C, lower left panel). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45258" pm="."><plain>Expression of PeCYCs at the floral dorsal region might correlate with orchid floral zygomorphic development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s20"><title><text><SENT sid="45259" pm="."><plain>Nuclear localization of class I PePCF10 and class II PeCIN8 proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45260" pm="."><plain>Orchid ovule development is precisely initiated by pollination. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45261" pm="."><plain>Because of the successive expression of PePCF10 and PeCIN8 during ovule development, we further characterized these two genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45262" pm="."><plain>To examine the subcellular localization of the two proteins, PePCF10–GFP and PeCIN8–GFP fusion proteins were constructed, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45263" pm="."><plain>Both PePCF10–GFP and PeCIN8–GFP fusion proteins were detected predominantly in nuclei derived from Phalaenopsis petal protoplasts (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45264" pm="."><plain>The results are consistent with sequence-based prediction of the subcellular localization and putative transcription factor activity of PePCF10 and PeCIN8. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45265" pm="."><plain>Localization patterns of PePCF10–GFP and PeCIN8–GFP fusion proteins in P. aphrodite petal protoplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45266" pm="."><plain>Pictures show fluorescence and bright-field confocal microscopy images. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45267" pm="."><plain>Images were merged with use of Axio Vision Rel.4.8 software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45268" pm="."><plain>(A) Empty vector green fluorescence in the cytoplasm and nucleus of a flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45269" pm="."><plain>(B) Cell in (A) stained with propidium iodide (PI; red) to show the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45270" pm="."><plain>(C) Merged image of (A) and (B) to show green fluorescence both in the cytoplasm and the nucleus of a flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45271" pm="."><plain>(D) Cell in (A), (B) and (C) visualized by bright-field confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45272" pm="."><plain>(E) PePCF10–GFP green fluorescence in the nucleus of a flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45273" pm="."><plain>(F) Cell in (E) stained with PI (red) to show the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45274" pm="."><plain>(G) Merged image of (E) and (F) to show the nuclear localization in a flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45275" pm="."><plain>(H) Cell in (E), (F) and (G) visualized by bright-field confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45276" pm="."><plain>(I) PeCIN8–GFP green fluorescence in the nucleus of a flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45277" pm="."><plain>(J) Cell in (I) stained with PI (red) to show the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45278" pm="."><plain>(K) Merged image of (I) and (J) to show the nuclear localization in a flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45279" pm="."><plain>(L) Cell in (I), (J) and (K) visualized by bright-field confocal microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45280" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0005"/></fig></sec><sec id="s21"><title><text><SENT sid="45281" pm="."><plain>Interaction behaviors of class I PePCF10 and class II PeCIN8 proteins </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45282" pm="."><plain>Several studies have provided evidence that TCP TFs can bind DNA as homo- or heterodimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45283" pm="."><plain>So far TCPs have been found to form heterodimers only between specific members of the same class (Kosugi and Ohashi, 2002; Viola et al., 2011; Danisman et al., 2012; Yang et al., 2012; Aguilar-Martinez and Sinha, 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45284" pm="."><plain>To investigate the protein–protein interactions between PePCF10 and PeCIN8 proteins, we used bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45285" pm="."><plain>The constructs were co-transfected and transiently expressed in the petal protoplasts of Phalaenopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45286" pm="."><plain>Interaction fluorescence signals were observed in YN–PePCF10 and YC–PePCF10 (Fig. 6I, J, K, L) as well as YN–PeCIN8 and YC–PeCIN8 (Fig. 6Q, R, S, T), which suggests that both PePCF10 and PeCIN8 can form homodimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45287" pm="."><plain>In addition, the signals were localized in the nucleus, as indicated by the nuclear dye propidium iodide (PI). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45288" pm="."><plain>However, interaction was not observed with the combination of YN–PeCIN8 and YC–PCF10 (Fig. 6U, V, W, X). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45289" pm="."><plain>Therefore, PePCF10 and PeCIN8 may not form heterodimers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45290" pm="."><plain>No fluorescence was detected with the empty vector control (Fig. 6A, B, C, D) and no yellow fluorescence was detected when only the C-terminal half of the YFP was co-bombarded with PePCF10 or PeCIN8 constructs (Fig. 6E, F, G, H, M, N, O, P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45291" pm="."><plain>Yeast two-hybrid experiments were also performed to analyse the behavior of PePCF10 and PeCIN8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45292" pm="."><plain>The results were similar to those of the BiFC assay, except that PePCF10 homodimer was not observed (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S10</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45293" pm="."><plain>It is possible that interaction between PePCF10 proteins was blocked by the steric hindrance of fused PePCF10–GAL4 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45294" pm="."><plain>We also tested interactions between PePCF10 and 23 Arabidopsis TCPs systematically by yeast two-hybrid assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45295" pm="."><plain>Results showed that PePCF10 is considered to interact with many TCP proteins which belong to the PCF, CYC/TB1, or CIN clade (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S11</ext-link>), suggesting that PePCF10 may have broad specificity in terms of its interacting partners. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45296" pm="."><plain>Arabidopsis TCP14, which is closest to PePCF10, appears to interact with PePCF10 strongly, supporting the above-described BiFC data in which PePCF10 forms a homodimer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45297" pm="."><plain>However, Arabidopsis TCP3, TCP4, and TCP10, which are close to PeCIN8, also showed interaction with PePCF10 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S11</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45298" pm="."><plain>These data suggest that the specificity of protein–protein interaction of TCP could be somewhat different between Arabidopsis and orchid. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45299" pm="."><plain>Bimolecular fluorescence complementation (BiFC) visualization of TCP dimerization in transiently transfected P. aphrodite petal protoplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45300" pm="."><plain>(A–D) Co-expression of non-fused YN with non-fused YC was unable to reconstitute a fluorescent YFP chromophore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45301" pm="."><plain>(E–H) Co-expression of non-fused YN with YC-PePCF10 was also unable to reconstitute a fluorescent YFP chromophore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45302" pm="."><plain>(I–L) PeTCP10 interacts with PeTCP10 protein in nucleus of flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45303" pm="."><plain>(M–P) Co-expression of non-fused YN with YC-PeCIN8 was also unable to reconstitute a fluorescent YFP chromophore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45304" pm="."><plain>(Q–T) PeCIN8 interacts with PeCIN8 protein in nucleus of flower cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45305" pm="."><plain>(U–X) Co-expression of YN-PeCIN8 with YC-PePCF10 was unable to reconstitute a fluorescent YFP chromophore. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45306" pm="."><plain>The fluorescence indicates interaction between the indicated partner proteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45307" pm="."><plain>The images were obtained from the yellow fluorescent protein channel or bright field or are a merged image of the yellow fluorescence, and cells stained with PI represented in red. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45308" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 20 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0006"/></fig></sec><sec id="s22"><title><text><SENT sid="45309" pm="."><plain>Functional characterization of the two PeTCP genes in transgenic Arabidopsis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45310" pm="."><plain>We constructed transgenic Arabidopsis plants expressing PePCF10 (OXPCF10) under the control of the CaMV 35S promoter via Agrobacterium-mediated transformation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45311" pm="."><plain>Twenty-five of the 100 independently transformed OXPCF10 transgenic T1 lines showed kanamycin resistance and a similar phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45312" pm="."><plain>Among 25 T2 lines, 12 showed a 3:1 segregating kanamycin resistance phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45313" pm="."><plain>The rosette size of OXPCF10 plants was normal (Fig. 7B), and we chose the seventh and eighth rosette leaf for observation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45314" pm="."><plain>OXPCF10 plants showed a round-leaf phenotype (Fig. 7G, L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45315" pm="."><plain>The leaf area of the seventh rosette leaf was smaller for OXPCF10 than wild-type (WT) plants (Fig. 7P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45316" pm="."><plain>A previous study indicated that Arabidopsis leaf size regulation is mainly controlled by cell number and size (Tsukaya, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45317" pm="."><plain>To assess the contributions of cell number and size to the reduced leaf size of the seventh rosette leaf in OXPCF10 plants, we compared the seventh and eighth rosette leaves of WT and transgenic plants by scanning electron microscopy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45318" pm="."><plain>For seventh rosette leaves, the adaxial epidermal cell size was larger for OXPCF10 than WT plants, and the adaxial epidermal cell number was significantly reduced (Fig. 8A, B, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45319" pm="."><plain>For the eighth rosette leaves, the adaxial epidermal cell size and cell number did not differ between WT and transgenic plants (Fig. 8F, G, U); the abaxial epidermal cell size and cell number of seventh rosette leaves (Fig. 8K, L, U) and eighth rosette leaves did not differ (Fig. 8P, Q, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45320" pm="."><plain>The altered leaf size and round leaves of OXPCF10 plants were related to decreased adaxial epidermal cell number and increased cell size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45321" pm="."><plain>Rosette leaves of wild-type (WT) and transgenic Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45322" pm="."><plain>(A–E) rosette of WT (A), OXPCF10 (B), PCF10SRDX (C), OXCIN8 (D) and CIN8SRDX (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45323" pm="."><plain>(F–J) Seventh rosette leaf from WT (F), OXPCF10 (G), PCF10SRDX (H), OXCIN8 (I) and CIN8SRDX (J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45324" pm="."><plain>(K–O) Eighth rosette leaf from WT (K), OXPCF10 (L), PCF10SRDX (M), OXCIN8 (N) and CIN8SRDX (O). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45325" pm="."><plain>(P) Seventh and eighth rosette leaf area of WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45326" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (*P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.001 compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45327" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45328" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 1cm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0007"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45329" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron micrographs of leaf epidermal cells of WT and transgenic Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45330" pm="."><plain>(A–E) Adaxial epidermis in the seventh rosette leaf from WT (A), OXPCF10 (B), PCF10SRDX (C), OXCIN8 (D) and CIN8SRDX (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45331" pm="."><plain>(F–J) Adaxial epidermis in the eighth rosette leaf from WT (F), OXPCF10 (G), PCF10SRDX (H), OXCIN8 (I) and CIN8SRDX (J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45332" pm="."><plain>(K–O) Abaxial epidermis in the seventh rosette leaf from WT (K), OXPCF10 (L), PCF10SRDX (M), OXCIN8 (N) and CIN8SRDX (O). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45333" pm="."><plain>(P–T) Abaxial epidermis in the eighth rosette leaf from WT (P), OXPCF10 (Q), PCF10SRDX (R), OXCIN8 (S) and CIN8SRDX (T). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45334" pm="."><plain>(U) Seventh and eighth rosette leaf epidermal cell number for WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45335" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45336" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats (n=200 each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45337" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 100 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0008"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45338" pm="."><plain>The flowers were smaller and less expanded for OXPCF10 than WT plants (Fig. 9A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45339" pm="."><plain>Flower petals were smaller (Fig. 9F, G, K) and the adaxial petal epidermis contained cells with reduced size (Fig. 10A, B) but increased number (Fig. 10K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45340" pm="."><plain>A similar phenotype was observed for abaxial epidermal cells (Fig. 10F, G, K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45341" pm="."><plain>The altered petal size of OXPCF10 plants was related to the reduced epidermal cell size and increased epidermal cell number. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F9" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 9.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45342" pm="."><plain>Flowers of WT and transgenic Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45343" pm="."><plain>(A–E) Side views of WT (A), OXPCF10 (B), PCF10SRDX (C), OXCIN8 (D) and CIN8SRDX (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45344" pm="."><plain>(F–J) Petals of WT (F), OXPCF10 (G), PCF10SRDX (H), OXCIN8 (I) and CIN8SRDX (J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45345" pm="."><plain>(K) Petal area of WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45346" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (**P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001, compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45347" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats (n=10 each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45348" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 1mm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0009"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F10" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 10.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45349" pm="."><plain>Scanning electron micrographs of epidermal cells of WT and transgenic Arabidopsis petals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45350" pm="."><plain>(A–E) Adaxial epidermal cells of WT (A), OXPCF10 (B), PCF10SRDX (C), OXCIN8 (D) and CIN8SRDX (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45351" pm="."><plain>(F–J) Abaxial epidermal cells of WT (F), OXPCF10 (G), PCF10SRDX (H), OXCIN8 (I) and CIN8SRDX (J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45352" pm="."><plain>(K) Epidermal cell number of WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45353" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01, ***P&lt;0.001, compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45354" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats (n=200 each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45355" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 50 μm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0010"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45356" pm="."><plain>Siliques were shorter for OXPCF10 than WT plants (Fig. 11A, B, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45357" pm="."><plain>The total seed number per silique of OXPCF10 plants was significantly reduced (Fig. 11G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45358" pm="."><plain>Big reduction of seeds observed in the overexpressed plants might relate to the abnormal gametogenesis (Takeda et al., 2006; Sarvepalli and Nath, 2011; Viola et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45359" pm="."><plain>The seed size was larger for OXPCF10 than WT plants (data not shown) and the seed weight was significantly increased (Fig. 11H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45360" pm="."><plain>The altered silique length and seed size and weight of OXPCF10 plants suggested that PePCF10 may be involved in reproductive development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F11" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 11.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="45361" pm="."><plain>Siliques and seeds of WT and transgenic Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45362" pm="."><plain>(A–E) Siliques of WT (A), OXPCF10 (B), PCF10SRDX (C), OXCIN8 (D) and CIN8SRDX (E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45363" pm="."><plain>(F) Silique length of WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45364" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (*P&lt;0.05, ***P&lt;0.001, compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45365" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats (n=20 each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45366" pm="."><plain>(G) Seeds per silique of WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45367" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (***P&lt;0.001, compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45368" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats (n=20 each). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45369" pm="."><plain>(H) Weight (mg) of 1000 seeds of WT, OXPCF10, PCF10SRDX, OXCIN8 and CIN8SRDX plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45370" pm="."><plain>Asterisks indicate statistically significant differences (*P&lt;0.05, **P&lt;0.01 compared with WT by Student’s t-test). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45371" pm="."><plain>Errors bar represent the SD of three biological repeats. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45372" pm="."><plain>Scale bars: 1mm. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="exbotj_erw273_f0011"/></fig><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45373" pm="."><plain>In addition to overexpression of PePCF10 in Arabidopsis, we converted PePCF10 to a chimeric repressor by fusing it with the SRDX repression domain (PCF10SRDX). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45374" pm="."><plain>Twenty-six of the 100 independently transformed PCF10SRDX transgenic T1 lines showed kanamycin resistance and a similar phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45375" pm="."><plain>Among 26 T2 lines, 13 showed a 3:1 segregating kanamycin resistance phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45376" pm="."><plain>The rosette size of PCF10SRDX plants was reduced and leaves showed a wrinkled surface and downward curl (Fig. 7C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45377" pm="."><plain>The leaf area of the seventh and eighth rosette leaf did not differ between WT and transgenic plants, but transgenic lines showed slightly enlarged leaves (Fig. 7F, H, K, M, P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45378" pm="."><plain>Similar phenotypes were reported in mutant and transgenic lines, with altered proliferation of leaf blade cells (Serrano-Cartagena et al., 2000; Bemis and Torii, 2007; Kieffer et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45379" pm="."><plain>For seventh rosette leaves, the adaxial epidermis contained cells with reduced size but increased number in PCF10SRDX plants (Fig. 8A, C, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45380" pm="."><plain>For eighth rosette leaves, the adaxial epidermal cell size and cell number did not differ between WT and transgenic plants (Fig. 8F, H, U) and the abaxial epidermal cell size and cell number of seventh rosette leaves did not differ (Fig. 8K, M, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45381" pm="."><plain>The abaxial epidermal cell size of the eighth rosette leaves was larger for transgenic than WT plants and the cell number was less (Fig. 8P, R, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45382" pm="."><plain>Although the leaf area was not altered in PCF10SRDX plants (Fig. 7P), the adaxial epidermal cell size was smaller and cell number greater in the seventh rosette leaf and the abaxial epidermal cell size was larger and cell number lower in the eighth rosette leaf. PePCF10 may regulate cell proliferation and differentiation and thus generate a wrinkled surface and downwardly curled rosette leaves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45383" pm="."><plain>The morphology of the flowers did not differ between PCF10SRDX and WT plants (Fig. 9A, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45384" pm="."><plain>However, petals were smaller for PCF10SRDX than WT flowers (Fig. 9H, K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45385" pm="."><plain>The adaxial epidermal cell size of petals did not differ (Fig. 10A, C), but the adaxial epidermal cell number was lower (Fig. 10K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45386" pm="."><plain>In addition, the abaxial epidermal cell size of petals was larger for PCF10SRDX than WT plants (Fig. 10F, H) and the abaxial epidermal cell number was less (Fig. 10K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45387" pm="."><plain>The silique length, total seed number per silique, and seed size did not differ between the WT and PCF10SRDX plants (Fig. 11A, C, F, G), but the seed weight of PCF10SRDX plants was significantly decreased (Fig. 11H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45388" pm="."><plain>These results suggest a function for PePCF10 in cell proliferation in vegetative and reproductive tissues. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45389" pm="."><plain>The same strategy was adopted to functionally characterize PeCIN8. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45390" pm="."><plain>Twenty-four of the 100 independently transformed OXCIN8 transgenic T1 lines showed kanamycin resistance and a similar phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45391" pm="."><plain>Among 24 T2 lines, 11 showed a 3:1 segregating kanamycin resistance phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45392" pm="."><plain>The rosette size of OXCIN8 plants was reduced (Fig. 7D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45393" pm="."><plain>The rosette leaves showed a round-leaf phenotype (Fig. 7I, N). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45394" pm="."><plain>The leaf area of the seventh rosette leaf was smaller compared with the WT plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45395" pm="."><plain>The leaf area of the eighth rosette leaf did not differ when compared with WT (Fig. 7P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45396" pm="."><plain>Similar phenotypic effects were observed on transgenic lines with altered proliferation of leaf blade cells (Schommer et al., 2008; Sarvepalli and Nath, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45397" pm="."><plain>The adaxial epidermal cell size of the seventh and eighth rosette leaf was smaller for OXCIN8 than WT plants (Fig. 8A, D, F, I) and the adaxial epidermal cell number was greater (Fig. 8U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45398" pm="."><plain>The abaxial epidermal cells of the seventh and eighth rosette leaf of OXCIN8 plants showed the opposite pattern. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45399" pm="."><plain>The abaxial epidermal cell size of the seventh and eighth rosette leaf was larger for OXCIN8 than WT plants (Fig. 8K, N, P, S) and the abaxial epidermal cell number was less (Fig. 8U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45400" pm="."><plain>The altered leaf size and round leaves of OXCIN8 plants were related to changed cell number and cell size in both the adaxial and abaxial sides of the leaf. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45401" pm="."><plain>The adaxial epidermal cell size and cell number did not differ between OXCIN8 and WT petals (Fig. 10A, D, K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45402" pm="."><plain>However, the abaxial epidermal cell size was larger for OXCIN8 than WT (Fig. 10F, I) and the abaxial epidermal cell number was less (Fig. 10K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45403" pm="."><plain>Although the petal area was not modified in OXCIN8 plants (Fig. 9K), the abaxial epidermal cell size was larger and cell number lower than those of WT petals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45404" pm="."><plain>The siliques were longer for OXCIN8 than WT plants (Fig. 11A, D, F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45405" pm="."><plain>The total seed number per silique was increased in OXCIN8 plants (Fig. 11G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45406" pm="."><plain>However, the seed size did not differ between OXCIN8 and WT seeds and seed weight did not differ (Fig. 11H). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45407" pm="."><plain>PeCIN8 fused with SRDX-overexpressed transgenic plants (CIN8SRDX) were also produced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45408" pm="."><plain>Twenty-five of the 100 independently transformed CIN8SRDX transgenic T1 lines showed kanamycin resistance and a similar phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45409" pm="."><plain>Among 25 T2 lines, 12 showed a 3:1 segregating kanamycin resistance phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45410" pm="."><plain>The rosette size of CIN8SRDX plants was normal (Fig. 7E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45411" pm="."><plain>However, the rosette leaves showed a wrinkled surface and a downward curl (Fig. 7E, J, O). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45412" pm="."><plain>The leaf area of the seventh rosette leaf seemed slightly larger for CIN8SRDX than WT plants; however, the eighth rosette leaf area was significantly larger (Fig. 7P). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45413" pm="."><plain>For seventh rosette leaves, the adaxial epidermal cell size was larger for CIN8SRDX than WT plants, and the adaxial epidermal cell number was smaller (Fig. 8A, E, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45414" pm="."><plain>For eighth rosette leaves, the adaxial epidermal cell size seemed smaller for CIN8SRDX than WT plants and the adaxial epidermal cell number was higher (Fig. 8F, J, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45415" pm="."><plain>For both seventh and eighth rosette leaves, the abaxial epidermal cell size was larger for CIN8SRDX than WT plants and the abaxial epidermal cell number was lower (Fig. 8K, O, P, T, U). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45416" pm="."><plain>These results suggest that the wrinkled surface and downwardly curled rosette leaves of CIN8SRDX plants were due to increased adaxial epidermal cell number and abaxial epidermal cell size. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45417" pm="."><plain>The flowers of CIN8SRDX plants were less expanded (Fig. 9E) and significantly smaller than those of WT plants (Fig. 9F, J, K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45418" pm="."><plain>The adaxial epidermal cell size seemed smaller for CIN8SRDX than WT petals (Fig. 10A, E) and the adaxial epidermal cell number was significantly increased (Fig. 10K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45419" pm="."><plain>The abaxial epidermal cells were larger for CIN8SRDX than WT petals because of elongated cells (Fig. 10F, J), and the abaxial epidermal cell number was significantly decreased (Fig. 10K). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45420" pm="."><plain>The siliques were shorter for CIN8SRDX than WT plants (Fig. 11A, E, F) and the total seed number per silique was significantly increased (Fig. 11G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45421" pm="."><plain>The seed weight was greater for CIN8SRDX than WT plants (Fig. 11H). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s23"><title><text><SENT sid="45422" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45423" pm="."><plain>In the present study, we identified 23 TCP genes from P. equestris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45424" pm="."><plain>The number of TCP genes in P. equestris was similar to that in Arabidopsis (24) and rice (22) (Martín-Trillo and Cubas, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45425" pm="."><plain>As well, the gene number in each subfamily of TCP genes was similar among the three species (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45426" pm="."><plain>Although the genome size of Phalaenopsis is larger than that of Arabidopsis and rice—approximately 9 and 2.8 times, respectively—the number of genes among the genomes is similar (Cai et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45427" pm="."><plain>This fact suggests that the TCP family did not expand along with genome expansion of P. equestris during orchid evolution (Cai et al., 2015). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45428" pm="."><plain>TCP genes in orchids, like those Arabidopsis, rice and other plants, may participate in regulating multiple aspects of plant development such as gametophyte development (Takeda et al., 2006; Sarvepalli and Nath, 2011), hormone signal transduction (Aguilar-Martinez et al., 2007; Guo et al., 2010; Yanai et al., 2011), mitochondria biogenesis (Hammani et al., 2011), regulation of circadian clock (Pruneda-Paz et al., 2009; Giraud et al., 2010), lateral branching (Takeda et al., 2003; Aguilar-Martinez et al., 2007), flower development (Koyama et al., 2011; Uberti-Manassero et al., 2012), seed germination (Tatematsu et al., 2008; Rueda-Romero et al., 2012), and leaf development (Kieffer et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45429" pm="."><plain>Actually, the expression of TCP genes was broadly detected in various vegetative, reproductive tissues and different developmental stages of Phalaenopsis orchid (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45430" pm="."><plain>In most orchid flowers, ovary and ovule development is precisely triggered by pollination (Tsai et al., 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45431" pm="."><plain>Auxin is a positive regulator for the orchid ovule initiation (Tsai et al., 2005; Novak et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45432" pm="."><plain>We found PePCF10 predominantly expressed in ovules at early developmental stages (0–16 DAP) and PeCIN8 showed high expression at late developmental stages in ovules (16–64 DAP) (Fig. 3E and <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S9B</ext-link>), with overlapping expression at 16 DAP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45433" pm="."><plain>At about 16 DAP, when PePCF10 and PeCIN8 are co-expressed, placental protuberances develop from a single epidermal layer of the placenta (Chen et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45434" pm="."><plain>Archesporial cells are differentiated at the terminus of the nucellar filament. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45435" pm="."><plain>Later, periclinal divisions in epidermal cells surrounding the archesporial cells generate the inner integument (Arditti and Pridgeon, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45436" pm="."><plain>Thus, the function of the homodimer TF PePCF10 might be related to placenta growth and continued initiation of archesporial cells and inner integument. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45437" pm="."><plain>In addition, a homodimer of PeCIN8 might associate with the later developmental process of megagametogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45438" pm="."><plain>Further study of the relationship between PePCF10 and PeCIN8 will allow us to gain new insights into the regulation of the unique system of orchid ovule development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45439" pm="."><plain>Functional analysis by overexpressing PePCF10 or a chimeric repressor gene in Arabidopsis suggested that PePCF10 plays a role in regulating epidermal cell proliferation and differentiation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45440" pm="."><plain>Previous study suggested that TCP proteins could be dual-function transcription factors able to positively or negatively regulate expression of target genes (Herve et al., 2009; Wang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45441" pm="."><plain>Although the seventh and eighth rosette leaf areas of PCF10SRDX lines slightly differed from those of the WT, the epidermal cell number was increased or decreased in PCF10SRDX lines depending on the different epidermal cell axis. PePCF10 may act as a dual functional TF in regulating cell proliferation in the developing leaf, and the distinctive activities of PePCF10 may depend on its interaction with other proteins in the adaxial or abaxial side of the leaf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45442" pm="."><plain>Our results are consistent with the function of TCP proteins being dependent on the organ, tissue, or cellular context (Herve et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45443" pm="."><plain>The class II TCP gene CIN was reported to act as a repressor of cell proliferation in leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45444" pm="."><plain>High levels of miR319 or low miR319-targeted TCP activity might cause excess cell proliferation, thus resulting in a crinkled leaf in Arabidopsis, snapdragon, and tomato or larger leaves in monocotyledonous plants (rice and creeping bentgrass) (Nath et al., 2003; Palatnik et al., 2003; Ori et al., 2007; Yang et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45445" pm="."><plain>In this study, we found that the expression of PeCIN8 was broadly distributed in orchid vegetative and reproductive tissues (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45446" pm="."><plain>Overexpressed PeCIN8 or Arabidopsis with the chimeric repressor gene showed a varied leaf morphology associated with altered cell number and cell size of epidermal cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45447" pm="."><plain>In addition, the function of PeCIN8 was exhibited by the petal size. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45448" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, the epidermal cell number in the affected organs of transgenic plants was increased or decreased depending on different epidermal cell axis, so PeCIN8 may act as a dual-function TF in regulating cell proliferation in the developing leaf or petal. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45449" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have reported that Arabidopsis TCP genes including TCP2, TCP3, TCP4, TCP10, and TCP24 possess miR319-binding sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45450" pm="."><plain>The cleavage activity of miR319 on these AtTCP transcripts has been demonstrated (Nag et al., 2009; Palatnik et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45451" pm="."><plain>A similar finding was later shown in tomato LANCEOLATE (LA, SlTCP2), the closest homolog of AtTCP4 (Ori et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45452" pm="."><plain>Although PeCIN8 was predicted to possess an miR319 targeting site, it seems that cleavage of PeCIN8 transcripts did not occur in the PeCIN8-overexpressing Arabidopsis. Koyama et al. (2007) reported that the ectopic expression of AtTCP3 under the control of CaMV 35S promoter (35S:AtTCP3) did not show visible abnormalities compared with Arabidopsis wild-type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45453" pm="."><plain>However, overexpression of a mutant form of AtTCP3 without the miR319-binding sequence (35S:mAtTCP3) induced fusion of cotyledons, defects in the formation of shoots and elongation of hypocotyls in Arabidopsis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45454" pm="."><plain>Similar results were found when miR319-resistant or -sensitive versions of AtTCP2 and AtTCP4 were expressed, suggesting the phenotype differences are likely due to the presence of miR319 (Palatnik et al., 2003, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45455" pm="."><plain>In this study, overexpression of wild-type form of PeCIN8 induces small rosette size and rounder leaves, indicating a higher level of PeCIN8 transcripts in the transgenic Arabidopsis plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45456" pm="."><plain>These data, which contradict previous results, might be due to no cleavage of the PeCIN8 transcripts occurring or a lower sensitivity of PeCIN8 transcripts to Arabidopsis miR319 regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45457" pm="."><plain>It was reported that only one point mutation at the miR319-binding site of tomato LA alleles could confer partial resistance of LA transcripts to miR319 cleavage activity (Ori et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45458" pm="."><plain>This dominant mutation of LA in tomato resulted in small simple leaves instead of the large compound ones of wild type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45459" pm="."><plain>In addition, the AtTCP4 hyper-activation lines that expressed 35S:AtTCP4:VP16 under Arabidopsis Col-0 background show much smaller leaf sizes and rounder leaves (Sarvepalli and Nath, 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45460" pm="."><plain>This suggests that the regulation of TCP genes for plant development depends on the miR319 level or the ratio of TCP transcripts and miR319. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45461" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, we could not exclude the possibility that the post-transcriptional regulation of CIN-type TCP genes is different between Arabidopsis and P. equestris. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p content-type="indent"><text><SENT sid="45462" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we identified 23 members of the orchid TCP TF gene family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45463" pm="."><plain>These genes have broad expression profiles corresponding to multiple aspects of growth and development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45464" pm="."><plain>Orchid PePCF10 and PeCIN8 showed successive expression patterns during ovule development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45465" pm="."><plain>Additionally, both proteins could form homodimers and localize in the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45466" pm="."><plain>Functional analysis suggested that both genes might regulate cell proliferation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45467" pm="."><plain>These two genes may contribute to the unique functions of TCP TFs in orchids, controlling ovule initiation and development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s24"><title><text><SENT sid="45468" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45469" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45470" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Table S1.</ext-link> Primers used in this study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45471" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S1.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PePCF genes in various organs and developmental stages of floral bud of Phalaenopsis equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45472" pm="."><plain>Quantification was normalized to Actin4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45473" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S2.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PePCF genes in various developmental stages of ovule of P. equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45474" pm="."><plain>Quantification was normalized to Actin4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45475" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S3.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PeCIN genes in various organs and developmental stages of floral bud of P. equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis with use of PeActin4 as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45476" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S4.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PeCIN genes in various developmental stages of ovule of P. equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis with use of PeActin4 as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45477" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S5.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PePCF genes in various organs and developmental stages of floral bud of P. equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis with use of Pa18S rRNA as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45478" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S6.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PePCF genes in various developmental stages of ovule of P. equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis with use of Pa18S rRNA as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45479" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S7.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PeCIN genes in various organs and developmental stages of floral bud of P. equestris by real-time analysis with use of Pa18S rRNA as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45480" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S8.</ext-link> The expression patterns of PeCIN genes in various developmental stages of ovule of P. equestris by real-time RT-PCR analysis with use of Pa18S rRNA as internal control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45481" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S9.</ext-link> Heat map representation for the expression profiles of PePCF and PeCIN in various organs and developmental stages of floral bud (A), and in various developmental stages of ovule (B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45482" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S10.</ext-link> Analysis of protein interactions between PePCF10 and PeCIN8 by quantitative β-galactosidase activity assays. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="45483" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jxb.oxfordjournals.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1093/jxb/erw273/-/DC1">Figure S11.</ext-link> Result of yeast two-hybrid assay between PePCF10 and Arabidopsis TCPs (A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45484" pm="."><plain>Matrix describing experimental design shown in (B) and (C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="45485" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_67_17_5051__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="supp_erw273_Supplementary_Figure_1_11_Table_1.pdf"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="45486" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr Tzyy-Jen Chiou (Agricultural Biotechnology Research Center, Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan) for vector construction of BiFC assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45487" pm="."><plain>We also thank Dr Tzong-Yueh Chen (Department of Biotechnology and Bioindustry Sciences, National Cheng Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan) for assisting real-time RT-PCR experiment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45488" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan [grants NSC 99-2311-B-006-004-MY3 and MOST 103-2313-B-006-001-MY3]. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><def-list><title>Abbreviations:</title><def-item><term>BiFC</term><def><p>bimolecular fluorescence complementation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CaMV</term><def><p>cauliflower mosaic virus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CYC</term><def><p>CYCLOIDEA</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DAP</term><def><p>days after pollination</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GFP</term><def><p>green florescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HMM</term><def><p>hidden Markov model</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ORF</term><def><p>open reading frame</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>OX</term><def><p>overexpressing</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PCF</term><def><p>proliferating cell factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TB1</term><def><p>TEOSINTE BRANCHED1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TCP</term><def><p>TEOSINTE-BRANCHED/CYCLOIDEA/PCF</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TF</term><def><p>transcription factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PI</term><def><p>propidium iodide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>RT-PCR</term><def><p>reverse transcription–PCR</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WT</term><def><p>wild-type</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YC</term><def><p>C-terminal half of YFP</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YFP</term><def><p>yellow florescent protein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>YN</term><def><p>N-terminal half of YFP.</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="45489" pm="."><plain> Aguilar-MartinezJAPoza-CarrionCCubasP 2007  Arabidopsis BRANCHED1 acts as an integrator of branching signals within axillary buds. The Plant Cell 19, 458–472.17307924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="45490" pm="."><plain> Aguilar-MartinezJASinhaN 2013 Analysis of the role of Arabidopsis class I TCP genes AtTCP7, AtTCP8, AtTCP22, and AtTCP23 in leaf development. Frontiers in Plant Science 4, 406.24137171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="45491" pm="."><plain> ArdittiJPridgeonAM 1997 Orchid biology: Reviews and perspectives, VII. Dordrecht: Kluwer Academic Publishers. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="45492" pm="."><plain> Balsemão-PiresEAndradeLRSachetto-MartinsG 2013 Functional study of TCP23 in Arabidopsis thaliana during plant development. Plant Physiology and Biochemistry 67, 120–125.23562796 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="45493" pm="."><plain> BemisSMToriiKU 2007 Autonomy of cell proliferation and developmental programs during Arabidopsis aboveground organ morphogenesis. Developmental Biology 304, 367–381.17258192 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="45494" pm="."><plain> CaiJLiuXVannesteK 2015 The genome sequence of the orchid Phalaenopsis equestris . Nature Genetics 47, 65–72.25420146 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="45495" pm="."><plain> ChenYYLeePFHsiaoYYWuWLPanZJLeeYILiuKWChenLJLiuZJTsaiWC 2012 C- and D-class MADS-box genes from Phalaenopsis equestris (Orchidaceae) display functions in gynostemium and ovule development. Plant and Cell Physiology 53, 1053–1067.22499266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="45496" pm="."><plain> CloughSJBentAF 1998 Floral dip: a simplified method for Agrobacterium-mediated transformation of Arabidopsis thaliana . The Plant Journal 16, 735–743.10069079 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="45497" pm="."><plain> CubasPLauterNDoebleyJCoenE 1999 The TCP domain: a motif found in proteins regulating plant growth and development. The Plant Journal 18, 215–222.10363373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="45498" pm="."><plain> DanismanSvan der WalFDhondtS 2012  Arabidopsis class I and class II TCP transcription factors regulate jasmonic acid metabolism and leaf development antagonistically. Plant Physiology 159, 1511–1523.22718775 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="45499" pm="."><plain> DresslerRL 1993 Phylogeny and classification of the orchid family. Portland: Dioscorides Press. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="45500" pm="."><plain> GiraudENgSCarrieCDuncanOLowJLeeCPVan AkenOMillarAHMurchaMWhelanJ 2010 TCP transcription factors link the regulation of genes encoding mitochondrial proteins with the circadian clock in Arabidopsis thaliana . The Plant Cell 22, 3921–3934.21183706 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="45501" pm="."><plain> GuoZFujiokaSBlancaflorEBMiaoSGouXLiJ 2010 TCP1 modulates brassinosteroid biosynthesis by regulating the expression of the key biosynthetic gene DWARF4 in Arabidopsis thaliana . The Plant Cell 22, 1161–1173.20435901 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><text><SENT sid="45502" pm="."><plain> HammaniKGobertAHleibiehKChoulierLSmallI GiegéP 2011 An Arabidopsis dual-localized pentatricopeptide repeat protein interacts with nuclear proteins involved in gene expression regulation. The Plant Cell 23, 730–740.21297037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="45503" pm="."><plain> HerveCDabosPBardetCJauneauAAuriacMCRamboerALacoutFTremousaygueD 2009 In vivo interference with AtTCP20 function induces severe plant growth alterations and deregulates the expression of many genes important for development. Plant Physiology 149, 1462–1477.19091878 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="45504" pm="."><plain> HiratsuKMatsuiKKoyamaTOhme-TakagiM 2003 Dominant repression of target genes by chimeric repressors that include the EAR motif, a repression domain, in Arabidopsis . The Plant Journal 34, 733–739.12787253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="45505" pm="."><plain> HiratsuKOhtaMMatsuiKOhme-TakagiM 2002 The SUPERMAN protein is an active repressor whose carboxy-terminal repression domain is required for the development of normal flowers. FEBS Letters 514, 351–354.11943180 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="45506" pm="."><plain> IngramGCWaitesR 2006 Keeping it together: co-ordinating plant growth. Current Opinion in Plant Biology 9, 12–20.16326130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="45507" pm="."><plain> KarimiMBleysAVanderhaeghenRHilsonP 2007 Building blocks for plant gene assembly. Plant Physiology 145, 1183–1191.17965171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="45508" pm="."><plain> KiefferMMasterVWaitesRDaviesB 2011 TCP14 and TCP15 affect internode length and leaf shape in Arabidopsis . The Plant Journal 68, 147–158.21668538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="45509" pm="."><plain> KosugiSOhashiY 2002 DNA binding and dimerization specificity and potential targets for the TCP protein family. The Plant Journal 30, 337–348.12000681 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="45510" pm="."><plain> KoyamaTFurutaniMTasakaMOhme-TakagiM 2007 TCP transcription factors control the morphology of shoot lateral organs via negative regulation of the expression of boundary-specific genes in Arabidopsis . The Plant Cell 19, 473–484.17307931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="45511" pm="."><plain> KoyamaTMitsudaNSekiMShinozakiKOhme-TakagiM 2010 TCP transcription factors regulate the activities of ASYMMETRIC LEAVES1 and miR164, as well as the auxin response, during differentiation of leaves in Arabidopsis . The Plant Cell 22, 3574–3588.21119060 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="45512" pm="."><plain> KoyamaTOhme-TakagiMSatoF 2011 Generation of serrated and wavy petals by inhibition of the activity of TCP transcription factors in Arabidopsis thaliana . Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior 6, 697–699.21455021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="45513" pm="."><plain> LiSGutscheNZachgoS 2011 The ROXY1 C-terminal L**LL motif is essential for the interaction with TGA transcription factors. Plant Physiology 157, 2056–2068.21960138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="45514" pm="."><plain> LiSZachgoS 2013 TCP3 interacts with R2R3-MYB proteins, promotes flavonoid biosynthesis and negatively regulates the auxin response in Arabidopsis thaliana . The Plant Journal 76, 901–913.24118612 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="45515" pm="."><plain> LinHYChenJCWeiMJLienYCLiHHKoSSLiuZHFangSC 2014 Genome-wide annotation, expression profiling, and protein interaction studies of the core cell-cycle genes in Phalaenopsis aphrodite . Plant Molecular Biology 84, 203–226.24222213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="45516" pm="."><plain> LopezJASunYBlairPBMukhtarMS 2015 TCP three-way handshake: linking developmental processes with plant immunity. Trends in Plant Science 20, 238–245.25655280 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="45517" pm="."><plain> ManasseroNGViolaILWelchenEGonzalezDH 2013 TCP transcription factors: architectures of plant forms. Biomelecular Concepts 4, 111–127. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="45518" pm="."><plain> Martín-TrilloMCubasP 2010 TCP genes: a family snapshot ten years later. Trends in Plant Science 15, 31–39.19963426 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="45519" pm="."><plain> MitsudaNIkedaMTakadaSTakiguchiYKondouYYoshizumiTFujitaMShinozakiKMatsuiMOhme-TakagiM 2010 Efficient yeast one-/two-hybrid screening using a library composed only of transcription factors in Arabidopsis thaliana . Plant and Cell Physiology 51, 2145–2151.20980269 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="45520" pm="."><plain> Mondragon-PalominoMTrontinC 2011 High time for a roll call: gene duplication and phylogenetic relationships of TCP-like genes in monocots. Annals of Botany 107, 1533–1544.21444336 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><text><SENT sid="45521" pm="."><plain> NagAKingSJackT 2009 miR319a targeting of TCP4 is critical for petal growth and development in Arabidopsis . Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America 106, 22534–22539.20007771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><text><SENT sid="45522" pm="."><plain> NathUCrawfordBCWCarpenterRCoenE 2003 Genetic control of surface curvature. Science 299, 1404–1407.12610308 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><text><SENT sid="45523" pm="."><plain> NovakSDLunaLJ GamageRN 2014 Role of auxin in orchid development. Plant Signaling &amp; Behavior 9, e972277.25482818 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><text><SENT sid="45524" pm="."><plain> OriNCohenAREtzioniA 2007 Regulation of LANCEOLATE by miR319 is required for compound-leaf development in tomato. Nature Genetics 39, 787–791.17486095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><text><SENT sid="45525" pm="."><plain> PalatnikJFAllenEWuXSchommerCSchwabRCarringtonJCWeigelD 2003 Control of leaf morphogenesis by microRNAs. Nature 425, 257–263.12931144 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><text><SENT sid="45526" pm="."><plain> PalatnikJFWollmannHSchommerC 2007 Sequence and expression differences underlie functional specialization of Arabidopsis microRNAs miR159 and miR319 . Developmental Cell 13, 115–125.17609114 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><text><SENT sid="45527" pm="."><plain> Pruneda-PazJLBretonGParaA KaySA 2009 A functional genomics approach reveals CHE as a component of the Arabidopsis circadian clock. Science 323, 1481–1485.19286557 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><text><SENT sid="45528" pm="."><plain> QuevillonESilventoinenVPillaiSHarteNMulderNApweilerRLopezR 2005 InterProScan: protein domains identifier. Nucleic Acids Research 33, W116–W120.15980438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><text><SENT sid="45529" pm="."><plain> Rueda-RomeroPBarrero-SiciliaCGómez-CadenasACarboneroP Oñate-SánchezL 2012  Arabidopsis thaliana DOF6 negatively affects germination in non-after-ripened seeds and interacts with TCP14. Journal of Experimental Botany 63, 1937–1949.22155632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><text><SENT sid="45530" pm="."><plain> SarvepalliKNathU 2011 Hyper-activation of the TCP4 transcription factor in Arabidopsis thaliana accelerates multiple aspects of plant maturation. The Plant Journal 67, 595–607.21518050 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><text><SENT sid="45531" pm="."><plain> SchommerCPalatnikJFAggarwalPChételatACubasPFarmerEENathUWeigelD 2008 Control of jasmonate biosynthesis and senescence by miR319 targets. PLoS Biology 6, e230.18816164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><text><SENT sid="45532" pm="."><plain> Serrano-CartagenaJCandelaHRoblesPPonceMRPérez-PérezJMPiquerasPMicolJL 2000 Genetic analysis of incurvata mutants reveals three independent genetic operations at work in Arabidopsis leaf morphogenesis. Genetics 156, 1363–1377.11063708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><text><SENT sid="45533" pm="."><plain> TakedaTAmanoKOhtoM-aNakamuraKSatoSKatoTTabataSUeguchiC 2006 RNA interference of the Arabidopsis putative transcription factor TCP16 gene results in abortion of early pollen development. Plant Molecular Biology 61, 165–177.16786299 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><text><SENT sid="45534" pm="."><plain> TakedaTSuwaYSuzukiMKitanoHUeguchi-TanakaMAshikariMMatsuokaMUeguchiC 2003 The OsTB1 gene negatively regulates lateral branching in rice. The Plant Journal 33, 513–520.12581309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><text><SENT sid="45535" pm="."><plain> TamuraKDudleyJNeiMKumarS 2007 MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0. Molecular Biology and Evolution 24, 1596–1599.17488738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><text><SENT sid="45536" pm="."><plain> TatematsuKNakabayashiKKamiyaY NambaraE 2008 Transcription factor AtTCP14 regulates embryonic growth potential during seed germination in Arabidopsis thaliana . The Plant Journal 53, 42–52.17953649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><text><SENT sid="45537" pm="."><plain> ThompsonJDHigginsDG GibsonTJ 1994 CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice. Nucleic Acids Research 22, 4673–4680.7984417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><text><SENT sid="45538" pm="."><plain> TraasJ 2008 Whole-mount in situ hybridization of RNA probes to plant tissues. CSH Protocols, doi: 10.1101/pdb.prot4944. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><text><SENT sid="45539" pm="."><plain> TsaiWCChuangMHKuohCSChenWHChenHH 2004 Four DEF-like MADS box genes displayed distinct floral morphogenetic roles in Phalaenopsis orchid. Plant and Cell Physiology 45, 831–844.15295066 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><text><SENT sid="45540" pm="."><plain> TsaiWCHsiaoYYPanZJKuohCSChenWHChenHH 2008 The role of ethylene in orchid ovule development. Plant Science 175, 98–105. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><text><SENT sid="45541" pm="."><plain> TsaiWCLeePFChenHIHsiaoYYWeiWJPanZJChuangMHKuohCSChenWHChenHH 2005  PeMADS6, a GLOBOSA/PISTILLATA-like gene in Phalaenopsis equestris involved in petaloid formation, and correlated with flower longevity and ovary development. Plant and Cell Physiology 46, 1125–1139.15890679 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><text><SENT sid="45542" pm="."><plain> TsukayaH 2006 Mechanism of leaf-shape determination. Annual Review of Plant Biology 57, 477–496. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><text><SENT sid="45543" pm="."><plain> Uberti-ManasseroNGLuceroLEViolaILVegettiACGonzalezDH 2012 The class I protein AtTCP15 modulates plant development through a pathway that overlaps with the one affected by CIN-like TCP proteins. Journal of Experimental Botany 63, 809–823.22016421 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><text><SENT sid="45544" pm="."><plain> ViolaILUberti ManasseroNGRipollRGonzalezDH 2011 The Arabidopsis class I TCP transcription factor AtTCP11 is a developmental regulator with distinct DNA-binding properties due to the presence of a threonine residue at position 15 of the TCP domain. Biochemical Journal 435, 143–155.21241251 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0058"><text><SENT sid="45545" pm="."><plain> WangMYZhaoPMChengHQ 2013 The cotton transcription factor TCP14 functions in auxin-mediated epidermal cell differentiation and elongation. Plant Physiology 162, 1669–1680.23715527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0059"><text><SENT sid="45546" pm="."><plain> YanaiOShaniERussDOriN 2011 Gibberellin partly mediates LANCEOLATE activity in tomato. The Plant Journal 68, 571–582.21771122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0060"><text><SENT sid="45547" pm="."><plain> YangCLiDMaoDLiuXUEJiCLiXZhaoXChengZChenCZhuL 2013 Overexpression of microRNA319 impacts leaf morphogenesis and leads to enhanced cold tolerance in rice (Oryza sativa L.). Plant, Cell &amp; Environment 36, 2207–2218. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0061"><text><SENT sid="45548" pm="."><plain> YangXPangHBLiuBLQiuZJGaoQWeiLDongYWangYZ 2012 Evolution of double positive autoregulatory feedback loops in CYCLOIDEA2 clade genes is associated with the origin of floral zygomorphy. The Plant Cell 24, 1834–1847.22649271 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0062"><text><SENT sid="45549" pm="."><plain> YaoXMaHWangJ ZhangD 2007 Genome-wide comparative analysis and expression pattern of TCP gene families in Arabidopsis thaliana and Oryza sativa . Journal of Integrative Plant Biology 49, 885–897. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
