<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Bacteriol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Bacteriol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">jb</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Bacteriology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9193</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1098-5530</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Society for Microbiology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>1752 N St., N.W., Washington, DC</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5892119</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00779-17</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00779-17</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="72221" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional Landscape and Regulatory Roles of Small Noncoding RNAs in the Oxidative Stress Response of the Haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">sRNA Regulation of Oxidative Stress in <named-content content-type="genus-species">H. volcanii</named-content></alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short-authors">Gelsinger and DiRuggiero</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gelsinger</surname><given-names>Diego Rivera</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6721-8061</contrib-id><name><surname>DiRuggiero</surname><given-names>Jocelyne</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>a</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Biology, The Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland, USA</aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Metcalf</surname><given-names>William W.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><aff>University of Illinois at Urbana Champaign</aff></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to Jocelyne DiRuggiero, <email>jdiruggiero@jhu.edu</email>.</corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="72222" pm="."><plain>Citation Gelsinger DR, DiRuggiero J. 2018. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72224" pm="."><plain>Transcriptional landscape and regulatory roles of small noncoding RNAs in the oxidative stress response of the haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72225" pm="."><plain>J Bacteriol 200:e00779-17. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00779-17">https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00779-17</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><day>20</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>1</day><month>5</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>200</volume><issue>9</issue><elocation-id>e00779-17</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2018 Gelsinger and DiRuggiero.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gelsinger and DiRuggiero</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International license</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="zjb009184714001.pdf"/><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="72226" pm="."><plain>ABSTRACT </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="72227" pm="."><plain>Haloarchaea in their natural environment are exposed to hypersalinity, intense solar radiation, and desiccation, all of which generate high levels of oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72228" pm="."><plain>Previous work has shown that haloarchaea are an order of magnitude more resistant to oxidative stress than most mesophilic organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72229" pm="."><plain>Despite this resistance, the pathways haloarchaea use to respond to oxidative stress damage are similar to those of nonresistant organisms, suggesting that regulatory processes might be key to their robustness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72230" pm="."><plain>Recently, small regulatory noncoding RNAs (sRNAs) were discovered in Archaea under a variety of environmental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72231" pm="."><plain>We report here the transcriptional landscape and functional roles of sRNAs in the regulation of the oxidative stress response of the model haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72232" pm="."><plain>Thousands of sRNAs, both intergenic and antisense, were discovered using strand-specific sRNA sequencing (sRNA-seq), comprising 25 to 30% of the total transcriptome under no-challenge and oxidative stress conditions, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72233" pm="."><plain>We identified hundreds of differentially expressed sRNAs in response to hydrogen peroxide-induced oxidative stress in H. volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72234" pm="."><plain>The targets of a group of antisense sRNAs decreased in expression when these sRNAs were upregulated, suggesting that sRNAs are potentially playing a negative regulatory role on mRNA targets at the transcript level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72235" pm="."><plain>Target enrichment of these antisense sRNAs included mRNAs involved in transposon mobility, chemotaxis signaling, peptidase activity, and transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="72236" pm="."><plain>IMPORTANCE While a substantial body of experimental work has been done to uncover the functions of small regulatory noncoding RNAs (sRNAs) in gene regulation in Bacteria and Eukarya, the functional roles of sRNAs in Archaea are still poorly understood. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72237" pm="."><plain>This study is the first to establish the regulatory effects of sRNAs on mRNAs during the oxidative stress response in the haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72238" pm="."><plain>Our work demonstrates that common principles for the response to a major cellular stress exist across the 3 domains of life while uncovering pathways that might be specific to the Archaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72239" pm="."><plain>This work also underscores the relevance of sRNAs in adaptation to extreme environmental conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>archaea</kwd><kwd>extreme environments</kwd><kwd>noncoding RNA</kwd><kwd>oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>small RNA</kwd><kwd>transcriptional regulation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group id="award1"><funding-source id="gs1"><institution-wrap><institution>DOD | USAF | AFMC | Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR)</institution><institution-id>https://doi.org/10.13039/100000181</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id rid="gs1">FA9950-14-1-0118</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>DiRuggiero</surname><given-names>Jocelyne</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><counts><count count="10" count-type="supplementary-material"/><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="79"/><page-count count="17"/><word-count count="10559"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>May 2018</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="72240" pm="."><plain>INTRODUCTION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72241" pm="."><plain>Microbial communities that reside inside halite nodules from Salars in the Atacama Desert, Chile, are under extreme environmental pressures due to hypersalinity, intense solar radiation, and frequent desiccation-hydration cycles, which all generate high levels of oxidative stress (1, 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72242" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress occurs when the level of reactive oxygen species (ROS) produced in cells overwhelms antioxidant defense mechanisms and damage accumulates (3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72243" pm="."><plain>Through metagenomic studies, we found the dominant populations in these salt rocks to be haloarchaea such as Haloferax and Halobacterium (4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72244" pm="."><plain>These halophilic microorganisms are members of the third domain of life, the Archaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72245" pm="."><plain>Haloarchaea have previously been shown to be highly resistant to ROS damage, withstanding many times what Escherichia coli and other radiation-sensitive organisms can survive (5–7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72246" pm="."><plain>The haloarchaeon Halobacterium salinarum has been shown to use a wide range of strategies to combat damage from oxidative stress, including multiple copies of genomes (polyploidy) as the substrate for DNA repair, functional redundancy of DNA repair and detoxification enzymes (e.g., catalase), increased cytosolic manganese complexes to scavenge ROS, and differential regulation of genes in response to stress (5–9). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72247" pm="."><plain>However, pathways for DNA repair and protein turnover in haloarchaea are nearly identical to those in nonresistant bacteria and eukarya, suggesting that the regulation of these processes in response to oxidative stress might be key to their robustness. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72248" pm="."><plain>Previous work with H. salinarum oxidative stress gene regulatory networks revealed that a single transcription factor, RosR, regulates the appropriate dynamic response of nearly 300 genes to reactive oxygen species stress (5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72249" pm="."><plain>This work demonstrated that the oxidative stress response in H. salinarum impacted a wide array of cellular processes, engaging at least 50% of all the genes (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72250" pm="."><plain>These results underline the importance of gene regulation in haloarchaea for responding to and counteracting the damage caused by oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72251" pm="."><plain>In addition to transcription factors, small regulatory RNAs (sRNAs) similarly act as global gene regulators (10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72252" pm="."><plain>Small RNAs (sRNAs) are ubiquitously found in Bacteria and Eukarya, playing large-scale roles in gene regulation, transposable element silencing, defense against disease state, and foreign elements (11–14). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72253" pm="."><plain>Several types of sRNAs have been identified in the Eukarya (microRNAs [miRNAs], small interfering RNAs [siRNAs], and Piwi-interacting RNAs [piRNAs]) and they are typically 20 to 25 nucleotides (nt) long. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72254" pm="."><plain>Their major mode of interaction is through base pairing to the 3′ untranslated region (UTR) of their target mRNAs, inhibiting translation or triggering target degradation with associated protein components (Argonautes) (10). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72255" pm="."><plain>Bacterial sRNAs have been shown to modulate core metabolic functions and stress-related responses, such as nutrient deprivation, by binding target mRNAs and causing their degradation or preventing translation (11, 15). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72256" pm="."><plain>Most of the functionally characterized sRNAs in Bacteria bind the 5′ UTR of their target mRNA and are longer than their eukaryal counterparts, with sizes ranging from 50 to 500 nt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72257" pm="."><plain>These sRNAs can target multiple genes, including key transcription factors and regulators (11, 15, 16). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72258" pm="."><plain>As a consequence, a single sRNA can modulate the expression of large regulons and thus have a significant effect on metabolic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72259" pm="."><plain>For example, the bacterial sRNA OxyS, which is dramatically induced by oxidative stress, regulates the expression of approximately 40 genes and interacts directly with eight target mRNAs (11). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72260" pm="."><plain>sRNAs have been discovered to be abundant in Archaea, more specifically in haloarchaea, in response to a variety of environmental conditions, but the functional roles of these RNAs still remain poorly understood and a link between sRNAs expression and oxidative stress response has not been established (13, 17–24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72261" pm="."><plain>Only a few studies on sRNAs in hyperthermophiles, methanogens, and the haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii have been reported so far (13, 17–24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72262" pm="."><plain>In H. volcanii, large numbers of intergenic and antisense-encoded sRNAs, 145 and 45, respectively, were discovered by using microarray in addition to a novel class of sRNAs recently described in eukaryotes, tRNA-derived fragments (tRFs), and a new study found thousands of sRNAs present in this organism (19, 24, 25). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72263" pm="."><plain>In Sulfolobus solfataricus, 125 trans-encoded sRNAs and 185 cis-antisense sRNAs were identified using high-throughput sequencing (HTS), suggesting that 6.1% of all genes in S. solfataricus are associated with sRNAs (26). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72264" pm="."><plain>A comparative genome analysis of Methanosarcina mazei, M. barkeri, and M. acetivorans revealed that 30% of the antisense and 21% of the intergenic sRNAs identified were conserved across the 3 species (27). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72265" pm="."><plain>Coimmunoprecipitation with the Lsm protein (archaeal Hfq homolog) was used to “capture” sRNAs (17), but its functional role remains to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72266" pm="."><plain>While Ago homologs have also been found in archaeal genomes, there is no evidence for eukaryote-like RNA interference in these organisms (28). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72267" pm="."><plain>Rather, a defensive role against foreign genetic material was recently proposed, whereby archaeal Ago proteins direct guide-dependent cleavage of foreign DNA (29–31). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72268" pm="."><plain>Altogether, these studies suggest that sRNAs are as widespread and abundant in the Archaea as in the Bacteria and Eukarya. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72269" pm="."><plain>Target mRNA identification of sRNAs has proven to be difficult within the Archaea but is a necessary task for uncovering sRNA functionality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72270" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome sequencing (RNA-seq) in M. mazei cultures, grown under nitrogen starvation conditions, showed the differential expression of a number of sRNAs in response to nitrogen availability and enabled the identification of the first in vivo target for archaeal intergenic sRNAs (27, 32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72271" pm="."><plain>The potential target for sRNA162 is a bicistronic mRNA encoding a transcription factor involved in regulating the switch between carbon sources and a protein of unknown function (32). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72272" pm="."><plain>In Pyrobaculum, 3 antisense sRNAs were found opposite a ferric uptake regulator, a triose-phosphate isomerase, and transcription factor B, supporting a potential role for archaeal antisense sRNA in the regulation of iron, transcription, and core metabolism (33). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72273" pm="."><plain>sRNA deletion mutants can be used to identify potential biological functions and target genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72274" pm="."><plain>Deletion strains were successfully generated for H. volcanii, and phenotyping of the sRNAs deletion mutants revealed several severe growth defects under high temperatures, low salt concentrations, or specific carbon sources (9, 22). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72275" pm="."><plain>While these studies revealed that sRNAs likely play essential roles in the physiological responses to environmental challenges in the Archaea, the functional roles and mechanisms of action of these important posttranscriptional regulators still remain unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72276" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, no work has been done to investigate archaeal sRNAs in response to oxidative stress, a universal and frequent stressor in all domains of life that results in extensive cellular damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72277" pm="."><plain>To determine the impact of sRNAs during the oxidative stress response, we assessed the H. volcanii transcriptional landscape under no-challenge and oxidative stress conditions using comparative strand-specific small RNA sequencing (sRNA-seq). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="72278" pm="."><plain>RESULTS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72279" pm="."><plain>To identify globally small noncoding RNAs differentially expressed in response to oxidative stress in H. volcanii, we exposed 5 replicate cultures of H. volcanii to 2 mM H2O2, a dose that resulted in the survival of 80% of the cells (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72280" pm="."><plain>S1 in the supplemental material). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72281" pm="."><plain>RNA from these H2O2-treated cultures and from no-challenge cultures (controls) was sequenced using a strand-specific size-selected (50 to 500 nt) sRNA library preparation essential for sRNA discovery. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="sec2-1"><title><text><SENT sid="72282" pm="."><plain>Small noncoding RNA discovery in H. volcanii and normalized expression values. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72283" pm="."><plain>We obtained at total of 137 million sequence reads (41 Gb) across all replicates and conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72284" pm="."><plain>Following quality control and reference-based read mapping, we intersected the mapped reads against the H. volcanii reference genome to discover sRNA transcripts that we classified as antisense (overlapping a gene and/or its regulatory elements on the opposite strand) (Fig. 1A) and intergenic (in a noncoding region between two genes) (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72285" pm="."><plain>We were unable to identify previously described cis-internal sRNAs (24), because with our RNA-seq strategies, those transcripts would be confounded with the corresponding gene transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72286" pm="."><plain>To further validate the sRNAs we identified and reduce transcriptional noise in our data, we applied a rigorous two-pronged in silico approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72287" pm="."><plain>First, we used a stringent threshold requiring an sRNA (i) to be present in at least four of five biological replicate libraries, and (ii) to have a minimum expression of 40 transcripts per million ([TPM] average with standard deviation from replicates) for antisense sRNAs (asRNAs) and 14 TPM for intergenic sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72288" pm="."><plain>Second, we used the genome browser IGV to inspect visually and confirm each sRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72289" pm="."><plain>These novel transcripts represented 25 to 30% of the total transcriptome and were 50 to 1,000 nt in length (Fig. 2; see also Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72290" pm="."><plain>Putative mRNA targets for asRNAs were identified as the cis mRNAs encoded on the opposite strands with a minimum overlap of 8 nt, on the basis of IGV confirmation and reports for bacterial asRNAs (34). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72291" pm="."><plain>However, we found in our data that the median overlap between sRNAs and putative cis-mRNA targets was 221 nt, with only a small number having a minimum overlap length of 8 nt (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72292" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72293" pm="."><plain>Analyzing the upstream regions of sRNAs enabled the discovery that 30% of sRNAs contained a BRE and TATA box with centroids at nt −38 and −29 (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72294" pm="."><plain>S3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72295" pm="."><plain>The use of less-conservative parameters (nt −3 and +3) for BRE and TATA box centroids resulted in 70% of sRNAs having transcriptional motifs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72296" pm="."><plain>Genome viewer of antisense sRNAs (cis acting) (A) and intergenic sRNAs (trans acting) (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72297" pm="."><plain>Paired-end reads (100 bases) were mapped to the H. volcanii NCBI reference genome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72298" pm="."><plain>Reference genes are marked as black lines with arrowheads indicating their location on the plus strand (&gt;) or minus strand (&lt;). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72299" pm="."><plain>Reads marked in red are transcribed from the minus strand, while blue reads are transcribed from the plus strand. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72300" pm="."><plain>Untranslated regions were predicted using Rockhopper2 (pink lines). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72301" pm="."><plain>Green lines mark discovered sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72302" pm="."><plain>Coverage plots are in gray. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72303" pm="."><plain>Number of sRNAs (total, antisense, and intergenic) discovered under no-challenge and H2O2 challenge conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="72304" pm="."><plain>Normalized expression values in RNA-seq analyses are often reported as reads or fragments per kilobase of transcript per million mapped reads (RPKM or FPKM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72305" pm="."><plain>However, RPKM/FPKM has been shown to be inconsistent for comparisons between samples due to variable transcript lengths. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72306" pm="."><plain>Another expression value, transcripts per million (TPM), was found to be preferable, because it is independent of the mean expressed transcript length and TPM normalization performs better in multiple library comparisons (35–38). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72307" pm="."><plain>To minimize transcript length bias (sRNAs are generally smaller in length than protein-encoding genes) and to compare sRNA and mRNA expression levels, we chose to use TPM in our analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-2"><title><text><SENT sid="72308" pm="."><plain>Noncoding sRNA characterization in H. volcanii under no-challenge conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72309" pm="."><plain>H. volcanii grown under no-challenge conditions (42°C, complex medium) expressed a total of 1,533 sRNAs after quality control (as described above) (Fig. 2; Table S1), ranging from 49 to 1,000 nt in size and with an average length of 373 nt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72310" pm="."><plain>A majority of these sRNAs, 1,480 sRNAs (97%), were antisense to coding regions (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72311" pm="."><plain>The H. volcanii H53 auxotroph genome is 4 Mbp and contains 4,130 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72312" pm="."><plain>The genome constitutes a chromosome stably integrated with small chromosome pHV4 and 2 small chromosomes (pHV1 and pHV3), and it has been cured of plasmid pHV2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72313" pm="."><plain>A majority of sRNAs (68%) were carried on the chromosome and integrated small chromosome pHV4 (18%). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72314" pm="."><plain>No sRNAs were found on plasmid pHV2, as expected, while sRNAs were carried on the remaining small chromosomes pHV1 (2%) and pHV3 (12%). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72315" pm="."><plain>We compared mRNA expression to sRNA expression by constructing mRNA sequencing (mRNA-seq) libraries, using the same RNA pool and library preparation as the sRNA-seq libraries (omitting size selection) and calculating transcript expression as TPM (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72316" pm="."><plain>S4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72317" pm="."><plain>Relative to mRNA expression levels (average, 312.1 ± 1,079.1 TPM), the expression of sRNAs was on average higher (average, 1,107.9 ± 137.6 TPM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72318" pm="."><plain>We also found that a majority of sRNAs had higher expression levels than mRNAs (sRNA: range, 14.1 to 905,191.0 TPM; median, 108.5 TPM; mRNA: range, 1.0 to 210,162.0 TPM; median, 15.1 TPM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72319" pm="."><plain>Overall, 75% of sRNAs had expression values less than or equal to 320 TPM, 15% had expression levels similar to those of highly expressed mRNAs, (500 to 10,000 TPM), and 16 sRNAs (sRNAs no. 1771 to 1786) (Table S1) had very robust expression levels with TPMs ranging from 10,000 to 60,000 TPM (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72320" pm="."><plain>S4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72321" pm="."><plain>Lastly, 1 intergenic sRNA (STRG.2577.4), 111 nt in size, exhibited expression levels higher than any mRNA with a TPM of 905,191 (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72322" pm="."><plain>Transcript length did not correlate with expression levels, indicating that when we observed sRNAs with low expression levels, it was not an artifact of sequencing (i.e., longer transcripts receiving more read coverage thus skewing coverage based on length) (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72323" pm="."><plain>S5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72324" pm="."><plain>We found that 4 of the 5 most highly expressed sRNAs (TPM &gt; 30,000) were antisense to coding regions (Table S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72325" pm="."><plain>Putative mRNA targets of the most highly expressed asRNAs (≥10,000 TPM) included an IS4 family transposase (HVO_RS18385), ATP-cob(I)alamin adenosyltransferase (HVO_RS16235), transducer protein Htr36 (HVO_RS15355), pyridoxamine 5′-phosphate oxidase (HVO_RS07060), XerC/D integrase (HVO_RS01885), IS110 family transposase/pseudoregion (HVO_RS07375), protein translocase TatA (HVO_RS09630), deoxyhypusine synthase (HVO_RS00895), sugar ABC transporter permease (HVO_RS17705), hydrolase (HVO_RS12225), peptidase (HVO_RS08770), RND transporter (HVO_RS14695), and IS110 family transposase (HVO_RS02445). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72326" pm="."><plain>We do not report putative targets for intergenic sRNAs because of the inherent difficulty in reliably predicting these targets due to unknown degrees of complementarity (i.e., gaps in hybridization between an intergenic sRNA and an mRNA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-3"><title><text><SENT sid="72327" pm="."><plain>Noncoding sRNAs in H. volcanii under oxidative stress conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72328" pm="."><plain>H. volcanii under H2O2-induced oxidative stress conditions expressed 1,227 sRNAs, a 20% decrease in the number of sRNAs compared to that under the no-challenge condition (Fig. 2; Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72329" pm="."><plain>Despite this decrease, a pattern of sRNA distribution similar to that under the no-challenge condition was observed; more than 94% of sRNAs were antisense and a majority (69%) were carried on the main chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72330" pm="."><plain>A smaller average length of 337 nt was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72331" pm="."><plain>The overall TPM expression of sRNAs during oxidative stress was similar to that under the no-challenge state, with a decrease in expression level for the single most highly expressed sRNA (STRG.2577.4 in no-challenge, 905,191 TPM; STRG.2983.4 in H2O2, 810,120 TPM), which was an intergenic sRNA (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72332" pm="."><plain>S4B; Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72333" pm="."><plain>Putative targets for the most highly expressed asRNAs (≥10,000 TPM) included both 16S rRNA genes (HVO_RS1301 and HVO_RS18290, two sRNAs), an IS4 family transposase (HVO_RS18385), an M48 family peptidase (HVO_RS20365), a uracil-DNA glycosylase (HVO_RS09685), Agl cluster protein AglR (HVO_RS20160), a hypothetical protein (HVO_RS20230), transducer protein Htr36 (HVO_RS15355), an ISH3 family transposase/pseudoregion (HVO_RS19935), an IS4 family transposase (HVO_RS03870), (HVO_RS07060), and an ABC transporter ATP-binding protein (HVO_RS20010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72334" pm="."><plain>Of these most highly expressed sRNAs, 3 asRNAs (STRG.2050.2, STRG.3974.5, and STRG.4700.1) targeted the same mRNAs, and 3 intergenic sRNAs (STRG.3072.1, STRG.2702.1, and STRG.2983.4) were expressed under both the no-challenge and oxidative stress conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2-4"><title><text><SENT sid="72335" pm="."><plain>Regulatory effects and differential expression of sRNAs during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72336" pm="."><plain>To investigate the regulatory effects sRNAs on their target mRNAs, we compared the expression levels (TPM) of all antisense sRNAs against the expression levels (TPM) of the in silico predicted putative cis-mRNA targets (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72337" pm="."><plain>We found that a large population of asRNA-mRNA cis pairs exhibited lower mRNA target expression than the sRNA, under both experimental conditions (Fig. 3; Table S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72338" pm="."><plain>We conducted a pairwise t test between these cis pairs on expression level differences between sRNAs and putative cis-target mRNAs and found that 755 of sRNAs had significantly (P &lt; 0.05) higher expression, potentially indicating a negative regulatory relationship between sRNAs and putative cis-mRNA targets (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72339" pm="."><plain>Transcript per million (TPM) expression levels between sRNAs and their putative cis-mRNA targets during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72340" pm="."><plain>Each point represents the TPM ratio between an sRNA and its putative cis-mRNA target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72341" pm="."><plain>TPM values are the averages from sRNA and mRNA replicates with error bars representing standard deviations among replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72342" pm="."><plain>A pairwise t test was conducted between sRNA and putative cis-mRNA target replicates to infer significant difference in TPM expression between the cis pairs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72343" pm="."><plain>Orange points indicate a P value &lt;0.05, and gray points indicate a P value &gt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72344" pm="."><plain>The red line represents no change in the ratio of sRNA–cis-mRNA expression (slope = 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140003"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="72345" pm="."><plain>To further investigate this negative regulatory relationship between sRNAs and putative mRNA targets, we probed for differentially expressed sRNAs between the no-challenge and the oxidative stress conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72346" pm="."><plain>Candidate sRNAs were considered significantly up- or downregulated by oxidative stress using a false-discovery rate (FDR) of less than 5%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72347" pm="."><plain>Using this statistical framework, we identified a core set of differentially expressed sRNAs specific to oxidative stress (Fig. 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72348" pm="."><plain>Both intergenic and antisense sRNAs were differentially expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72349" pm="."><plain>Of the intergenic sRNAs, 48 were significantly differentially expressed (FDR &lt; 0.05), with 23 upregulated and 25 downregulated (see Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72350" pm="."><plain>S6; Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72351" pm="."><plain>Of these upregulated intergenic sRNAs, 79% had an increase in expression greater than or equal to a fold change of 2 (log2 fold change = 1) during oxidative stress, with the most upregulated intergenic sRNA (STRG.277.2) having a 16-fold increase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72352" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, a majority of downregulated intergenic sRNAs had large fold changes in expression (≤2-fold change), and 5 exhibited very robust downregulation (≤−4-fold change). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72353" pm="."><plain>A total of 605 antisense sRNAs were significantly (FDR &lt; 0.05) differentially expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72354" pm="."><plain>These sRNAs were either upregulated (309) or downregulated (296) during oxidative stress, indicating two populations of antisense sRNAs (Fig. 4A; Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72355" pm="."><plain>Fifty percent (302 sRNAs) of these differentially expressed sRNAs demonstrated a fold change in expression of ±2 or greater; the most upregulated sRNA had a fold change of 15 and the most downregulated sRNA had a fold change of −9, indicating a role for these sRNAs in the cellular response to oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72356" pm="."><plain>More antisense sRNAs were upregulated with a fold change in expression of 4 or greater (28 sRNAs) than were downregulated (20 sRNAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72357" pm="."><plain>We then compared differential expression levels between all significantly upregulated antisense sRNAs and their putative cis-mRNA targets and found that a population (133 sRNAs [22%]) of these upregulated antisense sRNAs had putative mRNA targets that were downregulated during oxidative stress (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72358" pm="."><plain>For example, during oxidative stress, 36 upregulated antisense sRNAs targeted transposase mRNAs, and 24 of these antisense sRNAs had putative cis-target transposase mRNAs downregulated (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72359" pm="."><plain>While a smaller subset of significantly (FDR &lt; 0.05) downregulated antisense sRNAs had their putative cis-mRNA target upregulated during oxidative stress (72 [11%]), it also indicated a correlative potential negative regulatory effect (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72360" pm="."><plain>(A) Heat map of log2-transformed fold change of differentially expressed antisense sRNAs (asRNAs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72361" pm="."><plain>(B) Differential expression fold changes of upregulated asRNAs and their putative cis-mRNA targets (averages and standard deviation error bars from replicates). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72362" pm="."><plain>(C) Differential expression fold changes of downregulated asRNAs and their putative cis-mRNA targets (averages and standard deviation error bars from replicates). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72363" pm="."><plain>(D) Differential expression fold changes of all transposase-targeting asRNAs and their putative cis-transposase mRNA targets (averages and standard deviation error bars from replicates). *, both the asRNA and the cis-target transposase mRNAs have significant differential expression based on an FDR of &lt;0.05. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="72364" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress-responsive asRNAs were predicted to overlap both the 5′ and 3′ UTRs of mRNAs (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72365" pm="."><plain>We found that 7% of asRNAs overlapped at the 5′ UTRs and 26% overlapped at the 3′ UTRs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72366" pm="."><plain>However, the majority of the asRNAs (67%) overlapped the coding sequences (CDSs) of mRNAs rather than the UTRs, which has not been previously reported (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72367" pm="."><plain>We calculated that, on average, the overlap between sRNAs and their putative cis-target mRNAs was 265 nt, the range was 8 to 992 nt, and the peak overlap was between 150 and 200 nt (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72368" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72369" pm="."><plain>Using Northern blot analysis, we recapitulated the in vivo differential expression patterns of selected candidate sRNAs, further confirming the transcript sizes and differential expression levels for oxidative stress sRNAs (STRG.3823.1, -4700.1, -8.6, -277.2, -3733.1, -2983.4, and -4213.4) (Fig. 6A and B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72370" pm="."><plain>We also showed that the strandedness (the strand on which the sRNA was carried) predicted by our sRNA-seq analysis was confirmed by our in vivo data using oligonucleotide probe Northern blotting of 5′ UTRs, 3′ UTRs, CDS antisense sRNAs, and intergenic sRNAs (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72371" pm="."><plain>Distribution of binding regions for antisense sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72372" pm="."><plain>UTR, untranslated region; CDS, coding sequence. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72373" pm="."><plain>Validation of differentially expressed sRNAs by Northern blots. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72374" pm="."><plain>(A) Representative Northern blot confirming sizes and differential expression patterns of an intergenic sRNA during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72375" pm="."><plain>(B) Quantification of Northern blots confirming the expression of intergenic sRNAs (random primed labeling) and strand specificity of sRNAs (oligonucleotide labeling). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72376" pm="."><plain>All classes of sRNAs were confirmed: antisense (5′ UTR, 3′ UTR, CDS) and intergenic sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140006"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec2-5"><title><text><SENT sid="72377" pm="."><plain>Target enrichment of sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72378" pm="."><plain>We identified in silico targets for the differentially expressed oxidative-stress responsive antisense sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72379" pm="."><plain>Genes for the putative target mRNAs were categorized according to cellular function by using archaeal Cluster of Orthologous Genes (arCOGs) and according to pathways by using gene ontologies (GO) from Database for Annotation, Visualization, and Integrated Discovery (DAVID). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72380" pm="."><plain>For sRNAs upregulated during H2O2 stress, we found a functional enrichment of target genes encoding transposases, involved in chemotaxis methyl-receptor signaling and in transcriptional regulation (transcription factors) (P &lt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72381" pm="."><plain>Genes from many other pathways that were not enriched were also the targets of antisense sRNAs, including peptidase activity genes and serine and threonine biosynthesis genes (Fig. 7A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72382" pm="."><plain>Twenty-three of these sRNAs targeted transposase genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72383" pm="."><plain>Each of these transposase mRNAs was downregulated, while their cognate sRNA was upregulated, and the sRNA was always located at the 5′ UTR of its target. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72384" pm="."><plain>Most transposases belonged to the IS family of transposases, except for one DDE transposase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72385" pm="."><plain>Three transcription factor families (IclR, ArcR, and AsnC) were also targeted by asRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72386" pm="."><plain>A functional enrichment gene ontology analysis found that downregulated sRNAs targeted genes involved in membrane transport (ABC transporters) and the biosynthesis of secondary metabolites, as well as hydrolases (Fig. 7B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72387" pm="."><plain>A significant proportion of enriched targets for both up- and downregulated sRNAs were genes encoding hypothetical proteins. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 7</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72388" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology enrichment analysis identifying the functional classification of gene targets of sRNAs during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72389" pm="."><plain>(A) Enriched target gene functions for upregulated sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72390" pm="."><plain>(B) Enriched target gene functions for downregulated sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140007"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="sec2-6"><title><text><SENT sid="72391" pm="."><plain>mRNA transcriptional response to oxidative stress in H. volcanii. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72392" pm="."><plain>To determine the transcriptional landscape of mRNAs during oxidative stress, especially for mRNAs that were predicted targets of sRNAs, we sequenced rRNA-depleted mRNA-seq libraries in parallel with the previously described sRNA-seq libraries (derived from the same pool of total RNA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72393" pm="."><plain>During H2O2-induced oxidative stress, one-fourth of all genes (1,176) were significantly differentially expressed with a false-discovery rate of less than 5% (see Table S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72394" pm="."><plain>Both catalase and superoxide dismutase, known ROS detoxification enzymes, were upregulated at the mRNA level, thus validating our experimental approach and characterizing H. volcanii response to oxidative stress at the transcriptional level (Fig. 8). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72395" pm="."><plain>A GO enrichment analysis (DAVID) was used to identify what pathways were enriched with differentially expressed genes during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72396" pm="."><plain>The most enriched (P &lt; 0.05) upregulated genes were involved in transcription, including various transcription factor families, all of the RNA polymerase subunit genes, and transcription initiation factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72397" pm="."><plain>Other enriched (P &lt; 0.05) upregulated pathways were involved in iron-sulfur cluster assembly, DNA topological change (topoisomerase), proteasomes, cell redox homeostasis, histidine metabolism, and 2-oxocarboxylic acid metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72398" pm="."><plain>The most upregulated gene was a reactive intermediate/imine deaminase with a fold change expression increase of 84. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72399" pm="."><plain>The most enriched (P &lt; 0.05) downregulated genes were Tn5-like IS4 transposases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72400" pm="."><plain>Other enriched (P &lt; 0.05) downregulated pathways were pyrroloquinoline quinone (PQQ) proteins, tetrapyrrole methyltransferases, and ABC transporters. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72401" pm="."><plain>Only two genes had a downregulation of &lt;−4-fold, and these were an iron transporter and lysine 6-monooxygenase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>FIG 8</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="72402" pm="."><plain>Distribution of differentially expressed genes during oxidative stress in H. volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72403" pm="."><plain>(A) MA plot of differentially expressed genes; each point represent a gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72404" pm="."><plain>Significant (FDR &lt; 5%) differentially expressed sRNAs are color coded as upregulated (blue) or downregulated (red) and known oxidative stress response genes (yellow). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72405" pm="."><plain>(B) Gene function for the most up- and downregulated sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="zjb9990947140008"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="72406" pm="."><plain>DISCUSSION </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72407" pm="."><plain>Previous studies of sRNAs in Archaea revealed the abundance of sRNAs within the third domain of life and have been pivotal in establishing a working hypothesis on archaeal sRNA functionality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72408" pm="."><plain>These studies have been limited to (i) microarray studies that do not enable de novo discovery of sRNAs, (ii) differential RNA-seq (dRNA-seq) approaches, which select only for primary transcripts and do not provide length (nt) information nor expression information (only coverage), and (iii) individual sRNA studies, which do not give a holistic view of the pathways being regulated within the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72409" pm="."><plain>Using a custom strand-specific sRNA-seq library preparation and analysis pipeline, we have developed a method to perform high-throughput analysis of the sRNA transcriptional landscape, expression, and regulatory effects, and to identify regulated gene pathways in response to environmental stressors within the Archaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72410" pm="."><plain>In this study, we propose that sRNA-mediated transcriptional regulation is key in regulating stress responses to environmental challenges, such as oxidative stress, in the haloarchaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72411" pm="."><plain>sRNAs have the potential to carry out large-scale regulation of genes involved in the oxidative stress response, resulting in increased resistance to extreme environmental stressors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72412" pm="."><plain>The discovery that sRNAs comprised nearly one-third of the total transcriptome of H. volcanii and included basal transcriptional promoters, under both no-challenge and oxidative stress conditions, suggests that sRNAs have an important functional role under a variety of environmental conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72413" pm="."><plain>We discovered thousands of sRNAs expressed in H. volcanii, with the majority being antisense to genes, indicating that antisense transcription was ubiquitous within the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72414" pm="."><plain>This is in stark contrast to most of the literature reporting that a majority of sRNAs discovered in Archaea were intergenic (9, 13, 22, 39). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72415" pm="."><plain>This discrepancy is likely due to previous studies being limited to microarray approaches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72416" pm="."><plain>Indeed, a recent study using directional RNA-seq (dRNA-seq) to map all transcription start sites (TSS) in H. volcanii found thousands of novel TSS, with 1,244 of these TSS being antisense to mRNAs (24). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72417" pm="."><plain>Most of the TSS (75%) of the sRNAs we discovered in H. volcanii had the same TSS (±10 nt) as those found in the dRNA-seq study by Babski et al. (24), further confirming our results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72418" pm="."><plain>This underlines the importance of HTS studies, especially strand-specific RNA-seq such as in our study, to discover the full extent of antisense sRNA expression in Archaea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72419" pm="."><plain>Our finding suggests that a priori cis-acting sRNAs may play a larger role than trans-acting sRNAs within the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72420" pm="."><plain>It should not be overlooked that the difficulty in finding in silico targets for intergenic sRNAs, because these sRNAs do not form 100% complementarity with their targets, might suggest that they have multiple mRNA targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72421" pm="."><plain>Antisense and intergenic sRNAs are broad classifications used in the archaeal small noncoding RNA field, but our data revealed that further classifications can be made on the basis of sRNA-mRNA binding characteristics (5′ UTR, 3′ UTR, and CDS), differential expression, and regulatory effects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72422" pm="."><plain>We found that only a small fraction of asRNAs targeted the 5′ UTRs of mRNAs, which is in concurrence with work demonstrating that most mRNAs in H. volcanii are leaderless (lacking a 5′ UTR). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72423" pm="."><plain>A majority of the 5′ UTR-binding sRNAs targeted transposons, providing further evidence that they may constitute their own class of sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72424" pm="."><plain>Within this context, 3′ UTR-binding sRNAs should also be considered another class of sRNAs, resembling eukaryotic sRNAs, which likely lead to the degradation of their target transcripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72425" pm="."><plain>The majority of the asRNAs we identified in H. volcanii had 100% complementarity within the CDS of their target mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72426" pm="."><plain>This is the first report of such a finding in any domain of life and might constitute an attribute unique to archaeal sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72427" pm="."><plain>We could not identify any “seed” binding region for these CDS-binding sRNAs, indicating that they likely have full occupancy on the mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72428" pm="."><plain>It is worth noting that there were only a few instances (&lt;20) where sRNAs overlapped more than the full length of the target mRNA (i.e., the asRNA is longer than the mRNA) or overlapped multiple cis-mRNA targets (i.e., the asRNA overlaps the 3′ UTR of one mRNA and the 5′ UTR of an adjacent mRNA), which is novel in the Archaea. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72429" pm="."><plain>Most H. volcanii sRNAs had a normalized expression value of 200 TPM or less, indicating that sRNA transcripts are relatively abundant in the cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72430" pm="."><plain>The use of a stringent thresholding approach resulted in a smaller number of more highly expressed sRNAs but avoided potentially reporting false positives with low TPM values or transcriptional noise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72431" pm="."><plain>In comparison, most mRNAs within H. volcanii had TPM values of 20 or less. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72432" pm="."><plain>We found a population of antisense sRNAs with significantly higher expression than their putative cis-mRNA targets, suggesting a potential negative regulatory role in sRNA-mRNA interactions (Fig. 3 and 4B) (40–42). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72433" pm="."><plain>This trend extended to many asRNAs (under both no-challenge and oxidative stress conditions), down to sRNAs with expression levels of 40 TPM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72434" pm="."><plain>Stronger evidence for a negative regulatory effect lies with a population of upregulated sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72435" pm="."><plain>A group of significantly upregulated asRNAs had target mRNAs that were downregulated during oxidative stress, indicating these asRNAs could potentially negatively regulate mRNA targets at the transcript level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72436" pm="."><plain>Whether this negative regulation is occurring during transcription initiation/elongation or if these asRNAs are causing mRNA degradation is currently unknown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72437" pm="."><plain>All the asRNAs targeting transposons at the 5′ UTR were upregulated, and the transposon mRNAs were downregulated (Fig. 4D), suggesting that these asRNAs might have a similar mechanistic function (6, 43, 44). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72438" pm="."><plain>If indeed these asRNAs are negatively regulating their target mRNAs in H. volcanii, we expected to find that downregulated asRNAs have upregulated target mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72439" pm="."><plain>Some downregulated asRNA targets exhibited this pattern, further supporting a potential negative regulation (Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72440" pm="."><plain>Many mRNA targets of both up- and downregulated asRNAs exhibited the same regulatory pattern, suggesting a potential nonnegative regulatory role for a group of asRNAs (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72441" pm="."><plain>Alternative hypotheses, reflecting the complexity of transcriptional regulation in the Archaea, can be formed: (i) these asRNAs may have a positive regulatory effect, such as stabilizing target mRNAs and masking them from degradation as seen with an intergenic sRNA (itsRNA) in M. mazei (23), (ii) trans-acting intergenic sRNAs might be targeting these mRNAs, negatively regulating them, and (iii) some may have an unknown function (23). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72442" pm="."><plain>The most enriched negatively regulated sRNA targets were transposases, chemotaxis proteins, and transcription factors. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72443" pm="."><plain>It has been shown that transposons are opportunistic, and under stress conditions, they can wreak havoc by hopping around in the genome causing double-strand breaks and hence need to be silenced (6, 43, 44). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72444" pm="."><plain>A functional enrichment of IS4 transposon genes that are downregulated during oxidative stress supports our observation that the upregulated sRNAs can potentially negatively regulate transposons and suggests that transposon activity is tightly regulated during oxidative stress in H. volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72445" pm="."><plain>sRNA-mediated regulation of chemotaxis transducer proteins during oxidative stress suggests interesting implications in sensing ROS and motility. H. volcanii expresses genes coding for a flagellum analog named “archaellum,” which are organized into an operon and are regulated by a network of regulators called the archaellum regulatory network (arn) (identified in crenarchaea) (45, 46). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72446" pm="."><plain>The regulation of these motility genes is still under investigation and so far is restricted to a few examples, such as under H2 or nitrogen limitation conditions in Methanococcus jannaschii and Methanococcus maripaludis (46–49). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72447" pm="."><plain>No direct transcriptional regulators of the archaellum have been identified in Euryarchaeota, but the deletion of archaellin genes, the presence of the H-domain set of type IV pillins, and Agl proteins have been shown to affect the assembly of the archaellum in H. volcanii (46, 50–52). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72448" pm="."><plain>Integral to how microorganisms maintain homeostasis in stressful and fluctuating environments are the gene regulatory networks composed of interacting regulatory transcription factors and their target gene promoters (53). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72449" pm="."><plain>Our discovery that sRNAs are targeting transcription factors provides evidence that sRNAs are likely deeply interlaced within complex gene regulatory networks of H. volcanii, and these sRNAs are key to maintaining homeostasis during environmental stresses such as oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72450" pm="."><plain>Many mRNA targets of differentially regulated sRNAs were hypothetical proteins, indicating that much remains to be elucidated in this organism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72451" pm="."><plain>Our whole transcriptional analysis demonstrated that close to one-third of the genes (∼1,100 [30%]) in H. volcanii were differentially regulated during constant H2O2-induced oxidative stress at ∼80% survival, which is in agreement with the transcriptional response of H. salinarum during constant H2O2-induced (929 genes [38%]) and paraquat-induced (1,099 genes [45%]) oxidative stresses at ∼80% survival (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72452" pm="."><plain>This indicates that transcriptional regulation is crucial in order to mount this oxidative stress response via gene activation and repression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72453" pm="."><plain>Two single-stranded DNA binding proteins (RpaB and RpaC) were found necessary for the increased survival of H. volcanii under ionizing radiation (a proxy for desiccation) and UV radiation, stressors that both cause oxidative stress (54, 55) (J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72454" pm="."><plain>DiRuggiero, unpublished data). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72455" pm="."><plain>In H. salinarum, Rpa operons were upregulated under ionizing radiation as well and contributed to resistance (56, 57). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72456" pm="."><plain>In conjunction with previous findings, we observed that two of the most upregulated genes during H2O2 oxidative stress were RpaB1 (HVO_RS10725, 23-fold change) and RpaB2 (HVO_RS06105, 8-fold change), confirming their roles in oxidative stress resistance in H. volcanii and likely other haloarchaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72457" pm="."><plain>One gene, a reactive intermediate/imine deaminase RidA-homolog (HVO_RS12485), was upregulated orders of magnitude more than any other gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72458" pm="."><plain>The encoded protein is known to be involved in the synthesis of branched-chain amino acids by speeding up the IlvA-catalyzed deamination of threonine into 2-ketobutyrate (58, 59). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72459" pm="."><plain>Previous work has shown that in the presence of reactive chlorine species (RCS), such as HOCl, imine deaminase seemed to inhibit IlvA activity suggesting that imine deaminase may have a different function in the presence of RCS (58, 60). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72460" pm="."><plain>Further studies found that imine deaminase can sense RCS and, in doing so, becomes a chaperone that prevents protein aggregation (58). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72461" pm="."><plain>Reactive oxygen species in hypersaline environments produce RCS (61). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72462" pm="."><plain>In addition, ROS cause extensive irreversible protein damage such as carbonylation, which in turn causes protein aggregation (62, 63). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72463" pm="."><plain>This reactive intermediate/imine deaminase is the most upregulated protein-encoding gene, suggesting that it may be playing a similar chaperone role to prevent protein aggregation, by sensing either ROS or RCS produced by H2O2 (58, 60). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72464" pm="."><plain>This study is the first to report on the transcriptional response of H. volcanii to oxidative stress, and while we found similar responses to H2O2 exposure as previously reported for H. salinarum (2), further validating our work and providing evidence that haloarchaea have evolved similar strategies to survive their environmental stresses, we also found responses that were unique to H. volcanii. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72465" pm="."><plain>Similarities to H. salinarum include the upregulation of genes encoding ROS scavenging proteins (catalase and superoxide dismutase) and iron sulfur assembly proteins (SufB and SufD), as well as proteasome genes, indicating high protein turnover, and many DNA repair genes (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72466" pm="."><plain>Most of the downregulated genes were involved with metabolism, such as sugar/phosphate/peptide ABC transporters, electron carriers (halocyanin), and tricarboxylic acid (TCA) cycle enzymes, possibly to halt growth until damage is repaired (2, 64). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72467" pm="."><plain>The most downregulated gene was for an iron ABC transporter, most likely to limit further production of ROS via Fenton reactions (2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72468" pm="."><plain>Of the unique responses to oxidative stress in H. volcanii, we found that genes encoding all of the RNA polymerase subunits and transcription elongation factors and seven basal transcription initiation factors (HVO_RS12755, 18.4-fold change; HVO_RS01380, 8.6-fold; HVO_RS09745, 6.5-fold; HVO_RS01840, 2.1-fold; HVO_RS05475, 1.74-fold; HVO_RS11835, 1.5-fold; HVO_RS05475, 1.3-fold change) were significantly upregulated in response to oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72469" pm="."><plain>The increase in sRNAs during oxidative stress could be attributed to this increase in transcription machinery. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72470" pm="."><plain>The majority of the 30S and 50S ribosomal subunits were downregulated, in contrast to that in H. salinarum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72471" pm="."><plain>The upregulations of genes coding for histidine biosynthesis and catabolism into glutamate and 2-oxocarboxylic acid metabolism were unknown to be involved in the oxidative stress response, which further demonstrates there are still more mechanisms to uncover for oxidative stress resistance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72472" pm="."><plain>RosR was identified as a global transcriptional regulator in H. salinarum, and it was strongly upregulated during oxidative stress (5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72473" pm="."><plain>RosR demonstrated no differential expression during oxidative stress in H. volcanii, indicating that it may play another role in this organism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72474" pm="."><plain>Cell cycle genes (parA and cdc6) involved in chromosome segregation (65) were downregulated, further suggesting that division is being arrested (halting growth) in order to repair damage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="72475" pm="."><plain>In this study, we showed for the first time that small noncoding RNAs are specifically associated with the oxidative stress response in archaea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72476" pm="."><plain>During oxidative stress, asRNAs were prevalently transcribed, comprising nearly 30% of the transcriptome of H. volcanii, and many upregulated asRNAs imparted a correlative negative regulatory effect on putative target mRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72477" pm="."><plain>These results support the hypothesis that some asRNAs in Archaea behave similarly to cis-acting bacterial sRNAs and eukaryotic siRNAs, which negatively regulate mRNAs by sharing extensive complementarity and facilitating RNA degradation (66, 67). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72478" pm="."><plain>The precise mechanism(s) of sRNA-mRNA mediated regulation, in particular, whether proteins are required to complex with sRNAs in order to mediate gene regulation, such as in Bacteria (Hfq) and Eukarya (Ago), remains to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72479" pm="."><plain>We also identified several classes of asRNAs, on the basis of their mRNA-binding patterns (3′ UTR, 5′ UTR, and CDS) and showed that CDS targeting of mRNAs was the predominant mode of action for sRNA hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72480" pm="."><plain>The mechanistic differences between these classes of sRNAs, as well as the regulatory roles of sRNAs in archaea and their functional importance in adaption to extreme environments, still need to be investigated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="72481" pm="."><plain>MATERIALS AND METHODS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec4-1"><title><text><SENT sid="72482" pm="."><plain>Culture growth conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72483" pm="."><plain>H. volcanii auxotrophic strain H53 (Δpyre2 ΔtrpA) was used for all experiments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72484" pm="."><plain>Culturing in liquid and solid media was done in rich medium (Hv-YPC) at 42°C and with shaking at 220 rpm (Amerex Gyromax 737) (68). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72485" pm="."><plain>Uracil and tryptophan were added to a final concentration of 50 μg/ml each. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-2"><title><text><SENT sid="72486" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress exposure. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72487" pm="."><plain>We exposed 5 biological replicates of H. volcanii strain H53 liquid cultures to the oxidative stress agent H2O2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72488" pm="."><plain>Initially, cultures were grown in 80 ml of Hv-YPC under optimal conditions to an optical density (OD) of 0.4 (mid-exponential phase). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72489" pm="."><plain>To ensure homogeneity, each replicate was subsequently split into two 40-ml cultures, one used for the no-challenge (control) condition and the other for the oxidative stress condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72490" pm="."><plain>For the latter condition, 2 mM H2O2 (80% survival rate, previously determined) was directly added to the cultures followed by a 1-h incubation at 42°C with shaking at 220 rpm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72491" pm="."><plain>Cultures were then rapidly cooled down and centrifuged at 5,000 × g for 5 min, and the pellets were resuspended in 18% seawater. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72492" pm="."><plain>The cell suspensions were then transferred to 1-ml tubes and centrifuged at 6,000 × g for 3 min, and the pellets were flash frozen and stored at −80°C until ready for RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72493" pm="."><plain>Control no-challenge culture replicates were processed in the same manner without the addition of H2O2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-3"><title><text><SENT sid="72494" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress survival curves. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72495" pm="."><plain>The assessment of survival in H. volcanii under oxidative stress conditions was conducted using microdilution plating as described previously (7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72496" pm="."><plain>The counts from replicates were averaged and the standard deviations calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72497" pm="."><plain>Survival was calculated as the number of viable cells following H2O2 treatment divided by the number of viable untreated cells and graphed with standard error bars. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-4"><title><text><SENT sid="72498" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72499" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted using the Zymo Quick-RNA Miniprep kit with the following modifications: after the addition of RNA lysis buffer to the frozen cell pellets, the cells were processed with 23-gauge needles and syringes to ensure complete cell lysis. H. volcanii liquid cultures are slimy and viscous; thus, to increase cellular lysis, 23-gauge needles and syringes were used to break down the cell pellets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72500" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was then extracted according to the standard kit protocol. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-5"><title><text><SENT sid="72501" pm="."><plain>Small RNA-sequencing library preparation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72502" pm="."><plain>Total RNA for each biological replicate and condition was size selected by denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72503" pm="."><plain>Twenty micrograms of total RNA was loaded onto a 7% denaturing urea polyacrylamide gel (SequaGel; National Diagnostics) in 0.5× Tris-borate-EDTA (TBE) buffer and run at a constant power of 30 W until the bromophenol blue bands reached the bottom of the gel. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72504" pm="."><plain>The gel was stained with SYBR Gold and visualized on a blue light box, and bands in the 50 to 500 nucleotide range, as indicated by the RNA Century Marker plus ladder (Thermo Fisher), were excised. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72505" pm="."><plain>Small RNAs (sRNA) were eluted by rotating overnight in 1.2 ml 0.3 M NaCl and were ethanol precipitated and DNase I (NEB) treated (37°C for 2 h) as previously described (69). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72506" pm="."><plain>Strand-specific libraries were prepared using the SMART-seq Ultralow RNA input kit (TaKaRa), and insert sizes were checked with the Bioanalyzer RNA pico kit (Agilent). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72507" pm="."><plain>Paired-end sequencing (2 × 150 bp) was carried out on the Illumina HiSeq 2500 platform at the Johns Hopkins University Genetic Resources Core Facility (GRCF). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-6"><title><text><SENT sid="72508" pm="."><plain>mRNA-sequencing library preparation. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72509" pm="."><plain>Individual mRNA-seq libraries were made from the same RNA pools as the sRNA-seq libraries above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72510" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was rRNA depleted using the Ribo-zero bacteria kit (Illumina) and sequenced using the sRNA-seq library preparation method described above but omitting the size selection by denaturing urea polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-7"><title><text><SENT sid="72511" pm="."><plain>sRNA- and RNA-seq read quality control and reference-based read mapping. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72512" pm="."><plain>The assessment of the quality of each sequencing library read was conducted using fastqc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72513" pm="."><plain>The program trim galore was used with base settings to trim adapter sequences from reads and to filter out low phred score reads (&lt;20). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72514" pm="."><plain>Short-length reads were preserved. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72515" pm="."><plain>Reads from each replicate were aggregated together per condition to get a set of consensus sRNAs and were mapped against the H. volcanii NCBI RefSeq genome (taxonomy identification [taxid] 2246; 1 chromosome, 4 plasmids) using the hisat2 aligner with strand-specific options turned on and splice aware options turned off, in paired-end mode (70). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-8"><title><text><SENT sid="72516" pm="."><plain>sRNA- and RNA-seq transcriptome assembly. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72517" pm="."><plain>The reference-based alignments were assembled into transcriptomes using the program stringtie to build full-length transcripts and calculate coverage and expression values (TPM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72518" pm="."><plain>The assembly was guided by a gene annotation file from the H. volcanii DS2 (NCBI RefSeq taxid 2246) genome to build transcripts and annotate them as either a gene or novel transcript (71). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72519" pm="."><plain>The minimum distance between reads for transcript assembly was specified at 30 nucleotides. gffcompare under default options was used to compare the assembled transcriptomes against the gene annotation file from H. volcanii DS2 (NCBI RefSeq taxid 2246) to annotate transcripts as genes or noncoding RNA (antisense or intergenic) (72, 73). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72520" pm="."><plain>In-house python scripts were used to bin transcripts that were annotated as genes, transcripts annotated as antisense (classified as a noncoding region opposite from a coding region), and transcripts annotated as intergenic (classified as a noncoding region between two coding regions), and antisense sRNAs were subsequently binned as 3′ UTR, 5′ UTR, or CDS overlapping. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-9"><title><text><SENT sid="72521" pm="."><plain>sRNA- and RNA-seq differential expression analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72522" pm="."><plain>We used a read count-based differential expression analysis to identify differentially expressed sRNAs during oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72523" pm="."><plain>The program featureCounts was used to rapidly count reads that map to the assembled sRNA transcripts (described above) (74). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72524" pm="."><plain>featureCounts was run with strand-specific options on, paired-end mode on, and multimapping off (74). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72525" pm="."><plain>The read counts were then used in the R differential expression software package DESeq2 (75). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72526" pm="."><plain>Briefly, read counts were converted into a data matrix and normalized by sequencing depth and geometric mean. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72527" pm="."><plain>Differential expression was calculated by finding the difference in read counts between the no-challenge state (control) normalized read counts and the oxidative stress normalized read counts (75). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72528" pm="."><plain>The differentially expressed sRNAs were filtered on the basis of the statistical parameter of false-discovery rate (FDR), and those that were equal to or under an FDR of 5% were classified as true differentially expressed sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-10"><title><text><SENT sid="72529" pm="."><plain>In silico validation of sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72530" pm="."><plain>Differentially expressed sRNAs were validated by two in silico methods: (i) visualization of transcripts and (ii) open reading frame protein homology search. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72531" pm="."><plain>In the first method, transcriptomes for each replicate and condition were visualized on the Integrated Genome Viewer (IGV) against the H. volcanii (NCBI RefSeq taxid 2246) genome and annotation (76). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72532" pm="."><plain>The sRNA transcript coordinates were used to locate putative sRNAs, and if it was found within an operon, it was eliminated from further analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72533" pm="."><plain>In the second method, blastx (default parameters) was used to search for protein and domain homology for each sRNA, and those that had significant homology with known proteins or domains were eliminated from further analysis (77). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-11"><title><text><SENT sid="72534" pm="."><plain>Regulatory element motif identification of sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72535" pm="."><plain>One hundred nucleotides upstream and downstream from the sRNA transcript start and stop coordinates were extracted using in-house python scripts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72536" pm="."><plain>These regions were searched for transcription motifs (BRE and TATA box) using multiple sequence alignments, visualization with WebLogo (default parameters), and motif searching with MEME and CentriMo (default parameters) (78, 79). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-12"><title><text><SENT sid="72537" pm="."><plain>In vivo validation of sRNAs by Northern blot analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72538" pm="."><plain>Twenty micrograms of total RNA and [32P]ATP end-labeled Century-Plus RNA markers was loaded onto 5% denaturing urea polyacrylamide gels (SequaGel; National Diagnostics) and run at 30 W for 1.5 h to ensure well-spaced gel migration from 50 to 1,000 nucleotides (nt). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72539" pm="."><plain>Gels were transferred onto Ultrahyb nylon membranes and hybridized with 2 types of probes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72540" pm="."><plain>For lowly expressed sRNAs, we probed with [γ-32P]dATP randomly primed amplicons generated with custom primers based on sRNA transcript genomic coordinates as determined by the sRNA-seq in silico analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72541" pm="."><plain>Probe primers were at a minimum of 10 nt inward from the predicted genomic coordinates (start and stop) to ensure accurate transcript detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72542" pm="."><plain>Hybridizations were performed at 65°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72543" pm="."><plain>To determine strandedness of sRNAs, we used [α-32P]dATP end-labeled oligonucleotide probes (20 to 23 nt) that were antisense to sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72544" pm="."><plain>Hybridizations were at 42°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72545" pm="."><plain>The rpl30 protein (HVO_RS16975) transcript was used as a loading control for differential expression calculation, because it was not differentially expressed under oxidative stress in this RNA-seq data set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72546" pm="."><plain>Differential expression was calculated using ImageJ. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-13"><title><text><SENT sid="72547" pm="."><plain>Gene ontology enrichment analysis of mRNA-targets. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72548" pm="."><plain>NCBI gene names for all mRNA targets of antisense sRNAs were uploaded into Database for Annotation, Visualization, and Integrated Discovery (DAVID) to determine the pathways and gene ontologies targeted by sRNAs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec4-14"><title><text><SENT sid="72549" pm="."><plain>Accession number(s). </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72550" pm="."><plain>All raw reads and processed data from these experiments are available at NCBI under BioProject <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bioproject/?term=PRJNA407425" assigning-authority="bioproject">PRJNA407425</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72551" pm="."><plain>Illumina raw sequence data (.fastq) for each replicate and condition are deposited in NCBI Sequence Read Archive with accession number SRP117726. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag>
<SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title><text><SENT sid="72552" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title><text><SENT sid="72553" pm="."><plain>Supplemental material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_200_9_e00779-17__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714s1.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714s2.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714s3.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714s4.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714s5.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714s6.pdf"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb009184714sd7.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714sd8.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714sd9.xlsx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="JB.00779-17_zjb999094714sd10.xlsx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec></SecTag>
</body><back><fn-group><SecTag type="SUPPL"><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p><text><SENT sid="72554" pm="."><plain>Supplemental material for this article may be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00779-17">https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00779-17</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="72555" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by grant FA9950-14-1-0118 from the AFOSR. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="72556" pm="."><plain>We thank Madeline Cassani, Zhao Zhang, and German Uritskiy for advice and guidance on sRNA-seq library preparation, Evan Hass and Vidya Balagopal for advice on Northern blotting, Jacques Ravel, Mike Humphrys, and David Mohr for sequencing efforts and technical advice, and John Kim and Sarah Woodson for helpful discussions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="72557" pm="."><plain>1.RobinsonCK, WierzchosJ, BlackC, Crits-ChristophA, MaB, RavelJ, AscasoC, ArtiedaO, ValeaS, RoldanM, Gomez-SilvaB, DiRuggieroJ 2015 Microbial diversity and the presence of algae in halite endolithic communities are correlated to atmospheric moisture in the hyper-arid zone of the Atacama Desert. Environ Microbiol 17:299–315. doi:10.1111/1462-2920.12364.24372972 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="72558" pm="."><plain>2.KaurA, VanPT, BuschCR, RobinsonCK, PanM, PangWL, ReissD, DiRuggieroJ, BaligaNS 2010 Coordination of frontline defense mechanisms under severe oxidative stress. Mol Syst Biol 6:393. doi:10.1038/msb.2010.50.20664639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="72559" pm="."><plain>3.ImlayJA 2008 Cellular defenses against superoxide and hydrogen peroxide. Annu Rev Biochem 77:755–776. doi:10.1146/annurev.biochem.77.061606.161055.18173371 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="72560" pm="."><plain>4.Crits-ChristophA, GelsingerDR, MaB, WierzchosJ, RavelJ, AscasoC, ArtiedaO, DavilaA, DiRuggieroJ 2016 Functional analysis of the archaea, bacteria, and viruses from a halite endolithic microbial community. Environ Microbiol 18:2064–2077. doi:10.1111/1462-2920.13259.26914534 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="72561" pm="."><plain>5.SharmaK, GillumN, BoydJL, SchmidA 2012 The RosR transcription factor is required for gene expression dynamics in response to extreme oxidative stress in a hypersaline-adapted archaeon. BMC Genomics 13:351. doi:10.1186/1471-2164-13-351.22846541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="72562" pm="."><plain>6.WhiteheadK, KishA, PanM, KaurA, ReissDJ, KingN, HohmannL, DiRuggieroJ, BaligaNS 2006 An integrated systems approach for understanding cellular responses to gamma radiation. Mol Syst Biol 2:47. doi:10.1038/msb4100091.16969339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="72563" pm="."><plain>7.RobinsonCK, WebbK, KaurA, JarugaP, DizdarogluM, BaligaNS, PlaceA, DiRuggieroJ 2011 A major role for nonenzymatic antioxidant processes in the radioresistance of Halobacterium salinarum. J Bacteriol 193:1653–1662. doi:10.1128/JB.01310-10.21278285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="72564" pm="."><plain>8.WebbKM, WuJ, RobinsonCK, TomiyaN, LeeY, DiRuggieroJ 2013 Effects of intracellular Mn on the radiation resistance of the halophilic archaeon Halobacterium salinarum. Extremophiles 17:485–497. doi:10.1007/s00792-013-0533-9.23532412 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="72565" pm="."><plain>9.SharmaA, GrichenkoO, MatrosovaVY, HoekeV, KlimenkovaP, ConzeIH, VolpeRP, TkavcbR, GostinþarG, Gunde-CimermanN, DiRuggieroJ, ShuryakgI, OzarowskihA, HoffmanaBM, DalyMJ 2017 Across the tree of life, radiation resistance is governed by antioxidant Mn2+, gauged by paramagnetic resonance. Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A 114:E9253–E9260. doi:10.1073/pnas.1713608114. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="72566" pm="."><plain>10.MorrisKV, MattickJS 2014 The rise of regulatory RNA. Nat Rev Genet 15:423–437. doi:10.1038/nrg3722.24776770 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="72567" pm="."><plain>11.AltuviaS, Weinstein-FischerD, ZhangA, PostowL, StorzG 1997 A small, stable RNA induced by oxidative stress: role as a pleiotropic regulator and antimutator. Cell 90:43–53. doi:10.1016/S0092-8674(00)80312-8.9230301 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="72568" pm="."><plain>12.CechTR, SteitzJA 2014 The noncoding RNA revolution-trashing old rules to forge new ones. Cell 157:77–94. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2014.03.008.24679528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="72569" pm="."><plain>13.MarchfelderA, FischerS, BrendelJ, StollB, MaierLK, JagerD, PrasseD, PlagensA, SchmitzRA, RandauL 2012 Small RNAs for defence and regulation in archaea. Extremophiles 16:685–696. doi:10.1007/s00792-012-0469-5.22763819 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="72570" pm="."><plain>14.PrasseD, EhlersC, BackofenR, SchmitzRA 2013 Regulatory RNAs in archaea: first target identification in methanoarchaea. Biochem Soc Trans 41:344–349. doi:10.1042/BST20120280.23356309 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="72571" pm="."><plain>15.AltuviaS 2004 Regulatory small RNAs: the key to coordinating global regulatory circuits. J Bacteriol 186:6679–6680. doi:10.1128/JB.186.20.6679-6680.2004.15466017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="72572" pm="."><plain>16.GottesmanS, StorzG 2011 Bacterial small RNA regulators: versatile roles and rapidly evolving variations. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol 3:a003798. doi:10.1101/cshperspect.a003798.20980440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="72573" pm="."><plain>17.FischerS, BenzJ, SpathB, MaierLK, StraubJ, GranzowM, RaabeM, UrlaubH, HoffmannJ, BrutschyB, AllersT, SoppaJ, MarchfelderA 2010 The archaeal Lsm protein binds to small RNAs. J Biol Chem 285:34429–34438. doi:10.1074/jbc.M110.118950.20826804 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="72574" pm="."><plain>18.FischerS, BenzJ, SpathB, Jellen-RitterA, HeyerR, DorrM, MaierLK, Menzel-HobeckC, LehrM, JantzerK, BabskiJ, SoppaJ, MarchfelderA 2011 Regulatory RNAs in Haloferax volcanii. Biochem Soc Trans 39:159–162. doi:10.1042/BST0390159.21265765 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="72575" pm="."><plain>19.HeyerR, DorrM, Jellen-RitterA, SpathB, BabskiJ, JaschinskiK, SoppaJ, MarchfelderA 2012 High throughput sequencing reveals a plethora of small RNAs including tRNA derived fragments in Haloferax volcanii. RNA Biol 9:1011–1018. doi:10.4161/rna.20826.22767255 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="72576" pm="."><plain>20.Schmitz-StreitR, JägerD, Jellen-RitterA, BabskiJ, SoppaJ, MarchfelderA 2011 Archaea employ small RNAs as regulators, p 131–145. In HessWR, MarchfelderA (ed), Regulatory RNAs in prokaryotes. Springer Verlag, Vienna, Austria. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="72577" pm="."><plain>21.SoppaJ, StraubJ, BrenneisM, Jellen-RitterA, HeyerR, FischerS, GranzowM, VossB, HessWR, TjadenB, MarchfelderA 2009 Small RNAs of the halophilic archaeon Haloferax volcanii. Biochem Soc Trans 37:133–136. doi:10.1042/BST0370133.19143617 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="72578" pm="."><plain>22.StraubJ, BrenneisM, Jellen-RitterA, HeyerR, SoppaJ, MarchfelderA 2009 Small RNAs in haloarchaea: identification, differential expression and biological function. RNA Biol 6:281–292. doi:10.4161/rna.6.3.8357.19333006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="72579" pm="."><plain>23.PrasseD, FörstnerKU, JägerD, BackofenR, SchmitzRA 2017 sRNA154 a newly identified regulator of nitrogen fixation in Methanosarcina mazei strain Gö1. RNA Biol 14:1544–1558. doi:10.1080/15476286.2017.1306170.28296572 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="72580" pm="."><plain>24.BabskiJ, HaasKA, Näther-SchindlerD, PfeifferF, FörstnerKU, HammelmannM, HilkerR, BeckerA, SharmaCM, MarchfelderA, SoppaJ 2016 Genome-wide identification of transcriptional start sites in the haloarchaeon Haloferax volcanii based on differential RNA-Seq (dRNA-Seq). BMC Genomics 17:629. doi:10.1186/s12864-016-2920-y.27519343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="72581" pm="."><plain>25.GebetsbergerJ, ZywickiM, KünziA, PolacekN 2012 tRNA-derived fragments target the ribosome and function as regulatory non-coding RNA in Haloferax volcanii. Archaea 2012:260909. doi:10.1155/2012/260909.23326205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="72582" pm="."><plain>26.WurtzelO, SapraR, ChenF, ZhuY, SimmonsBA, SorekR 2010 A single-base resolution map of an archaeal transcriptome. Genome Res 20:133–141. doi:10.1101/gr.100396.109.19884261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="72583" pm="."><plain>27.JägerD, SharmaCM, ThomsenJ, EhlersC, VogelJ, SchmitzRA 2009 Deep sequencing analysis of the Methanosarcina mazei Go1 transcriptome in response to nitrogen availability. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 106:21878–21882. doi:10.1073/pnas.0909051106.19996181 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="72584" pm="."><plain>28.LiY, LiuX, HuangL, GuoH, WangXJ 2010 Potential coexistence of both bacterial and eukaryotic small RNA biogenesis and functional related protein homologs in Archaea. J Genet Genomics 37:493–503. doi:10.1016/S1673-8527(09)60069-2.20816382 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="72585" pm="."><plain>29.WillkommS, OelligCA, ZanderA, RestleT, KeeganR, GrohmannD, SchneiderS 2017 Structural and mechanistic insights into an archaeal DNA-guided Argonaute protein. Nat Microbiol 2:17035. doi:10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.35.28319084 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B30"><text><SENT sid="72586" pm="."><plain>30.ZanderA, WillkommS, OferS, van WolferenM, EgertL, BuchmeierS, StöcklS, TinnefeldP, SchneiderS, KlinglA, AlbersS-V, WernerF, GrohmannD 2017 Guide-independent DNA cleavage by archaeal Argonaute from Methanocaldococcus jannaschii. Nat Microbiol 2:17034. doi:10.1038/nmicrobiol.2017.34.28319081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B31"><text><SENT sid="72587" pm="."><plain>31.WillkommS, ZanderA, GustA, GrohmannD 2015 A prokaryotic twist on Argonaute function. Life (Basel) 5:538–553. doi:10.3390/life5010538.25692904 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B32"><text><SENT sid="72588" pm="."><plain>32.JägerD, PernitzschSR, RichterAS, BackofenR, SharmaCM, SchmitzRA 2012 An archaeal sRNA targeting cis- and trans-encoded mRNAs via two distinct domains. Nucleic Acids Res 40:10964–10979. doi:10.1093/nar/gks847.22965121 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B33"><text><SENT sid="72589" pm="."><plain>33.BernickDL, DennisPP, LuiLM, LoweTM 2012 Diversity of antisense and other non-coding RNAs in archaea revealed by comparative small RNA sequencing in four Pyrobaculum species. Front Microbiol 3:231. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2012.00231.22783241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B34"><text><SENT sid="72590" pm="."><plain>34.ThomasonMK, StorzG 2010 Bacterial antisense RNAs: how many are there and what are they doing? Annu Rev Genet 44:167–188. doi:10.1146/annurev-genet-102209-163523.20707673 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B35"><text><SENT sid="72591" pm="."><plain>35.ConesaA, MadrigalP, TarazonaS, Gomez-CabreroD, CerveraA, McPhersonA, SzczeœniakMW, GaffneyDJ, EloLL, ZhangX, MortazaviA 2016 A survey of best practices for RNA-seq data analysis. Genome Biol 17:13. doi:10.1186/s13059-016-0881-8.26813401 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B36"><text><SENT sid="72592" pm="."><plain>36.LiB, DeweyCN 2011 RSEM: accurate transcript quantification from RNA-Seq data with or without a reference genome. BMC Bioinformatics 12:323. doi:10.1186/1471-2105-12-323.21816040 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B37"><text><SENT sid="72593" pm="."><plain>37.LiB, RuottiV, StewartRM, ThomsonJA, DeweyCN 2010 RNA-Seq gene expression estimation with read mapping uncertainty. Bioinformatics 26:493–500. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp692.20022975 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B38"><text><SENT sid="72594" pm="."><plain>38.WagnerGP, KinK, LynchVJ 2012 Measurement of mRNA abundance using RNA-seq data: RPKM measure is inconsistent among samples. Theory Biosci 131:281–285. doi:10.1007/s12064-012-0162-3.22872506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B39"><text><SENT sid="72595" pm="."><plain>39.BabskiJ, MaierLK, HeyerR, JaschinskiK, PrasseD, JägerD, RandauL, SchmitzRA, MarchfelderA, SoppaJ 2014 Small regulatory RNAs in Archaea. RNA Biol 11:484–493. doi:10.4161/rna.28452.24755959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B40"><text><SENT sid="72596" pm="."><plain>40.StorzG, VogelJ, WassarmanKM 2011 Regulation by small RNAs in bacteria: expanding frontiers. Mol Cell 43:880–891. doi:10.1016/j.molcel.2011.08.022.21925377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B41"><text><SENT sid="72597" pm="."><plain>41.HeL, HannonGJ 2004 MicroRNAs: small RNAs with a big role in gene regulation. Nat Rev Genet 5:522–531. doi:10.1038/nrg1379.15211354 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B42"><text><SENT sid="72598" pm="."><plain>42.De LayN, SchuDJ, GottesmanS 2013 Bacterial small RNA-based negative regulation: Hfq and its accomplices. J Biol Chem 288:7996–8003. doi:10.1074/jbc.R112.441386.23362267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B43"><text><SENT sid="72599" pm="."><plain>43.WheelerBS 2013 Small RNAs, big impact: small RNA pathways in transposon control and their effect on the host stress response. Chromosome Res 21:587–600. doi:10.1007/s10577-013-9394-4.24254230 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B44"><text><SENT sid="72600" pm="."><plain>44.CapyP, GasperiG, BiemontC, BazinC 2000 Stress and transposable elements: co-evolution or useful parasites? Heredity 85:101–106. doi:10.1046/j.1365-2540.2000.00751.x.11012710 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B45"><text><SENT sid="72601" pm="."><plain>45.HoffmannL, SchummerA, ReimannJ, HauratMF, WilsonAJ, BeebyM, WarscheidB, AlbersSV 2017 Expanding the archaellum regulatory network—the eukaryotic protein kinases ArnC and ArnD influence motility of Sulfolobus acidocaldarius. Microbiologyopen 6:e00414. doi:10.1002/mbo3.414. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B46"><text><SENT sid="72602" pm="."><plain>46.AlbersS-V, JarrellKF 2015 The archaellum: how Archaea swim. Front Microbiol 6:23. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2015.00023.25699024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B47"><text><SENT sid="72603" pm="."><plain>47.MukhopadhyayB, JohnsonEF, WolfeRS 2000 A novel pH2 control on the expression of flagella in the hyperthermophilic strictly hydrogenotrophic methanarchaeaon Methanococcus jannaschii. Proc Nat Acad Sci U S A 97:11522–11527. doi:10.1073/pnas.97.21.11522. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B48"><text><SENT sid="72604" pm="."><plain>48.HendricksonEL, LiuY, Rosas-SandovalG, PoratI, SöllD, WhitmanWB, LeighJA 2008 Global responses of Methanococcus maripaludis to specific nutrient limitations and growth rate. J Bacteriol 190:2198–2205. doi:10.1128/JB.01805-07.18203827 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B49"><text><SENT sid="72605" pm="."><plain>49.XiaQ, WangT, HendricksonEL, LieTJ, HackettM, LeighJA 2009 Quantitative proteomics of nutrient limitation in the hydrogenotrophic methanogen Methanococcus maripaludis. BMC Microbiol 9:149. doi:10.1186/1471-2180-9-149.19627604 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B50"><text><SENT sid="72606" pm="."><plain>50.EsquivelRN, PohlschroderM 2014 A conserved type IV pilin signal peptide H-domain is critical for the post-translational regulation of flagella-dependent motility. Mol Microbiol 93:494–504. doi:10.1111/mmi.12673.24945931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B51"><text><SENT sid="72607" pm="."><plain>51.TripepiM, ImamS, PohlschröderM 2010 Haloferax volcanii flagella are required for motility but are not involved in PibD-dependent surface adhesion. J Bacteriol 192:3093–3102. doi:10.1128/JB.00133-10.20363933 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B52"><text><SENT sid="72608" pm="."><plain>52.TripepiM, YouJ, TemelS, Önder Ö BrissonD, PohlschröderM 2012 N-glycosylation of Haloferax volcanii flagellins requires known Agl proteins and is essential for biosynthesis of stable flagella. J Bacteriol 194:4876–4887. doi:10.1128/JB.00731-12.22730124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B53"><text><SENT sid="72609" pm="."><plain>53.DarnellCL, SchmidAK 2015 Systems biology approaches to defining transcription regulatory networks in halophilic archaea. Methods 86:102–114. doi:10.1016/j.ymeth.2015.04.034.25976837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B54"><text><SENT sid="72610" pm="."><plain>54.StroudA, LiddellS, AllersT 2012 Genetic and biochemical identification of a novel single-stranded DNA-binding complex in Haloferax volcanii. Front Microbiol 3:224. doi:10.3389/fmicb.2012.00224.22719738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B55"><text><SENT sid="72611" pm="."><plain>55.SkowyraA, MacNeillSA 2012 Identification of essential and non-essential single-stranded DNA-binding proteins in a model archaeal organism. Nucleic Acids Res 40:1077–1090. doi:10.1093/nar/gkr838.21976728 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B56"><text><SENT sid="72612" pm="."><plain>56.DeVeauxLC, llerJA, SmithJ, PetriskoJ, WellsDP, DasSarmaS 2007 Extremely radiation-resistant mutants of a halophilic archaeon with increased single-stranded DNA-binding protein (RPA) gene expression. Radiat Res 168:507–514. doi:10.1667/RR0935.1.17903038 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B57"><text><SENT sid="72613" pm="."><plain>57.McCreadyS, MullerJA, BoubriakI, BerquistBR, NgWL, DassarmaS 2005 UV irradiation induces homologous recombination genes in the model archaeon, Halobacterium sp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72614" pm="."><plain>NRC-1. Saline Systems 1:3. doi:10.1186/1746-1448-1-3.16176594 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B58"><text><SENT sid="72615" pm="."><plain>58.MüllerA, LangklotzS, LupilovaN, KuhlmannK, BandowJE, LeichertLIO 2014 Activation of RidA chaperone function by N-chlorination. Nat Commun 5:5804. doi:10.1038/ncomms6804.25517874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B59"><text><SENT sid="72616" pm="."><plain>59.LambrechtJA, FlynnJM, DownsDM 2012 Conserved YjgF protein family deaminates reactive enamine/imine intermediates of pyridoxal 5′-phosphate (PLP)-dependent enzyme reactions. J Biol Chem 287:3454–3461. doi:10.1074/jbc.M111.304477.22094463 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B60"><text><SENT sid="72617" pm="."><plain>60.DahlJ-U, GrayMJ, JakobU 2015 Protein quality control under oxidative stress conditions. J Mol Biol 427:1549–1563. doi:10.1016/j.jmb.2015.02.014.25698115 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B61"><text><SENT sid="72618" pm="."><plain>61.StutzJ, AckermannR, FastJD, BarrieL 2002 Atmospheric reactive chlorine and bromine at the Great Salt Lake, Utah. Geophys Res Let 29:18-1–18-4. doi:10.1029/2002GL014812. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B62"><text><SENT sid="72619" pm="."><plain>62.NyströmT 2005 Role of oxidative carbonylation in protein quality control and senescence. EMBO J 24:1311–1317. doi:10.1038/sj.emboj.7600599.15775985 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B63"><text><SENT sid="72620" pm="."><plain>63.SuzukiYJ, CariniM, ButterfieldDA 2010 Protein carbonylation. Antioxid Redox Signal 12:323–325. doi:10.1089/ars.2009.2887.19743917 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B64"><text><SENT sid="72621" pm="."><plain>64.ScharfB, EngelhardM 1993 Halocyanin, an archaebacterial blue copper protein (type I) from Natronobacterium pharaonis. Biochemistry 32:12894–12900. doi:10.1021/bi00210a043.8251512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B65"><text><SENT sid="72622" pm="."><plain>65.LindasA-C, BernanderR 2013 The cell cycle of archaea. Nat Rev Microbiol 11:627–638. doi:10.1038/nrmicro3077.23893102 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B66"><text><SENT sid="72623" pm="."><plain>66.WatersLS, StorzG 2009 Regulatory RNAs in bacteria. Cell 136:615–628. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2009.01.043.19239884 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B67"><text><SENT sid="72624" pm="."><plain>67.MackGS 2007 MicroRNA gets down to business. Nat Biotechnol 25:631–638. doi:10.1038/nbt0607-631.17557095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B68"><text><SENT sid="72625" pm="."><plain>68.Dyall-SmithML 2001 The Halohandbook. Protocols for haloarchaeal genetics. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.haloarchaea.com/resources/halohandbook/">http://www.haloarchaea.com/resources/halohandbook/</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B69"><text><SENT sid="72626" pm="."><plain>69.ZhangZ, TheurkaufWE, WengZ, ZamorePD 2012 Strand-specific libraries for high throughput RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) prepared without poly(A) selection. Silence 3:9. doi:10.1186/1758-907X-3-9.23273270 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B70"><text><SENT sid="72627" pm="."><plain>70.KimD, LangmeadB, SalzbergSL 2015 HISAT: a fast spliced aligner with low memory requirements. Nat Methods 12:357–360. doi:10.1038/nmeth.3317.25751142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B71"><text><SENT sid="72628" pm="."><plain>71.PerteaM, PerteaGM, AntonescuCM, ChangT-C, MendellJT, SalzbergSL 2015 StringTie enables improved reconstruction of a transcriptome from RNA-seq reads. Nat Biotech 33:290–295. doi:10.1038/nbt.3122. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B72"><text><SENT sid="72629" pm="."><plain>72.PerteaGM 2015 gffcompare. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/gpertea/gffcompare">https://github.com/gpertea/gffcompare</ext-link>.  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B73"><text><SENT sid="72630" pm="."><plain>73.PerteaM, KimD, PerteaGM, LeekJT, SalzbergSL 2016 Transcript-level expression analysis of RNA-seq experiments with HISAT, StringTie and Ballgown. Nat Protoc 11:1650–1667. doi:10.1038/nprot.2016.095.27560171 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B74"><text><SENT sid="72631" pm="."><plain>74.LiaoY, SmythGK, ShiW 2014 featureCounts: an efficient general purpose program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features. Bioinformatics 30:923–930. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btt656.24227677 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B75"><text><SENT sid="72632" pm="."><plain>75.LoveMI, HuberW, AndersS 2014 Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol 15:550. doi:10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8.25516281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B76"><text><SENT sid="72633" pm="."><plain>76.RobinsonJT, ThorvaldsdottirH, WincklerW, GuttmanM, LanderES, GetzG, MesirovJP 2011 Integrative genomics viewer. Nat Biotechnol 29:24–26. doi:10.1038/nbt.1754.21221095 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B77"><text><SENT sid="72634" pm="."><plain>77.AltschulSF, GishW, MillerW, MyersEW, LipmanDJ 1990 Basic local alignment search tool. J Mol Biol 215:403–410. doi:10.1016/S0022-2836(05)80360-2.2231712 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B78"><text><SENT sid="72635" pm="."><plain>78.CrooksGE, HonG, ChandoniaJ-M, BrennerSE 2004 WebLogo: a sequence logo generator. Genome Res 14:1188–1190. doi:10.1101/gr.849004.15173120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B79"><text><SENT sid="72636" pm="."><plain>79.BaileyTL, BodenM, BuskeFA, FrithM, GrantCE, ClementiL, RenJ, LiWW, NobleWS 2009 MEME SUITE: tools for motif discovery and searching. Nucleic Acids Res 37:W202–W208. doi:10.1093/nar/gkp335.19458158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
