<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" open-status="O" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nutr Metab (Lond)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nutr Metab (Lond)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nutrition &amp; Metabolism</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1743-7075</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5504778</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">200</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12986-017-0200-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Review</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="58733" pm="."><plain>Hyperglycemia-induced oxidative stress and heart disease-cardioprotective effects of rooibos flavonoids and phenylpyruvic acid-2-O-β-D-glucoside </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dludla</surname><given-names>Phiwayinkosi V.</given-names></name><address><phone>+27 219380877</phone><email>pdludla@mrc.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Joubert</surname><given-names>Elizabeth</given-names></name><address><email>JoubertL@arc.agric.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>Christo J.F.</given-names></name><address><email>christo.muller@mrc.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Louw</surname><given-names>Johan</given-names></name><address><email>johan.louw@mrc.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Rabia</given-names></name><address><email>rabia.johnson@mrc.ac.za</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9155 0024</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.415021.3</institution-id><institution/><institution>Biomedical Research and Innovation Platform (BRIP), South African Medical Research Council, </institution></institution-wrap>P.O. Box 19070, Tygerberg, 7505 South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2214 904X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11956.3a</institution-id><institution>Division of Medical Physiology, </institution><institution>Faculty of Health Sciences, Stellenbosch University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tygerberg, South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0388 8690</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.428715.d</institution-id><institution>Plant Bioactives Group, Post-Harvest and Wine Technology Division, </institution><institution>Agricultural Research Council (ARC) Infruitec- Nietvoorbij, </institution></institution-wrap>Stellenbosch, South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2214 904X</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.11956.3a</institution-id><institution>Department of Food Science, </institution><institution>Stellenbosch University, </institution></institution-wrap>Stellenbosch, South Africa </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442325.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Biochemistry and Microbiology, </institution><institution>University of Zululand, </institution></institution-wrap>KwaDlangezwa, South Africa </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>45</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1"><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="58734" pm="."><plain>Diabetic patients are at an increased risk of developing heart failure when compared to their non-diabetic counter parts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58735" pm="."><plain>Accumulative evidence suggests chronic hyperglycemia to be central in the development of myocardial infarction in these patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58736" pm="."><plain>At present, there are limited therapies aimed at specifically protecting the diabetic heart at risk from hyperglycemia-induced injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58737" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress, through over production of free radical species, has been hypothesized to alter mitochondrial function and abnormally augment the activity of the NADPH oxidase enzyme system resulting in accelerated myocardial injury within a diabetic state. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58738" pm="."><plain>This has led to a dramatic increase in the exploration of plant-derived materials known to possess antioxidative properties. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58739" pm="."><plain>Several edible plants contain various natural constituents, including polyphenols that may counteract oxidative-induced tissue damage through their modulatory effects of intracellular signaling pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58740" pm="."><plain>Rooibos, an indigenous South African plant, well-known for its use as herbal tea, is increasingly studied for its metabolic benefits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58741" pm="."><plain>Prospective studies linking diet rich in polyphenols from rooibos to reduced diabetes associated cardiovascular complications have not been extensively assessed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58742" pm="."><plain>Aspalathin, a flavonoid, and phenylpyruvic acid-2-O-β-D-glucoside, a phenolic precursor, are some of the major compounds found in rooibos that can ameliorate hyperglycemia-induced cardiomyocyte damage in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58743" pm="."><plain>While the latter has demonstrated potential to protect against cell apoptosis, the proposed mechanism of action of aspalathin is linked to its capacity to enhance the expression of nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2 (Nrf2) expression, an intracellular antioxidant response element. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58744" pm="."><plain>Thus, here we review literature on the potential cardioprotective properties of flavonoids and a phenylpropenoic acid found in rooibos against diabetes-induced oxidative injury. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Diabetes mellitus</kwd><kwd>Hyperglycemia</kwd><kwd>Oxidative stress</kwd><kwd>Cardiomyopathy</kwd><kwd>Rooibos</kwd><kwd>Polyphenols</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001321</institution-id><institution>National Research Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>87836</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Rabia</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001322</institution-id><institution>South African Medical Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="58745" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par18"><text><SENT sid="58746" pm="."><plain>The prevalence of diabetes mellitus (DM) is increasing at an alarming rate worldwide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58747" pm="."><plain>According to recent data by the International Diabetes Federation, the number of individuals living with DM is 415 million, and this figure is estimated to reach 642 million by the year 2040 [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58748" pm="."><plain>Type 2 DM, which is associated with insulin resistance and obesity, represents approximately 90% of diabetic cases worldwide [2]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58749" pm="."><plain>Type 1 DM is characterized by deficient insulin secretion and chronic hyperglycemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58750" pm="."><plain>Chronic hyperglycemia remains the leading causal factor for the development of cardiovascular disease (CVD) and heart failure (HF) in a diabetic state [3, 4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58751" pm="."><plain>Chronic hyperglycemia alters the myocardial substrate preference in cardiomyocytes and augments production of free radical species, giving rise to oxidative stress [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58752" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress may directly induce cardiac structural remodeling, a prominent sign of diabetic cardiomyopathy (DCM) [6, 7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58753" pm="."><plain>DCM is a distinct clinical entity that was first described about four decades ago [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58754" pm="."><plain>The diagnosis of DCM remains nebulous and the precise mechanism explaining DCM has been partially explained. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58755" pm="."><plain>Although they remain mainly non-ischemic, distinctively affecting the heart muscle, cardiomyopathies play a pre-dominant role in inducing HF and are one of the major causes of death in Africa [8, 9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58756" pm="."><plain>Currently, there is no specific treatment for DCM; however, therapeutic drugs certainly play a significant role in the treatment of diabetes and its cardiovascular complications. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par19"><text><SENT sid="58757" pm="."><plain>Insulin and metformin are the commonly used therapies for the treatment of DM and have been shown to present limited cardiac protective properties [10–12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58758" pm="."><plain>It is known that CVD-related deaths in individuals with DM are still a major concern [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58759" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, lifestyle intervention of restricted energy intake and physical activity in persons with impaired glucose tolerance has been shown to improve CVD function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58760" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, most individuals do not adhere to such lifestyle interventions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58761" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, antioxidants are among the leading therapies being investigated for their efficacy against various metabolic complications [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58762" pm="."><plain>In the last decade, there has been much interest in the potential health benefits of plant polyphenols, such as resveratrol, mangiferin and aspalathin as dietary antioxidants [16–18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58763" pm="."><plain>The rooibos flavonoid and dihydrochalcone, aspalathin, has been investigated and reported to contribute to the antidiabetic properties of rooibos extract as reviewed by Muller and colleagues [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58764" pm="."><plain>This flavonoid and others have been shown to exert their therapeutic effects by mainly regulating the expression of key genes involved in energy metabolism and oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58765" pm="."><plain>Prime examples include 5′-adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase (AMPK), which is crucial for maintenance of myocardial substrate metabolism and nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2 (Nrf2), a transcription factor that is upregulated in response to oxidative stress [18, 19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58766" pm="."><plain>This review will discuss the cardioprotective potential of rooibos flavonoids and the phenylpropenoic acid, phenylpyruvic acid-2-O-β-D-glucoside (PPAG), against hyperglycemia-induced injury and heart disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58767" pm="."><plain>Physiological context is provided by a short overview of the role of oxidative stress in a diabetic heart. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="Sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="58768" pm="."><plain>Mechanisms of oxidative stress leading to cardiac tissue damage </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par20"><text><SENT sid="58769" pm="."><plain>Chronic hyperglycemia is strongly associated with enhanced oxidative stress-induced myocardial injury [13, 20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58770" pm="."><plain>This has been confirmed by various laboratory studies showing strong correlation between oxidative stress and matrix remodeling in cardiomyocytes isolated from diabetic heart tissue [21, 22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58771" pm="."><plain>Oxidative stress is aggravated by enhanced levels of Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS) within cardiomyocytes [21, 23, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58772" pm="."><plain>Abnormal ROS production elicits an increased pro-inflammatory response resulting in myocardial apoptosis [25]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58773" pm="."><plain>Some of the well-known reactive oxygen substances, associated with myocardial damage include superoxide anion (O2 •−) and hydrogen peroxide (H2O2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58774" pm="."><plain>Generation of ROS is generally a cascade of reactions that starts with the formation of O2 •− [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58775" pm="."><plain>Superoxide anion rapidly dismutates to H2O2, either spontaneously or catalytically by superoxide dismutase (SOD), while H2O2 is decomposed by catalase (CAT) to water and oxygen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58776" pm="."><plain>However, the mitochondrial electron transport chain and the actions of the nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate-oxidase (NADPH oxidase; Nox) enzymes remain the foremost sources of stress in cardiomyocytes (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58777" pm="."><plain>Mitochondrial structural modification is affiliated with reduced endogenous antioxidant status in cardiomyocytes from diabetic heart tissue [24, 27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58778" pm="."><plain>Correspondingly, augmented activity of NADPH oxidase is demonstrated in the myocardium of diabetic animals at the same rate as oxidative damage [28].Fig. 1Chronic hyperglycemia is strongly associated with enhanced oxidative stress-induced myocardial injury. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58779" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrial electron transport chain and the actions of the nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate-oxidase (NADPH oxidase) enzymes remain the foremost sources of stress in cardiomyocytes </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par21"><text><SENT sid="58780" pm="."><plain>The mitochondrion is an essential organelle for intracellular energy production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58781" pm="."><plain>Increasing the cellular demand of the mitochondrion to produce energy is associated with accelerated ROS production. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58782" pm="."><plain>Given that a diabetic heart has a diminished mitochondrial antioxidant capacity [29], it is therefore not surprising that minor alterations in mitochondrial structure or function induced by increased ROS are associated with major changes in the heart muscle [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58783" pm="."><plain>Increased ROS and mitochondrial depolarization, subsequent to diastolic dysfunction, have been reported in patients with metabolic disturbances [31, 32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58784" pm="."><plain>However, data explaining the precise role of mitochondrial dysfunction in a diabetic heart are still lacking. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par22"><text><SENT sid="58785" pm="."><plain>Concurrent with energy generation is the constant generation of ROS within the mitochondria [33]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58786" pm="."><plain>Accumulation of these radicals results in the induction of mitochondrial permeability transition (MPT) and the opening of high conductance permeability transition pores [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58787" pm="."><plain>MPT formation has been reported to lead to an altered redox state of the mitochondria [30]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58788" pm="."><plain>With disease states, the MPT opening is unique for being nonselective and allowing for the accumulation of excessive calcium (Ca2+) and other toxic compounds [35, 36]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58789" pm="."><plain>The fate of the cell after an insult depends on the extent of MPT pore formation [36–38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58790" pm="."><plain>If MPT pore formation occurs only to a limited extent, the cell may recover through cell recovery mechanisms such as activation of mitophagy/ubiquitination, whereas if MPT pore formation is exacerbated, it accelerates apoptosis [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58791" pm="."><plain>If it occurs to an even larger degree, the cell is likely to undergo necrotic cell death [38]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58792" pm="."><plain>Thus, prevention of mitochondrial membrane depolarization may play a role in reducing myocardial injury associated with chronic hyperglycemia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par23"><text><SENT sid="58793" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, Nox is another system that plays a notable role in the generation of ROS in many cell types, including cardiomyocytes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58794" pm="."><plain>Nox generates intracellular ROS by transferring electrons from NADPH across the cell membrane and coupling these to molecular oxygen to produce O2 •−. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58795" pm="."><plain>Nox exists in different isoforms, i.e. Nox1 to Nox4, with Nox2 and Nox4 predominant in the heart muscle [39, 40]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58796" pm="."><plain>Nox1 has been identified to be the major source of ROS production in vascular tissues, resulting in low levels of nitric oxide [41, 42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58797" pm="."><plain>Decreased levels of nitric oxide are connected to impaired endothelium-dependent vasodilation of coronary arteries [43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58798" pm="."><plain>Human aortic endothelial cells exposed to high glucose concentrations display amplified expression of Nox1 concomitant to enhanced oxidative damage [44]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58799" pm="."><plain>The same study showed that diabetic mice lacking Nox1 had profound anti-atherosclerotic outcome related to reduced ROS generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58800" pm="."><plain>Although Nox2 and Nox4 are predominant in the heart muscles, these two ROS producing enzymes are also expressed in other cell types and are implicated in agonist-stimulated redox-sensitive signal transduction [39]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58801" pm="."><plain>Nox2 has been shown to play a central role in insulin resistance-mediated oxidative damage in vascular tissue [45, 46]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58802" pm="."><plain>Nox2 knockout transgenic mice with endothelial-specific insulin resistance present reduced ROS production and vascular dysfunction [45]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58803" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, the Nox4 isoform is specifically expressed in mitochondria of cardiomyocytes; and mice lacking the Nox4 gene show reduced free radical damage [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58804" pm="."><plain>Its overexpression in the mouse heart deteriorates cardiac dysfunction by initiating apoptosis through cytochrome c release [28]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58805" pm="."><plain>Cytochrome c is a vital component of the mitochondrial electron transport chain, acting as an electron shuttle during redox generation of ATP [47]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58806" pm="."><plain>Its release and mitochondrial depolarization are considered key physiological events of apoptosis [48]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58807" pm="."><plain>In cardiomyocytes exposed to high glucose concentrations, cytochrome c release is enough to cause apoptosis, independent of mitochondrial depolarization status [49]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58808" pm="."><plain>Complex systems within the apoptotic pathway exacerbate myocardial injury through cytochrome c release [50]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58809" pm="."><plain>Therefore, interventions that could inhibit pro-apoptotic proteins and mitochondrial cytochrome c release could salvage myocardial injury. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="58810" pm="."><plain>Endogenous cardioprotective mechanisms </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="58811" pm="."><plain>Activation of AMPK </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par24"><text><SENT sid="58812" pm="."><plain>AMPK is a heterotrimeric protein composed of a catalytic alpha, non-catalytic beta and gamma subunit. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58813" pm="."><plain>The main function of this kinase is to preserve ATP or to promote alternative pathways of ATP generation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58814" pm="."><plain>It functions as a sensor during low energy states such as ischemia to change substrate utilization and thereby increase or decrease ATP synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58815" pm="."><plain>Its activation is controlled by an increase in the AMP:ATP ratio [51]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58816" pm="."><plain>Stimulation of AMPK leads to phosphorylation of many target proteins important for ATP synthesis and utilization while concurrently inhibiting ATP-consuming pathways such as fatty acid synthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58817" pm="."><plain>In the diabetic heart, AMPK activation is linked to phosphorylation of both acetyl-CoA carboxylase and malonyl-CoA decarboxylase; however, its association with the latter in the heart remains to be fully elucidated [52–54]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58818" pm="."><plain>Acetyl-CoA carboxylase and malonyl-CoA decarboxylase are both important for the interconversion of acetyl-CoA to malonyl-CoA (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58819" pm="."><plain>Phosphorylation of acetyl-CoA carboxylase by AMPK reduces the generation of malonyl-CoA; thus promoting the entry of FFAs for beta-oxidation into mitochondria through carnitine palmitoyltransferase I [55]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58820" pm="."><plain>Resultant increased levels of ATP and citrate through beta-oxidation are responsible for the allosteric inhibition of glycolysis through phosphofructokinase-1 [56]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58821" pm="."><plain>This causes accelerated ROS production and associated membrane peroxidation [24, 26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58822" pm="."><plain>Hence, adequate control of uptake and oxidation of FFAs remain crucial for optimal functioning of the myocardium, especially in a diabetic state.Fig. 2AMPK is associated with the phosphorylation of ACC and MCD to regulate myocardial energy metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58823" pm="."><plain>Chronic hyperglycemia activates AMPK, resulting in the phosphorylation of ACC, releasing the inhibitory effect of malonly-CoA on CPT1 and subsequently leading to enhanced entry of FFAs via CPT1 into the mitochondria for beta-oxidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58824" pm="."><plain>Abnormally increased beta-oxidation is further accountable for mitochondrial membrane damage through peroxyl radicals. Keys: ACC- acetyl-CoA carboxylase; AMPK- 5’ adenosine monophosphate (AMP)-activated protein kinase; CPT1- carnitine palmitoyltransferase 1; FFA- free fatty acid; MCD- malonyl-CoA decarboxylase </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="58825" pm="."><plain>Activation of Nrf2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par25"><text><SENT sid="58826" pm="."><plain>Free radicals within mitochondria are generally removed by mitochondrial SOD, thereby generating H2O2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58827" pm="."><plain>This process allows H2O2 to be further reduced to water by glutathione (GSH) or CAT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58828" pm="."><plain>GSH remains an important intracellular antioxidant to prevent free radical damage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58829" pm="."><plain>GSH can easily be oxidized to its disulfide form during oxidation reactions; thus, NADP transhydrogenase enzymes remain important to maintain the reduced form of this co-factor [57]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58830" pm="."><plain>NADP transhydrogenase functions by transferring electrons from a reduced form of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) to NADP+ in order to regenerate GSH [58]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58831" pm="."><plain>Reduced expression of GSH is consistently reported in experimental models investigating a diabetic heart [21, 24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58832" pm="."><plain>This was confirmed when investigated in either human subjects at risk of CVD or mice that are chronically subjected to hyperglycemia and hyperlipidemia [59, 60]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par26"><text><SENT sid="58833" pm="."><plain>Expression of antioxidant response genes, including GSH is regulated by the redox-sensitive transcription factor, Nrf2 [61]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58834" pm="."><plain>Nrf2 is a transcriptional regulator that is activated in response to intracellular stress (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58835" pm="."><plain>Genes activated by Nrf2 can be classified into different groups, including phase II detoxifying and cytoprotective enzymes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58836" pm="."><plain>Nrf2 resides in the cytoplasm, where it is subjected to continuous degradation by the ubiquitin-proteasome [62]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58837" pm="."><plain>Under stressful conditions such as ischemia or oxidative stress, Nrf2 is activated by disassociating from its negative regulator Kelch-like ECH-associated protein 1 (Keap1) and translocates to the nucleus. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58838" pm="."><plain>Once in the nucleus, it forms a heterodimer with Maf protein before binding to the antioxidant response element (ARE) to initiate and activate antioxidant defence genes [63]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58839" pm="."><plain>An overview of the pathway associated with the activation of Nrf2 and its protective effect against ROS in a cardiac cell is illustrated by Fig. 3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58840" pm="."><plain>Activation of Nrf2 in epithelial cells has been shown to induce GSH synthesis and thus protects against oxidative stress [64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58841" pm="."><plain>In addition to its negative regulation of Nrf2, Keap1 also acts as a sensor for a wide array of stressors that could activate Nrf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58842" pm="."><plain>Significant down-regulation of cardiac Nrf2 expression is concomitant to increased ROS and reactive nitrogen species damage in hearts of diabetic animals [62–64]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58843" pm="."><plain>Thus, agents that can significantly up-regulate Nrf2 expression have a potential to protect cardiomyocytes against high glucose-induced apoptosis.Fig. 3The role of Nrf2 in response to increased ROS within a diabetic heart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58844" pm="."><plain>Nox and mitochondrial-ETC cause augmented production of O2 ∙−, which damages the cell through ROS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58845" pm="."><plain>The cell reacts by activating the Nrf2-mediated antioxidant response system. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58846" pm="."><plain>Activated Nrf2 causes it to dissociate from Keap1 and migrate into the nucleus where it binds ARE and cause increased expression of cytoprotective genes and phase II detoxifying enzymes to eliminate ROS. Keys: ARE-antioxidant response element; CAT- catalase; Gpx- glutathione peroxidase; GSH- glutathione; Keap1- Kelch-like ECH-associated protein 1; Nox- NADPH oxidase; O2 ∙− superoxide ion; Nrf2- nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2; ROS-reactive oxygen species </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><text><SENT sid="58847" pm="."><plain>Cardioprotective potential of current antidiabetic agents </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par27"><text><SENT sid="58848" pm="."><plain>Primary interventions that may salvage a diabetic heart at risk from myocardial infarction mainly target maintaining low blood sugar levels [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58849" pm="."><plain>While such interventions are achievable and beneficial to the heart, adherence to lifestyle changes remains a big challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58850" pm="."><plain>Therefore, antidiabetic agents that could suppress postprandial and chronic hyperglycemia may be effective in decreasing the risk of HF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58851" pm="."><plain>Despite evidence on the efficacy of antidiabetic and antidyslipidemic drugs such as dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitors and statins [65, 66], metformin remains the leading first line antidiabetic drug for type 2 diabetic individuals with known cardiac complications [67, 68]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58852" pm="."><plain>In addition to its accomplished antidiabetic properties [69, 70], metformin is associated with improved clinical outcomes in diabetic patients with HF [71, 72]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58853" pm="."><plain>Although clinical data are lacking, metformin enhances the efficacy of a number of synthetic drugs and novel medicinal compounds currently screened for metabolic benefits in vitro [73–75]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58854" pm="."><plain>Metformin monotherapy or its use as an add-on effect to glibenclamide improves the intracellular antioxidant status of the myocardium in streptozotocin-induced diabetic Sprague-Dawley rats [76]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58855" pm="."><plain>In addition to improving the antioxidant capacity of heart cells, metformin may benefit the heart by enhancing autophagy and inhibiting MPT opening [77, 78]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58856" pm="."><plain>However, an increasing toll of cardiovascular related deaths in diabetic patients on treatment warrants further investigation into alternative treatment regimes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="58857" pm="."><plain>Cardioprotective potential of rooibos </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par28"><text><SENT sid="58858" pm="."><plain>In recent years, the use of plant-derived products as a cardioprotective therapy is receiving increasing attention [59, 79, 80]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58859" pm="."><plain>Rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) is an indigenous South African plant well-known for its potential health benefits. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58860" pm="."><plain>Rooibos tea is available in two forms: a “fermented” or oxidized form; and an “unfermented” or unoxidized form (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58861" pm="."><plain>The unfermented product is also referred to as green rooibos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58862" pm="."><plain>The “fermentation” process gives fermented rooibos its distinctive reddish-brown colour, while unfermented rooibos tea maintains its green colour (Fig. 4b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58863" pm="."><plain>The fermentation process is important to develop the characteristic taste and aroma of rooibos tea, traditionally consumed [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58864" pm="."><plain>Its effect on the health outcomes of rooibos is obscured if the products do not originate from the same bush due to large inherent variation in the phenolic content of the rooibos plant [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58865" pm="."><plain>However, it is well established fermentation decreased the flavonoid content of rooibos [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58866" pm="."><plain>Infusions and extracts prepared from unfermented rooibos have higher antioxidant capacity than those from fermented rooibos, largely due to higher levels of flavonoids, in particular aspalathin in the unoxidized plant material [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58867" pm="."><plain>Consumption of a “ready-to-drink” unfermented rooibos beverage as opposed to one produced from fermented rooibos effected a 28% higher total radical-trapping antioxidant potential in the plasma of human subjects [82]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58868" pm="."><plain>Nonetheless, both forms of rooibos are increasingly studied in experimental diabetes and related complications, given that fermented rooibos is more readily available and forms the bulk of rooibos production [81].Fig. 4Photos of a rooibos plantation (a) and the two forms of processed plant material (b), fermented and unfermented rooibos with spray-dried powders of their hot water extracts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58869" pm="."><plain>The fermentation process gives fermented rooibos its distinctive reddish-brown colour, while unfermented rooibos tea maintains its green colour </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par29"><text><SENT sid="58870" pm="."><plain>In a recent study, Oh and colleagues have demonstrated that the total flavonoid content of a water extract of rooibos, determined using a colorimetric assay based on aluminium complexation, is higher than that of lemongrass tea, mulberry leaf tea, bamboo leaf tea, lotus leaf tea, and persimmon leaf tea [83]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58871" pm="."><plain>However, they further showed that the total flavonoid content of this extract is slightly lower than that of green and black tea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58872" pm="."><plain>Von Gadow and colleagues have also previously shown that both fermented and unfermented rooibos, when tested together with green, oolong and black tea, present strong antioxidant properties in vitro [84]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58873" pm="."><plain>They further showed that this antioxidant effect, as evaluated using the 2,2-diphenyl-1-picrylhydrazyl radical assay, was reduced in the order: green tea &gt; unfermented rooibos &gt; fermented rooibos &gt; semifermented rooibos &gt; black tea &gt; oolong tea. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58874" pm="."><plain>Accompanying its well-documented antioxidant capacity [18, 84–89], rooibos has been shown to inhibit adipogenesis in vitro [90], reverse palmitate-induced insulin resistance in 3T3-L1 adipocytes [91] and prevent inflammation in vivo [92–94]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58875" pm="."><plain>An aspalathin-enriched green rooibos extract, containing 18.4% aspalathin has demonstrated an even higher hypoglycemic potential through its inhibitory effect of alpha-glucosidase and suppressing fasting plasma glucose levels in animal models [91, 95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58876" pm="."><plain>Another green rooibos extract, containing 6.6% aspalathin promoted glucose transporter 4 translocation to the plasma membrane and suppressed advanced glycation end products (AGEs)-induced oxidative damage in cultured skeletal L6 muscle cells, pancreatic beta-cells and obese diabetic KK-Ay mice [96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58877" pm="."><plain>Rooibos inhibits experimentally-induced oxidative stress [21]; and improved cardiovascular function by reducing lipid peroxidation, blood pressure and angiotensin-converting (ACE) enzyme in various experimental models [97–100]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58878" pm="."><plain>Moreover, it protected against ischemia-reperfusion injury by modulating the phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/protein kinase B (PI3K-AKT) pathway [101]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58879" pm="."><plain>Controlling free fatty acid oxidation by modulating phosphorylation of AMPK remains central in the preventive effect of rooibos against diabetes associated cardiac complications [90, 91, 96]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58880" pm="."><plain>The cardioprotective potential of rooibos is summarized in Table 1.Table 1The cardioprotective effect of rooibos, its flavonoids and a phenylpropenoic acidRooibos/compoundsModelExperimental outcomeReferencesRooibosAqueous extract of fermented rooibos on cardiomyocytes isolated from diabetic ratsPrevented experimentally induced oxidative stress and ischemia[21]Fermented rooibos tea for 6 weeks in human subjects at risk of cardiovascular disease (CVD)Reduced CVD risk by improving lipid profile and redox status[59]Aqueous extract of fermented rooibos in endothelial cells from human umbilical veins (HUVECs)Prevented vascular-induced inflammation by enhancing nitric oxide production[86, 92, 93]Aqueous extract of fermented rooibos on non-diabetic ratsActed as a bronchodilator, antispasmodic and blood pressure lowering effects[97]Fermented rooibos tea in healthy human subjectsPrevented myocardial infarction by inhibiting angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)[98–100]Aqueous extracts of fermented and unfermented rooibos in non-diabetic ratsReversed ischemia-reperfusion injury[101]Aspalathin and nothofaginAspalathin and nothofagin on high glucose-induced vascular in HUVECs and micePrevented inflammation and thrombosis by suppressing TNF-α, IL-6 and NF-κB[118, 119]Aspalathin in H9c2 cardiomyocytes exposed to high glucose and cardiomyocytes isolated from insulin resistant ratsPrevented cell apoptosis by reducing phosphorylation of AMPK; decreasing inflammation and lipid accumulation; and attenuated oxidative damage via increasing Nrf2 expression[73, 124–126]Orientin and isoorientinOrientin on isolated hearts of nondiabetic rats, rabbits and guinea pigs as well as H9c2 cellsPrevented ischemia-reperfusion injury and platelet aggregation by inhibiting mPTP formation and apoptosis[137–139]Orientin and isoorientinOrientin on ratsPrevented myocardial infarction[134]Isoorientin in low density lipoprotein isolated from human plasmaPrevented formation of atherosclerotic lesions by inhibiting low density lipoprotein (LDL) oxidation[135]Orientin in non-diabetic ratsAttenuated ventricular remodeling associated with myocardial infarction[136]Orientin and isoorientin in lipopolysaccharide-induced reperfusion injuryProtected vascular barrier integrity by inhibiting hyperpermeability[223]Vitexin and isovitexinVitexin on primary cardiomyocytes and isolated rat hearts and on ratsPrevented ischemia-reperfusion injury by reducing calcium overload and modulating ERK1/2 signaling and MAPK pathway[146, 149, 224]Vitexin on primary rat cardiomyocytesPrevented cardiac hypertrophy by inhibiting calcineurin and CaMKII signaling pathways[151]Vitexin on dogsReduced aortic pressure, arterial and pulmonary capillary pressure and heart rate[150, 225]Vitexin on ratsAttenuated acute doxorubicin cardiotoxicity by reducing oxidative stress and apoptosis[226]Luteolin and chrysoeriolLuteolin on isolated rat cardiomyocytes, rabbit hearts and anesthetized pigsPrevented ischemia-reperfusion injury and enhanced relative coronary flow[157, 159, 162]Luteolin on rat endothelium-denuded aortic ringsInduced vasorelaxion by regulating calcium and potassium channels and reducing oxidative stress[227]Luteolin on vascular smooth muscle cells and ratsPrevented hypertensive vascular remodeling[160]Luteolin on diabetic and normal ratsAlleviated vascular complications associated with insulin resistance through the Pparγ pathway[161]Luteolin and chrysoeriolLuteolin-7-glucoside on isolated primary rat cardiomyocytesPrevented ischemia-reperfusion injury and increased of coronary flow[228]Chrysoeriol in rats under anesthesia and H9c2 cellsReduced arterial blood pressure and protected against doxorubicin-induced cardiotoxicity[97, 172]Quercetin and rutinQuercetin on ratsProtected against diabetic cardiomyopathy, autoimmune myocarditis, LDL-oxidation, and doxorubicin-induced lipid peroxidation[185–192]Quercetin in either endothelial cells or ratsPresented antihypertensive potential and reduced cardiac hypertrophy by increasing antioxidant capacity[229–233]Hyperoside and rutinHyperoside in vitro and in vivoProtected against hyperglycemia induced inflammation[208]Hyperoside in ECV304 cellsPrevented advanced glycation end products and promoted via the c-Jun N-terminal kinases (JNK) pathway[205]Hyperoxide in vitro and in vivoHydrogen peroxide induced cell damage and ischemia reperfusion injury[209, 211, 212]Rutin on ratsProtected against advanced glycation end products, oxidative stress and myocardial infarction[199, 234, 235]Phenylpyruvic acid-2-O-β-D-glucoside (PPAG)PPAG on high-glucose exposed H9c2 cellsProtected against substrate impairment, mitochondrial depolarization and cell apoptosis[221] </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par30"><text><SENT sid="58881" pm="."><plain>A profound relationship between a diet rich in polyphenols and health has given hope to long-term effective interventions that could prolong the onset of diabetes and its co-morbidities [102]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58882" pm="."><plain>Flavonoids constitute a major sub-class of polyphenols, which can be further divided into different sub-groups such as dihydrochalcones, flavonols and flavones, the predominant rooibos flavonoid sub-groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58883" pm="."><plain>Variations in the hydroxylation pattern, glycosylation and chromane ring (Ring C) underpin their structural differences (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58884" pm="."><plain>Structural features of flavonoids relevant for their antioxidant properties [103] also explain binding affinity to plasma proteins [104] and enzymes such as alpha-glucosidase [105]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58885" pm="."><plain>Whilst in vitro data suggest flavonoid aglycones to be more effective than their glycosides, lack of in vivo data precludes broad generalizations concerning the effect of glycosylation on the benefits of flavonoids for human health [106].Table 2Molecular structures of flavonoids and a phenylpropenoid present in rooibos </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par31"><text><SENT sid="58886" pm="."><plain>In the following sections the focus will fall on flavonoids found in rooibos that have an ameliorative effect against various metabolic diseases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58887" pm="."><plain>Of interest is the predominance of C-glucosyl flavonoids in rooibos, and in particular the dihydrochalcones (aspalathin and nothofagin) and their flavone derivatives (orientin, isoorientin, vitexin and isovitexin). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58888" pm="."><plain>The major flavonols are O-glycosyl derivatives of quercetin, i.e. quercetin-3-O-robinobioside, hyperoside, isoquercitrin, and rutin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58889" pm="."><plain>The aglycones, luteolin, chrysoeriol and quercetin, are present in low to trace levels in rooibos [107]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58890" pm="."><plain>Discussion of their bioactivities is included to underscore the health potential of rooibos. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par32"><text><SENT sid="58891" pm="."><plain>PPAG is per definition not a phenolic compound due to the absence of a hydroxyl group on the phenyl ring. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58892" pm="."><plain>This compound is a biosynthetic precursor of flavonoids [108] and rooibos is one of the few plants demonstrated to date to be a substantial source. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="58893" pm="."><plain>Rooibos dihydrochalcones </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par33"><text><SENT sid="58894" pm="."><plain>The dihydrochalcone, aspalathin is unique to rooibos, while its 3-deoxy analogue, nothofagin, is relatively rare with its presence also confirmed in Notofagus fusca and Schoepfia chinensis [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58895" pm="."><plain>Unfermented rooibos tea beverage contains 10-fold or more aspalathin and nothofagin when compared to the fermented product [107, 109]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58896" pm="."><plain>This is not surprising as the fermentation process is known to reduce their content in rooibos [81, 110]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58897" pm="."><plain>Despite C-glycosides having very low bioavailability due to the inability of intestinal enzymes to hydrolyze the C-C bond linking the sugar moiety to the aglycone and thus influencing their absorption process [111], aspalathin has been reported in the plasma of subjects who consumed 500 mL of green rooibos infusion, containing 287 mg aspalathin [112]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58898" pm="."><plain>However, generally as reported for other dihydrochalcones [113, 114], the human gut microbiota can possibly enhance the absorption of aspalathin and nothofagin in the small intestine by splitting off the aglycone from the glucose moiety [115]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58899" pm="."><plain>In vivo, the low levels of aspalathin are difficult to detect in serum, however metabolites (glucuronides and sulfates) of aspalathin and nothofagin have been detected in urine of human subjects 5 h after consumption of 500 mL of either fermented or unfermented rooibos [109]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58900" pm="."><plain>Recent data have demonstrated that aspalathin is absorbed and metabolized in mice to mostly sulphate conjugates detected in urine, while the mode of absorption is hypothesized to occur through the monolayer paracellularly [116]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par34"><text><SENT sid="58901" pm="."><plain>The biological of activity of aspalathin and nothofagin has been primary associated with their known strong antioxidant properties [73, 117]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58902" pm="."><plain>Both compounds protected against high glucose-induced vascular inflammation and platelet aggregation when tested in endothelial cells and mice; however, nothofagin did not have any anticoagulant effect in mice [118, 119]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58903" pm="."><plain>Increasing research is presented focusing on aspalathin and its enhanced efficacy to prevent metabolic-associated complications in vitro and in vivo models [18, 120–122]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58904" pm="."><plain>Our laboratory has presented recent evidence that aspalathin reversed palmitate-induced insulin resistance in cultured adipocytes [123], while it prevented high glucose-inducedapoptosis by improving substrate metabolism in H9c2 cells exposed to high glucose or cardiomyocytes from insulin resistant rats [73, 124, 125]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58905" pm="."><plain>In addition to regulating AMPK and enhancing Nrf2 expression, aspalathin can modulate the expression of peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor gamma and sterol regulatory element-binding protein 1/2, transcriptional factors involved in lipid metabolism, in addition to inhibiting inflammation via interleukin-6/Janus kinase 2 pathways, leading to reduced myocardial apoptosis [73, 124, 126]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="58906" pm="."><plain>Rooibos flavones </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par35"><text><SENT sid="58907" pm="."><plain>The major flavones present in rooibos include orientin and isoorientin, the flavone derivatives of aspalathin, and vitexin and isovitexin, the flavone derivatives of nothofagin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58908" pm="."><plain>Minor flavones include the aglycones, luteolin, and chrysoeriol (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58909" pm="."><plain>Lower levels of flavones are present in fermented rooibos [81]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58910" pm="."><plain>Food processing may also change their content. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58911" pm="."><plain>The orientin and isoorientin content of a ready-to-drink rooibos beverage showed a slight change as a result of pasteurization and storage, postulated to be due to the conversion of aspalathin to these compounds [110, 127]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58912" pm="."><plain>Except for luteolin, there is very limited data on the characteristic metabolism and transportation of these flavone glucosides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58913" pm="."><plain>The absorption of orientin, isoorientin and vitexin has been reported on Caco-2 cell monolayers [128, 129], with transporter mediated efflux in addition to passive diffusion shown to be the predominant mode of transportation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58914" pm="."><plain>In a pharmacokinetics study using Sprague–Dawley rats, intravenous administration of a 20 mg/kg dose of orientin was found to be highly recovered in plasma and eliminated within 90 min after intravenous administration [130]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58915" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, permeability and absorption rate of luteolin has been shown to be significantly greater in the colon and ileum compared to the duodenum and jejunum in rats [131]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58916" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, some of these compounds, including isoorientin may be deglycosylated to their aglycones by gut microbiota as reviewed by Muller et al. [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par36"><text><SENT sid="58917" pm="."><plain>The strong antioxidant properties of flavones have been associated with their free radical scavenging properties [132]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58918" pm="."><plain>Although very few studies are available on the antidiabetic properties of orientin and isoorientin, extracts with abundant levels of vitexin, orientin and isoorientin have been shown to inhibit adipogenesis in 3T3-L1 adipocytes [90, 133]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58919" pm="."><plain>Relevant to the cardiovascular system, these compounds have been reported to inhibit high glucose-induced vascular inflammation [134], atherosclerosis [135], cardiac remodeling [136] and ischemia-reperfusion injury [137–139]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58920" pm="."><plain>Additional protective effects of these compounds are summarized in Table 1 and are mainly mediated by nuclear factor kappa B, a transcriptional factor involved in diabetic-induced HF [140]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58921" pm="."><plain>Moreover, isoorientin has been shown to reduce other diabetic associated complications such as lipid toxicity and insulin resistance [141]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58922" pm="."><plain>Together with direct radical scavenging activity, the protective mechanism of isoorientin has been linked to the induction of Nrf2 pathway-driven antioxidant response through phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase signaling [142]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58923" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, oral administration of vitexin and isovitexin at 1 mg/kg has been shown to reduce postprandial blood glucose levels in sucrose loaded normoglycemic mice [143]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58924" pm="."><plain>In addition to inhibiting α-glucosidase [144], vitexin and isovitexin rich extracts have been demonstrated to attenuate diabetes linked complications such as adipogenesis and AGEs in vitro [132, 145]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58925" pm="."><plain>Vitexin reverses ischemia-reperfusion injury in perfused rat hearts and brain by attenuating inflammatory response and apoptosis [146–149]; it increased coronary artery blood flow and cardiac output in anesthetized animals [150]; and it improved cardiac hypertrophy by reducing the expression of calcium downstream effectors, calcineurin-NFATc3 and phosphorylated calmodulin kinase II (CaMKII), both in vitro and in vivo [151]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58926" pm="."><plain>Other associated cardioprotective mechanisms of vitexin may include inhibiting cardiomyocyte apoptosis by reducing calcium overload and extracellular signal regulated kinase (ERK1/2) [152]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par37"><text><SENT sid="58927" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, although available in trace levels in rooibos, release of luteolin from orientin and isoorientin in the gut may enhance the levels to physiological relevance. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58928" pm="."><plain>Accumulative evidence suggests strong ameliorative effect of luteolin against diabetes and CVD associated complications [153–155]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58929" pm="."><plain>The antidiabetic properties of luteolin include improving hepatic insulin sensitivity by suppressing gluconeogenesis in diet-induced obese mice [153]; it prevented neuronal injury and cognitive performance by attenuating oxidative stress in rats [154]; and attenuated morphological destruction of the kidney in rats [155]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58930" pm="."><plain>The anti-inflammatory properties of luteolin include inhibiting elevated levels of interleukin-1β and nuclear factor kappa B [156–158]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58931" pm="."><plain>Relevant to the heart, luteolin reduced systolic and diastolic blood pressure of various animal models [159, 160]; it improved contractile function [161]; and blocked apoptosis following ischemia-reperfusion in adult rat cardiomyocytes via downregulating microRNA-208b-3p [162]; it attenuated HF in a rat model of DCM [163]; and protected against acute and chronic periods of isoproterenol-induced myocardial infarction by suppressing mitochondrial lipid peroxidation [164]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58932" pm="."><plain>One of the important mechanisms linked to the cardioprotective effect of luteolin during ischemia-reperfusion injury include regulation of ERK1/2 and c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), which are pathways implicated in generation of inflammation [165]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58933" pm="."><plain>The number of functional hydroxyl groups on the structure of luteolin directly correlates to its scavenging effect of hydroxyl radicals [166]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par38"><text><SENT sid="58934" pm="."><plain>Another flavone of interest that is present in very low quantities in rooibos is chrysoeriol [167]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58935" pm="."><plain>Chrysoeriol has been previously shown to be more effective in the protection against lipid peroxidation than its glycoside (chrysoeriol-6-O-acetyl-4′-β-D-glucoside) when tested in vitro [168]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58936" pm="."><plain>In addition to preventing H2O2-induced oxidative stress in osteoblasts [169], chrysoeriol protected Raw264.7 macrophages from lipopolysaccharide-induced inflammation by blocking activator protein 1, which is crucial in the transcriptional activation of inducible nitric oxide synthase [170]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58937" pm="."><plain>A hydroalcoholic extract of Tecoma stans, containing 96% chrysoeriol presented an enhanced activity to inhibit pancreatic lipase [171]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58938" pm="."><plain>Relevant to the heart, chrysoeriol can lower arterial blood pressure in rats under anesthesia [97]; and it can protect against doxorubicin-induced cardiotoxicity by inhibiting apoptosis in H9c2 cells [172]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58939" pm="."><plain>However, no published study is available on the effect of chrysoeriol on a diabetic heart at present. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="58940" pm="."><plain>Rooibos flavonols </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par39"><text><SENT sid="58941" pm="."><plain>Quercetin and its glycosides, quercetin-3-O-robinobioside, hyperoside, isoquercitrin, and rutin are classified by a distinct 3-hydroxyflavone backbone and are the major flavonols present in rooibos (Table 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58942" pm="."><plain>Generally, based on a specific population assessed, the average intake of flavonols may range between 20 to 35 mg/day [173, 174]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58943" pm="."><plain>Although additional studies are required to validate their bioavailability, flavonol aglycones have been shown to be highly absorbed in the gut [175]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58944" pm="."><plain>The type of sugar moiety and stability of aglycone largely affect the absorption of each compound as shown for quercetin glycosides from onions being better absorbed than pure aglycones [173, 176]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58945" pm="."><plain>Another study has demonstrated that isoquercitrin and hyperoside are highly absorbable in rats [177]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58946" pm="."><plain>Regular consumption of flavonols has been found to be protective against ischemic heart disease in some individuals [178]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58947" pm="."><plain>Quercetin attenuated paracetamol-induced liver damage and impairment of kidney function such as intracytoplasmic vacuolization and brush border loss in rats [179]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58948" pm="."><plain>Quercetin has a high affinity to inhibit AGEs such as methylglyoxal and glyoxal in a bovine serum albumin system [180]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par40"><text><SENT sid="58949" pm="."><plain>Quercetin and rutin further exhibit a broad range of pharmacological activities within the myocardium (Table 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58950" pm="."><plain>These compounds presented atherosclerosis lowering properties by reducing hepatic fatty acid synthesis in mice [181]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58951" pm="."><plain>They enhanced glucose uptake in muscle cells subjected to oxidative stress [182] and prevented against dyslipidemia associated complications such as inflammation and lipid toxicity by enhancing antioxidant capacity in rats [183]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58952" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in the heart, quercetin and rutin have been shown to directly alleviate DCM by improving myocardial ultrastructure in diabetic animals through aldose reductase, oxidative stress inhibitory activity and modulation of cardiac calcium homeostasis [184–187]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58953" pm="."><plain>The use of quercetin at a dose of 10 mg/kg body weight for 28 days protected against autoimmune myocarditis by suppressing oxidative stress in rats [188]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58954" pm="."><plain>Quercetin is thought to exert cardiac protection through quenching lipid peroxidation, as it is a known scavenger of peroxyl radicals [189–192]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58955" pm="."><plain>In a double-blind randomized clinical trial on women (n = 72), quercetin supplementation (500 mg capsule daily) for 10 weeks significantly reduced systolic blood pressure but had no effect on other cardiovascular parameters and inflammatory biomarkers [193]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58956" pm="."><plain>Likewise, rutin protected against myocardial damage in a diabetic state by decreasing postprandial hyperglycemia and slowing down formation of AGEs in various experimental models [194–197]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58957" pm="."><plain>In combination with aspalathin, rutin reduced blood glucose concentrations of streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats over a 6 h monitoring period [95]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58958" pm="."><plain>It further improved glucose homeostasis in streptozotocin-induced diabetic rats suppressing gluconeogenesis [197]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58959" pm="."><plain>Regulation of glucose metabolism and increasing intracellular antioxidant capacity have been proposed to be the main cardioprotective effects of both quercetin and rutin [198, 199]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="Par42"><text><SENT sid="58960" pm="."><plain>Like quercetin and chrysoeriol, hyperoside is often present in very low quantities in a cup of fermented rooibos tea [167]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58961" pm="."><plain>Plants and extracts rich in hyperoside have been established to display antidiabetic properties [200–202]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58962" pm="."><plain>Hyperoside prevented against diabetic nephropathy by inhibiting apoptosis and albuminuria in glomerular podocytes isolated from diabetic rats and mice [203, 204]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58963" pm="."><plain>Other biological activities of hyperoside include reducing accelerated production of AGEs in ECV304 cells via the JNK pathway [205]; suppression of inflammation through reducing nuclear factor-κB activation in mouse peritoneal macrophages [206]; and inhibition of α-glucosidase and apoptosis in liver cells [207]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58964" pm="."><plain>In the heart, hyperoside protected hyperglycemia-induced inflammation in vitro and in vivo [208]; hydrogen peroxide-induced oxidative damage [209, 210]; and it protected against ischemic-reperfusion injury in isolated rat hearts [211]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58965" pm="."><plain>The protective mechanism of hyperoside against diabetes and heart associated complications has been mainly through suppressing cell apoptosis, improving mitochondrial function and regulating Nrf2 and extracellular signal-regulated protein kinase signaling [212, 213]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="58966" pm="."><plain>PPAG </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par43"><text><SENT sid="58967" pm="."><plain>PPAG is a phenylpropenoic glucoside (Table 2) that acts as a precursor in the flavonoid biosynthesis pathway and has been shown by various studies to be present in rooibos [18, 81, 108]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58968" pm="."><plain>The occurrence of PPAG in rooibos was described for the first time about two decades ago [108] and its bioavailability profile is yet to be established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58969" pm="."><plain>Phenylpyruvic acids apparently play a key role in the biosynthesis of a number of secondary metabolites, including PPAG [214]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58970" pm="."><plain>The biological activity of a compound with similar structure to PPAG such as 3-phenylpyruvate has long been reported to display antidiabetic properties [215, 216]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58971" pm="."><plain>Exposure of cardiomyocytes isolated from diabetic rats to a low concentration of fermented rooibos that contains a relatively high level of PPAG (0.71 g/100 g extract) prevents oxidative stress and apoptosis [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58972" pm="."><plain>Recent findings indicated that this compound attenuates insulin resistance and protects beta cells from obese and streptozotocin-induced mice against endoplasmic reticulum stress-induced apoptosis [217–219]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58973" pm="."><plain>Data available on the cardioprotective properties of PPAG are limited to a study in H9c2 cardiomyocytes, showing that PPAG abolishes high glucose-induced altered myocardial substrate metabolism and apoptosis by increasing the Bcl2/Bax ratio and reducing caspase 3/7 activity [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58974" pm="."><plain>This study further showed that PPAG displayed reduced capacity to protect H9c2 cells against oxidative stress. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58975" pm="."><plain>This result was anticipated since PPAG is not expected to be an active antioxidant as it lacks the phenolic structural features that are required for free radical scavenging ability [220]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58976" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, PPAG used in combination with a known antidiabetic agent such as metformin demonstrated better protection of cardiomyocytes exposed to high glucose-induced oxidative stress than when used as a monotherapy [221]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58977" pm="."><plain>Correspondingly, Patel et al. [222] recently showed that PPAG has no inhibitory effect on cytochrome P450 enzymes, CYP2C8, CYP2C9, and CYP3A4, which are important in the metabolism of hypoglycemic drugs, such as thiazolidinediones and sulfonylureas. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58978" pm="."><plain>Supporting the potential use of nutraceutical agents such as PPAG, especially in combination with a current antidiabetic agent to attenuate oxidative stress-induced damage and protect diabetic individuals at risk of myocardial infarction needs further investigation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="58979" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="Par44"><text><SENT sid="58980" pm="."><plain>Blood glucose lowering therapies such as metformin and insulin have played a major role in prolonging lives of diabetic patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58981" pm="."><plain>However, tight control of blood glucose remains a challenge in such patients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58982" pm="."><plain>By contrast, ameliorative therapies for oxidative stress, including polyphenols as an adjunct to current blood lowering drugs, show promise in protecting diabetic hearts in experimental models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58983" pm="."><plain>In recent years, rooibos has gained popularity due to its potential use as a dietary supplement that is rich in polyphenols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58984" pm="."><plain>The presence of constituents such as aspalathin, nothofagin and PPAG that are unique to rooibos or rarely occur in other plants make it attractive for scientific investigation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58985" pm="."><plain>The compounds present in rooibos continue to present robust biological properties that are associated with ameliorative effects on inflammation and apoptosis, leading to improved cardiac function in different animal models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58986" pm="."><plain>In addition, current evidence has suggested that the combinational use of some of these compounds with known antidiabetic agents such as metformin may enhance their biological efficacy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58987" pm="."><plain>However, this review clearly highlights the evidence gap pertaining to the molecular mechanisms associated with the cardioprotective effect of rooibos and its polyphenols. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58988" pm="."><plain>Once these molecular mechanisms are established, in addition to verification of such findings in clinical studies, it could make a significant step in accelerating development of an evidenced-based rooibos nutraceutical. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58989" pm="."><plain>It is therefore imperative that we further investigate the mechanism(s) by which rooibos flavonoids and PPAG modulate diabetes-induced cardiovascular related complications thereby identifying new therapeutic candidates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>ACE</term><def><p>Angiotensin-converting enzyme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AGEs</term><def><p id="Par2">Advanced glycation end products</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>AMPK</term><def><p id="Par3">5′-adenosine monophosphate-activated protein kinase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ARE</term><def><p>Antioxidant response element</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CaMKII</term><def><p>Calmodulin kinase II</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CAT</term><def><p id="Par4">Catalase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>CVD</term><def><p id="Par5">Cardiovascular disease</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DCM</term><def><p id="Par6">Diabetic cardiomyopathy</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>DM</term><def><p id="Par7">Diabetes mellitus</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ERK1/2</term><def><p>Extracellular signal-regulated protein kinases 1 and 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>FFAs</term><def><p id="Par8">Free fatty acids</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GSH</term><def><p id="Par9">Glutathione</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub></term><def><p id="Par10">Hydrogen peroxide</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HF</term><def><p id="Par11">Heart failure</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>HUVECs</term><def><p>Human umbilical vein endothelial cells</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IL-6</term><def><p>Interleukin-6</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>JNK- c</term><def><p>Jun N-terminal kinases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Keap1</term><def><p>Kelch-like ECH-associated protein 1</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LDL</term><def><p>Low density lipoprotein</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MAPK</term><def><p>Mitogen-activated protein kinases</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MPT</term><def><p id="Par12">Mitochondrial permeability transition</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>NF-kB</term><def><p>Nuclear factor kappa B</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Nox</term><def><p id="Par13">NADPH oxidase</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>Nrf2</term><def><p id="Par14">Nuclear factor (erythroid-derived 2)-like 2</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PPAG</term><def><p id="Par15">Phenylpyruvic acid-2-<italic>O</italic>-β-D-glucoside</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ROS</term><def><p id="Par16">Reactive oxygen species</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>SOD</term><def><p id="Par17">Superoxide dismutase</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="58990" pm="."><plain>Not applicable. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par45"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="58991" pm="."><plain>Not applicable. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par46"><text4fund><text><SENT sid="58992" pm="."><plain>This research was funded in part by the National Research Foundation (NRF) Thuthuka Programme Grant 87,836 and the South Africa Medical Research Council’s Biomedical Research and Innovation Platform. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58993" pm="."><plain>The grantholders acknowledge that opinions, findings and conclusions or recommendations expressed in any publication generated by the NRF supported research are those of the authors, and that the NRF accepts no liability whatsoever in this regard. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58994" pm="."><plain>Funding from Stellenbosch University and Ernst Ethel Erikson trust is also acknowledged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58995" pm="."><plain>The PhD from which this study emanated was funded by the South African Medical Research Council under SAMRC Internship Scholarship Programme. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58996" pm="."><plain>The funding body had no role in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></ack></SecTag><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors’ contributions</title><p>PVD, EJ, CJF, JL and RJ performed literature search and wrote the manuscript. All authors reviewed, edited and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par47">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par48">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par49">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher’s Note</title><p id="Par41">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="58997" pm="."><plain>1.International Diabetes Federation (IDF). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58998" pm="."><plain>IDF Diabetes atlas 7th edition. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://idf.org">idf.org</ext-link> [Internet]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58999" pm="."><plain>Accessed at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.diabetesatlas.org">http://www.diabetesatlas.org</ext-link>/. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59000" pm="."><plain>Accessed 12 December 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="59001" pm="."><plain>2.World Health Organization (WHO). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59002" pm="."><plain>Global status report on noncommunicable diseases 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59003" pm="."><plain>World Health 176. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59004" pm="."><plain>2014; doi:ISBN 9789241564854. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="59005" pm="."><plain>3.GinsbergBJMazzeRClinical consequences of the diabetes control and complications trialN J Med1994914221224<?supplied-pmid 8202266?>8202266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="59006" pm="."><plain>4.BoudinaSAbelEDDiabetic cardiomyopathy, causes and effectsRev Endocr Metab Disord2010111313910.1007/s11154-010-9131-7<?supplied-pmid 20180026?>20180026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="59007" pm="."><plain>5.KukidomeDNishikawaTSonodaKImotoKFujisawaKYanoMMotoshimaHTaguchiTMatsumuraTArakiEActivation of AMP-activated protein kinase reduces hyperglycemia-induced mitochondrial reactive oxygen species production and promotes mitochondrial biogenesis in human umbilical vein endothelial cellsDiabetes200655112012710.2337/diabetes.55.01.06.db05-0943<?supplied-pmid 16380484?>16380484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="59008" pm="."><plain>6.Casaclang-VerzosaGGershBJTsangTSStructural and functional remodeling of the left atrium: Clinical and therapeutic implications for atrial fibrillationJ Am Coll Cardiol200851111110.1016/j.jacc.2007.09.026<?supplied-pmid 18174029?>18174029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="59009" pm="."><plain>7.RublerSDlugashJYuceogluYZKumralTBranwoodAWGrishmanANew type of cardiomyopathy associated with diabetic glomerulosclerosisAm J Cardiol197230659560210.1016/0002-9149(72)90595-4<?supplied-pmid 4263660?>4263660 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="59010" pm="."><plain>8.KengneAPDzudieASobngwiEHeart failure in sub-Saharan Africa: A literature review with emphasis on individuals with diabetesVasc Health Risk Manag20084112313010.2147/vhrm.2008.04.01.123<?supplied-pmid 18629376?>18629376 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="59011" pm="."><plain>9.MbanyaJCNMotalaAASobngwiEAssahFKEnoruSTDiabetes in sub-Saharan AfricaLancet201037597332254226610.1016/S0140-6736(10)60550-8<?supplied-pmid 20609971?>20609971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="59012" pm="."><plain>10.JonassenAKSackMNMjøsODYellonDMMyocardial protection by insulin at reperfusion requires early administration and is mediated via Akt and p70s6 kinase cell-survival signalingCirc Res200189121191119810.1161/hh2401.101385<?supplied-pmid 11739285?>11739285 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="59013" pm="."><plain>11.EurichDTMajumdarSRMcAlisterFATsuyukiRTJohnsonJAImproved clinical outcomes associated with metformin in patients with diabetes and heart failureDiabetes Care200528102345235110.2337/diacare.28.10.2345<?supplied-pmid 16186261?>16186261 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="59014" pm="."><plain>12.YinMVan der HorstICCvan MelleJPQianCvan GilstWHSilljéHHWDe BoerRAMetformin improves cardiac function in a nondiabetic rat model of post-MI heart failureAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol20113012H459H46810.1152/ajpheart.00054.2011<?supplied-pmid 21572014?>21572014 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="59015" pm="."><plain>13.BoudinaSAbelEDDiabetic cardiomyopathy revisitedCirculation2007115253213322310.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.679597<?supplied-pmid 17592090?>17592090 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="59016" pm="."><plain>14.MaritimACSandersRAWatkinsJBDiabetes, oxidative stress, and antioxidants: A reviewJ Biochem Mol Toxicol2003171243810.1002/jbt.10058<?supplied-pmid 12616644?>12616644 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="59017" pm="."><plain>15.FordESIntake and circulating concentrations of antioxidants in metabolic syndromeCurr Atheroscler Rep20068644845210.1007/s11883-006-0018-8<?supplied-pmid 17045069?>17045069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="59018" pm="."><plain>16.SzkudelskiTSzkudelskaKAnti-diabetic effects of resveratrolAnn N Y Acad Sci20111215343910.1111/j.1749-6632.2010.05844.x<?supplied-pmid 21261639?>21261639 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="59019" pm="."><plain>17.SellamuthuPSMuniappanBPPerumalSMKandasamyMAntihyperglycemic effect of mangiferin in streptozotocin induced diabetic ratsJ Heal Sci200955220621410.1248/jhs.55.206 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="59020" pm="."><plain>18.Muller CJ, Malherbe CJ, Chellan N, Yagasaki K, Miura Y, Joubert E. Potential of rooibos, its major C-glucosyl flavonoids and Z-2-(β-D-glucopyranoloxy)-3-phenylpropenoic acid in prevention of metabolic syndrome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59022" pm="."><plain>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59023" pm="."><plain>2016; doi:10.1080/10408398.2016.1157568. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="59024" pm="."><plain>19.TanYIchikawaTLiJSiQYangHChenXGoldblattCSMeyerCJLiXCaiLCuiTDiabetic downregulation of Nrf2 activity via ERK contributes to oxidative stress-induced insulin resistance in cardiac cells in vitro and in vivoDiabetes201160262563310.2337/db10-1164<?supplied-pmid 21270272?>21270272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="59025" pm="."><plain>20.TarquiniRLazzeriCPalaLRotellaCMGensiniGFThe diabetic cardiomyopathyActa Diabetol201148317318110.1007/s00592-010-0180-x<?supplied-pmid 20198391?>20198391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="59026" pm="."><plain>21.DludlaPVMullerCJFLouwJJoubertESalieROpokuARJohnsonRThe cardioprotective effect of an aqueous extract of fermented rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) on cultured cardiomyocytes derived from diabetic ratsPhytomedicine201421559560110.1016/j.phymed.2013.10.029<?supplied-pmid 24268738?>24268738 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="59027" pm="."><plain>22.UemuraSMatsushitaHLiWGlassfordAJAsagamiTLeeKHHarrisonDGTsaoPSDiabetes mellitus enhances vascular matrix metalloproteinase activity: role of oxidative stressCirc Res200188121291129810.1161/hh1201.092042<?supplied-pmid 11420306?>11420306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="59028" pm="."><plain>23.RajamaniUEssopMFHyperglycemia-mediated activation of the hexosamine biosynthetic pathway results in myocardial apoptosisAm J Physiol Cell Physiol20102991C139C14710.1152/ajpcell.00020.2010<?supplied-pmid 20410435?>20410435 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="59029" pm="."><plain>24.GiaccoFBrownleeMOxidative stress and diabetic complicationsCirc Res201010791058107010.1161/CIRCRESAHA.110.223545<?supplied-pmid 21030723?>21030723 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="59030" pm="."><plain>25.CaiLLiWWangGGuoLJiangYKangYJHyperglycemia-induced apoptosis in mouse myocardium: Mitochondrial cytochrome c-mediated caspase-3 activation pathwayDiabetes20025161938194810.2337/diabetes.51.6.1938<?supplied-pmid 12031984?>12031984 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="59031" pm="."><plain>26.SharmaPJhaABDubeyRSPessarakliMReactive oxygen species, oxidative damage, and antioxidative defense mechanism in plants under stressful conditionsJ Bot20122012217037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="59032" pm="."><plain>27.AnsleyDMWangBOxidative stress and myocardial injury in the diabetic heartJ Pathol2013229223224110.1002/path.4113<?supplied-pmid 23011912?>23011912 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="59033" pm="."><plain>28.KurodaJAgoTMatsushimaSZhaiPSchneiderMDSadoshimaJNADPH oxidase 4 (Nox4) is a major source of oxidative stress in the failing heartProc Natl Acad Sci U S A201010735155651557010.1073/pnas.1002178107<?supplied-pmid 20713697?>20713697 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="59034" pm="."><plain>29.HuynhKBernardoBCMcMullenJRRitchieRHDiabetic cardiomyopathy: mechanisms and new treatment strategies targeting antioxidant signaling pathwaysPharmacol Ther2014142337541510.1016/j.pharmthera.2014.01.003<?supplied-pmid 24462787?>24462787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="59035" pm="."><plain>30.Marín-GarcíaJAkhmedovATMoeGWMitochondria in heart failure: The emerging role of mitochondrial dynamicsHeart Fail Rev201318443945610.1007/s10741-012-9330-2<?supplied-pmid 22707247?>22707247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="59036" pm="."><plain>31.SackMNType 2 diabetes, mitochondrial biology and the heartJ Mol Cell Cardiol200946684284910.1016/j.yjmcc.2009.02.001<?supplied-pmid 19217910?>19217910 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="59037" pm="."><plain>32.MontaigneDMarechalXLefebvrePModineTFayadGDehondtHHurtCCoisneAKoussaMRemy-JouetIZerimechFBoulangerELacroixDStaelsBNeviereRMitochondrial dysfunction as an arrhythmogenic substrate: A translational proof-of-concept study in patients with metabolic syndrome developing post-operative atrial fibrillationJ Am Coll Cardiol201362161466147310.1016/j.jacc.2013.03.061<?supplied-pmid 23644086?>23644086 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="59038" pm="."><plain>33.ZamzamiNMarchettiPCastedoMDecaudinDMachoAHirschTSusinSAPetitPXMignotteBKroemerGSequential reduction of mitochondrial transmembrane potential and generation of reactive oxygen species in early programmed cell deathJ Exp Med1995182236737710.1084/jem.182.2.367<?supplied-pmid 7629499?>7629499 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="59039" pm="."><plain>34.BainesCPThe molecular composition of the mitochondrial permeability transition poreJ Mol Cell Cardiol200946685085710.1016/j.yjmcc.2009.02.007<?supplied-pmid 19233198?>19233198 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="59040" pm="."><plain>35.CromptonMThe mitochondrial permeability transition pore and its role in cell deathBiochem J1999341Pt 223324910.1042/bj3410233<?supplied-pmid 10393078?>10393078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR36"><text><SENT sid="59041" pm="."><plain>36.LemastersJJNieminenALQianTTrostLCElmoreSPNishimuraYCroweRACascioWEBradhamCABrennerDAHermanBThe mitochondrial permeability transition in cell death: A common mechanism in necrosis, apoptosis and autophagyBiochim Biophys Acta-Bioenerg.199813661–217719610.1016/S0005-2728(98)00112-1 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR37"><text><SENT sid="59042" pm="."><plain>37.KwongJQMolkentinJDPhysiological and pathological roles of the mitochondrial permeability transition pore in the heartCell Metab201521220621410.1016/j.cmet.2014.12.001<?supplied-pmid 25651175?>25651175 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR38"><text><SENT sid="59043" pm="."><plain>38.GalluzziLBravo-San PedroJMVitaleIAaronsonSAAbramsJMAdamDAlnemriESAltucciLAndrewsDAnnicchiarico-PetruzzelliMBaehreckeEHBazanNGBertrandMJBianchiKBlagosklonnyMVBlomgrenKBornerCBredesenDEBrennerCCampanellaMCandiECecconiFChanFKChandelNSChengEHChipukJECidlowskiJACiechanoverADawsonTMDawsonVLDe LaurenziVDe MariaRDebatinKMDi DanieleNDixitVMDynlachtBDEl-DeiryWSFimiaGMFlavellRAFuldaSGarridoCGougeonMLGreenDRGronemeyerHHajnoczkyGHardwickJMHengartnerMOIchijoHJosephBJostPJKaufmannTKeppOKlionskyDJKnightRAKumarSLemastersJJLevineBLinkermannALiptonSALockshinRALópez-OtínCLugliEMadeoFMalorniWMarineJCMartinSJMartinouJCMedemaJPMeierPMelinoSMizushimaNMollUMuñoz-PinedoCNuñezGOberstAPanaretakisTPenningerJMPeterMEPiacentiniMPintonPPrehnJHPuthalakathHRabinovichGARavichandranKSRizzutoRRodriguesCMRubinszteinDCRudelTShiYSimonHUStockwellBRSzabadkaiGTaitSWTangHLTavernarakisNTsujimotoYBergheTVVandenabeelePVillungerAWagnerEFWalczakHWhiteEWoodWGYuanJZakeriZZhivotovskyBMelinoGKroemerGEssential versus accessory aspects of cell death: Recommendations of the NCCD 2015Cell Death Differ2014221587310.1038/cdd.2014.137<?supplied-pmid 25236395?>25236395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR39"><text><SENT sid="59044" pm="."><plain>39.BedardKKrauseKHThe NOX family of ROS-generating NADPH oxidases: Physiology and pathophysiologyPhysiol Rev200787124531310.1152/physrev.00044.2005<?supplied-pmid 17237347?>17237347 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR40"><text><SENT sid="59045" pm="."><plain>40.MapangaRFEssopMFDamaging effects of hyperglycemia on cardiovascular function: Spotlight on glucose metabolic pathwaysAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol20163102H153H17310.1152/ajpheart.00206.2015<?supplied-pmid 26519027?>26519027 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR41"><text><SENT sid="59046" pm="."><plain>41.ParaviciniTMTouyzRMNADPH oxidases, reactive oxygen species, and hypertension: Clinical implications and therapeutic possibilitiesDiabetes Care200831Suppl 2S170S18010.2337/dc08-s247<?supplied-pmid 18227481?>18227481 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR42"><text><SENT sid="59047" pm="."><plain>42.FuXJPengYBHuYPShiYZYaoMZhangXNADPH oxidase 1 and its derived reactive oxygen species mediated tissue injury and repairOxidative Med Cell Longev2014201428285410.1155/2014/282854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR43"><text><SENT sid="59048" pm="."><plain>43.Stockklauser-FärberKBallhausenTLauferARösenPInfluence of diabetes on cardiac nitric oxide synthase expression and activityBiochim Biophys Acta200015351102010.1016/S0925-4439(00)00078-8<?supplied-pmid 11113627?>11113627 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR44"><text><SENT sid="59049" pm="."><plain>44.GraySPDi MarcoEOkabeJSzyndralewiezCHeitzFMontezanoACDe HaanJBKoulisCEl-OstaAAndrewsKLChin-DustingJPFTouyzRMWinglerKCooperMESchmidtHHHWJandeleit-DahmKANADPH Oxidase 1 plays a key role in diabetes mellitus-accelerated atherosclerosisCirculation2013127181888190210.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.112.132159<?supplied-pmid 23564668?>23564668 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR45"><text><SENT sid="59050" pm="."><plain>45.SukumarPViswambharanHImrieHCubbonRMYuldashevaNGageMGallowaySSkromnaAKandaveluPSantosCXGatenbyVKSmithJBeechDJWheatcroftSBChannonKMShahAMKearneyMTNox2 NADPH oxidase has a critical role in insulin resistance-related endothelial cell dysfunctionDiabetes20136262130213410.2337/db12-1294<?supplied-pmid 23349484?>23349484 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR46"><text><SENT sid="59051" pm="."><plain>46.DuJFanLMMaiALiJMCrucial roles of Nox2-derived oxidative stress in deteriorating the function of insulin receptors and endothelium in dietary obesity of middle-aged miceBr J Pharmacol201317051064107710.1111/bph.12336<?supplied-pmid 23957783?>23957783 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR47"><text><SENT sid="59052" pm="."><plain>47.BoekemaEJBraunHPSupramolecular structure of the mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation systemJ Biol Chem200728211410.1074/jbc.R600031200<?supplied-pmid 17102127?>17102127 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR48"><text><SENT sid="59053" pm="."><plain>48.ElmoreSApoptosis: A review of programmed cell deathToxicol Pathol200735449551610.1080/01926230701320337<?supplied-pmid 17562483?>17562483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR49"><text><SENT sid="59054" pm="."><plain>49.YuXYSongYHGengYJLinQXShanZXLinSGLiYGlucose induces apoptosis of cardiomyocytes via microRNA-1 and IGF-1Biochem Biophys Res Commun2008376354855210.1016/j.bbrc.2008.09.025<?supplied-pmid 18801338?>18801338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR50"><text><SENT sid="59055" pm="."><plain>50.AnJChenYHuangZCritical upstream signals of cytochrome c release induced by a novel Bcl-2 inhibitorJ Biol Chem200427918191331914010.1074/jbc.M400295200<?supplied-pmid 14966123?>14966123 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR51"><text><SENT sid="59056" pm="."><plain>51.ZunguMSchislerJCEssopMFMcCuddenCPattersonCWillisMSRegulation of AMPK by the ubiquitin proteasome systemAm J Pathol2011178141110.1016/j.ajpath.2010.11.030<?supplied-pmid 21224036?>21224036 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR52"><text><SENT sid="59057" pm="."><plain>52.ParkSHGammonSRKnippersJDPaulsenSRRubinkDSWinderWWPhosphorylation-activity relationships of AMPK and acetyl-CoA carboxylase in muscleJ Appl Physiol20029262475248210.1152/japplphysiol.00071.2002<?supplied-pmid 12015362?>12015362 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR53"><text><SENT sid="59058" pm="."><plain>53.SambandamNSteinmetzMChuAAltarejosJYDyckJRBLopaschukGDMalonyl-CoA decarboxylase (MCD) is differentially regulated in subcellular compartments by 5’AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) studies using H9c2 cells overexpressing MCD and AMPK by adenoviral gene transfer techniqueEur J Biochem2004271132831284010.1111/j.1432-1033.2004.04218.x<?supplied-pmid 15206948?>15206948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR54"><text><SENT sid="59059" pm="."><plain>54.BrownseyRWBooneANElliottJEKulpaJELeeWMRegulation of acetyl-CoA carboxylaseBiochem Soc Trans200634Pt 222322710.1042/BST0340223<?supplied-pmid 16545081?>16545081 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR55"><text><SENT sid="59060" pm="."><plain>55.MakaulaSAdamTEssopMFUpstream stimulatory factor 1 transactivates the human gene promoter of the cardiac isoform of acetyl-CoA carboxylaseArch Biochem Biophys200644619110010.1016/j.abb.2005.10.025<?supplied-pmid 16376850?>16376850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR56"><text><SENT sid="59061" pm="."><plain>56.RandlePJGarlandPBHalesCNNewsholmeEAThe glucose fatty-acid cycle its role in insulin sensitivity and the metabolic disturbances of diabetes mellitusLancet1963281728578578910.1016/S0140-6736(63)91500-9 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR57"><text><SENT sid="59062" pm="."><plain>57.RevolloJGrimmAImaiSThe regulation of nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide biosynthesis by Nampt/PBEF/visfatin in mammalsCurr Opin2007232164170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR58"><text><SENT sid="59063" pm="."><plain>58.RydströmJMitochondrial NADPH, transhydrogenase and diseaseBiochim Biophys Acta-Bioenerg200617575–672172610.1016/j.bbabio.2006.03.010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR59"><text><SENT sid="59064" pm="."><plain>59.MarnewickJLRautenbachFVenterINeethlingHBlackhurstDMWolmaransPMacHariaMEffects of rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) on oxidative stress and biochemical parameters in adults at risk for cardiovascular diseaseJ Ethnopharmacol20111331465210.1016/j.jep.2010.08.061<?supplied-pmid 20833235?>20833235 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR60"><text><SENT sid="59065" pm="."><plain>60.BhattMPLimYCHwangJNaSKimYMHaKSC-peptide prevents hyperglycemia-induced endothelial apoptosis through inhibition of reactive oxygen species-mediated transglutaminase 2 activationDiabetes201362124325310.2337/db12-0293<?supplied-pmid 22923476?>22923476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR61"><text><SENT sid="59066" pm="."><plain>61.HeXKanHCaiLMaQNrf2 is critical in defense against high glucose-induced oxidative damage in cardiomyocytesJ Mol Cell Cardiol2009461475810.1016/j.yjmcc.2008.10.007<?supplied-pmid 19007787?>19007787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR62"><text><SENT sid="59067" pm="."><plain>62.KobayashiAKangMIWataiYTongKIShibataTUchidaKYamamotoMOxidative and electrophilic stresses activate Nrf2 through inhibition of ubiquitination activity of Keap1Mol Cell Biol200626122122910.1128/MCB.26.1.221-229.2006<?supplied-pmid 16354693?>16354693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR63"><text><SENT sid="59068" pm="."><plain>63.BryanHKOlayanjuAGoldringCEParkBKThe Nrf2 cell defence pathway: Keap1-dependent and -independent mechanisms of regulationBiochem Pharmacol201385670571710.1016/j.bcp.2012.11.016<?supplied-pmid 23219527?>23219527 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR64"><text><SENT sid="59069" pm="."><plain>64.KodeARajendrasozhanSCaitoSYangSRMegsonILRahmanIResveratrol induces glutathione synthesis by activation of Nrf2 and protects against cigarette smoke-mediated oxidative stress in human lung epithelial cellsAm J Physiol Lung Cell Mol Physiol20082943L478L48810.1152/ajplung.00361.2007<?supplied-pmid 18162601?>18162601 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR65"><text><SENT sid="59070" pm="."><plain>65.ScheenAJCardiovascular effects of dipeptidyl peptidase-4 inhibitors: from risk factors to clinical outcomesPostgrad Med2013125372010.3810/pgm.2013.05.2659<?supplied-pmid 23748503?>23748503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR66"><text><SENT sid="59071" pm="."><plain>66.TaylorFHuffmanMDMacedoAFMooreTHBurkeMDavey SmithGWardKEbrahimSStatins for the primary prevention of cardiovascular diseaseCochrane Database Syst Rev20131CD004816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR67"><text><SENT sid="59072" pm="."><plain>67.KhuranaRMalikISMetformin: safety in cardiac patientsPostgrad Med J201086237137310.1136/hrt.2009.173773<?supplied-pmid 20547605?>20547605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR68"><text><SENT sid="59073" pm="."><plain>68.MessaoudiSERongenGAde BoerRARiksenNPThe cardioprotective effects of metforminCurr Opin Lipidol201122644545310.1097/MOL.0b013e32834ae1a7<?supplied-pmid 21897229?>21897229 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR69"><text><SENT sid="59074" pm="."><plain>69.BaileyCJMetformin: effects on micro and macrovascular complications in type 2 diabetesCardiovasc Drugs Ther200822321522410.1007/s10557-008-6092-0<?supplied-pmid 18288595?>18288595 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR70"><text><SENT sid="59075" pm="."><plain>70.PapanasNMaltezosEOral antidiabetic agents: anti-atherosclerotic properties beyond glucose lowering?Curr Pharm Des200915273179319210.2174/138161209789057995<?supplied-pmid 19754390?>19754390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR71"><text><SENT sid="59076" pm="."><plain>71.LexisCPvan der HorstICLipsicEWieringaWGde BoerRAvan den HeuvelAFvan der WerfHWSchurerRAPundziuteGTanESNieuwlandWWillemsenHMDorhoutBMolmansBHvan der Horst-SchriversANWolffenbuttelBHter HorstGJvan RossumACTijssenJGHillegeHLde SmetBJvan der HarstPvan VeldhuisenDJGIPS-III Investigators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59077" pm="."><plain>Effect of metformin on left ventricular function after acute myocardial infarction in patients without diabetes: the GIPS-III randomized clinical trialJAMA2014311151526153510.1001/jama.2014.3315<?supplied-pmid 24687169?>24687169 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR72"><text><SENT sid="59078" pm="."><plain>72.RosiakMPostulaMKaplon-CieslickaATrzeplaECzlonkowskiAFilipiakKJOpolskiGMetformin treatment may be associated with decreased levels of NT-proBNP in patients with type 2 diabetesAdv Med Sci201358236236810.2478/ams-2013-0009<?supplied-pmid 24327531?>24327531 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR73"><text><SENT sid="59079" pm="."><plain>73.JohnsonRDludlaPJoubertEFebruaryFMazibukoSGhoorSMullerCLouwJAspalathin, a dihydrochalcone C-glucoside, protects H9c2 cardiomyocytes against high glucose-induced shifts in substrate preference and apoptosisMol Nutr Food Res201660492293410.1002/mnfr.201500656<?supplied-pmid 26773306?>26773306 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR74"><text><SENT sid="59080" pm="."><plain>74.TanXHuJCombination therapy for type 2 diabetes: dapagliflozin plus metforminExpert Opin Pharmacother201617111712610.1517/14656566.2016.1121235<?supplied-pmid 26567559?>26567559 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR75"><text><SENT sid="59081" pm="."><plain>75.FalahRRTalibWHShbailatSJCombination of metformin and curcumin targets breast cancer in mice by angiogenesis inhibition, immune system modulation and induction of p53 independent apoptosisTher Adv Med Oncol20179423525210.1177/1758834016687482<?supplied-pmid 28491145?>28491145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR76"><text><SENT sid="59082" pm="."><plain>76.ErejuwaOOSulaimanSAWahabMSASirajudeenKNSSallehMSGurtuSAntioxidant protective effect of glibenclamide and metformin in combination with honey in pancreas of streptozotocin-induced diabetic ratsInt J Mol Sci20101152056206610.3390/ijms11052056<?supplied-pmid 20559501?>20559501 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR77"><text><SENT sid="59083" pm="."><plain>77.XieZHeCZouMHAMP-activated protein kinase modulates cardiac autophagy in diabetic cardiomyopathyAutophagy20117101254125510.4161/auto.7.10.16740<?supplied-pmid 21685727?>21685727 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR78"><text><SENT sid="59084" pm="."><plain>78.PaivaMARutter-LocherZGonçalvesLMProvidênciaLADavidsonSMYellonDMMocanuMMEnhancing AMPK activation during ischemia protects the diabetic heart against reperfusion injuryAm J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol20113006H2123H213410.1152/ajpheart.00707.2010<?supplied-pmid 21421816?>21421816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR79"><text><SENT sid="59085" pm="."><plain>79.RíosJLFranciniFSchinellaGRNatural products for the treatment of type 2 diabetes mellitusPlanta Med20158112–13975994<?supplied-pmid 26132858?>26132858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR80"><text><SENT sid="59086" pm="."><plain>80.ShuklaSKGuptaSOjhaSKSharmaSBCardiovascular friendly natural products: a promising approach in the management of CVDNat Prod Res201024987389810.1080/14786410903417378<?supplied-pmid 20461632?>20461632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR81"><text><SENT sid="59087" pm="."><plain>81.JoubertEDe BeerDRooibos (Aspalathus linearis) beyond the farm gate: From herbal tea to potential phytopharmaceuticalS Afr J Bot201177486988610.1016/j.sajb.2011.07.004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR82"><text><SENT sid="59088" pm="."><plain>82.VillañoDPecorariaMTestaMFRaguzziniAStalmachACrozierATubiliCSerafiniMUnfermented and fermented rooibos teas (Aspalathus linearis) increase plasma total antioxidant capacity in healthy humansFood Chem2010123367968310.1016/j.foodchem.2010.05.032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR83"><text><SENT sid="59089" pm="."><plain>83.OhJJoHChoARKimSJHanJAntioxidant and antimicrobial activities of various leafy herbal teasFood Control201331240340910.1016/j.foodcont.2012.10.021 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR84"><text><SENT sid="59090" pm="."><plain>84.Von GadowAJoubertEHansmannCFComparison of the antioxidant activity of rooibos tea (Aspalathus linearis) with green, oolong and black teaFood Chem1997601737710.1016/S0308-8146(96)00312-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR85"><text><SENT sid="59091" pm="."><plain>85.JoubertEWintertonPBritzTJFerreiraDSuperoxide anion and α, α-diphenyl-β-picrylhydrazyl radical scavenging capacity of rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) aqueous extracts, crude phenolic fractions, tannin and flavonoidsFood Res Int200437213313810.1016/j.foodres.2003.09.011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR86"><text><SENT sid="59092" pm="."><plain>86.WaisundaraVYHoonLYFree radical scavenging ability of Aspalathus linearis in two in vitro models of diabetes and cancerJ Tradit Complement Med20155317417810.1016/j.jtcme.2014.11.009<?supplied-pmid 26151031?>26151031 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR87"><text><SENT sid="59093" pm="."><plain>87.UlicnáOVancováOBozekPCárskyJSebekováKBoorPNakanoMGreksákMRooibos tea (Aspalathus linearis) partially prevents oxidative stress in streptozotocin-induced diabetic ratsPhysiol Res2006552157164<?supplied-pmid 15910170?>15910170 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR88"><text><SENT sid="59094" pm="."><plain>88.HongISLeeHYKimHPAnti-oxidative effects of Rooibos tea (Aspalathus linearis) on immobilization-induced oxidative stress in rat brainPLoS One201491e8706110.1371/journal.pone.0087061<?supplied-pmid 24466326?>24466326 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR89"><text><SENT sid="59095" pm="."><plain>89.Ajuwon OR, Marnewick JL, Davids LM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59096" pm="."><plain>Rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) and its major flavonoids – potential against oxidative stress-induced conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59097" pm="."><plain>InTech 2015;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5772/61614">http://doi.org/10.5772/61614</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR90"><text><SENT sid="59098" pm="."><plain>90.SandersonMMazibukoSEJoubertEDe BeerDJohnsonRPheifferCLouwJMullerCJFEffects of fermented rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) on adipocyte differentiationPhytomedicine201421210911710.1016/j.phymed.2013.08.011<?supplied-pmid 24060217?>24060217 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR91"><text><SENT sid="59099" pm="."><plain>91.Mazibuko SE. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59100" pm="."><plain>In vitro and in vivo effect of Aspalathus linearis and its major polyphenols on carbohydrate and lipid metabolism in insulin resistant models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59101" pm="."><plain>Doctoral dissertation, University of Zululand, 2014. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59102" pm="."><plain>Accessed 12 December 2016. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR92"><text><SENT sid="59103" pm="."><plain>92.BabaHOhtsukaYHarunaHLeeTNagataSMaedaMYamashiroYShimizuTStudies of anti-inflammatory effects of rooibos tea in ratsPediatr Int200951570070410.1111/j.1442-200X.2009.02835.x<?supplied-pmid 19419525?>19419525 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR93"><text><SENT sid="59104" pm="."><plain>93.Beltrán-DebónRRullARodríguez-SanabriaFIswaldiIHerranz-LópezMAragonèsGCampsJAlonso-VillaverdeCMenéndezJAMicolVSegura-CarreteroAJovenJContinuous administration of polyphenols from aqueous rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) extract ameliorates dietary-induced metabolic disturbances in hyperlipidemic micePhytomedicine201118541442410.1016/j.phymed.2010.11.008<?supplied-pmid 21211952?>21211952 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR94"><text><SENT sid="59105" pm="."><plain>94.SmithCSwartACRooibos (Aspalathus linearis) facilitates an anti-inflammatory state, modulating IL-6 and IL-10 while not inhibiting the acute glucocorticoid response to a mild novel stressor in vivoJ Funct Foods201627425410.1016/j.jff.2016.08.055 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR95"><text><SENT sid="59106" pm="."><plain>95.MullerCJFJoubertEDe BeerDSandersonMMalherbeCJFeySJLouwJAcute assessment of an aspalathin-enriched green rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) extract with hypoglycemic potentialPhytomedicine2012201323910.1016/j.phymed.2012.09.010<?supplied-pmid 23083813?>23083813 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR96"><text><SENT sid="59107" pm="."><plain>96.KamakuraRSonMJDe BeerDJoubertEMiuraYYagasakiKAntidiabetic effect of green rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) extract in cultured cells and type 2 diabetic model KK-A(y) miceCytotechnology201567469971010.1007/s10616-014-9816-y<?supplied-pmid 25410530?>25410530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR97"><text><SENT sid="59108" pm="."><plain>97.KhanAUGilaniAHSelective bronchodilatory effect of rooibos tea (Aspalathus linearis) and its flavonoid, chrysoeriolEur J Nutr200645846346910.1007/s00394-006-0620-0<?supplied-pmid 17080260?>17080260 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR98"><text><SENT sid="59109" pm="."><plain>98.PerssonIAPerssonKHäggSAnderssonRGEffects of green tea, black tea and rooibos tea on angiotensin-converting enzyme and nitric oxide in healthy volunteersPublic Health Nutr201013573073710.1017/S1368980010000170<?supplied-pmid 20144258?>20144258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR99"><text><SENT sid="59110" pm="."><plain>99.PerssonIAJosefssonMPerssonKAnderssonRGTea flavanols inhibit angiotensin-converting enzyme activity and increase nitric oxide production in human endothelial cellsJ Pharm Pharmacol20065881139114410.1211/jpp.58.8.0016<?supplied-pmid 16872562?>16872562 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR100"><text><SENT sid="59111" pm="."><plain>100.PerssonIAThe pharmacological mechanism of angiotensin-converting enzyme inhibition by green tea, rooibos and enalaprilat-a study on enzyme kineticsPhytother Res201226451752110.1002/ptr.3588<?supplied-pmid 22095883?>22095883 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR101"><text><SENT sid="59112" pm="."><plain>101.PantsiWGMarnewickJLEsterhuyseAJRautenbachFvan RooyenJRooibos (Aspalathus linearis) offers cardiac protection against ischaemia/reperfusion in the isolated perfused rat heartPhytomedicine201118141220122810.1016/j.phymed.2011.09.069<?supplied-pmid 21982437?>21982437 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR102"><text><SENT sid="59113" pm="."><plain>102.TangneyCCRasmussenHEPolyphenols, inflammation, and cardiovascular diseaseCurr Atheroscler Rep201315532410.1007/s11883-013-0324-x<?supplied-pmid 23512608?>23512608 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR103"><text><SENT sid="59114" pm="."><plain>103.BorsWHellerWMichelCSaranMFlavonoids as antioxidants: determination of radical-scavenging efficienciesMethods Enzymol199018634335510.1016/0076-6879(90)86128-I<?supplied-pmid 2172711?>2172711 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR104"><text><SENT sid="59115" pm="."><plain>104.XiaoJKaiGA review of dietary polyphenol-plasma protein interactions: characterization, influence on the bioactivity, and structure-affinity relationshipCrit Rev Food Sci Nutr20125218510110.1080/10408398.2010.499017<?supplied-pmid 21991992?>21991992 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR105"><text><SENT sid="59116" pm="."><plain>105.XiaoJKaiGYamamotoKChenXAdvance in dietary polyphenols as α-glucosidases inhibitors: a review on structure-activity relationship aspectCrit Rev Food Sci Nutr201353881883610.1080/10408398.2011.561379<?supplied-pmid 23768145?>23768145 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR106"><text><SENT sid="59117" pm="."><plain>106.Xiao J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59118" pm="?"><plain>Dietary flavonoid aglycones and their glycosides: Which show better biological significance? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59119" pm="."><plain>Crit Rev Food Sci Nutr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59120" pm="."><plain>2015; doi: 10.1080/10408398.2015.1032400. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR107"><text><SENT sid="59121" pm="."><plain>107.BeeldersTSiggeGOJoubertEde BeerDde VilliersAKinetic optimisation of the reversed phase liquid chromatographic separation of rooibos tea (Aspalathus linearis) phenolics on conventional high performance liquid chromatographic instrumentationJ Chromatogr A2012121912813910.1016/j.chroma.2011.11.012<?supplied-pmid 22153205?>22153205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR108"><text><SENT sid="59122" pm="."><plain>108.Marais C, Steenkamp JA, Ferreira D. Occurrence of phenylpyruvic acid in woody plants: Biosynthetic significance and synthesis of an enolic glucoside derivative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59124" pm="."><plain>J Chem Soc Perkin Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59125" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59126" pm="."><plain>1996;(24):2915-2918. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR109"><text><SENT sid="59127" pm="."><plain>109.StalmachAMullenWPecorariMSerafiniMCrozierABioavailability of C-linked dihydrochalcone and flavanone glucosides in humans following ingestion of unfermented and fermented rooibos teasJ Agric Food Chem200957157104711110.1021/jf9011642<?supplied-pmid 19534535?>19534535 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR110"><text><SENT sid="59128" pm="."><plain>110.Joubert E, De Beer D. Antioxidants of rooibos beverages: role of plant composition and processing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59130" pm="."><plain>In: Preedy V. Processing and impact on antioxidants in beverages, 1st edition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59132" pm="."><plain>Academic Press; 2014. p. 131–143. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR111"><text><SENT sid="59134" pm="."><plain>111.CourtsFLWilliamsonGThe occurrence, fate and biological activities of C-glycosyl flavonoids in the human dietCrit Rev Food Sci Nutr201555101352136710.1080/10408398.2012.694497<?supplied-pmid 24915338?>24915338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR112"><text><SENT sid="59135" pm="."><plain>112.BreiterTLaueCKresselGGröllSEngelhardtUHHahnABioavailability and antioxidant potential of rooibos flavonoids in humans following the consumption of different rooibos formulationsFood Chem2011128233834710.1016/j.foodchem.2011.03.029<?supplied-pmid 25212140?>25212140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR113"><text><SENT sid="59136" pm="."><plain>113.CuervoAHeviaALópezPSuárezASánchezBMargollesAGonzálezSAssociation of polyphenols from oranges and apples with specific intestinal microorganisms in systemic lupus erythematosus patientsNutrients.2015721301131710.3390/nu7021301<?supplied-pmid 25690419?>25690419 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR114"><text><SENT sid="59137" pm="."><plain>114.OzdalTSelaDAXiaoJBoyaciogluDChenFCapanogluEThe reciprocal interactions between polyphenols and gut microbiota and effects on bioaccessibilityNutrients.2016827810.3390/nu8020078<?supplied-pmid 26861391?>26861391 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR115"><text><SENT sid="59138" pm="."><plain>115.KoutsosATuohyKMLovegroveJAApples and cardiovascular health--is the gut microbiota a core consideration?Nutrients2015763959399810.3390/nu7063959<?supplied-pmid 26016654?>26016654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR116"><text><SENT sid="59139" pm="."><plain>116.BowlesSJoubertEDe BeerDLouwJBrunschwigCNjorogeMLawrenceNWiesnerLChibaleKMullerCIntestinal transport characteristics and metabolism of C-glucosyl dihydrochalcone, aspalathinMolecules201722455410.3390/molecules22040554 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR117"><text><SENT sid="59140" pm="."><plain>117.SnijmanPWJoubertEFerreiraDLiXCDingYGreenIRGelderblomWCAntioxidant activity of the dihydrochalcones aspalathin and nothofagin and their corresponding flavones in relation to other rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) flavonoids, epigallocatechin gallate, and troloxJ Agric Food Chem200957156678668410.1021/jf901417k<?supplied-pmid 19722573?>19722573 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR118"><text><SENT sid="59141" pm="."><plain>118.KuSKKwakSKimYBaeJSAspalathin and nothofagin from rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) inhibits high glucose-induced inflammation in vitro and in vivoInflammation201538144545510.1007/s10753-014-0049-1<?supplied-pmid 25338943?>25338943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR119"><text><SENT sid="59142" pm="."><plain>119.KuSKLeeWKangMBaeJSAntithrombotic activities of aspalathin and nothofagin via inhibiting platelet aggregation and FIIa/FXaArch Pharm Res20153861080108910.1007/s12272-014-0501-7<?supplied-pmid 25325928?>25325928 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR120"><text><SENT sid="59143" pm="."><plain>120.NajafianMNajafianBNajafianZThe effect of aspalathin on levels of sugar and lipids in streptozotocin-induced diabetic and normal ratsZahedan J Res Med Sci20161811e4963 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR121"><text><SENT sid="59144" pm="."><plain>121.KawanoANakamuraHHataSMinakawaMMiuraYYagasakiKHypoglycemic effect of aspalathin, a rooibos tea component from Aspalathus linearis, in type 2 diabetic model db/db micePhytomedicine200916543744310.1016/j.phymed.2008.11.009<?supplied-pmid 19188054?>19188054 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR122"><text><SENT sid="59145" pm="."><plain>122.SonMJMinakawaMMiuraYYagasakiKAspalathin improves hyperglycemia and glucose intolerance in obese diabetic ob/ob miceEur J Nutr20135261607161910.1007/s00394-012-0466-6<?supplied-pmid 23238530?>23238530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR123"><text><SENT sid="59146" pm="."><plain>123.MazibukoSEJoubertEJohnsonRLouwJOpokuARMullerCJAspalathin improves glucose and lipid metabolism in 3T3-L1 adipocytes exposed to palmitateMol Nutr Food Res201559112199220810.1002/mnfr.201500258<?supplied-pmid 26310822?>26310822 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR124"><text><SENT sid="59147" pm="."><plain>124.JohnsonRDludlaPVMullerCJHuisamenBEssopMFLouwJThe transcription profile unveils the cardioprotective effect of aspalathin against lipid toxicity in an in vitro H9c2 modelMolecules201722221910.3390/molecules22020219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR125"><text><SENT sid="59148" pm="."><plain>125.SmitSEAn investigation into the effects of aspalathin on myocardial glucose transport using cardiomyocytes, and terminally differentiated H9c2 cells2016MSc (Medical Physiology) ThesisStellenbosch University </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR126"><text><SENT sid="59149" pm="."><plain>126.DludlaPVMullerCJFJoubertELouwJEssopMFGabuzaKBGhoorSHuisamenBJohnsonRAspalathin protects the heart against hyperglycemia-induced oxidative damage by up-regulating Nrf2 expressionMolecules201722112910.3390/molecules22010129 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR127"><text><SENT sid="59150" pm="."><plain>127.JoubertEBeeldersTde BeerDMalherbeCJde VilliersAJSiggeGOVariation in phenolic content and antioxidant activity of fermented rooibos herbal tea infusions: Role of production season and quality gradeJ Agric Food Chem201260369171917910.1021/jf302583r<?supplied-pmid 22920220?>22920220 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR128"><text><SENT sid="59151" pm="."><plain>128.ShiJZhuLLiYZhengHYuJLuLLiuZIn vitro study of UGTs metabolism and permeability of orientin and isoorientin, two active flavonoid C-glycosidesDrug Metab Lett201610210111010.2174/1872312810666160219121217<?supplied-pmid 26891873?>26891873 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR129"><text><SENT sid="59152" pm="."><plain>129.LiuLGuoLZhaoCWuXWangRLiuCCharacterization of the intestinal absorption of seven flavonoids from the flowers of Trollius chinensis using the Caco-2 cell monolayer modelPLoS One2015103e011926310.1371/journal.pone.0119263<?supplied-pmid 25789809?>25789809 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR130"><text><SENT sid="59153" pm="."><plain>130.LiDWangQYuanZFZhangLXuLCuiYDuanKPharmacokinetics and tissue distribution study of orientin in rat by liquid chromatographyJ Pharm Biomed Anal200847242943410.1016/j.jpba.2008.01.035<?supplied-pmid 18395390?>18395390 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR131"><text><SENT sid="59154" pm="."><plain>131.ZhouPLiLPLuoSQJiangHDZengSIntestinal absorption of luteolin from peanut hull extract is more efficient than that from individual pure luteolinJ Agric Food Chem200856129630010.1021/jf072612+<?supplied-pmid 18052241?>18052241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR132"><text><SENT sid="59155" pm="."><plain>132.LikhitwitayawuidKKlongsiriwetCJongbunprasertVSritularakBWongseripipatanaSFlavones with free radical scavenging activity from Goniothalamus tenuifoliusArch Pharm Res200629319920210.1007/BF02969393<?supplied-pmid 16596991?>16596991 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR133"><text><SENT sid="59156" pm="."><plain>133.KimJLeeISeoJJungMKimYYimNBaeKVitexin, orientin and other flavonoids from Spirodela polyrhiza inhibit adipogenesis in 3T3-L1 cellsPhytother Res201024101543154810.1002/ptr.3186<?supplied-pmid 20878708?>20878708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR134"><text><SENT sid="59157" pm="."><plain>134.KuSKKwakSBaeJSOrientin inhibits high glucose-induced vascular inflammation in vitro and in vivoInflammation20143762164217310.1007/s10753-014-9950-x<?supplied-pmid 24950780?>24950780 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR135"><text><SENT sid="59158" pm="."><plain>135.OrregoRLeivaECheelJInhibitory effect of three C-glycosylflavonoids from Cymbopogon citratus (Lemongrass) on human low density lipoprotein oxidationMolecules200914103906391310.3390/molecules14103906<?supplied-pmid 19924037?>19924037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR136"><text><SENT sid="59159" pm="."><plain>136.LiuLYMaQQLiJYXuJYuanLLiJPHuangXLThe therapeutic effect of orientin on myocardial infarction ratsLishizhen Medicine and Materia Medica Research20138201318071810 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR137"><text><SENT sid="59160" pm="."><plain>137.LiuLWuYHuangXOrientin protects myocardial cells against hypoxia-reoxygenation injury through induction of autophagyEur J Pharmacol2016776909810.1016/j.ejphar.2016.02.037<?supplied-pmid 26875637?>26875637 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR138"><text><SENT sid="59161" pm="."><plain>138.LuNSunYZhengXOrientin-induced cardioprotection against reperfusion is associated with attenuation of mitochondrial permeability transitionPlanta Med2011771098499110.1055/s-0030-1250718<?supplied-pmid 21283956?>21283956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR139"><text><SENT sid="59162" pm="."><plain>139.LamKYLingAPKohRYWongYPSayYHA review on medicinal properties of orientinAdv Pharmacol Sci201620164104595<?supplied-pmid 27298620?>27298620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR140"><text><SENT sid="59163" pm="."><plain>140.FuXCWangMWLiSPWangHLAnti-apoptotic effect and the mechanism of orientin on ischaemic/reperfused myocardiumJ Asian Nat Prod Res20068326527210.1080/10286020500207347<?supplied-pmid 16864433?>16864433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR141"><text><SENT sid="59164" pm="."><plain>141.YuanLHanXLiWRenDYangXIsoorientin prevents hyperlipidemia and liver injury by regulating lipid metabolism, antioxidant capability, and inflammatory cytokine release in high-fructose-fed miceJ Agric Food Chem201664132682268910.1021/acs.jafc.6b00290<?supplied-pmid 26961674?>26961674 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR142"><text><SENT sid="59165" pm="."><plain>142.LimJHParkHSChoiJKLeeISChoiHJIsoorientin induces Nrf2 pathway-driven antioxidant response through phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase signalingArch Pharm Res200730121590159810.1007/BF02977329<?supplied-pmid 18254247?>18254247 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR143"><text><SENT sid="59166" pm="."><plain>143.ChooCYSulongNYManFWongTWVitexin and isovitexin from the leaves of Ficus deltoidea with in-vivo α-glucosidase inhibitionJ Ethnopharmacol2012142377678110.1016/j.jep.2012.05.062<?supplied-pmid 22683902?>22683902 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR144"><text><SENT sid="59167" pm="."><plain>144.YaoYChengXWangLWangSRenGA determination of potential α-glucosidase inhibitors from Azuki Beans (Vigna angularis)Int J Mol Sci201112106445645110.3390/ijms12106445<?supplied-pmid 22072898?>22072898 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR145"><text><SENT sid="59168" pm="."><plain>145.PengXZhengZChengKWShanFRenGXChenFWangMInhibitory effect of mung bean extract and its constituents vitexin and isovitexin on the formation of advanced glycation end productsFood Chem2008106247548110.1016/j.foodchem.2007.06.016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR146"><text><SENT sid="59169" pm="."><plain>146.DongLFanYShaoXChenZVitexin protects against myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury in Langendorff-perfused rat hearts by attenuating inflammatory response and apoptosisFood Chem Toxicol201149123211321610.1016/j.fct.2011.09.040<?supplied-pmid 22001368?>22001368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR147"><text><SENT sid="59170" pm="."><plain>147.WangYZhenYWuXJiangQLiXChenZZhangGDongLVitexin protects brain against ischemia/reperfusion injury via modulating mitogen-activated protein kinase and apoptosis signaling in micePhytomedicine201522337938410.1016/j.phymed.2015.01.009<?supplied-pmid 25837275?>25837275 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR148"><text><SENT sid="59171" pm="."><plain>148.DongLYLiSZhenYLWangYNShaoXLuoZGCardioprotection of vitexin on myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury in rat via regulating inflammatory cytokines and MAPK pathwayAm J Chin Med.20134161251126610.1142/S0192415X13500845<?supplied-pmid 24228599?>24228599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR149"><text><SENT sid="59172" pm="."><plain>149.WangXSHuXCChenGLYuanXYangRNLiangSRenJSunJCKongGQGaoSGFengXSEffects of vitexin on the pharmacokinetics and mRNA expression of CYP isozymes in ratsPhytother Res201529336637210.1002/ptr.5260<?supplied-pmid 25447838?>25447838 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR150"><text><SENT sid="59173" pm="."><plain>150.ShaoXDongLYLiXLGuoYJiangQFangMEffects of vitexin on hemodynamics and myocardial oxygen consumption in anesthetized dogsAnhui Med and Pharm J201092010004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR151"><text><SENT sid="59174" pm="."><plain>151.LuCCXuYQWuJCHangPZWangYWangCWuJWQiJCZhangYDuZMVitexin protects against cardiac hypertrophy via inhibiting calcineurin and CaMKII signaling pathwaysNaunyn Schmiedeberg's Arch Pharmacol2013386874775510.1007/s00210-013-0873-023624753 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR152"><text><SENT sid="59175" pm="."><plain>152.DongLYChenZWGuoYChengXPShaoXMechanisms of vitexin preconditioning effects on cultured neonatal rat cardiomyocytes with anoxia and reoxygenationAm J Chin Med.200836238539710.1142/S0192415X08005849<?supplied-pmid 18457368?>18457368 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR153"><text><SENT sid="59176" pm="."><plain>153.KwonEYJungUJParkTYunJWChoiMSLuteolin attenuates hepatic steatosis and insulin resistance through the interplay between the liver and adipose tissue in mice with diet-induced obesityDiabetes20156451658166910.2337/db14-0631<?supplied-pmid 25524918?>25524918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR154"><text><SENT sid="59177" pm="."><plain>154.LiuYTianXGouLSunLLingXYinXLuteolin attenuates diabetes-associated cognitive decline in ratsBrain Res Bull201394232910.1016/j.brainresbull.2013.02.001<?supplied-pmid 23415807?>23415807 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR155"><text><SENT sid="59178" pm="."><plain>155.WangGGLuXHLiWZhaoXZhangCProtective effects of luteolin on diabetic nephropathy in STZ-induced diabetic ratsEvid Based Complement Alternat Med20112011323171<?supplied-pmid 21584231?>21584231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR156"><text><SENT sid="59179" pm="."><plain>156.LamySMoldovanPLBen SaadAAnnabiBBiphasic effects of luteolin on interleukin-1β-induced cyclooxygenase-2 expression in glioblastoma cellsBiochim Biophys Acta20151853112613510.1016/j.bbamcr.2014.10.010<?supplied-pmid 25409926?>25409926 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR157"><text><SENT sid="59180" pm="."><plain>157.BagliEStefaniotouMMorbidelliLZicheMPsillasKMurphyCFotsisTLuteolin inhibits vascular endothelial growth factor-induced angiogenesis; inhibition of endothelial cell survival and proliferation by targeting phosphatidylinositol 3′-kinase activityCancer Res200464217936794610.1158/0008-5472.CAN-03-3104<?supplied-pmid 15520200?>15520200 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR158"><text><SENT sid="59181" pm="."><plain>158.WengZPatelABVasiadiMTherianouATheoharidesTCLuteolin inhibits human keratinocyte activation and decreases NF-κB induction that is increased in psoriatic skinPLoS One201492e9073910.1371/journal.pone.0090739<?supplied-pmid 24587411?>24587411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR159"><text><SENT sid="59182" pm="."><plain>159.AbdallaSZargaMASabriSEffects of the flavone luteolin, isolated from Colchicum richii, on guinea-pig isolated smooth muscle and heart and on blood pressure and blood flowPhytother Res19948526527010.1002/ptr.2650080503 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR160"><text><SENT sid="59183" pm="."><plain>160.SuJXuHTYuJJGaoJLLeiJYinQSLiBPangMXSuMXMiWJChenSHLvGYLuteolin ameliorates hypertensive vascular remodeling through inhibiting the proliferation and migration of vascular smooth muscle cellsEvid Based Complement Alternat Med20152015364876<?supplied-pmid 26495010?>26495010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR161"><text><SENT sid="59184" pm="."><plain>161.El-BassossyHMAbo-WardaSMFahmyAChrysin and luteolin alleviate vascular complications associated with insulin resistance mainly through PPAR-γ activationAm J Chin Med.20144251153116710.1142/S0192415X14500724<?supplied-pmid 25169908?>25169908 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR162"><text><SENT sid="59185" pm="."><plain>162.BianCXuTZhuHPanDLiuYLuoYWuPLiDLuteolin inhibits Ischemia/reperfusion-induced myocardial injury in rats via downregulation of microRNA-208b-3pPLoS One20151012e014487710.1371/journal.pone.0144877<?supplied-pmid 26658785?>26658785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR163"><text><SENT sid="59186" pm="."><plain>163.WangGLiWLuXBaoPZhaoXLuteolin ameliorates cardiac failure in type I diabetic cardiomyopathyJ Diabetes Complicat201226425926510.1016/j.jdiacomp.2012.04.007<?supplied-pmid 22626874?>22626874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR164"><text><SENT sid="59187" pm="."><plain>164.SunGBSunXWangMYeJXSiJYXuHBMengXBQinMSunJWangHWSunXBOxidative stress suppression by luteolin-induced heme oxygenase-1 expressionToxicol Appl Pharmacol2012265222924010.1016/j.taap.2012.10.002<?supplied-pmid 23051850?>23051850 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR165"><text><SENT sid="59188" pm="."><plain>165.WuXXuTLiDZhuSChenQHuWPanDZhuHSunHERK/PP1a/PLB/SERCA2a and JNK pathways are involved in luteolin-mediated protection of rat hearts and cardiomyocytes following ischemia/reperfusionPLoS One2013812e8295710.1371/journal.pone.0082957<?supplied-pmid 24386130?>24386130 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR166"><text><SENT sid="59189" pm="."><plain>166.OdontuyaGHoultJRHoughtonPJStructure-activity relationship for antiinflammatory effect of luteolin and its derived glycosidesPhytother Res200519978278610.1002/ptr.1723<?supplied-pmid 16220571?>16220571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR167"><text><SENT sid="59190" pm="."><plain>167.ToyodaMTanakaKHoshinoKAkiyamaHTanimuraASaitoYProfiles of potentially antiallergic flavonoids in 27 kinds of health tea and green tea infusionsJ Agric Food Chem19974572561256410.1021/jf970024y </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR168"><text><SENT sid="59191" pm="."><plain>168.MishraBPriyadarsiniKIKumarMSUnnikrishnanMKMohanHEffect of O-glycosilation on the antioxidant activity and free radical reactions of a plant flavonoid, chrysoeriolBioorg Med Chem200311132677268510.1016/S0968-0896(03)00232-3<?supplied-pmid 12788341?>12788341 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR169"><text><SENT sid="59192" pm="."><plain>169.KimYHLeeYSChoiEMChrysoeriol isolated from Eurya cilliata leaves protects MC3T3-E1 cells against hydrogen peroxide-induced inhibition of osteoblastic differentiationJ Appl Toxicol201030766667310.1002/jat.1539<?supplied-pmid 20981859?>20981859 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR170"><text><SENT sid="59193" pm="."><plain>170.ChoiDYLeeJYKimMRWooERKimYGKangKWChrysoeriol potently inhibits the induction of nitric oxide synthase by blocking AP-1 activationJ Biomed Sci200512694995910.1007/s11373-005-9028-8<?supplied-pmid 16228289?>16228289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR171"><text><SENT sid="59194" pm="."><plain>171.RamirezGZamilpaAZavalaMPerezJMoralesDTortorielloJChrysoeriol and other polyphenols from Tecoma stans with lipase inhibitory activityJ Ethnopharmacol20161851810.1016/j.jep.2016.03.014<?supplied-pmid 26970570?>26970570 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR172"><text><SENT sid="59195" pm="."><plain>172.LiuZSongXDXinYWangXJYuHBaiYYLiuJHZhangCNHuiRTProtective effect of chrysoeriol against doxorubicin-induced cardiotoxicity in vitroChin Med J20091222126522656<?supplied-pmid 19951587?>19951587 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR173"><text><SENT sid="59196" pm="."><plain>173.HollmanPCKatanMBDietary flavonoids: intake, health effects and bioavailabilityFood Chem Toxicol1999379–1093794210.1016/S0278-6915(99)00079-4<?supplied-pmid 10541448?>10541448 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR174"><text><SENT sid="59197" pm="."><plain>174.VogiatzoglouAMulliganAALentjesMALubenRNSpencerJPSchroeterHKhawKTKuhnleGGFlavonoid intake in European adults (18 to 64 years)PLoS One2015105e012813210.1371/journal.pone.0128132<?supplied-pmid 26010916?>26010916 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR175"><text><SENT sid="59198" pm="."><plain>175.ScalbertAMorandCManachCRémésyCAbsorption and metabolism of polyphenols in the gut and impact on healthBiomed Pharmacother200256627628210.1016/S0753-3322(02)00205-6<?supplied-pmid 12224598?>12224598 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR176"><text><SENT sid="59199" pm="."><plain>176.HollmanPCDe VriesJHVan LeeuwenSDMengelersMJKatanMBAbsorption of dietary quercetin glycosides and quercetin in healthy ileostomy volunteersAm J Clin Nutr199562612761282<?supplied-pmid 7491892?>7491892 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR177"><text><SENT sid="59200" pm="."><plain>177.ChangQZuoZChowMSHoWKDifference in absorption of the two structurally similar flavonoid glycosides, hyperoside and isoquercitrin, in ratsEur J Pharm Biopharm200559354955510.1016/j.ejpb.2004.10.004<?supplied-pmid 15760736?>15760736 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR178"><text><SENT sid="59201" pm="."><plain>178.HertogMGFeskensEJHollmanPCKatanMBKromhoutDDietary antioxidant flavonoids and risk of coronary heart disease: the Zutphen Elderly StudyLancet199334288781007101110.1016/0140-6736(93)92876-U<?supplied-pmid 8105262?>8105262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR179"><text><SENT sid="59202" pm="."><plain>179.YousefMIOmarSAEl-GuendiMIAbdelmegidLAPotential protective effects of quercetin and curcumin on paracetamol-induced histological changes, oxidative stress, impaired liver and kidney functions and haematotoxicity in ratFood Chem Toxicol201048113246326110.1016/j.fct.2010.08.034<?supplied-pmid 20804811?>20804811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR180"><text><SENT sid="59203" pm="."><plain>180.LiXZhengTSangSLvLQuercetin inhibits advanced glycation end product formation by trapping methylglyoxal and glyoxalJ Agric Food Chem20146250121521215810.1021/jf504132x<?supplied-pmid 25412188?>25412188 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR181"><text><SENT sid="59204" pm="."><plain>181.OdbayarTOBadamhandDKimuraTTakashiYTsushidaTIdeTComparative studies of some phenolic compounds (quercetin, rutin, and ferulic acid) affecting hepatic fatty acid synthesis in miceJ Agric Food Chem200654218261826510.1021/jf061135c<?supplied-pmid 17032037?>17032037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR182"><text><SENT sid="59205" pm="."><plain>182.DhanyaRArunKBSyamaHPNishaPSundaresanASanthosh KumarTRJayamurthyPRutin and quercetin enhance glucose uptake in L6 myotubes under oxidative stress induced by tertiary butyl hydrogen peroxideFood Chem201415854655410.1016/j.foodchem.2014.02.151<?supplied-pmid 24731381?>24731381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR183"><text><SENT sid="59206" pm="."><plain>183.HuQHZhangXPanYLiYCKongLDAllopurinol, quercetin and rutin ameliorate renal NLRP3 inflammasome activation and lipid accumulation in fructose-fed ratsBiochem Pharmacol201284111312510.1016/j.bcp.2012.03.005<?supplied-pmid 22426011?>22426011 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR184"><text><SENT sid="59207" pm="."><plain>184.KrishnaKMAnnapurnaAGopalGSChalamCRMadanKKumarVKPrakashGJPartial reversal by rutin and quercetin of impaired cardiac function in streptozotocin-induced diabetic ratsCan J Physiol Pharmacol200583434335510.1139/y05-009<?supplied-pmid 15877109?>15877109 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR185"><text><SENT sid="59208" pm="."><plain>185.WangYBGeZMKangWQLianZXYaoJZhouCYRutin alleviates diabetic cardiomyopathy in a rat model of type 2 diabetesExp Ther Med.201592451455<?supplied-pmid 25574214?>25574214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR186"><text><SENT sid="59209" pm="."><plain>186.GuimaraesJFCMuzioBPRosaCMNascimentoAFSugizakiMMFernandesAAHCicognaACPadovaniCROkoshiMPOkoshiKRutin administration attenuates myocardial dysfunction in diabetic ratsCardiovasc Diabetol2015149010.1186/s12933-015-0255-7<?supplied-pmid 26185015?>26185015 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR187"><text><SENT sid="59210" pm="."><plain>187.MahmoudMFHassanNAEl BassossyHMFahmyAQuercetin protects against diabetes-induced exaggerated vasoconstriction in rats: effect on low grade inflammationPLoS One201385e6378410.1371/journal.pone.0063784<?supplied-pmid 23717483?>23717483 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR188"><text><SENT sid="59211" pm="."><plain>188.MilenkovićMArsenović-RaninNStojić-VukanićZBufanBVučićevićDJančićIQuercetin ameliorates experimental autoimmune myocarditis in ratsJ Pharm Pharm Sci201013331131910.18433/J3VS3S<?supplied-pmid 21092705?>21092705 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR189"><text><SENT sid="59212" pm="."><plain>189.CaiQRahnROZhangRDietary flavonoids, quercetin, luteolin and genistein, reduce oxidative DNA damage and lipid peroxidation and quench free radicalsCancer Lett199711919910710.1016/S0304-3835(97)00261-9<?supplied-pmid 18372528?>18372528 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR190"><text><SENT sid="59213" pm="."><plain>190.PsotováJChlopcíkováSGrambalFSimánekVUlrichováJInfluence of silymarin and its flavonolignans on doxorubicin-iron induced lipid peroxidation in rat heart microsomes and mitochondria in comparison with quercetinPhytother Res200216Suppl 1S63S6710.1002/ptr.811<?supplied-pmid 11933142?>11933142 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR191"><text><SENT sid="59214" pm="."><plain>191.MeyerASHeinonenMFrankelENAntioxidant interactions of catechin, cyanidin, caffeic acid, quercetin, and ellagic acid on human LDL oxidationFood Chem1998611–2717510.1016/S0308-8146(97)00100-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR192"><text><SENT sid="59215" pm="."><plain>192.KamadaCda SilvaELOhnishi-KameyamaMMoonJHTeraoJAttenuation of lipid peroxidation and hyperlipidemia by quercetin glucoside in the aorta of high cholesterol-fed rabbitFree Radic Res200539218519410.1080/10715760400019638<?supplied-pmid 15763966?>15763966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR193"><text><SENT sid="59216" pm="."><plain>193.ZahediMGhiasvandRFeiziAAsgariGDarvishLDoes quercetin improve cardiovascular risk factors and inflammatory biomarkers in women with type 2 diabetes: a double-blind randomized controlled clinical trialInt J Prev Med201347777785<?supplied-pmid 24049596?>24049596 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR194"><text><SENT sid="59217" pm="."><plain>194.FernandesAANovelliELOkoshiKOkoshiMPDi MuzioBPGuimarãesJFFernandesJAInfluence of rutin treatment on biochemical alterations in experimental diabetesBiomed Pharmacother201064321421910.1016/j.biopha.2009.08.007<?supplied-pmid 19932588?>19932588 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR195"><text><SENT sid="59218" pm="."><plain>195.PashikantiSde AlbaDRBoissonneaultGACervantes-LaureanDRutin metabolites: novel inhibitors of nonoxidative advanced glycation end productsFree Radic Biol Med201048565666310.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2009.11.019<?supplied-pmid 19969069?>19969069 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR196"><text><SENT sid="59219" pm="."><plain>196.Cervantes-LaureanDSchrammDDJacobsonELHalaweishIBrucknerGGBoissonneaultGAInhibition of advanced glycation end product formation on collagen by rutin and its metabolitesJ Nutr Biochem200617853154010.1016/j.jnutbio.2005.10.002<?supplied-pmid 16443355?>16443355 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR197"><text><SENT sid="59220" pm="."><plain>197.PrincePKamalakkannanNRutin improves glucose homeostasis in streptozotocin diabetic tissues by altering glycolytic and gluconeogenic enzymesJ Biochem Mol Toxicol20062029610210.1002/jbt.2011716615078 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR198"><text><SENT sid="59221" pm="."><plain>198.AhnJLeeHKimSParkJHaTThe anti-obesity effect of quercetin is mediated by the AMPK and MAPK signaling pathwaysBiochem Biophys Res Commun2008373454554910.1016/j.bbrc.2008.06.077<?supplied-pmid 18586010?>18586010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR199"><text><SENT sid="59222" pm="."><plain>199.UmaraniVMuvvalaSRameshALakshmiBVSravanthiNRutin potentially attenuates fluoride-induced oxidative stress-mediated cardiotoxicity, blood toxicity and dyslipidemia in ratsToxicol Mech Methods201525214314910.3109/15376516.2014.1003359<?supplied-pmid 25560802?>25560802 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR200"><text><SENT sid="59223" pm="."><plain>200.LiangTYueWLiQComparison of the phenolic content and antioxidant activities of Apocynum venetum L. (Luo-Bu-Ma) and two of its alternative speciesInt J Mol Sci201011114452446410.3390/ijms11114452<?supplied-pmid 21151449?>21151449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR201"><text><SENT sid="59224" pm="."><plain>201.DezsiSBădărăuASBischinCVodnarDCSilaghi-DumitrescuRGheldiuAMMocanAVlaseLAntimicrobial and antioxidant activities and phenolic profile of Eucalyptus globulus Labill. and Corymbia ficifolia (F. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59225" pm="."><plain>Muell.) K.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59226" pm="."><plain>Hill &amp; L.A.S. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59227" pm="."><plain>Johnson leavesMolecules20152034720473410.3390/molecules20034720<?supplied-pmid 25786160?>25786160 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR202"><text><SENT sid="59228" pm="."><plain>202.WangSSWangDMPuWJLiDWPhytochemical profiles, antioxidant and antimicrobial activities of three Potentilla speciesBMC Complement Altern Med20131332110.1186/1472-6882-13-321<?supplied-pmid 24252124?>24252124 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR203"><text><SENT sid="59229" pm="."><plain>203.ZhouLAnXFTengSCLiuJSShangWBZhangAHYuanYGYuJYPretreatment with the total flavone glycosides of Flos Abelmoschus manihot and hyperoside prevents glomerular podocyte apoptosis in streptozotocin-induced diabetic nephropathyJ Med Food201215546146810.1089/jmf.2011.1921<?supplied-pmid 22439874?>22439874 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR204"><text><SENT sid="59230" pm="."><plain>204.ZhangJFuHXuYNiuYAnXHyperoside reduces albuminuria in diabetic nephropathy at the early stage through ameliorating renal damage and podocyte injuryJ Nat Med201670474074810.1007/s11418-016-1007-z<?supplied-pmid 27255369?>27255369 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR205"><text><SENT sid="59231" pm="."><plain>205.ZhangZSethielMSShenWLiaoSZouYHyperoside downregulates the receptor for advanced glycation end products (RAGE) and promotes proliferation in ECV304 cells via the c-Jun N-terminal kinases (JNK) pathway following stimulation by advanced glycation end-products in vitroInt J Mol Sci20131411226972270710.3390/ijms141122697<?supplied-pmid 24252909?>24252909 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR206"><text><SENT sid="59232" pm="."><plain>206.KimSJUmJYLeeJYAnti-inflammatory activity of hyperoside through the suppression of nuclear factor-κB activation in mouse peritoneal macrophagesAm J Chin Med201139117118110.1142/S0192415X11008737<?supplied-pmid 21213407?>21213407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR207"><text><SENT sid="59233" pm="."><plain>207.LiuXZhuLTanJZhouXXiaoLYangXWangBGlucosidase inhibitory activity and antioxidant activity of flavonoid compound and triterpenoid compound from Agrimonia Pilosa LedebBMC Complement Altern Med2014141210.1186/1472-6882-14-12<?supplied-pmid 24410924?>24410924 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR208"><text><SENT sid="59234" pm="."><plain>208.KuSKKwakSKwonOJBaeJSHyperoside inhibits high-glucose-induced vascular inflammation in vitro and in vivoInflammation20143751389140010.1007/s10753-014-9863-8<?supplied-pmid 24609927?>24609927 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR209"><text><SENT sid="59235" pm="."><plain>209.LiZLLiuJCHuJLiXQWangSWYiDHZhaoMGProtective effects of hyperoside against human umbilical vein endothelial cell damage induced by hydrogen peroxideJ Ethnopharmacol2012139238839410.1016/j.jep.2011.11.020<?supplied-pmid 22120016?>22120016 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR210"><text><SENT sid="59236" pm="."><plain>210.PiaoMJKangKAZhangRKoDOWangZHYouHJKimHSKimJSKangSSHyunJWHyperoside prevents oxidative damage induced by hydrogen peroxide in lung fibroblast cells via an antioxidant effectBiochim Biophys Acta20081780121448145710.1016/j.bbagen.2008.07.012<?supplied-pmid 18761393?>18761393 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR211"><text><SENT sid="59237" pm="."><plain>211.HanJXuanJLHuHRChenZWProtective effect against myocardial ischemia reperfusion injuries induced by hyperoside preconditioning and its relationship with PI3K/Akt signaling pathway in ratsZhongguo Zhong Yao Za Zhi2015401118123<?supplied-pmid 25993800?>25993800 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR212"><text><SENT sid="59238" pm="."><plain>212.HouJYLiuYLiuLLiXMProtective effect of hyperoside on cardiac ischemia reperfusion injury through inhibition of ER stress and activation of Nrf2 signalingAsian Pac J Trop Med201691768010.1016/j.apjtm.2015.12.001<?supplied-pmid 26851792?>26851792 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR213"><text><SENT sid="59239" pm="."><plain>213.LiZLHuJLiYLXueFZhangLXieJQLiuZHLiHYiDHLiuJCWangSWThe effect of hyperoside on the functional recovery of the ischemic/reperfused isolated rat heart: potential involvement of the extracellular signal-regulated kinase 1/2 signaling pathwayFree Radic Biol Med20135713214010.1016/j.freeradbiomed.2012.12.023<?supplied-pmid 23291593?>23291593 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR214"><text><SENT sid="59240" pm="."><plain>214.JoubertEDe BeerDMalherbeCJMullerNBonnetSLVan Der WesthuizenJHFerreiraDOccurrence and sensory perception of Z-2-(β-D-glucopyranosyloxy)-3- phenylpropenoic acid in rooibos (Aspalathus linearis)Food Chem201313621078108510.1016/j.foodchem.2012.09.014<?supplied-pmid 23122165?>23122165 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR215"><text><SENT sid="59241" pm="."><plain>215.MalaisseWJSenerAWelshMMalaisse-LagaeFHellerstromCChristopheJMechanism of 3-phenylpyruvate-induced insulin releaseMetabolic aspects Biochem J19832103921927<?supplied-pmid 6409083?>6409083 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR216"><text><SENT sid="59242" pm="."><plain>216.Ben-AbrahamRGazitVVofsiOBen-ShlomoIReznickAZKatzYBeta-phenylpyruvate and glucose uptake in isolated mouse soleus muscle and cultured C2C12 muscle cellsJ Cell Biochem200390595796310.1002/jcb.10690<?supplied-pmid 14624455?>14624455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR217"><text><SENT sid="59243" pm="."><plain>217.MullerCJFJoubertEPheifferCGhoorSSandersonMChellanNFeySJLouwJZ-2-(β-d-glucopyranosyloxy)-3-phenylpropenoic acid, an α-hydroxy acid from rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) with hypoglycemic activityMol Nutr Food Res201357122216222210.1002/mnfr.201300294<?supplied-pmid 23943314?>23943314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR218"><text><SENT sid="59244" pm="."><plain>218.MathijsIda CunhaDAHimpeELadriereLChellanNRouxCRJoubertEMullerCCnopMLouwJBouwensLPhenylpropenoic acid glucoside augments pancreatic beta cell mass in high-fat diet-fed mice and protects beta cells from ER stress-induced apoptosisMol Nutr Food Res201458101980199010.1002/mnfr.201400211<?supplied-pmid 25044754?>25044754 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR219"><text><SENT sid="59245" pm="."><plain>219.HimpeECunhaDASongIBuglianiMMarchettiPCnopMBouwensLPhenylpropenoic acid glucoside from rooibos protects pancreatic beta cells against cell death induced by acute injuryPLoS One2016116e015760410.1371/journal.pone.0157604<?supplied-pmid 27299564?>27299564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR220"><text><SENT sid="59246" pm="."><plain>220.OrzelJDaszykowskiMKazuraMDe BeerDJoubertESchulzeAEBeeldersTDe VilliersAMalherbeCJWalczakBModeling of the total antioxidant capacity of rooibos (Aspalathus linearis) tea infusions from chromatographic fingerprints and identification of potential antioxidant markersJ Chromatogr A2014136610110910.1016/j.chroma.2014.09.030<?supplied-pmid 25283576?>25283576 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR221"><text><SENT sid="59247" pm="."><plain>221.DludlaPVMullerCJJoubertELouwJGabuzaKBHuisamenBEssopMFJohnsonRPhenylpyruvic acid-2-O-β-D-glucoside attenuates high glucose-induced apoptosis in H9c2 cardiomyocytesPlanta Med2016821468147410.1055/s-0042-110856<?supplied-pmid 27405104?>27405104 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR222"><text><SENT sid="59248" pm="."><plain>222.PatelOMullerCJoubertELouwJRosenkranzBAwortweCInhibitory Interactions of Aspalathus linearis (rooibos) extracts and compounds, aspalathin and Z-2-(β-D-glucopyranosyloxy)-3-phenylpropenoic acid, on cytochromes metabolizing hypoglycemic and hypolipidemic drugsMolecules20162111151510.3390/molecules21111515 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR223"><text><SENT sid="59249" pm="."><plain>223.LeeWKuSKBaeJSVascular barrier protective effects of orientin and isoorientin in LPS-induced inflammation in vitro and in vivoVasc Pharmacol201462131410.1016/j.vph.2014.04.006 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR224"><text><SENT sid="59250" pm="."><plain>224.CheXWangXZhangJPengCZhenYShaoXZhangGDongLVitexin exerts cardioprotective effect on chronic myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury in rats via inhibiting myocardial apoptosis and lipid peroxidationAm J Transl Res20168833193328<?supplied-pmid 27648122?>27648122 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR225"><text><SENT sid="59251" pm="."><plain>225.OcchiutoFCircostaCDe PasqualeABriguglioFComparative haemodynamic effects of the flavonoids rhoifolin and vitexin in the dogPhytother Res19904311812010.1002/ptr.2650040310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR226"><text><SENT sid="59252" pm="."><plain>226.SunZYanBYuWYYaoXMaXShengGMaQVitexin attenuates acute doxorubicin cardiotoxicity in rats via the suppression of oxidative stress, inflammation and apoptosis and the activation of FOXO3aExp Ther Med201612318791884<?supplied-pmid 27588105?>27588105 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR227"><text><SENT sid="59253" pm="."><plain>227.JiangHXiaQWangXSongJBruceICLuteolin induces vasorelaxion in rat thoracic aorta via calcium and potassium channelsPharmazie2005606444447<?supplied-pmid 15997834?>15997834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR228"><text><SENT sid="59254" pm="."><plain>228.LiaoPHHungLMChenYHKuanYHZhangFBLinRHShihHCTsaiSKHuangSSCardioprotective effects of luteolin during ischemia-reperfusion injury in ratsCirc J201175244345010.1253/circj.CJ-10-0381<?supplied-pmid 21178298?>21178298 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR229"><text><SENT sid="59255" pm="."><plain>229.ChallaSRAkulaAMetlaSGopalPNPartial role of nitric oxide in infarct size limiting effect of quercetin and rutin against ischemia-reperfusion injury in normal and diabetic ratsIndian J Exp Biol2011493207210<?supplied-pmid 21452600?>21452600 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR230"><text><SENT sid="59256" pm="."><plain>230.GalindoPRodriguez-GómezIGonzález-ManzanoSDueñasMJiménezRMenéndezCVargasFTamargoJSantos-BuelgaCPérez-VizcaínoFDuarteJGlucuronidated quercetin lowers blood pressure in spontaneously hypertensive rats via deconjugationPLoS One201273e3267310.1371/journal.pone.0032673<?supplied-pmid 22427863?>22427863 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR231"><text><SENT sid="59257" pm="."><plain>231.GuoXDZhangDYGaoXJParryJLiuKLiuBLWangMQuercetin and quercetin-3-O-glucuronide are equally effective in ameliorating endothelial insulin resistance through inhibition of reactive oxygen species-associated inflammationMol Nutr Food Res20135761037104510.1002/mnfr.201200569<?supplied-pmid 23504962?>23504962 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR232"><text><SENT sid="59258" pm="."><plain>232.AnnapurnaAReddyCSAkondiRBRaoSRCardioprotective actions of two bioflavonoids, quercetin and rutin, in experimental myocardial infarction in both normal and streptozotocin-induced type I diabetic ratsJ Pharm Pharmacol200961101365137410.1211/jpp.61.10.0014<?supplied-pmid 19814870?>19814870 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR233"><text><SENT sid="59259" pm="."><plain>233.LiMJiangYJingWSunBMiaoCRenLQuercetin provides greater cardioprotective effect than its glycoside derivative rutin on isoproterenol-induced cardiac fibrosis in the ratCan J Physiol Pharmacol2013911195195910.1139/cjpp-2012-0432<?supplied-pmid 24117263?>24117263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR234"><text><SENT sid="59260" pm="."><plain>234.PanchalSKPoudyalHArumugamTVBrownLRutin attenuates metabolic changes, nonalcoholic steatohepatitis, and cardiovascular remodeling in high-carbohydrate, high-fat diet-fed ratsJ Nutr201114161062106910.3945/jn.111.137877<?supplied-pmid 21508207?>21508207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR235"><text><SENT sid="59261" pm="."><plain>235.SaklaniRGuptaSKMohantyIRKumarBSrivastavaSMathurRCardioprotective effects of rutin via alteration in TNF-α, CRP, and BNP levels coupled with antioxidant effect in STZ-induced diabetic ratsMol Cell Biochem20164201–2657210.1007/s11010-016-2767-1<?supplied-pmid 27443845?>27443845 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
