<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" open-status="O" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Bot</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">exbotj</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Experimental Botany</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-0957</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2431</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6137968</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jxb/ery250</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ery250</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Papers</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Growth and Development</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="81368" pm="."><plain>VIRESCENT-ALBINO LEAF 1 regulates leaf colour development and cell division in rice </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Ping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn-0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yunfeng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Peng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Guoling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sang</surname><given-names>Xianchun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>Yinghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Xiaoqin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Yidan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Junyang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Tianquan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Fangming</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Nan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Changwei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Zhenglin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Renhong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7597-987X</contrib-id><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>Guanghua</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001">Rice Research Institute, Key Laboratory of Application and Safety Control of Genetically Modified Crops, Academy of Agricultural Sciences, Southwest University, Chongqing, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence: <email>heghswu@163.com</email></corresp><fn id="fn-0001"><p><text><SENT sid="81369" pm="."><plain>These authors contributed equally to this work. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2018-08-08"><day>08</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>08</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>69</volume><issue>20</issue><fpage>4791</fpage><lpage>4804</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author(s) 2018. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Experimental Biology.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="ery250.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="81370" pm="."><plain>The second enzyme of the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway, PurD, is involved in leaf-colour development and the cell division process in rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><title><text><SENT sid="81371" pm="."><plain>Abstract </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="81372" pm="."><plain>The de novo synthesis of purine nucleotides is crucial to all living organisms, but limited information is available for plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81373" pm="."><plain>In this study, we isolated a virescent-albino leaf 1 (val1) mutant of rice (Oryza sativa) that produces dynamic green-revertible albino and narrow-leaf phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81374" pm="."><plain>In albino leaves, chloroplast development was defective, pigment contents were reduced, and cell division was impaired compared with the wild-type. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81375" pm="."><plain>Map-based cloning revealed that VAL1 encodes a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase (PurD), the second enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81376" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization analysis demonstrated that VAL1 was localized in the chloroplast. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81377" pm="."><plain>Our results demonstrate that VAL1 is a crucial enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway and is involved in regulating chloroplast development, chlorophyll metabolism, and cell division during leaf development in rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>Cell division</kwd><kwd>chloroplast development</kwd><kwd><italic>de novo</italic> purine biosynthesis</kwd><kwd>phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase</kwd><kwd>pigment metabolism</kwd><kwd>rice</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Key Research and Development Project</named-content></funding-source><award-id>2017YFD0100201</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Project of Chongqing Science &amp; Technology Commission</named-content></funding-source><award-id>CSTCCXLJRC201713</award-id><award-id>CSTC2016SHMS-ZTZX0017</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="81378" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81379" pm="."><plain>Chloroplasts are semi-autonomous organelles responsible for the conversion of energy from sunlight, and for the synthesis of organic molecules by means of photosynthesis in higher plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81380" pm="."><plain>Chlorophyll is the primary photosynthetic pigment, and functions in the absorption and transformation of light energy into energy-storage molecules, carbohydrates, and oxygen; it is thus fundamental to the survival and reproduction of all living organisms (Fromme et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81381" pm="."><plain>In higher plants, defective chloroplast development and chlorophyll metabolism lead to changes in chlorophyll content and leaf colour. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81382" pm="."><plain>Leaf-colour mutants are not only useful as markers in hybrid breeding, but can also be used to study development-related processes such as photosynthesis, chlorophyll metabolism, and chloroplast development, and thus have considerable potential for research and practical application (Du et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81383" pm="."><plain>In higher plants, variation in leaf colour is conspicuous, and in rice its diverse phenotypes include virescent, albino, stripe, chlorina, stay-green, zebra, and yellow variegated forms (Yoo et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81384" pm="."><plain>A substantial number of leaf-colour genes have been mapped, but only a few have been cloned. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81385" pm="."><plain>The two CAO homologous genes in rice, OsCAO1 and OsCAO2, encode a chlorophyll a oxygenase, which catalyses the conversion of chlorophyll a to chlorophyll b. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81386" pm="."><plain>Mutation of OsCAO1 causes a pale-green leaf phenotype (Lee et al., 2005; Yang et al., 2016). OsChlD, OsChlH, and OsChlI encode Mg-chelatase subunits that catalyse the chelation of Mg2+ into protoporphyrin IX. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81387" pm="."><plain>Mutations of these three genes all cause a yellow-green leaf phenotype to different degrees of severity (Jung et al., 2003; Deng et al., 2014; Zhang et al., 2015). YELLOW-GREEN LEAF 1 (YGL1) encodes a chlorophyll synthase that catalyses the esterification of a chlorophyllide to complete the final step of chlorophyll biosynthesis in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81388" pm="."><plain>The mutant ygl1 displays yellow-green leaves in young plants owing to decreased chlorophyll accumulation (Wu et al., 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81389" pm="."><plain>The above-mentioned genes all affect the development of leaf pigmentation by regulating the synthesis and degradation of chlorophyll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81390" pm="."><plain>Defective chloroplast development can also lead to the formation of leaf-colour mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81391" pm="."><plain>For example, VIRESCENT 1 (V1) encodes a chloroplast protein that regulates chloroplast RNA metabolism and promotes the establishment of the plastid genetic system in rice. VIRESCENT 2 (V2) encodes a novel type of guanylate kinase and is essential for chloroplast development in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81392" pm="."><plain>The v1 and v2 mutants each develop chlorotic leaves at restrictive temperatures (Sugimoto et al., 2007). VIRESCENT 3 (V3) and STRIPE 1 (St1) respectively encode the large and small subunits of ribonucleotide reductase, which is required for chloroplast biogenesis in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81393" pm="."><plain>The v3 and st1 mutants show chlorotic leaves in a growth stage-dependent manner under field conditions (Yoo et al., 2009). OsPPR1 encodes a novel pentatricopeptide repeat (PPR) protein, which is essential for chloroplast biogenesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81394" pm="."><plain>Antisense transgenic plants display typical chlorophyll-deficient mutant phenotypes of albinism and lethality (Gothandam et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81395" pm="."><plain>Thus, mutations in genes involved in chlorophyll metabolism and chloroplast development result in abnormal leaf-colour phenotypes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81396" pm="."><plain>The de novo synthesis of the purine nucleotide is crucial for all living organisms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81397" pm="."><plain>The synthetic pathway is composed of 11 enzymatic steps, leading to the formation of inosinate, and provides the adenine and guanine purines necessary for almost all biochemical processes, including DNA and RNA metabolism, the biosynthetic intermediates ATP and GTP, co-enzymes, and cytokinins, as well as being a vital metabolic regulator in cell signalling (Smith and Atkins, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81398" pm="."><plain>Although purine plays an important role in plant growth and development, limited information on the synthetic pathway in plants is available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81399" pm="."><plain>The Arabidopsis PURINE BIOSYNTHESIS 4 (PUR4) gene encodes a formylglycinamidine ribonucleotide synthase, which is the fourth enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81400" pm="."><plain>The pur4 mutation is lethal to the male gametophyte and homozygous pur4 plants cannot be obtained, which indicates that de novo purine synthesis is specifically necessary for pollen development (Berthomé et al., 2008). CIA1 encodes a Gln phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate amidotransferase 2 (ATase2), which is one of the three ATase isozymes responsible for the first committed step of de novo purine biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81401" pm="."><plain>The loss-of-function mutant in Arabidopsis and ATase2-RNAi transgenic tobacco (Nicotiana tabacum) plants show normal green cotyledons but small and albino/pale-green mosaic leaves and reduced chloroplast protein import, which indicates that de novo purine biosynthesis is important for chloroplast development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81402" pm="."><plain>In addition, de novo synthesis of purine plays a crucial role in cell division (Hung et al., 2004). PHOSPHORIBOSYLAMINE-GLYCINE LIGASE (PurD) is the second enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway, and catalyses the conversion of 5′-phosphoribosylamine (PRA) to 5′-phosphoribosyl-l-glycinamide (GAR) (Smith and Atkins, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81403" pm="."><plain>In recent years, the biological function of PurD in mycelial growth and the virulence of bacterial strains has been extensively studied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81404" pm="."><plain>For example, strains of Gibberella zeae (Kim et al., 2007), Xanthomonas oryzae pv. oryzae (Park et al., 2007), and Brucella abortus (Truong et al., 2015) harbouring mutations in PurD show reduced virulence against plants, which indicates that purD plays a vital role in the growth and virulence of bacterial strains. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81405" pm="."><plain>However, investigation of the biological functioning of purD in plants is incomplete. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81406" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that purD is a single-copy and mono-functional enzyme in Arabidopsis, and the gene shows a high degree of conserved homology to purD in prokaryotic and eukaryotic species (Schnorr et al., 1994). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81407" pm="."><plain>However, studies on the physiological characteristics and biological function of purD in plants are still required. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81408" pm="."><plain>In this study, we isolated a virescent-albino leaf 1 (val1) mutant, which exhibits a chlorotic and narrow-leaf phenotype, decreased quantities of chlorophyll and carotenoids over the entire growth period, and abnormal chloroplast development on the albino side of the leaf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81409" pm="."><plain>Map-based cloning revealed that VAL1 encodes a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase, the enzyme involved in the second step of the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81410" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization analysis demonstrated that VAL1 was localized in chloroplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81411" pm="."><plain>VAL1 plays a crucial role in the expression of genes associated with chloroplast development and pigment metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81412" pm="."><plain>This is the first report to implicate involvement of the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway in the development of leaf pigmentation and in cell division, and provides novel insights into the mechanisms underlying chloroplast development, pigment accumulation, and cell division in rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="81413" pm="."><plain>Material and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="81414" pm="."><plain>Plant material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81415" pm="."><plain>The rice (Oryza sativa) virescent-albino leaf 1 (val1) mutant was derived from an ethylmethane sulfonate-treated population of rice ‘Jinhui 10’, which was used as the wild-type (WT) strain for phenotypic observations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81416" pm="."><plain>The plants were grown in an experimental field at the Southwest University Rice Research Institute (Chongqing, China). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="81417" pm="."><plain>Physiological analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81418" pm="."><plain>Photosynthetic pigments were extracted from ~0.1 g of newly developed mature leaves from the WT, val1, and transgenic plants in 25 ml extraction buffer (ethanol:acetone, 1:1; v/v) for 24 h at room temperature in the dark. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81419" pm="."><plain>The concentrations of chlorophyll a and b, and carotenoids were determined using a UV-1800PC spectrophotometer (Mapada Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81420" pm="."><plain>Ltd, China) at 663, 645, and 470 nm, respectively, and calculated according to the method of Lichtenthaler (1987). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81421" pm="."><plain>The first leaf from the top of the WT, val1, and transgenic plants was used to measure photosynthetic rate, stomatal conductance, intercellular CO2 concentration, and transpiration rate using a LI-6400 portable photosynthesis meter (LiCor, Lincoln, NE, USA) according to the manufacturer’s instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81422" pm="."><plain>Data presented are the means (±SD) of three biological repeats. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="81423" pm="."><plain>Transmission electron microscopy </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81424" pm="."><plain>Leaves of the WT, val1, and transgenic plants at the tiller stage were collected and cut into 1-mm2 squares, fixed in primary fixative solution (3.5% glutaraldehyde), and then post-fixed for 2 h in 1% osmium tetroxide after washing with 0.1 mol l−1 phosphate buffer saline. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81425" pm="."><plain>Tissues were stained with uranyl acetate, dehydrated in ethanol, and embedded in Spurr’s medium prior to thin-sectioning. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81426" pm="."><plain>Samples were stained again and examined using a H-7500 TEM (Hitachi, Japan) as described previously (Dong et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="81427" pm="."><plain>Paraffin-sectioning and histological analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81428" pm="."><plain>Leaves were collected at the tiller stage and fixed in 50% ethanol, 0.9 M glacial acetic acid, and 3.7% formaldehyde for 12 h at 4 °C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81429" pm="."><plain>The fixed samples were dehydrated with a graded series of ethanol, infiltrated with xylene, and embedded in paraffin (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81430" pm="."><plain>A rotary microtome (RM2245; Leica, Hamburg, Germany) was used to cut 8-μm-thick sections, which were transferred onto poly-L-lysine-coated glass slides, deparaffinized in xylene, and dehydrated through an ethanol series (Ren et al., 2018). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81431" pm="."><plain>Light microscopy was performed using an Eclipse E600 microscope (Nikon, Tokyo, Japan). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s7"><title><text><SENT sid="81432" pm="."><plain>Fine-mapping of VAL1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81433" pm="."><plain>The val1 mutant was crossed with ‘Xinong1A’ (bred by the Southwest University Rice Research Institute) and 2885 F2 plants exhibiting the mutational phenotype were selected for high-resolution mapping. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81434" pm="."><plain>Gene fine-mapping was conducted using simple sequence repeat markers obtained from the publicly available rice databases Gramene (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gramene.org">http://www.gramene.org</ext-link>) and the Rice Genomic Research Program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rgp.dna.affrc.go.jp/E/publicdata/caps/index.html">http://rgp.dna.affrc.go.jp/E/publicdata/caps/index.html</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81435" pm="."><plain>Insertion/deletion markers were developed from comparisons of genomic sequences from ‘Xinong1A’ and ‘Jinhui 10’ in our laboratory. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81436" pm="."><plain>The sequences of primers used in the fine-mapping and candidate gene analysis are listed in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s8"><title><text><SENT sid="81437" pm="."><plain>Vector construction for genetic complementation, RNAi, and over-expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81438" pm="."><plain>For the complementation test, a 7199-bp genomic fragment was cloned into the binary vector pCAMBIA1301. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81439" pm="."><plain>The resulting recombinant plasmids were introduced into val1 using the Agrobacterium tumefaciens-mediated transformation method as described previously (Zhang et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81440" pm="."><plain>To generate a construct for RNAi, a 328-bp fragment of VAL1 complementary DNA was amplified and inserted into the vector pTCK303 to obtain the intermediate vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81441" pm="."><plain>For overexpression of VAL1, the 1580-bp full-length coding sequence of VAL1 was amplified from ‘Jinhui 10’ cDNA and cloned into vector pTCK303 to generate the intermediate vector. VAL1 was driven by the rice ubiquitin promoter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81442" pm="."><plain>The RNAi and overexpression recombinant plasmids were transformed into ‘Jinhui 10’ plants using the A. tumefaciens-mediated transformation method (Zhang et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81443" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s9"><title><text><SENT sid="81444" pm="."><plain>RNA extraction and quantitative real-time PCR analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81445" pm="."><plain>Total rice RNA was extracted from the roots, culms, leaf sheaths, leaves, and young panicles using the RNAprep Pure Plant Kit (Tiangen Co. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81446" pm="."><plain>Ltd, China). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81447" pm="."><plain>The first-strand cDNA was synthesized using the SuperScript® III Reverse Transcriptase Kit (Invitrogen). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81448" pm="."><plain>qRT-PCR analysis was performed using Novostar-SYBR Supermix (Novoprotein, Shanghai, China) in an ABI Biosystems 7500 Real-Time PCR System. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81449" pm="."><plain>At least three replicates were performed and the mean expression level was calculated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81450" pm="."><plain>Genes used for qRT-PCR analysis were as previously described (Wang et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81451" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s10"><title><text><SENT sid="81452" pm="."><plain>Multiple sequence alignment and phylogenetic tree construction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81453" pm="."><plain>Protein sequences were acquired using the BLAST tool in the PHYTOZOME portal, with a 10−5 EXPECT value threshold (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html#!search?show=BLAST">http://phytozome.jgi.doe.gov/pz/portal.html#!search? show=BLAST</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81454" pm="."><plain>A phylogenetic tree was constructed using MEGA 5.0 with the maximum-likelihood method based on the Jones–Taylor–Thornton matrix-based model with the lowest Bayesian information criterion scores (Tamura et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s11"><title><text><SENT sid="81455" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide and cytokinin measurements </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81456" pm="."><plain>Samples of the WT and val1 mutant seedlings (0.1 g) were frozen in liquid nitrogen and homogenized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81457" pm="."><plain>Nucleotides were extracted using the trichloroacetic acid (TCA) method as described previously (Hajirezaei et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81458" pm="."><plain>The nucleotide and cytokinin contents in the TCA extracts were measured using a HPLC system (Kontron, Eching, Germany) fitted with a Partisil-SAX anion-exchange column, and detected by absorption at OD254. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81459" pm="."><plain>Identification and quantification was completed by comparison with standards, as described previously (Hajirezaei et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s12"><title><text><SENT sid="81460" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide treatment in vitro </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81461" pm="."><plain>Wild-type and val1 seeds were surface-sterilized after husking and grown in half-strength Murashige and Skoog medium (pH 5.8) containing different concentrations (0, 1, 5, and 10 mM) of adenine nucleotide (AMP), guanine nucleotide (GMP), or AMP and GMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81462" pm="."><plain>The seeds were incubated at 28 °C under a 16/8 h light/dark photoperiod. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81463" pm="."><plain>Continual observation of seedling phenotypes was undertaken for 7–10 d. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s13"><title><text><SENT sid="81464" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81465" pm="."><plain>The full-length coding region of VAL1 was amplified and cloned into the expression cassette 35S-GFP-NOS (pA7) in order to generate the VAL1-GFP (green fluorescent protein) fusion vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81466" pm="."><plain>Both pA7-VAL1-GFP and empty pA7-GFP plasmids were transformed into rice protoplasts as described previously (Ma et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81467" pm="."><plain>After overnight incubation at 28 °C, GFP fluorescence was observed using a confocal laser-scanning microscopy (Olympus FLUOVIEW FV1000; Japan). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81468" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s14"><title><text><SENT sid="81469" pm="."><plain>In situ hybridization </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81470" pm="."><plain>For the VAL1 and His4 probes, a gene-specific cDNA was amplified and labelled using a DIG RNA Labelling Kit (Roche). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81471" pm="."><plain>Pretreatment of sections, hybridization, and immunological detection were performed as described previously (Zhang et al., 2017). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81472" pm="."><plain>The primer sequences are listed in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s15"><title><text><SENT sid="81473" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81474" pm="."><plain>Total proteins from 10-d-old WT and val1 seedlings were isolated using a Plant Total Protein Extraction Kit (Sangon Biotech). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81475" pm="."><plain>An equal amount of protein was separated on 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81476" pm="."><plain>The proteins were transferred to iBlot 2 PVDF Regular Stacks using the iBlot 2 Gel Transfer Device (Invitrogen), immunoblotted with various primary antibodies (Agrisera and Beijing Protein Innovation Company) and AP-conjugated Affinipure Goat Anti-Rabbit IgG (Jackson ImmunoResearch) according to the recommended dilution ratios in the iBind Cards using the iBind Western Device (Invitrogen), and detected using the NBT/BCIP substrate (Sangon Biotech). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s16"><title><text><SENT sid="81477" pm="."><plain>Transcriptome analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81478" pm="."><plain>Seedlings of the WT and val1 mutant were used for RNA extraction and transcriptome sequencing with two biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81479" pm="."><plain>The purity and concentration of RNA were measured using a NanoPhotometer spectrophotometer (Implen, Westlake Village, CA, USA) and a Qubit® RNA Assay Kit in a Qubit® 2.0 Fluorometer (Life Technologies, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81480" pm="."><plain>Library construction and RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) were conducted by Omicgene Biological Technology (Wuhan, China) on a HiSeq X Ten platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81481" pm="."><plain>RNA-seq short reads were aligned to the indica rice genome with HISAT2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/hisat2/index.shtml">https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/hisat2/index.shtml</ext-link>), and the expression level of each gene was computed using StringTie (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/stringtie/">https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/stringtie/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81482" pm="."><plain>The expression-level data were analysed using the gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) software (version 2.07) to identify functionally related groups of genes (gene sets) with statistically significant enrichment (Subramanian et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81483" pm="."><plain>The gene set files used in GSEA were constructed in accordance with the genome annotation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mbkbase.org/R498">http://www.mbkbase.org/R498</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81484" pm="."><plain>The significance of differentially expressed genes (DGEs) was determined using q-values &lt;0.005 and |log2 (fold-change)| &gt;1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81485" pm="."><plain>Gene Ontology (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/">http://www.geneontology.org/</ext-link>) analyses were performed by referring to GOseq (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.18129/B9.bioc.goseq">http://dx.doi.org/10.18129/B9.bioc.goseq</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s17"><title><text><SENT sid="81486" pm="."><plain>Flow cytometric analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81487" pm="."><plain>For nuclear staining, the shoot apex from rice seedlings was cut into small pieces in 400 µl Partec CyStain UV Precise P Lysis solution (Sysmex Partec) on ice, and then filtered with a 30-µm filter to remove cellular debris. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81488" pm="."><plain>After staining with Partec CyStain UV Precise P Staining solution (including DAPI) (Sysmex Partec), the nuclei were analysed using CyFlow Space (Sysmex Partec). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81489" pm="."><plain>A total of 30 000 events were recorded, and the data were analysed using the FCS Express software (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.denovosoftware.com/">https://www.denovosoftware.com/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s18"><title><text><SENT sid="81490" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s19"><title><text><SENT sid="81491" pm="."><plain>The val1 mutation confers a green-revertible albino and narrow-leaf phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81492" pm="."><plain>In the wild type (WT), the leaves of the plant appeared green throughout the growth period except in the later mature stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81493" pm="."><plain>In contrast, in the val1 mutant, new albino leaves were developed at the early seedling stage (Fig. 1A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81494" pm="."><plain>The leaves subsequently turned green with an albino margin and displayed a mixed phenotype in which green and albino leaves were present from the later seedling stage to the tiller stage (Fig. 1B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81495" pm="."><plain>During the heading stage, the leaves were almost gray-green in colour, and only a small number of leaves showed marginal albinism (Fig. 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81496" pm="."><plain>Thus, the older the leaves, the smaller the area of albinism (Fig. 1A–C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81497" pm="."><plain>These observations demonstrated that the phenotype of val1 was displayed in a growth stage-dependent manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81498" pm="."><plain>In addition, in accordance with the albino leaf phenotype of the val1 mutant, the leaf chlorophyll content was significantly reduced in the mutant compared with the WT at the seedling and tiller stages (Fig. 1D, E), and slightly reduced at the mature stage (Fig. 1F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81499" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these observations over the full life cycle demonstrated that val1 was a dynamic green-revertible albino mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81500" pm="."><plain>We also examined the expression of the phenotypes and the leaf pigment contents in relation to temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81501" pm="."><plain>The val1 mutant always displayed albino leaves with lower pigment contents than those of the WT at temperatures of 20 °C (C20), 30 °C (C30), and under an alternate light/dark cycle (12 h light at 30 °C/12 h dark at 20 °C; L30 °C/D20 °C) (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81502" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81503" pm="."><plain>These results indicated that the albino-leaf phenotype of val1 in the early seedling stage was not affected by temperature, and we therefore determined that val1 was a temperature-insensitive, green-revertible albino mutant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81504" pm="."><plain>Phenotypic characteristics of the wild-type (WT) and the val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81505" pm="."><plain>(A–C) Phenotypes of the WT and val1 at the seedling stage (A), tiller stage (B), and heading stage (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81506" pm="."><plain>Close-up images of the leaves of the WT and val1 are shown at top-right. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81507" pm="."><plain>(D–F) Chlorophyll content of the leaves of the WT and val1 at the seedling stage (D), tiller stage (E), and heading stage (F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81508" pm="."><plain>(G) Leaf blade widths of the WT and val1 plants for the 1st–14th leaves produced across the total growth period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81509" pm="."><plain>(H) Transverse sections of the seventh leaf blade of the WT and val1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81510" pm="."><plain>Yellow triangles indicate small vascular bundles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81511" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81512" pm="."><plain>(I–L) Comparisons of the number of small vascular bundles (SV) (I), the distance between the small vascular bundles (J), and the number of cells (K) and the size of cells (L) between the small vascular bundles in the WT and val1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81513" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25001"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="81514" pm="."><plain>The leaf width in val1 was reduced significantly compared with the WT, and the narrow-leaf phenotype was increasingly pronounced over the course of plant development (Fig. 1A–C, G). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81515" pm="."><plain>To examine the basis for the narrow-leaf phenotype, histological analysis of transverse sections of the leaf blade showed that, compared with the WT, the number of small vascular bundles was reduced by 39.3% (Fig. 1H, I), and the distance between the small vascular bundles was reduced by 33.2% (Fig. 1H, J). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81516" pm="."><plain>The number of cells between the small vascular bundles was reduced by 24.1% (Fig. 1H, K), but the size of the cells was similar to that of the WT (Fig. 1H, L). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81517" pm="."><plain>These results indicated that the reduced leaf width may have been caused by the reduced number of vascular bundles and the reduced number of cells between the small vascular bundles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81518" pm="."><plain>In addition, val1 plants also displayed dwarfism and smaller spikelets compared with the WT (Fig. 1A–C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s20"><title><text><SENT sid="81519" pm="."><plain>Molecular cloning and identification of VAL1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81520" pm="."><plain>The VAL1 gene was previously mapped to a region of about 171 kb on chromosome 8 (Ma, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81521" pm="."><plain>In the current study, the location of VAL1 was narrowed to within a physical distance of 29.69 kb between the simple sequence repeat marker SSR8-1 and the insertion/deletion marker ID30. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81522" pm="."><plain>This interval includes four annotated genes (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gramene.org/">http://www.gramene.org/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81523" pm="."><plain>Sequencing analysis identified a single-nucleotide substitution from T to C within the LOC_Os08g09210 gene, causing an amino acid mutation of Phe-358 to Ser-358 in the val1 mutant (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81524" pm="."><plain>To confirm whether the mutation of LOC_Os08g09210 resulted in the mutant phenotype, we performed a complementation experiment by transforming a 7198-bp WT DNA fragment containing LOC_Os08g09210 into the val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81525" pm="."><plain>The mutant phenotype was completely rescued in the transgenic plants (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81526" pm="."><plain>The contents of chlorophyll and carotenoids and the photosynthetic rate in the transgenic plants were almost identical to those of the WT (Fig. 2C, E–H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81527" pm="."><plain>In addition, the chloroplast ultrastructure as observed by TEM was similar to that of the WT, displaying well-developed lamellar structures and equipped with normal thylakoid membranes and stacked grana (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81528" pm="."><plain>We performed RNAi to silence VAL1 in the WT plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81529" pm="."><plain>In the transgenic plants, the quantity of VAL1 transcripts was greatly reduced (Fig. 2D), and a dynamic green phenotype similar to that of the val1 mutant was observed (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81530" pm="."><plain>The contents of chlorophyll and carotenoids and the photosynthetic rate in the transgenic plants were significantly reduced compared with the WT (Fig. 2C, E–H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81531" pm="."><plain>Observation by TEM showed that the mesophyll cells were almost empty and lacked obvious intact organelles, and the chloroplasts were completely degraded, similar to those of val1 (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81532" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results confirmed that LOC_Os08g09210 corresponded to the VAL1 gene. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81533" pm="."><plain>Molecular identity of VAL1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81534" pm="."><plain>(A) Map-based cloning of the VAL1 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81535" pm="."><plain>(B) Phenotypes of the wild-type (WT), complemented (-C), val1, and VAL1-RNAi plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81536" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 5 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81537" pm="."><plain>(C) Chlorophyll contents of the leaves of the WT, complemented, and VAL1-RNAi plants at the tiller stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81538" pm="."><plain>(D) Expression analysis of VAL1 in the leaves of the WT and the three RNAi lines by qRT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81539" pm="."><plain>(E–H) Photosynthetic rate (E), stomatal conductance (F), intercellular CO2 concentration (G), and transpiration rate (H) of the WT, complemented, and VAL1-RNAi plants at the heading stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81540" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s21"><title><text><SENT sid="81541" pm="."><plain>Expression pattern of VAL1 and subcellular localisation of the VAL1 protein </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81542" pm="."><plain>To determine the expression pattern of VAL1, quantitative reverse transcription-PCR (qRT-PCR) analysis was performed. VAL1 was expressed in a variety of tissues, including the roots, stems, leaves, leaf sheaths, and panicles, with higher levels in the leaves (with higher chlorophyll content) than in the other tissues examined (Fig. 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81543" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have shown that the leaves of rice emerge from the sheath in an ordered manner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81544" pm="."><plain>Generally, when the third leaf has fully emerged from the sheath, the shoot includes the fourth to seventh immature leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81545" pm="."><plain>The leaf cells in the upper half of the third leaf (L3U) and basal (lower) half of the third leaf (L3L) contain mature chloroplasts, whereas those in the shoot base (SB) and fourth leaf above the shoot base (L4) contain proplastids and early-developing immature chloroplasts (Fig. 3B; Yoo et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81546" pm="."><plain>In our present study, qRT-PCR analysis showed that VAL1 was universally expressed in the SB, L4, L2, L3L, and L3U samples, with the highest levels detected in L3L (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81547" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns of VAL1 and subcellular localization of the VAL1 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81548" pm="."><plain>(A) Expression pattern of VAL1 in different tissues as indicated by real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81549" pm="."><plain>(B, C) Expression patterns of VAL1 in the leaf as indicated by real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81550" pm="."><plain>(D) Expression patterns of VAL1 by in situ hybridization. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81551" pm="."><plain>Black arrows indicate the procambium cells and vascular bundles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81552" pm="."><plain>Red arrows indicate the margin of the P3 primordium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81553" pm="."><plain>(E) Analysis of the subcellular localization of the VAL1 protein in rice protoplasts. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81554" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 50 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81555" pm="."><plain>SB, shoot base; L4, fourth leaf; L2, second leaf; L3L, basal half of the third leaf; L3U, upper half of the third leaf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81556" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25003"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="81557" pm="."><plain>For a more detailed analysis of the expression pattern of VAL1, transverse and longitudinal sections of the shoot apical meristem (SAM) were examined for VAL1 signals by in situ hybridization (Fig. 3D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81558" pm="."><plain>First, strong signals were observed in the SAM (Fig. 3D1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81559" pm="."><plain>Next, scattered strong signals were detected in the P2 primordia (Fig. 3D2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81560" pm="."><plain>In the P3 primordia, VAL1 signals were concentrated at the margin of the P3 primordium and the procambium cells (Fig. 3D2), which may predict the sites of differentiation of procambium cells from fundamental cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81561" pm="."><plain>In the P4 primordia, VAL1 signals were primarily restricted to the vascular bundles, with no preference for the xylem or phloem (Fig. 3D3, D4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81562" pm="."><plain>These results suggested that VAL1 may be involved in leaf development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81563" pm="."><plain>To examine the subcellular localization of the VAL1 protein, constructs producing the GFP and the GFP-VAL1 ORF fusion protein were transiently expressed in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81564" pm="."><plain>In cells that expressed GFP alone, green fluorescence was detected consistently throughout the cell except in the vacuole in protoplasts, and the GFP-VAL1 ORF fusion protein was localized in the chloroplast (Fig. 3E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81565" pm="."><plain>These results indicated that VAL1 was localized in the chloroplast. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s22"><title><text><SENT sid="81566" pm="."><plain>VAL1 encodes a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81567" pm="."><plain>A blastp analysis was performed on the NCBI protein database using the VAL1 protein sequence. VAL1 encodes a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase (PurD), which belongs to the ATP-grasp superfamily. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81568" pm="."><plain>Alignment of amino acid sequences of VAL1 and other phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase family members revealed that the sequences showed a high degree of homology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81569" pm="."><plain>The protein structure was analysed using the PSIPRED protein prediction database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/">http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81570" pm="."><plain>VAL1 was predicted to include three conserved domains, designated GARS_N, GARS_A, and GRAS_C, of which the GARS_A domain contained an ATP-binding site. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81571" pm="."><plain>In addition, it was predicted by ChloroP (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ChloroP/</ext-link>) that VAL1 contained a chloroplast transit peptide at the N-terminus (amino acid residues 1–68; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81572" pm="."><plain>S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81573" pm="."><plain>The phylogenetic tree indicated that VAL1 is widely present in many photosynthetic organisms (Fig. 4), including lower aquatic algae, terrestrial ferns, gymnosperms, and angiosperms, and it showed a high degree of homology, which suggests that VAL1 in rice may be descended from VAL1 of algae. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81574" pm="."><plain>In addition, the rice genome contains a VAL1 homolog designated LOC_Os12g09540, which is also predicted to encode a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase. LOC_Os12g09540 was also expressed in leaves, with the highest levels detected in L3U (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81575" pm="."><plain>S3A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81576" pm="."><plain>However, LOC_Os12g09540 and VAL1 do not belong to the same evolutionary lineage, which indicates a certain degree of differentiation in molecular function between the homologs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81577" pm="."><plain>Phylogenetic tree for the VAL1 protein. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81578" pm="."><plain>The tree was constructed using the maximum-likelihood method based on the Jones–Taylor–Thornton matrix-based model. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81579" pm="."><plain>Bootstrap values calculated from 500 replicates are given at the branch nodes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81580" pm="."><plain>The VAL1 protein is highlighted in red. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s23"><title><text><SENT sid="81581" pm="."><plain>Complementation of the nucleotide in vitro partially restores the phenotype </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81582" pm="."><plain>VAL1 encodes a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase, which is the second enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81583" pm="."><plain>S4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81584" pm="."><plain>To confirm its involvement in the pathway, the transcriptomic profiles of seedlings of val1 and WT grown under normal conditions were characterized by RNA-seq with two biological replicates for each genotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81585" pm="."><plain>The Pearson correlation coefficient between the two replicates was greater than 0.95. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81586" pm="."><plain>Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) was used to examine the data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81587" pm="."><plain>This is a statistical approach that allows identification of over-represented gene sets among differentially up- or down-regulated genes of a transcriptomic analysis (Subramanian et al., 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81588" pm="."><plain>There was significant enrichment in the over-representation of genes associated with the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway (Fig. 5A, Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81589" pm="."><plain>S4B), which indicated that the mutation of VAL1 caused disruption of de novo purine biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81590" pm="."><plain>In addition, the contents of the de novo purine biosynthesis products AMP and GMP in val1 seedlings were lower than those of the WT (Fig. 5B), which further indicated that VAL1 was involved in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81591" pm="."><plain>The decreased AMP and GMP contents in the val1 mutant may influence plastid genome replication and division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81592" pm="."><plain>We therefore used qRT-PCR to examine the expression of SGR and rps12, which are single-copy genes in the plant nuclear and plastid genomes, as representatives of the copy numbers of nuclear and chloroplastic genomes, respectively (Sugimoto et al., 2007; Yoo et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81593" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of both SGR and rps12 were reduced in the val1 mutant (Fig. 5C), which indicated that nuclear and chloroplastic genome replication appeared to be arrested by limited AMP and GMP levels. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81594" pm="."><plain>Phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase (PurD) and de novo purine biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81595" pm="."><plain>(A) Gene set enrichment analysis of genes associated with the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81596" pm="."><plain>The green line indicates enrichment score calculated by gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81597" pm="."><plain>(B) AMP and GMP contents in the wild-type (WT) and val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81598" pm="."><plain>(C) Expression of rps12 and SGR in seedlings of the WT and val1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81599" pm="."><plain>(D) Leaf morphology of the WT and val1 mutant after growth in Murashige and Skoog liquid medium supplemented with various concentrations (0, 1, 5, or 10 mM) of AMP, GMP, or AMP and GMP together for 2 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81600" pm="."><plain>(E) Chlorophyll content of plants of the WT and val1 mutant shown in (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81601" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25005"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="81602" pm="."><plain>Next, we investigated whether the mutant phenotypes could be complemented biochemically by exogenous application of AMP and GMP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81603" pm="."><plain>Application of AMP, GMP, and AMP and GMP together partially restored the green colour of the val1 leaf (Fig. 5D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81604" pm="."><plain>Low concentrations (1 and 5 mM) of AMP, GMP, and AMP and GMP promoted accumulation of chlorophyll in WT leaves, whereas high concentrations (10 mM) repressed chlorophyll accumulation and inhibited plant growth (Fig. 5D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81605" pm="."><plain>In the val1 mutant, chlorophyll content was elevated with increasing concentrations of AMP, GMP, and AMP and GMP (Fig. 5E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81606" pm="."><plain>Thus, the applications partially restored the accumulation of chlorophyll in the val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81607" pm="."><plain>In addition, low concentrations (10 and 100 nM) of the synthetic cytokinin benzylaminopurine (6-BA) did not rescue the mutant phenotype, and a high concentration of 6-BA (1000 nM) severely inhibited plant growth (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81608" pm="."><plain>S5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s24"><title><text><SENT sid="81609" pm="."><plain>VAL1 affects chloroplast development and pigment metabolism </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81610" pm="."><plain>Previous research has indicated that chloroplast development in the albino portion of the leaf in val1 plants is severely defective (Ma, 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81611" pm="."><plain>Thus, expression analysis of genes associated with chloroplast development and photosynthesis were compared between WT and val1 plants by qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81612" pm="."><plain>The transcript levels of rbcL and RbcS (encoding the large and small subunit of Rubisco, respectively), psaA, psaB, psaC, and psbA, psbB, psbC (encoding two reaction-centre polypeptides of PSI and PSII, respectively), atpA and atpB (encoding the alpha- and beta-subunits of chloroplast ATP synthase, respectively), petB and petC (encoding the cytochrome b6 subunit and the Rieske FeS centre of cytochrome b6f complex, respectively) were significantly reduced in the val1 mutant compared with the WT (Fig. 6A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81613" pm="."><plain>The protein accumulation levels of RbcL, PsaA, PsbA, and atpA were consistent with the transcript levels (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81614" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results indicated that the VAL1 mutation affected the expression of genes associated with chloroplast development and photosynthesis, which resulted in defective chloroplast development. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81615" pm="."><plain>Expression of genes associated with chloroplast development, photosynthesis, and pigment metabolism in the wild-type (WT) and val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81616" pm="."><plain>(A) Expression analysis of genes associated with chloroplast development and photosynthesis in the WT and val1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81617" pm="."><plain>(B) Western blots of proteins associated with chloroplast development and photosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81618" pm="."><plain>Actin was used as an internal control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81619" pm="."><plain>(C) Expression analysis of genes associated with pigment metabolism in the WT and val1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81620" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25006"/></fig><p><text><SENT sid="81621" pm="."><plain>Given that the val1 mutant displayed reduced chlorophyll and carotenoid contents, the expression levels of pigment metabolism-related genes were compared between WT and val1 plants by qRT-PCR analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81622" pm="."><plain>The transcript levels of pigment metabolism-related genes were reduced in the val1 mutant compared with those of the WT to different degrees. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81623" pm="."><plain>For example, the transcript levels of the chlorophyll synthesis pathway gene CAO and the carotenoid synthesis pathway genes PSY1, PSY2, and PSY3 were all significantly reduced in the val1 mutant compared with the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81624" pm="."><plain>The other genes involved in the synthesis of chlorophyll and carotenoids, such as ChlD, ChlI, ChlM, YGL1, DVR, HEMA, HEMD, and PDS were also slightly reduced in the val1 mutant compared with the WT (Fig. 6C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81625" pm="."><plain>In the heading stage, the expression of these genes related to chloroplast development, photosynthesis, and pigment metabolism were not significantly reduced in the val1 mutant compared with the WT (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81626" pm="."><plain>S6A, B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81627" pm="."><plain>To obtain further insights into the function of VAL1, the transcriptomic profiles of seedings of val1 and the WT were characterized. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81628" pm="."><plain>A total of 3683 DEGs between val1 and WT were identified, including 1813 up- and 1870 down-regulated DEGs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81629" pm="."><plain>GO enrichment analysis showed that the expression of genes involved in chloroplast development, photosynthesis, and pigment biosynthesis were changed dramatically. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81630" pm="."><plain>For chloroplast development and photosynthesis a total of 34 DEGs were identified, comprising 32 down- and two up-regulated genes; for example, the expression of rbcL, psaG,and psbR showed decreases of 53.6, 74.1, and 82.6%, respectively, in val1 (Supplementary Table S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81631" pm="."><plain>For pigment biosynthesis a total of 25 DEGs were identified, comprising 16 down- and nine up-regulated genes; for example, the expression of PORA and CAO1 showed decreases of 85.9% and 47.5%, respectively, in val1 (Supplementary Table S3). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s25"><title><text><SENT sid="81632" pm="."><plain>VAL1 is involved in cell division in leaves </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81633" pm="."><plain>Since the number of vascular bundles and cells between the small vascular bundles was significantly reduced in the narrow leaves of val1, we speculated that this may have been caused by impaired cell proliferation of leaf primordia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81634" pm="."><plain>To text this hypothesis, flow cytometry was used to monitor the amount of DNA in the nuclear suspensions in the shoot apex of WT and val1 plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81635" pm="."><plain>The results revealed a significant increase in the number of cells in the S phase and decreases in the G2/M phases of the cell cycle, implying that the cell cycle was delayed at the S phase (Fig. 7A–C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81636" pm="."><plain>The expression patterns of histone H4 were characterized by in situ hybridization and it was found to be relatively evenly expressed throughout the P1 leaf primordium in the WT, whereas the frequency of cells that expressed histone H4 was reduced by 29.2% in the val1 mutant (Fig. 7D, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81637" pm="."><plain>In the P2 leaf primordium, histone H4 was mainly expressed at the margins of the primordium, and the frequency of cells that expressed histone H4 was reduced by 27.7% in the val1 mutant compared with the WT (Fig. 7D, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81638" pm="."><plain>These results confirmed that the decreased number of cells was caused by impaired cell proliferation during the early development of primordia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81639" pm="."><plain>Given that de novo purine synthesis leads to the synthesis of cytokinins, we measured the contents of isopentenyladenine (iP) and trans-zeatin (tZA) in WT and val1 seedlings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81640" pm="."><plain>The content of iP was reduced by 67.9%, whereas that of tZA was increased slightly in the val1 mutant compared with the WT (Fig. 7F). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81641" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results supported the contention that the decreased number of cells was caused by impaired cell proliferation, which may have been due to the reduced content of cytokinins during the early development of leaf primordia in the val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F7" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7.
</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81642" pm="."><plain>Involvement of VAL1 in cell division in leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81643" pm="."><plain>(A, B) Flow cytometry measurements of nuclei from the shoot apex in 10-d-old wild-type (WT) (A) and val1 plants (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81644" pm="."><plain>(C) Quantification of the DNA profiles of WT and val1 plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81645" pm="."><plain>(D) Expression of histone H4 in cross-sections of the shoot apical meristems in the WT and val1 at the tiller stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81646" pm="."><plain>Black and red lines represent P1 and P2 primordia, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81647" pm="."><plain>Scale bars are 100 µm. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81648" pm="."><plain>(E) Frequency of histone H4-expressing cells in the leaf primordia indicated by red circles in (D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81649" pm="."><plain>P1, P1 promordium; P2, P2 promordium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81650" pm="."><plain>(F) Contents of isopentenyladenine and trans-zeatin in the WT and val1 mutant seedlings. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81651" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25007"/></fig></sec><sec id="s26"><title><text><SENT sid="81652" pm="."><plain>Application value of VAL1 in rice breeding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81653" pm="."><plain>The shade of the leaf colour in rice is determined by the content of chlorophyll. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81654" pm="."><plain>Chlorophyll is the main pigment of plants for photosynthesis and plays a key role in the absorption, transmission, and conversion of light energy (Fromme et al., 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81655" pm="."><plain>To assess the application value of VAL1 in rice breeding, we expressed VAL1 under the control of the ubiquitin promoter in the WT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81656" pm="."><plain>In the tillering stage, the green leaf colour was slightly darker in transgenic plants compared with the WT (Fig. 8A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81657" pm="."><plain>The chlorophyll and carotenoid contents were significantly increased (Fig. 8C), and the photosynthetic rate was increased in transgenic plants compared with the WT (Fig. 8 D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81658" pm="."><plain>The qRT-PCR results showed that the expression level of VAL1 was significantly increased in transgenic plants compared with the WT (Fig. 8B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81659" pm="."><plain>The expression levels of photosynthesis-associated genes rbcL, RbcS, psaA, psbA, petA, petG, atpA, and LhcpII, were significantly increased to different degrees in transgenic plants compared with the WT (Fig. 8H). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81660" pm="."><plain>These results indicated that VAL1 played an important role in regulation of plant photosynthesis by modulating the expression of related genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81661" pm="."><plain>Thus, plants with overexpressed VAL1 showed a higher photosynthetic ability, and could hence they could be utilized in breeding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F8" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8.</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81662" pm="."><plain>Application value of VAL1 in rice breeding. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81663" pm="."><plain>(A) Phenotypes of the wild-type (WT) and VAL1-overexpressing plants in the tiller stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81664" pm="."><plain>(B) Expression analysis of VAL1 in the leaf of the WT and three VAL1-overexpressing lines by real-time PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81665" pm="."><plain>(C) Chlorophyll content of the leaf of the WT and VAL1-overexpressing plants in the tiller stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81666" pm="."><plain>(D–G) Photosynthetic rate (D), stomatal conductance (E), intercellular CO2 concentration (F), and transpiration rate (G) of the WT and VAL1-overexpressing plants at the heading stage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81667" pm="."><plain>(H) Expression analysis of genes associated with photosynthesis in the WT and VAL1-overexpressing plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81668" pm="."><plain>Data are means (±SD) of three biological replicates. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ery25008"/></fig></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s27"><title><text><SENT sid="81669" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81670" pm="."><plain>In our present study, VAL1 was shown to encode a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase, the second enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81671" pm="."><plain>Subcellular localization indicated that the VAL1 protein was localized in the chloroplast (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81672" pm="."><plain>VAL1 is a novel regulator that regulates chloroplast development, pigment metabolism, and cell division, and thereby affects the development of leaf colour and blade width in rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81673" pm="."><plain>Many genes associated with leaf colour have been cloned in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81674" pm="."><plain>Metabolic pathways associated with chlorophyll synthesis and degradation, and chloroplast development have been elucidated, and mutation of genes involved in these metabolic pathways leads to changes in leaf colour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81675" pm="."><plain>For example, mutations in the genes OsCHlH (Jung et al., 2003), OsCHlD and OsCHlI (Zhang et al., 2015), OsDVR (Wang et al., 2010), OsGluRs (Liu et al., 2007), YGL1 (Wu et al., 2007), OsCAO1 and OsCAO2 (Lee et al., 2005; Yang et al., 2016), OsPPR1 (Gothandam et al., 2005), YSA (Su et al., 2012), SGR (Jiang et al., 2007), NYC1 (Kusaba et al., 2007), V1 (Kusumi et al., 2011), V2 (Sugimoto et al., 2004), and V3 and st1 (Yoo et al., 2009) produce different types of leaf-colour mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81676" pm="."><plain>In the val1 mutant, the expression levels of chlorophyll- and photosynthesis-associated genes were significantly reduced, and chloroplast development was defective (Figs 2D, 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81677" pm="."><plain>Thus, similar to the above-mentioned leaf-colour mutants, the green-revertible albino phenotype of the val1 mutant was caused by disruption of chlorophyll metabolism and chloroplast development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81678" pm="."><plain>Previous research has indicated that the phenotypes of the majority of green-revertible albino leaf-colour mutants are regulated by temperature and development, or by a combination of the two. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81679" pm="."><plain>For example, the temperature-sensitive seedling-colour mutant tsc-1 displays a white, light-yellow, and normal green leaf when grown at 23.1 °C, 26.1 °C, and 30.1 °C, respectively (Dong et al., 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81680" pm="."><plain>In contrast, the albino leaf phenotype of the val1 mutant at the early seedling stage was not affected by temperature, which indicated that val1 is a temperature-insensitive mutant (Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81681" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81682" pm="."><plain>Developmentally regulated mutants, such as the ysa mutant, develop albino leaves before the three-leaf (L3) stage and gradually turn green and recover to the normal green leaf colour at the six-leaf stage (Su et al., 2012). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81683" pm="."><plain>The temperature-conditional and developmentally-regulated mutants v3 and st1 largely exhibit a normal green-leaf phenotype up to the L3 stage and develop chlorotic leaves until the maximum tiller stage, but recover to develop mostly green leaves after heading. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81684" pm="."><plain>At temperatures of 20 °C or 30 °C, these mutants produce chlorotic leaves, whereas under an alternate light/dark cycle (12 h light at 30 °C/12 h dark at 20 °C), these mutants develop leaves of an almost normal green colour (Yoo et al., 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81685" pm="."><plain>In our present study, the val1 mutant initially produced albino new leaves, but these subsequently turned green and only a small number of leaves showed marginal albinism at later developmental stages (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81686" pm="."><plain>The results indicated that val1 is a novel green-revertible albino mutant, for which the phenotype is regulated by development and is independent of temperature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81687" pm="."><plain>Nucleotide metabolism is a crucial process in all living organisms (Smith and Atkins, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81688" pm="."><plain>Although the de novo biosynthesis of purine nucleotides is essential for plant growth and development, little information is available on the molecular mechanism of the purine biosynthesis pathway in plants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81689" pm="."><plain>The Arabidopsis gene CIA1 encodes a Gln phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate amidotransferase 2 (ATase2), which is one of three ATase isozymes responsible for the first step of de novo purine biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81690" pm="."><plain>The cia1 mutant displays normal green cotyledons, together with small and albino/pale-green mosaic leaves that contain slightly smaller cells but only half the cell number of the WT, which indicates that de novo purine biosynthesis is important for chloroplast biogenesis and cell division (Hung et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81691" pm="."><plain>Our present study showed that VAL1 encodes a phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase, the second enzyme in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81692" pm="."><plain>In the val1 mutant, chloroplast development was severely defective and chlorophyll metabolism was disrupted, which resulted in the dynamic green-revertible albino leaf phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81693" pm="."><plain>Taken together, the findings indicated that VAL1 is a crucial enzyme that regulates the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway, which may be involved in the development of leaf colour in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81694" pm="."><plain>In addition, the val1 mutant developed narrow leaves, caused by diminished cell division owing to the reduced content of cytokinins in the leaf (Fig. 7), and led to a reduced number of vascular bundles and fewer cells between the small vascular bundles (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81695" pm="."><plain>Thus, the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway may also be involved in the process of cell division in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81696" pm="."><plain>The location of the pathway within plant cells is presently still in dispute, although the subcellular localization of multiple enzymes provides convincing evidence (Smith and Atkins, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81697" pm="."><plain>Our current study showed that VAL1 contained a chloroplast transit peptide and was localized in the chloroplast (Fig. 3), which indicated that at least part of the de novo purine biosynthesis occurs in the chloroplasts in rice. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81698" pm="."><plain>It is worth considering why the mutation of VAL1 caused a dynamic green-revertible albino phenotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81699" pm="."><plain>One hypothesis is that VAL1 paralogs might perform the same or similar functions at later growth stages, and eventually offset the loss caused by mutation in the VAL1 gene. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81700" pm="."><plain>This explanation was confirmed by phylogenetic analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81701" pm="."><plain>There was one VAL1-like gene, LOC_Os12g09540, which showed high similarity to VAL1 at the amino acid level (Fig. 4; Supplementary Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81702" pm="."><plain>S2), and LOC_Os12g09540 was also highly expressed in leaves, with the highest levels detected in L3U (Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81703" pm="."><plain>S3A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81704" pm="."><plain>One reasonable interpretation is that there is a threshold level of purine nucleotides that needs to be met for normal chloroplast biogenesis and chlorophyll metabolism. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81705" pm="."><plain>Under rapid growth conditions, purine nucleotides are channelled into cell division, the purine nucleotide level in the mutant drops below the threshold, and chloroplasts fail to develop normally, causing the mutant to display albino leaves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81706" pm="."><plain>When the division and growth rate of leaf cells are slower, purine nucleotides have time to accumulate in the mutant cells, eventually reaching the threshold level, and the mutant leaves subsequently turn green in the later stages. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81707" pm="."><plain>In val1 seedlings, the contents of the de novo purine biosynthesis products adenine nucleotide (AMP) and guanine nucleotide (GMP) were lower than those of the WT seedlings (Fig. 5B), which indicated that the purine nucleotide level in the mutant dropped below the threshold. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81708" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, in the val1 mutant, application of AMP, GMP, and AMP and GMP together partially restored the accumulation of chlorophyll in the val1 mutant (Fig. 5D, E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81709" pm="."><plain>Taken together, these results indicated that the dynamic green-revertible albino process may be regulated by the threshold level of purine nucleotides. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81710" pm="."><plain>In addition, purine nucleotides are maintained in intracellular pools through a combination of de novo synthesis and salvage pathways (Zrenner et al., 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81711" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have demonstrated that the strong demand for nucleotides in growing and dividing cells is met by de novo synthesis, whereas non-growing cells may be able to maintain their pools of nucleotides by salvaging (Ashihara and Crozier, 1999; Zrenner et al., 2006). VAL1 achieved the highest expression levels in the WT leaves at the L3 stage, and accumulated more in L3L but decreased dramatically in L3U (Fig. 3C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81712" pm="."><plain>These observations suggested that VAL1 might play an important role at the early leaf development stage, with a relatively minor role in the mature leaf. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81713" pm="."><plain>Thus, another reasonable interpretation is that the de novo purine biosynthesis process regulates chloroplast development and chlorophyll metabolism at the early leaf development stage, and the salvage pathway regulates chloroplast development and chlorophyll metabolism in mature leaves. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s28"><title><text><SENT sid="81714" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81715" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data are available at JXB online. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81716" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81717" pm="."><plain>S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81718" pm="."><plain>The val1 mutant is a temperature-insensitive green-revertible albino mutant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81719" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81720" pm="."><plain>S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81721" pm="."><plain>Protein sequence alignment of VAL1. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81722" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81723" pm="."><plain>S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81724" pm="."><plain>Expression patterns of LOC_Os12g09540. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81725" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81726" pm="."><plain>S4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81727" pm="."><plain>VAL1 participates in the de novo purine biosynthesis pathway. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81728" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81729" pm="."><plain>S5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81730" pm="."><plain>Exogenous application of 6-BA to the wild-type and val1 mutant. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81731" pm="."><plain>Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81732" pm="."><plain>S6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81733" pm="."><plain>Expression of genes associated with chloroplast development, photosynthesis, and pigment metabolism in the wild-type and val1 mutant in the heading stage. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81734" pm="."><plain>Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81735" pm="."><plain>Primers used in the study. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81736" pm="."><plain>Table S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81737" pm="."><plain>DEGs annotated within chloroplast development and photosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="81738" pm="."><plain>Table S3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81739" pm="."><plain>DEGs annotated within pigment biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="81740" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Figures S1-S6 and Tables S1-S3</label><media xlink:href="ery250_suppl_supplementary_figs-s1-s6_tables-s1-s3.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="81741" pm="."><plain>Click here for additional data file. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="81742" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by the National Key Research and Development Project (2017YFD0100201), and the Project of Chongqing Science &amp; Technology Commission Grants CSTCCXLJRC201713 and CSTC2016SHMS-ZTZX0017. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><text><SENT sid="81743" pm="."><plain> AshiharaH, CrozierA 1999 Biosynthesis and metabolism of caffeine and related purine alkaloids in plants. Advances in Botanical Research30, 117–205. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><text><SENT sid="81744" pm="."><plain> BerthoméR, ThomassetM, MaeneM, BourgeoisN, FrogerN, BudarF 2008 pur4 mutations are lethal to the male, but not the female, gametophyte and affect sporophyte development in Arabidopsis. Plant Physiology147, 650–660.18441219 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><text><SENT sid="81745" pm="."><plain> DengXJ, ZhangHQ, WangY, HeF, LiuJL, XiaoX, ShuZF, LiW, WangGH, WangGL 2014 Mapped clone and functional analysis of leaf-color gene Ygl7 in a rice hybrid (Oryza sativa L. ssp. indica). PLoS ONE9, e99564.24932524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><text><SENT sid="81746" pm="."><plain> DongH, FeiGL, WuCY, et al 2013 A rice virescent-yellow leaf mutant reveals new insights into the role and assembly of plastid caseinolytic protease in higher plants. Plant Physiology162, 1867–1880.23803583 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><text><SENT sid="81747" pm="."><plain> DongYJ, DongWQ, ShiSY, JinQS 2001 Identification and genetic analysis of a thermo-sensitive seedling-colour mutant in rice (Oryza sativa L.). Breeding Science51, 1–4. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><text><SENT sid="81748" pm="."><plain> DuP, LingYH, SangXC, ZhaoFM, XieR, YangZL, HeGH 2009 Gene mapping related to yellow green leaf in a mutant line in rice (Oryza sadva L.). Genes &amp; Genomics31, 165–171. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><text><SENT sid="81749" pm="."><plain> FrommeP, MelkozernovA, JordanP, KraussN 2003 Structure and function of photosystem I: interaction with its soluble electron carriers and external antenna systems. FEBS Letters555, 40–44.14630316 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><text><SENT sid="81750" pm="."><plain> GothandamKM, KimES, ChoH, ChungYY 2005 OsPPR1, a pentatricopeptide repeat protein of rice is essential for the chloroplast biogenesis. Plant Molecular Biology58, 421–433.16021404 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><text><SENT sid="81751" pm="."><plain> HajirezaeiMR, BörnkeF, PeiskerM, TakahataY, LerchlJ, KirakosyanA, SonnewaldU 2003 Decreased sucrose content triggers starch breakdown and respiration in stored potato tubers (Solanum tuberosum). Journal of Experimental Botany54, 477–488.12508058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><text><SENT sid="81752" pm="."><plain> HungWF, ChenLJ, BoldtR, SunCW, LiHM 2004 Characterization of Arabidopsis glutamine phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate amidotransferase-deficient mutants. Plant Physiology135, 1314–1323.15266056 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><text><SENT sid="81753" pm="."><plain> JiangH, LiM, LiangN, et al 2007 Molecular cloning and function analysis of the stay green gene in rice. The Plant Journal52, 197–209.17714430 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><text><SENT sid="81754" pm="."><plain> JungKH, HurJ, RyuCH, ChoiY, ChungYY, MiyaoA, HirochikaH, AnG 2003 Characterization of a rice chlorophyll-deficient mutant using the T-DNA gene-trap system. Plant &amp; Cell Physiology44, 463–472.12773632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><text><SENT sid="81755" pm="."><plain> KimJE, MyongK, ShimWB, YunSH, LeeYW 2007 Functional characterization of acetylglutamate synthase and phosphoribosylamine-glycine ligase genes in Gibberella zeae. Current Genetics51, 99–108.17146619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><text><SENT sid="81756" pm="."><plain> KusabaM, ItoH, MoritaR, et al 2007 Rice NON-YELLOW COLORING1 is involved in light-harvesting complex II and grana degradation during leaf senescence. The Plant Cell19, 1362–1375.17416733 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><text><SENT sid="81757" pm="."><plain> KusumiK, SakataC, NakamuraT, KawasakiS, YoshimuraA, IbaK 2011 A plastid protein NUS1 is essential for build-up of the genetic system for early chloroplast development under cold stress conditions. The Plant Journal68, 1039–1050.21981410 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><text><SENT sid="81758" pm="."><plain> LeeS, KimJH, YooES, LeeCH, HirochikaH, AnG 2005 Differential regulation of chlorophyll a oxygenase genes in rice. Plant Molecular Biology57, 805–818.15952067 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><text><SENT sid="81759" pm="."><plain> LichtenthalerHK 1987 Chlorophylls and carotenoids – pigments of photosynthetic biomembranes. Methods in Enzymology148, 350–382. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><text><SENT sid="81760" pm="."><plain> LiuW, FuY, HuG, SiH, ZhuL, WuC, SunZ 2007 Identification and fine mapping of a thermo-sensitive chlorophyll deficient mutant in rice (Oryza sativa L.). Planta226, 785–795.17541632 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0090"><text><SENT sid="81761" pm="."><plain> Ma JRen D, Wu GZhu X, Ma L, Ling YSang X, He G 2014 Genetic analysis and gene mapping of a marginal albino leaf mutant mal in rice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81762" pm="."><plain>The Crop Journal40, 591–599. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><text><SENT sid="81763" pm="."><plain> MaL, SangX, ZhangT, et al 2017 ABNORMAL VASCULAR BUNDLES regulates cell proliferation and procambium cell establishment during aerial organ development in rice. New Phytologist213, 275–286.27545518 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><text><SENT sid="81764" pm="."><plain> ParkYJ, SongES, KimYT, NohTH, KangHW, LeeBM 2007 Analysis of virulence and growth of a purine auxotrophic mutant of Xanthomonas oryzae pathovar oryzae. FEMS Microbiology Letters276, 55–59.17888004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><text><SENT sid="81765" pm="."><plain> RenD, YuH, RaoY, et al 2018 ‘Two-floret spikelet’ as a novel resource has the potential to increase rice yield. Plant Biotechnology Journal16, 351–353.29024337 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><text><SENT sid="81766" pm="."><plain> SchnorrKM, NygaardP, LaloueM 1994 Molecular characterization of Arabidopsis thaliana cDNAs encoding three purine biosynthetic enzymes. The Plant Journal6, 113–121.7920700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><text><SENT sid="81767" pm="."><plain> SmithPM, AtkinsCA 2002 Purine biosynthesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81768" pm="."><plain>Big in cell division, even bigger in nitrogen assimilation. Plant Physiology128, 793–802.11891236 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><text><SENT sid="81769" pm="."><plain> SuN, HuML, WuDX, et al 2012 Disruption of a rice pentatricopeptide repeat protein causes a seedling-specific albino phenotype and its utilization to enhance seed purity in hybrid rice production. Plant Physiology159, 227–238.22430843 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><text><SENT sid="81770" pm="."><plain> SubramanianA, TamayoP, MoothaVK, et al 2005 Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA102, 15545–15550. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><text><SENT sid="81771" pm="."><plain> SugimotoH, KusumiK, NoguchiK, YanoM, YoshimuraA, IbaK 2007 The rice nuclear gene, VIRESCENT 2, is essential for chloroplast development and encodes a novel type of guanylate kinase targeted to plastids and mitochondria. The Plant Journal52, 512–527.17727616 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><text><SENT sid="81772" pm="."><plain> SugimotoH, KusumiK, TozawaY, YazakiJ, KishimotoN, KikuchiS, IbaK 2004 The virescent-2 mutation inhibits translation of plastid transcripts for the plastid genetic system at an early stage of chloroplast differentiation. Plant &amp; Cell Physiology45, 985–996.15356324 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><text><SENT sid="81773" pm="."><plain> TamuraK, PetersonD, PetersonN, StecherG, NeiM, KumarS 2011 MEGA5: molecular evolutionary genetics analysis using maximum likelihood, evolutionary distance, and maximum parsimony methods. Molecular Biology and Evolution28, 2731–2739.21546353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><text><SENT sid="81774" pm="."><plain> TruongQL, ChoY, BarateAK, KimS, WataraiM, HahnTW 2015 Mutation of purD and purF genes further attenuates Brucella abortus strain RB51. Microbial Pathogenesis79, 1–7.25546140 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><text><SENT sid="81775" pm="."><plain> WangP, GaoJ, WanC, ZhangF, XuZ, HuangX, SunX, DengX 2010 Divinyl chlorophyll(ide) a can be converted to monovinyl chlorophyll(ide) a by a divinyl reductase in rice. Plant Physiology153, 994–1003.20484022 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><text><SENT sid="81776" pm="."><plain> WangZ-W, LvJ, XieS-Z, et al 2017 OsSLA4 encodes a pentatricopeptide repeat protein essential for early chloroplast development and seedling growth in rice. Plant Growth Regulation84, 249–260. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><text><SENT sid="81777" pm="."><plain> WuZ, ZhangX, HeB, et al 2007 A chlorophyll-deficient rice mutant with impaired chlorophyllide esterification in chlorophyll biosynthesis. Plant Physiology145, 29–40.17535821 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><text><SENT sid="81778" pm="."><plain> YangY, XuJ, HuangL, et al 2016 PGL, encoding chlorophyllide a oxygenase 1, impacts leaf senescence and indirectly affects grain yield and quality in rice. Journal of Experimental Botany67, 1297–1310.26709310 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><text><SENT sid="81779" pm="."><plain> YooSC, ChoSH, SugimotoH, LiJ, KusumiK, KohHJ, IbaK, PaekNC 2009 Rice virescent3 and stripe1 encoding the large and small subunits of ribonucleotide reductase are required for chloroplast biogenesis during early leaf development. Plant Physiology150, 388–401.19297585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><text><SENT sid="81780" pm="."><plain> ZhangH, LiuLL, CaiMH, et al 2015 A point mutation of magnesium chelatase OsCHLI gene dampens the interaction between CHLI and CHLD subunits in rice. Plant Molecular Biology Reporter33, 1975–1987. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><text><SENT sid="81781" pm="."><plain> ZhangT, LiY, MaL, et al 2017 LATERAL FLORET 1 induced the three-florets spikelet in rice. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, USA114, 9984–9989. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><text><SENT sid="81782" pm="."><plain> ZrennerR, StittM, SonnewaldU, BoldtR 2006 Pyrimidine and purine biosynthesis and degradation in plants. Annual Review of Plant Biology57, 805–836. </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
