<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20031101//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Pathog</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plospath</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Pathogens</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1553-7366</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1553-7374</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2483930</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18688274</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">07-PLPA-RA-0602R5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Immunology/Immunity to Infections</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases/Protozoal Infections</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The Role of B-cells and IgM Antibodies in Parasitemia, Anemia, and VSG Switching in Trypanosoma brucei–Infected Mice </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">B-Cells and IgM in African Trypanosomiasis</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Magez</surname><given-names>Stefan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schwegmann</surname><given-names>Anita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Claes</surname><given-names>Filip</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Drennan</surname><given-names>Michael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>De Baetselier</surname><given-names>Patrick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brombacher</surname><given-names>Frank</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Division of Immunology, Institute for Infectious Diseases and Molecular Medicine (IIDMM), Health Science Faculty, University of Cape Town, and International Centre for Genetic Engineering and Biotechnology (ICGEB), Cape Town, South Africa</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Molecular and Cellular Recognition, VIB, Brussels, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Cellular and Molecular Immunology, Vrije Universiteit Brussel (VUB), Brussels, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Laboratory of Serology, Institute for Tropical Medicine “Prins Leopold”, Antwerpen, Belgium</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Black</surname><given-names>Samuel</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">University of Massachusetts Amherst, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>fbrombac@mweb.co.za</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Conceived and designed the experiments: SM RA FB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Performed the experiments: SM AS RA FC MD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Analyzed the data: SM AS RA FC MD FB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: SM PDB FB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Wrote the paper: SM AS PDB FB. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>8</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>8</day><month>8</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>8</issue><elocation-id>e1000122</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>4</day><month>9</month><year>2007</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Magez et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>African trypanosomes are extracellular parasitic protozoa, predominantly transmitted by the bite of the haematophagic tsetse fly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>The main mechanism considered to mediate parasitemia control in a mammalian host is the continuous interaction between antibodies and the parasite surface, covered by variant-specific surface glycoproteins. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Early experimental studies have shown that B-cell responses can be strongly protective but are limited by their VSG-specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>We have used B-cell (µMT) and IgM-deficient (IgM−/−) mice to investigate the role of B-cells and IgM antibodies in parasitemia control and the in vivo induction of trypanosomiasis-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>These infection studies revealed that that the initial setting of peak levels of parasitemia in Trypanosoma brucei–infected µMT and IgM−/− mice occurred independent of the presence of B-cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>However, B-cells helped to periodically reduce circulating parasites levels and were required for long term survival, while IgM antibodies played only a limited role in this process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Infection-associated anemia, hypothesized to be mediated by B-cell responses, was induced during infection in µMT mice as well as in IgM−/− mice, and as such occurred independently from the infection-induced host antibody response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Antigenic variation, the main immune evasion mechanism of African trypanosomes, occurred independently from host antibody responses against the parasite's ever-changing antigenic glycoprotein coat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Collectively, these results demonstrated that in murine experimental T. brucei trypanosomiasis, B-cells were crucial for periodic peak parasitemia clearance, whereas parasite-induced IgM antibodies played only a limited role in the outcome of the infection. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="summary"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Author Summary </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>African trypanosomiasis is a disease caused by different species of extracellular flagellated protozoan trypanosome parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomes have developed a mechanism of regular antigenic variation of their variant-specific surface glycoprotein (VSG) coat which allows chronic infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Replacement of this coat occurs at rapid regular time intervals, allowing the parasite to escape from an effective host antibody responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>So far, primary T-cell independent antibody responses have been described to constitute the main host defense mechanism, relying largely on IgM antibody induction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Using genetically engineered B lymphocyte- or IgM-deficient mouse strains, we show that lack of B-cells or IgM did not prevent infection-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>More importantly, we show that in the absence of IgM, parasitemia was controlled almost as well as in wild-type mice, with only slightly increased mortality. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>In addition, we show in vivo that antigenic variation is not affected by the lack of IgM. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s1"><title><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>African trypanosomes are extracellular protozoa that cause chronic infections in humans and livestock and are predominantly transmitted by the bite of the haematophagic tsetse fly [1]. Trypanosoma brucei gambiense and Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense are the causative agents of West/Central- and East-African Sleeping Sickness respectively, also called Human African Trypanosomiasis (HAT), and are responsible for an estimated 500,000 infection cases per annum [2]. Trypanosoma congolense, Trypanosoma vivax and Trypanosoma b. brucei are considered the main cause for livestock infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>These infections have striking effects on economic growth, with losses exceeding 1 billion US $/year in Africa [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Livestock trypanosomiasis moreover affect public health, as infected animals serve as a reservoir for tsetse transmission to humans [2],[4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The main mechanism generally considered to mediate parasitemia control in a mammalian host, is the continuous interaction between antibodies and the parasite surface, covered by variant-specific surface glycoproteins (VSG) [5]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomes undergo antigenic variation by either changing VSG expression sites, known as in situ switching of transcriptional control, or by gene replacement resulting in a switch of the terminal telomeric VSG gene itself [6],[7]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Studies in experimental rodent infection models have implicated T-cell-independent anti-VSG IgM responses to be the first line of host defence against proliferating parasites [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Experimental approaches using mice depleted of B-cells by polyclonal antibody treatment [9], or infections followed by drug-treatment [10], have shown that B-cell responses can be strongly protective but are limited by their VSG-specificity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>This has recently been confirmed in a Cape Buffalo model for natural trypanosomiasis resistance [11]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Recently however, using a chimera bovine model, it was shown that trypanosomiasis sensitivity or resistance was not solely linked to the haematopoietic background of the host, suggesting that other additional host derived factors might also play an important role in the determination of bovine resistance phenotypes [12]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Apart from immune mediated control of infection, the initial setting of parasitemia levels and waves of successive parasitemia peaks are regulated by trypanosomes themselves. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>This coincides with the differentiation of actively dividing ‘long slender’ parasites into non-dividing ‘short stumpy’ parasites [1], [13]–[15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>In experimental murine trypanosomiasis infection models, pleomorphic parasite populations consist of both ‘long slender’ and ‘short stumpy’ differentiation forms whereas monomorphic populations consist of ‘long slender’ forms only. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The latter is highly virulent and kills mice rapidly due to the exponential growth of the ‘long slenders’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>The interaction between the different trypanosome forms and the host immune system can therefore be studied by performing experimental infections using pleomorphic and monomorphic trypanosomes that upon infection initially express the same VSG coat (clonal). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>One of the most detrimental consequences of trypanosomiasis is anemia, which has been described in experimental mouse models [16]–[18] and livestock [19],[20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>In cattle, monitoring of the dramatic decrease in packed red cell volume (PCV) is the main tool for diagnosis of animal trypanosomiasis, only followed later by parasite detection in the circulation [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In human infections, in particular during the hematolymphatic stage of disease, blood and serum anomalies including anemia are also commonly present [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>However, there is currently a lack of data to explain the occurrence of trypanosomiasis-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Some studies have suggested infection-induced anti-VSG antibodies are involved in an erythrolytic process [23], whereas other studies have suggested that trypanosomes release toxic components which directly lyse red blood cells (RBC) [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>However, we have recently shown that the severity of anemia did not correlate with the actual parasite load [18]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Considering (i) the limited knowledge of the role of individual antibody isotypes in trypanosomiasis control, and (ii) the unclear role of B-cells in the in vivo induction of trypanosomiasis-associated anemia, we used B-cell (µMT) and IgM-deficient (IgM−/−) mice to address these points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Our results showed that although B-cell- and IgM-deficient mice infected with the clonal T. brucei AnTat 1.1E parasites exhibited a reduced life span and impaired parasitaemia clearance, infection-induced IgMs played only a limited role in host survival during non-clonal infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In addition, the presence or absence of B-cells or infection-induced IgM antibodies did not change the rate of trypanosome surface antigenic variation nor did it affect the occurrence of infection-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Therefore, our results show that in mice the overall importance of the infection-induced IgM response is limited. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s2"><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Animals </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Eight to 12 week old female BALB/c mice, BALB/c µMT [25] mice and IgM-deficient BALB/c (IgM−/−) mice [26], as well as C57BL/6 and C57BL/6 µMT mice were obtained from an SPF breeding facility at the University of Cape Town. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>All mice were housed in filter-top cages and maintained in SPF barrier facilities in individual ventilated cages at the University of Cape Town, or at the Institute for Tropical Medicine Antwerp. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Tsetse flies (Glossina morsitans morsitans) were available from the insectaria at the Prins Leopold Institute of Tropical Medicine Antwerp (ITMA), originating from puparia collected in Kariba (Zimbabwe) and Handeni (Tanzania). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Flies were fed on rabbits and maintained at 26°C and at a relative humidity of 65%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Animal ethics approval for the tsetse fly feeding on live animals was obtained from the Animal Ethical Committee of the Institute of Tropical Medicine, Antwerp (Belgium). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Parasites </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The T. brucei brucei AnTat (Antwerp Trypanosoom antigen type) 1.1E, the T. brucei brucei AnTat 1.1 and the non-cloned reference T. brucei TSW196 parasite stocks were kindly provided by Dr. N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Van Meirvenne and E. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Magnus (Lab. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Serology, Institute of Tropical Medicine (ITG), Antwerp, Belgium) and the MITat 1.2 and 1.4 parasite stocks by Dr. M.A.J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Ferguson (Dept. of Biochemistry, The University of Dundee, Scotland). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>The T . b. brucei AnTat 1.1 clonal, monomorphic parasite strain was originally generated as a daughter clone of the AnTat 1.1E clonal, pleomorphic parasite strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>This was done by 25 cycles of syringe passing on day 4 of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Due to the short interval between passages, the AnTat 1.1 parasite is highly virulent and expresses only one type of VSG throughout infection, which is homologous to the initial VSG expressed by the AnTat 1.1E clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Similarly, the T. brucei brucei MITat (Molteno Institute Trypanozoon antigen type) 1.2 and 1.4 clonal, monomorphic parasites are highly virulent and express only one VSG that is non-homologous to the initial VSG expressed by the AnTat 1.1E clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The TSW196 T. b. brucei non-clonal, pleomorphic parasite stock was isolated in 1978 in Côte d'Ivoire, from infected pig and was transferred to an OF1 mice in order to make stabilates for storage at −80°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>It is catalogued at the ITG as ITMAS300500A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The AnTaR 1 (Antwerp Trypanozoon antigen repertoire) non-clonal, pleomorphic parasite strain was isolated in 1966 in Uganda from the bloodstream of infected bushbuck. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Pleomorphic parasite populations are defined as consisting of both ‘long slender’ and ‘short stumpy’ differentiation forms, whereas monomorphic parasite populations consist of only ‘long slender’ forms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The terms clonal and non-clonal indicates that the parasite population used to infect mice initially express identical or multiple, different VSGs respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Infection re-challenge, parasitemia &amp; red blood cell counts </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Infections were initiated by intraperitoneal (i.p.) injection of 5×103 parasites, unless stated otherwise. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Parasites and red blood cells in a 2.5 µl blood sample 1/200 diluted in PBS, were counted every 2 to 4 days, using a light microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>For super-infection experiments, mice were initially infected with 5000 T. brucei AnTat 1.1E parasites by i.p. injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>On day 6 or day 10 post primary infection, mice were super-infected with 5000 homologous highly virulent monomorphic AnTat 1.1 parasites or equally virulent monomorphic MITat 1.4 parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>These monomorphic parasites were capable of expressing only one type of VSG during infection which were either homologous (AnTat 1.1) or non-homologous (MITat 1.4) to the VSG initially expressed during primary infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>For tsetse fly challenge experiments, freshly emerged tsetse flies were infected by feeding on AnTaR 1 infected mice at the peak of parasitemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>In order to obtain a pleomorphic trypanosome population at high titer, these mice were immune suppressed with cyclophosphamide (20mg/kg). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>28 days after the infecting blood meal, flies were screened for a mature salivary gland infection by induced probing on pre-warmed glass slides followed by a microscopic analysis for the presence of metacyclic trypanosomes in the saliva. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Infection of tsetse flies with T. brucei parasites was performed in compliance with the regulations for biosafety and under approval from the Environmental administration of the Flemish government. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>To initiate a natural infection, one individual tsetse fly with a mature salivary gland infection was allowed to feed per mouse. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>To avoid interrupted tsetse feeding, mice were anesthetized prior to the tsetse exposure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Parasite burden of all mice was monitored every day for 1 week following super-infection and survival of all mice was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>The experiment was performed in WT BALB/c mice as well is in BALB/c µMT, and IgM−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>10 mice per group were used. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Anti-VSG antibody titer determination by ELISA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Infection-induced anti-VSG titers were determined by ELISA as described before [27]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Briefly, anti-VSG mouse antibody isotypes were detected using biotin coupled goat-anti-mouse Ig isotype antibodies (Pharmingen) in combination with streptavidin alkaline-phosphatase (AP) for development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Optical density was determined at 450 nm using a VERSAmax ELISA reader (Molecular Division). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>Quantitative real time RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Washed DE52 purified trypanosomes were lysed in TriReagent (Molecular Research Centre) and total RNA extracted according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Contaminating genomic DNA was digested using molecular grade RNase-free DNAse I (Promega). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Reverse transcriptase and cDNA quantification by real-time PCR on the Lightcycler (Roche Diagnostics) was performed as recently described [28] using the DNA Master Hybridization Probe Kit (Roche Diagnostics) according to the manufacturers instructions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Amplification primers used were: VSG AnTat 1.1E (GenBank accession X01843): (forward 5′-GAA TGC GAC ACG GAA AGC G-3′, reverse 5′-CGT CGT TGG CTG CTT GGA G; 399 base pair product), VSG MITat 1.2 (forward 5′-ATG GAC ACC AGC GGA ACA AAC-3′, reverse 5′-TCC AGG CGT CGA TCC ACG-3′; 259 base pair product), gene tubulin zeta (GenBank accession AF241275) (forward 5′-TCC CGT CCA TTT CAG GTC C-3′, reverse 5′-GTG CAT CAG CAT ACC ATC CAG T-3′; 294 base pair product). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Specific hybridization probes for the three genes were respectively VSG AnTat 1.1E flourescein labeled 5′-CTG CT TGC TTG TAG GTG CTG CCG-3′, LC640 5′-CGT TAC AGT TGC CAG TTT AGC TGC GA-3′, VSG MITat 1.2 (GenBank accession X56762) flourescein labeled 5′-TAG CGA ACA GCC AAA CAG CCG TCA C-3′, LC705 5′- GTC CAG GCG CTC GAT GCA TTA CAG-3′, and (Tubulin zeta) flourescein labeled 5′-TGC CTG TAC CAC CAG CTA AAC TGT GT-3′, LC640 5′-TAC CAA AAT TGC CTC AAA CTC CTC CG-3′). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>A standard curve for AnTat 1.1E, MITat 1.2 and tubulin zeta, was established by 10-fold dilutions of a positive sample and included as a standard and a “calibrator control”. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Target mRNA levels in IgM+/+, µMT and IgM−/− derived trypanosomes were determined by comparing the sample threshold cycle number against the target gene standard curve using the Second Derivative Maximum function of the Lightcycler software (Roche Diagnostics). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>The same dilutions of the samples were used for the AnTat 1.1E, MITat 1.2 and tubulin zeta RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>AnTat 1.1E VSG levels for each sample ware normalized by dividing the calculated AnTat 1.1E value by the calculated tubulin zeta value. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The MITat 1.2 RT-PCR served as negative control on AnTat 1.1E derived mRNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent data for each sample was detected at the annealing step at 60°C and hybridization probe specificity cross-checked. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Graphic and statistical result analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>All graphic result presentations were prepared using GraphPad Prism software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The same software was used for statistical analysis of data. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Comparative analysis of survival data was done using a designated GraphPad Prism statistical module using a Logrank test. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s3"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><title><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>B-cells are essential to prolong survival during African trypanosomiasis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To address the role of B lymphocytes during experimental trypanosomiasis, comparative infection studies were performed in B-cell-deficient (µMT) and WT C57BL/6 mice, using the pleomorphic T. b. brucei AnTat 1.1E clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>This parasite clone has been used in the past as a well established model for experimental trypanosomiasis in mice, and produces a relatively chronic infection that lasts usually over a month, before killing the host. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>The pleomorphic annotation refers to the fact that blood parasite populations comprise both proliferating ‘long slender’ parasites and ‘short stumpy’ non-proliferating parasites, which are awaiting transmission to the tsetse fly vector. Figure 1A shows that in C57BL/6 mice, the absence of B-cells had neither an influence on the initial growth rate of the trypanosomes, nor on the height of the parasitemia at 6 days post infection, corresponding to the first peak in WT mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, post-peak parasite removal and prolongation of the mean survival of the infected mice were clearly B-cell dependent (Fig. 1A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Important to note is that even in the absence of any anti-trypanosome antibody response, mice controlled a slowly but gradually increasing level of infection for up to 4 weeks. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The eventual death of all µMT and WT mice was associated with exponential parasite proliferation growth, resulting in parasitemia levels up to 2×109 parasites/ml. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>High parasitemia before death was largely independent of the genetic background of the mice, since comparative experimental infections in WT and µMT deficient mice on either a BALB/c or C57BL/6 background yielded similar results (Fig. 1 C,D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1000122-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The effect of B-cells in trypanosomiasis control of clonal infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>(A) C57BL/6 WT (○) and µMT (•) mice were infected with a pleomorphic T. brucei AnTat 1.1E clone by intra-peritoneal inoculation of 5000 parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Parasitemia was followed by microscopy analysis of tail-cut blood samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Values are presented as mean±SD of 10 individual mice per group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>(B) Mortality of all infected mice was recorded. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>One representative from 3 experiments is shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>(C,D) The same experiment was performed with BALB/c WT (□) and µMT BALB/c (▪) mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>M.S. = median survival time in days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>(*: p&lt;0.0001 compared to WT) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000122.g001"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Trypanosome-induced IgMs have a limited impact on host survival </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>As parasite VSGs rapidly change, primary immunity provided by T-cell independent IgMs, is believed to confer a crucial impact on trypanosomiasis control [8],[27],[29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In order to test this in vivo, IgM−/− and control WT mice were infected with clonal, pleomorphic T. b. brucei AnTat 1.1E parasites as described above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, in the absence of IgM, mice were able to reduce peak parasitemia levels, albeit with delayed kinetics and reduced efficacy as compared to WT controls (Fig. 2A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>The reduced capacity to clear successive parasitemia waves resulted in a slight, but significant, accelerated mortality (Fig. 2B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1000122-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The effect of IgMs in high-, intermediate- or low-virulent infections. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>BALB/c WT (□) and IgM−/− (▴) mice were infected with (A/B) 5000 parasites of the pleomorphic AnTat 1.1E clone by intra-peritoneal injection, (C/D) non clonal T. brucei AnTaR 1 parasites through exposure to tsetse fly or (E/F) with 5000 parasites of the low virulent field isolate TSW196 by intra-peritoneal injection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Parasitemia and mortality of infected mice was assessed as in Fig. 1, using 10 mice per experimental group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>M.S. = median survival time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000122.g002"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>To evaluate whether changes in intrinsic parasite virulence affects the importance of antibodies in trypanosomiasis control, and to mimic natural conditions, tsetse fly infections were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Surprisingly, the absence or presence of IgM's had no impact on the parasitemia development and survival of mice infected with AnTaR 1 parasites (Fig. 2C and 2D), which are a non-clonal, pleomorphic T. b. brucei stock. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In a second attempt to mimic a more natural infection, usually characterized in cattle by a non-clonal, low-level parasitemia, mice were infected with non-clonal, pleomorphic T. b. brucei TSW196 parasites derived from a field isolate. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>When infected with TSW196 parasites, a low virulent infection was obtained in mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Here again, no significant differences in parasite burden or mortality were observed between WT and IgM−/− mice (Fig. 2E and 2F), suggesting no significant role for IgM responses against the non-cloned T. b. brucei TSW196 parasite strain. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><title><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>IgM−/− mice produce compensatory soluble IgD antibodies during trypanosome infections </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>Antibody binding of the parasite surface is considered to be a crucial step in protective host mechanism used to neutralize blood borne parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Here, the ability of mice to produce VSG-binding antibody responses was measured in the presence or absence of IgM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>In WT mice, infection with clonal, pleomorphic AnTat 1.1E parasites induced rapid VSG-binding IgM antibody serum titers (Fig. 3) with increasing concentrations towards peak parasitemia (day 7). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>VSG-binding IgG2a and IgG3 antibody titers were detected with a delay of 2 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Other VSG binding antibody isotypes were hardly detectable (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>A similar kinetic for IgG2a and IgG3 was seen in infected IgM−/− mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>However, in these mice IgM titers were replaced by compensatory VSG-binding soluble IgD titers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1000122-g003" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Trypanosome infected IgM−/− mice produce compensatory IgD titers. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Sera were collected from T. brucei AnTat 1.1E infected WT and IgM−/− BALB/c mice, and were analyzed as serial dilutions (log 10) in a solid phase VSG coated ELISA, using isotype-specific antibodies for detection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Sera were collected throughout the first peak and clearance phase from 5 individual mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Values are presented as means. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000122.g003"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3d"><title><text><SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>IgM antibodies protect against a homologous re-challenge infection </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Previous studies have suggested that during pleomorphic infections, parasitemia peak clearance involves mainly macrophage-mediated removal of non-dividing ‘short stumpy’ parasites that predominate at this time point [13],[30],[31]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>The antibody results presented above may suggest that infection-induced IgMs do contribute to peak parasitemia clearance of clonal parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>In order to evaluate the functional activity of antibodies in control of actively proliferating ‘long slender’ parasites, an infection model was established using slow killing pleomorphic and fast killing monomorphic ‘long slender’ T. brucei clones, expressing either homologous or non-homologous VSGs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>First WT, µMT and IgM−/− mice were infected with 5000 AnTat 1.1E parasites, resulting in relatively slow mortality kinetics (Fig. 4A, combining results of Fig. 1D and 2B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>In parallel, the same 3 mouse strains were infected with 5000 highly virulent monomorphic AnTat 1.1 parasites (expressing only a VSG that was homologous to the initial VSG of the AnTat 1.1E clone) or with 5000 non-homologous VSG monomorphic MITat 1.4 parasites. Figure 4B shows that both monomorphic parasite clones kill their WT host within 5 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Identical results were obtained in µMT and IgM−/− mice (data not shown), suggesting that through their accelerated exponential growth, these parasites have reached a level of virulence that is lethal before an in vivo efficient B-cell response can be initiated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1000122-g004" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>The role of IgM in VSG-specific protection. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>(A) BALB/c WT (□), IgM−/− (▴) and µMT (▪) mice were infected with 5000 pleomorphic AnTat 1.1E parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>(B) BALB/c WT mice were infected with 5000 monomorphic AnTat 1.1 (•) or MITat 1.4 (▒) parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>(C) AnTat 1.1E infected BALB/c WT (□) mice were super-infected (S.I.) on day 6 or (D) on day 10 with 5000 parasites of a homologous, monomorphic AnTat 1.1 (•) or a non-homologous monomorphic, MITat 1.4 (▒) strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>(E) AnTat 1.1E infected BALB/c µMT (□) and (F) BALB/c IgM−/− (□) mice were super-infected with AnTat 1.1 (•) or MITat 1.4 (▒) parasites using the same strategy described above in C–D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>(G) BALB/c WT (□) and BALB/c nu/nu (▾) mice were infected with 5000 AnTat 1.1E parasites and (H) were super-infected AnTat 1.1 (•) or MITat 1.4 (▒) parasites using the same strategy described above in C–D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>All primary and super-infections were done by intra-peritoneal inoculation of 5000 parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Mortality was recorded using 10 mice per experimental group and the results were compared to mice that only received the primary infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>One out of 3 representative experiments is shown. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000122.g004"/></fig></SecTag><p><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Next, a combination infection model using pleomorphic parasites for a primary infection, and monomorphic parasites for a re-challenge infection was established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>WT mice were infected with pleomorphic AnTat 1.1E parasites (Fig. 4C) and on day 6 after primary infection, when the parasite load was greater than 108 parasites/ml (data not shown), they were re-challenged with 5000 monomorphic AnTat 1.1 or MITat 1.4 parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>These monomorphic parasites expressed VSGs that were either homologous (AnTat 1.1) or non-homologous (MITat 1.4) to the initial VSG expressed during primary infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>This resulted in significant earlier mortality of re-challenged mice, as compared to primary infected mice, irrespective of the homology of the VSG being expressed by the parasite during re-challenge (Fig. 4C) (p&lt;0.0001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>This earlier mortality was triggered by uncontrolled growth of ‘long slender’ forms of the monomorphic clones (Fig. 4C), as mice died with high parasitemia exceeding 109 parasites/ml blood after temporary remission of their primary pleomorphic infection (parasitemia data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>However, when re-challenged at day 10 with monomorphic AnTat 1.1 parasites, expressing homologous VSGs, rapid host killing was not observed demonstrating VSG-specific resistance (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Indeed re-challenge at day 10 with non-homologous VSG expressing parasites (MITat 1.4) resulted in significantly accelerated mortality (M.S. = 18 days) as compared to control WT and AnTat 1.1 infected mice (M.S. = 34 days for both groups) (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>However, the observed host killing occurred with slower kinetics than observed in Fig. 4B. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>VSG-specific resistance at day 10 was absent in µMT mice (Fig. 4E) which displayed a mean survival of 15 days. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>This was not unexpected since both monomorphic parasites killed WT mice within 4–5 days (Fig. 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>VSG-specific resistance in IgM−/− mice re-challenged at the same time point with the same parasite was significantly impaired as compared to WT mice (p&lt;0.0001) (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>However, IgM−/− mice infected with AnTat 1.1 survived 1 week longer (Fig. 4F) than the 15 days observed in µMT mice (Fig. 4E). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>This earlier mortality of IgM−/− mice as compared to WT mice, showed that IgM's play only a minor role in protection against homologous re-challenge infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>In contrast T-cell deficient mice, which would be expected to produce T-cell independent anti-VSG IgM antibodies, were fully protected against homologous challenge (Fig. 4G and 4H). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><title><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>Antigenic variation occurs in the absence of antibody responses </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Antigenic variation is a characteristic feature of trypanosomes allowing escape from protective host immune responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>It is suggested to result in characteristic waves of parasitemia through interplay with anti-VSG-specific antibodies [32]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, the presence of VSG switching during in vitro cultivation of trypanosomes under selective drug pressure, demonstrated that antigenic variation can occur in the absence of antibody mediated events [33] . </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>However, this is not conclusive for in vivo conditions in mammals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>Due to B-cell mediated selection pressure, one might expect differences in the overall VSG-specific RNA species. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>Quantification of VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA by Real Time RT-PCR from AnTat 1.1E infected B-cell deficient (µMT) or wild-type mice showed similar VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA concentrations during the first parasitemia peak (Fig. 5A, B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Using irrelevant VSG MITat 1.2 specific primers, no amplification signal was obtained under identical real time RT-PCR conditions, demonstrating the VSG specificity of the assay (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA was undetectable in parasites isolated from the second peak of parasitemia of WT mice, due to efficient elimination of the VSG AnTat 1.1E parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Interestingly in µMT mice, VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA from second peak parasites was strikingly reduced despite exponential parasite growth (Fig. 5B), which suggests that the main evasion mechanism is an intrinsic genetic program. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>The finding of 3.5 % remaining VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA in µMT-derived parasites compared to the sensitivity level of &gt;1%, may reflect a slight reduction in efficiency of clonal parasite elimination in the absence of antibody-mediated selection pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The possibility that a reduction of VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA was due to a proliferation/growth arrest of parasites could be ruled out as the total amount of VSG-specific RNA species using quantification by Uni-primers (able to amplify all VSG RNA species) was similar during the first and second peak, shown in Fig. 5C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>This was confirmed by microscopy analysis of infected blood of µMT mice (day 14–22), that contained around 50% dividing ‘long slender’ parasites and 20% non-dividing ‘short stumpy’ parasites (Fig. 5D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1000122-g005" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Quantitative analysis of VSG switching. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Switching of VSG expression was followed by real time RT-PCR, by amplification of peak stage parasite RNA with primers specific for VSG AnTat 1.1E and the housekeeping genes tubulin-zeta (Tubulin). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>(A) RNA was isolated from WT derived and (B) µMT derived parasites on the first and second peak, respectively occurring on day 6 and 14. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Expression of VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA on the second peak was calculated and compared to the first peak, after normalization of the first and second peak VSG AnTat 1.1E specific RNA to tubulin-zeta gene expression.. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>One representative of two experiments are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>(C) Similarly, total VSG mRNA was amplified from first and second peak µMT derived parasites, using VSG-Uni primers, and results were normalized using Tubulin gene expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>(D) To assess parasite proliferation in µMT mice, the occurrence of dividing ‘long slender’ parasites versus intermediate and non-dividing ‘short stumpy’ parasites was analyzed by light microscopy on day 4 and compared to the chronic infection stage (up to day 22). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000122.g005"/></fig></SecTag></sec><sec id="s3f"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>B-cells are not involved in the induction of trypanosomiasis-associated anemia </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Infection-induced anemia is an important morbidity factor in African trypanosomiasis and has been linked to B-cell responses, due to lysis of red blood cells after opsonization with VSG-specific antibodies [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>However, trypanosomiasis-induced anemia was as severe in µMT mice as in WT mice (Fig. 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>This was independent of the mouse genetic background, as similar patterns of anemia development were recorded in C57BL/6 (Fig. 6A) and BALB/c mice (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, trypanosomiasis associated anemia also occurred in the absence of a functional IgM response (Fig. 6B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="ppat-1000122-g006" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000122.g006</object-id><label>Figure 6</label><caption><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Trypanosomiasis-associated anemia is present in µMT mice. </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>(A) C57BL/6 WT (○) and µMT (•) mice were infected with a pleomorphic T. brucei AnTat 1.1E clone by intra-peritoneal inoculation of 5000 parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>(B) BALB/c WT (□), µMT (▪) and IgM−/− (▴) mice were infected by intra-peritoneal inoculation of 5000 with the pleomorphic AnTat 1.1E clone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>RBC counts were followed by microscopy analysis of tail-cut blood samples. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Values are presented as mean±SD of 10 individual mice per group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ppat.1000122.g006"/></fig></SecTag></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s4"><title><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>African Trypanosomiasis is a textbook example of an extracellular parasitic infection where antigenic variation of the variant-specific surface glycoprotein (VSG) and subsequent antibody responses of the host result in a prolonged period of parasitemia control [1],[3],[4],[32]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>For the parasite, this lengthened time is required to increase the chance of successful parasite transmission through the tsetse vector. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>While resistance to trypanosomiasis in some mammals such as the Cape Buffalo is linked to their capacity to mount an efficient anti-parasite antibody response, trypano-tolerance in cattle can also develop independently of their genetic haematopoietic background [34]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>These observations suggest that besides antibodies, additional host factors can contribute to parasite control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>During the chronic phase of trypanosomiasis, the continuous interplay between the parasite and its host's immune system results in infection-associated pathology, including anemia [14]–[20], [31]–[35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Despite the importance of anemia, the exact mechanisms underlying its induction remained unsolved [35]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>Some studies, showing that in vitro VSG-sensitized RBC can be lysed by VSG-specific antibodies, have suggested that anemia may be linked to B-cell responses and that antibody mediated lysis may be a contributing factor in vivo [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Other studies have suggested that trypanosomes themselves release components which directly lyse RBC [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Based on in vitro observations, it was proposed that destruction of RBC's could occur as a result of an active GPI-VSG transfer between trypanosome and erythrocyte membranes, followed by the anti-VSG mediated complement-dependent lysis [23]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>However no in vivo data was obtained to support this hypothesis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we have previously not been able to find any significant correlation between the severity of anemia and parasite load [18]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Using gene deficient mouse models, we have now dissected the role of B-cells and IgM-responses in parasite elimination, host survival, antigenic variation and in Trypanosoma-induced anemia. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>We have clearly shown that infected µMT mice still developed anemia, suggesting that B-cells are not involved in the induction of trypanosomiasis-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>This B-cell independent trypanosomiasis-induced anemia may be mediated by TNF [18],[36],[37], although the exact mode of action remains to be elucidated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>TNF could have a crucial impact on anemia through its capacity to modulate the activation, growth and the phagocytic potential of macrophages involved in antibody independent erythrophagocytosis [38]–[40], a process which is dependent on IFNγ [41]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>Infections with clonal, pleomorphic T. brucei parasites (AnTat 1.1E), demonstrated an essential role for B-cells in host protection and corroborated previous B-cell depletion studies [9],[10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>However, IgM was found to play only a limited role in primary infection with clonal, pleomorphic parasites, perhaps due to the presence of VSG-specific IgG2a and IgG3 and compensatory IgD antibodies or other Ig isotypes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, our results in BALB/c µMT and C57BL/6 µMT mice showed that the genetic background of the host has an impact on parasite growth and differentiation, independent of the B-cell compartment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Indeed, in C57BL/6 µMT mice the first parasitemia peak was consistently lower than the BALB/c µMT, albeit in both strains the peak is reached at the same time point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Also, since T-cell deficient mice were found to be fully protected against re-challenge with a homologous parasite, the antibody mediated VSG-specific protection observed on day 10 was T-cell independent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>However, the significance of the extended survival of the T-cell deficient mice is beyond the scope of this paper. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Re-challenge studies with the homologous monomorphic AnTat 1.1 strain demonstrated that while VSG-specific IgM's were induced early during infection, they were not able to efficiently protect against monomorphic parasites during the first peak of infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>This was evidenced by the impaired protection in wild-type mice when re-infected with the homologous VSG-expressing AnTat 1.1 strain early during infection at day 6 (see Fig. 4C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>In contrast, VSG-specific IgM responses were able to fully protect WT mice against re-infection at day 10 after primary infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>However, efficient elimination of actively proliferating monomorphic parasites occurred only when the parasites used for re-challenge expressed a VSG that was homologous to those expressed during primary infection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>These observations support the notion that antibodies can only exert their full anti-trypanosome activity in an immunological environment that develops later than day 6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>At this early time point, activated macrophages play a crucial role in parasite destruction via the secretion of inflammatory molecules such as nitric oxide (NO) and TNF, and through phagocytosis of damaged and opsonized parasites. Although IgM−/− mice survived a few days longer when re-infected on day 10 with the homologous VSG-expressing AnTat 1.1 parasite, as compared to re-infection using non-homologous VSG-expressing MITat 1.4 parasites (Fig. 4F), this prolonged survival in IgM−/− mice (MS = 12 days) was much less pronounced than the prolonged survival obtained in WT mice, where re-challenge on day 10 did not result in accelerated mortality at all (Fig. 4D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>This demonstrated that VSG-specific IgD and/or IgG responses were not able to efficiently compensate for IgM immunity, irrespectively of the homology of the VSG being expressed by the parasite during re-challenge. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Because MITat 1.4 re-challenged IgM−/− mice (Fig. 4F) survived longer than MITat 1.4 primary infected IgM−/− mice (Fig. 4B), we concluded that a primary host immune responses from day 10, had a negative effect on parasite growth rate, which seems to be VSG-independent. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>A similar observation has been reported in natural infections where relative resistance or susceptibility to trypanosomiasis in cattle could not always be correlated to the host's capacity of mounting an efficient anti-VSG response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>Instead trypano-tolerance was found to be associated with elevated Type I cytokine production (IFNγ &amp; TNF), increased macrophage activation and NO production [34],[42]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>Similarly, during initial exponential parasite growth phase, SCID mice displayed a lymphocyte-independent parasite growth regulating mechanism which gradually triggered the differentiation of proliferating ‘long slender’ parasites into non-dividing ‘short stumpy’ forms causing the infection to reach a plateau [13],[43]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>This mechanism of B-cell independent parasite control may therefore involve an intrinsic regulation of parasite growth/differentiation by a parasite released short-stumpy inducing factor [44]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>In contrast to the results from infection using clonal, pleomorphic parasites, infections with a non-clonal, pleomorphic field isolate (TSW196) showed that IgM−/− mice were able to remit parasitic waves as efficiently as wild-type control mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Infection-induced IgM's may therefore be compensated for, perhaps by IgG's or other Ig isotypes, during host protective responses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>Similarly, no prominent role for IgM was observed in non-clonal tsetse fly initiated infections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>However, in this case it should be noted that the AnTaR 1 T. brucei parasite used for tsetse fly transmission caused a highly virulent infection in all experimental groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Moreover, we can not exclude the possibility that WT mice do not make sufficient IgM in response to tsetse fly initiated infections and that IgM's are important for wave remission. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>These results may also suggest that either tsetse fly saliva components, or other factors involving intrinsic characteristics of tsetse fly transmitted parasites, actively prevent the induction of efficient B-cell responses in mice as a defence mechanism against the host immune system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>Although, previous in vitro experiments indicated that trypanosomes in culture may undergo VSG switching in the absence of antibody-mediated pressure [33], this has never been demonstrated in vivo. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>We have shown that antigenic variation occurring in vivo is independent of antibody induction or selective pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Although clonally infected µMT mice had overall impaired parasite clearance and shortened survival, the virtual absence of VSG AnTat1.1E specific RNA in µMT mice 10 days after first peak of infection, demonstrated that parasites switched their VSG independently of antibody selective pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Moreover, the remaining 3.5% VSG AnTat1.1E specific RNA in µMT mice and 3% VSG AnTat1.1E specific RNA in IgM-deficient mice, indicated that antibodies are mostly needed for complete elimination of the remaining non-switched parasites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>Interesting to note is the apparently unaltered VSG switching rate between parasites growing in WT and µMT mice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>This observation suggests that antibody independent host or parasite factors drive the actual switching process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>While the production of a VSG-specific stumpy-inducing factor by the parasite itself appears unlikely, it is feasible that inflammatory mediators such as NO, oxygen radicals or inflammatory cytokines such as TNF and IFNg, produced by activated macrophages or T-cells could impact on the activation of antigenic variation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Future repetitions of the experiments presented here in BALB/c nu/nu and/or RAG−/− mice could potentially shed more light on the mechanisms at work here. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>In summary, the genetic approach of our study using applicable gene deficient mice has allowed us to discriminate the in vivo roles of B-cells as well as IgM-responses in parasite growth control, host survival and pathology associated with trypanosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Our report shows that B-cells are not involved in the induction of trypanosomiasis-associated anemia. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>Moreover, although infections with the clonal, pleomorphic T. brucei AnTat 1.1E parasites in µMT and IgM−/− mice indicated a limited role for infection-induced anti-VSG antibodies in parasitemia control and host survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>Moreover, non-clonal, low-virulent infections originating from field populations, as well as tsetse fly exposure experiments, indicated that IgM responses have no decisive role on either disease progression or host survival. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>Finally, this study demonstrated that in vivo parasite VSG switching operates as an intrinsically programmed genetic process that is independent of B-cell or antibody pressure, with the function of antibodies mainly limited to the elimination of the remaining non-switched parasites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>We thank Dr. M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Radwanska for her excellent guidance of the RT-PCR work and design of PCR primer pairs and research strategy, the execution of the tsetse fly challenge experiments, and the critical reading of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Also, Drs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>Anthony Cutler and Sarah Joseph are thanked for critical reading of the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>We thank T. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Baral, M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>Drennan, N. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>Allie, R. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Peterson, H. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Arendse, and the animal facility staff for excellent technical assistance. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>This work received financial support from the Fund for Scientific Research Flanders (FWO) and was executed in the context of a bilateral international scientific and technological cooperation grant from the Ministry of the Flemish Community. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>SM was a Postdoctoral Fellow of the FWO. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ppat.1000122-Vickerman1"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>1 VickermanK 1985 Developmental cycles and biology of pathogenic trypanosomes. Br Med Bull 41 105 114 3928017 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-WHO1"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>2 WHO 1998 Control and surveillance of African trypanosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Report of a WHO Expert Committee. World Health Organ Tech Rep Ser 881 I VI 1–114 10070249 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-VandenBossche1"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>3 Van den BosscheP 2001 Some general aspects of the distribution and epidemiology of bovine trypanosomosis in southern Africa. Int J Parasitol 31 592 598 11334947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-vanMeirvenne1"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>4 van MeirvenneN 1999 Biological diagnosis of human African trypanosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Progress in human African trypanosomiasis, sleeping sickness. Paris ; London Springer 235 252  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Vanhamme1"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>5 VanhammeLPaysEMcCullochRBarryJD 2001 An update on antigenic variation in African trypanosomes. Trends Parasitol 17 338 343 11423377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Borst1"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>6 BorstP 2002 Antigenic variation and allelic exclusion. Cell 109 5 8 11955440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Pays1"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>7 PaysETebabiPPaysACoqueletHRevelardP 1989 The genes and transcripts of an antigen gene expression site from T. brucei. Cell 57 835 845 2720787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Reinitz1"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>8 ReinitzDMMansfieldJM 1990 T-cell-independent and T-cell-dependent B-cell responses to exposed variant surface glycoprotein epitopes in trypanosome-infected mice. Infect Immun 58 2337 2342 1694824 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Campbell1"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>9 CampbellGHEsserKMWeinbaumFI 1977 Trypanosoma rhodesiense infection in B-cell-deficient mice. Infect Immun 18 434 438 303620 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-deGee1"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>10 de GeeALMcCannPPMansfieldJM 1983 Role of antibody in the elimination of trypanosomes after DL-alpha-difluoromethylornithine chemotherapy. J Parasitol 69 818 822 6423794 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Guirnalda1"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>11 GuirnaldaPMurphyNBNolanDBlackSJ 2007 Anti-Trypanosoma brucei activity in Cape buffalo serum during the cryptic phase of parasitemia is mediated by antibodies. Int J Parasitol 37 1391 1399 17583714 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Naessens1"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>12 NaessensJLeakSGKennedyDJKempSJTealeAJ 2003 Responses of bovine chimaeras combining trypanosomosis resistant and susceptible genotypes to experimental infection with Trypanosoma congolense. Vet Parasitol 111 125 142 12531289 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Matthews1"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>13 MatthewsKR 1999 Developments in the differentiation of Trypanosoma brucei. Parasitol Today 15 76 80 10234191 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Black1"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>14 BlackSJSendashongaCNO'BrienCBorowyNKNaessensM 1985 Regulation of parasitaemia in mice infected with Trypanosoma brucei. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol 117 93 118 3896678 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Savill1"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>15 SavillNJSeedJR 2004 Mathematical and statistical analysis of the Trypanosoma brucei slender to stumpy transition. Parasitology 128 53 67 15002904 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Amole1"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>16 AmoleBOClarksonABJrShearHL 1982 Pathogenesis of anemia in Trypanosoma brucei-infected mice. Infect Immun 36 1060 1068 7201455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Mabbott1"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>17 MabbottNACoulsonPSSmythiesLEWilsonRASternbergJM 1998 African trypanosome infections in mice that lack the interferon-gamma receptor gene: nitric oxide-dependent and -independent suppression of T-cell proliferative responses and the development of anaemia. Immunology 94 476 480 9767434 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Magez1"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>18 MagezSRadwanskaMBeschinASekikawaKDe BaetselierP 1999 Tumor necrosis factor alpha is a key mediator in the regulation of experimental Trypanosoma brucei infections. Infect Immun 67 3128 3132 10338530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Cox1"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>19 CoxFE 1979 Pathogenesis of animal trypanosomiasis. Nature 277 603 604 423960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Murray1"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>20 MurrayMDexterTM 1988 Anaemia in bovine African trypanosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>A review. Acta Trop 45 389 432 2907267 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Ouma1"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>21 OumaJMwangiJMdachiRNjiruZNdung'U 2001 Validation of indirect Elisa systems for the serodiagnosis of bovine Trypanosomosis in endemic areas of Kenya. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>FAO/IAEA report. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>In Animal Trypanosomosis: diagnosis and epidemiology. Leiden, The Netherlands Backhuys Publishers 93 97  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Dumas1"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>22 DumasMBisserS 1999 Clinical aspects of human African trypanosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>In Progress in human African trypanosomiasis, sleeping sickness. Paris ; London Springer 215 252  </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Rifkin1"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>23 RifkinMRLandsbergerFR 1990 Trypanosome variant surface glycoprotein transfer to target membranes: a model for the pathogenesis of trypanosomiasis. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 87 801 805 2300563 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Tizard1"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>24 TizardIRHolmesWLNielsenK 1978 Mechanisms of the anemia in trypanosomiasis: studies on the role of the hemolytic fatty acids derived from Trypanosoma congolense. Tropenmed Parasitol 29 108 114 644654 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Kitamura1"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>25 KitamuraDRoesJKuhnRRajewskyK 1991 A B cell-deficient mouse by targeted disruption of the membrane exon of the immunoglobulin mu chain gene. Nature 350 423 426 1901381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Lutz1"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>26 LutzCLedermannBKosco-VilboisMHOchsenbeinAFZinkernagelRM 1998 IgD can largely substitute for loss of IgM function in B cells. Nature 393 797 801 9655395 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Radwanska1"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>27 RadwanskaMMagezSMichelAStijlemansBGeuskensM 2000 Comparative analysis of antibody responses against HSP60, invariant surface glycoprotein 70, and variant surface glycoprotein reveals a complex antigen-specific pattern of immunoglobulin isotype switching during infection by Trypanosoma brucei. Infect Immun 68 848 860 10639455 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Herbert1"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>28 HerbertDRHolscherCMohrsMArendseBSchwegmannA 2004 Alternative macrophage activation is essential for survival during schistosomiasis and downmodulates T helper 1 responses and immunopathology. Immunity 20 623 635 15142530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-OBeirne1"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>29 O'BeirneCLowryCMVoorheisHP 1998 Both IgM and IgG anti-VSG antibodies initiate a cycle of aggregation-disaggregation of bloodstream forms of Trypanosoma brucei without damage to the parasite. Mol Biochem Parasitol 91 165 193 9574934 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Sendashonga1"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>30 SendashongaCNBlackSJ 1982 Humoral responses against Trypanosoma brucei variable surface antigen are induced by degenerating parasites. Parasite Immunol 4 245 257 7122117 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Dempsey1"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>31 DempseyWLMansfieldJM 1983 Lymphocyte function in experimental African trypanosomiasis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>Role of antibody and the mononuclear phagocyte system in variant-specific immunity. J Immunol 130 405 411 6847889 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Black2"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>32 BlackSJSicardELMurphyNNolanD 2001 Innate and acquired control of trypanosome parasitaemia in Cape buffalo. Int J Parasitol 31 562 565 11334943 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Horn1"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>33 HornDCrossGA 1997 Analysis of Trypanosoma brucei vsg expression site switching in vitro. Mol Biochem Parasitol 84 189 201 9084039 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Williams1"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>34 WilliamsDJTaylorKNewsonJGichukiBNaessensJ 1996 The role of anti-variable surface glycoprotein antibody responses in bovine trypanotolerance. Parasite Immunol 18 209 218 9223176 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Witola1"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>35 WitolaWHLovelaceCE 2001 Demonstration of erythrophagocytosis in Trypanosoma congolense-infected goats. Vet Parasitol 96 115 126 11230918 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Naessens2"><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>36 NaessensJKitaniHNakamuraYYagiYSekikawaK 2005 TNF-alpha mediates the development of anaemia in a murine Trypanosoma brucei rhodesiense infection, but not the anaemia associated with a murine Trypanosoma congolense infection. Clin Exp Immunol 139 405 410 15730385 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Sileghem1"><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>37 SileghemMFlynnJNLogan-HenfreyLEllisJ 1994 Tumour necrosis factor production by monocytes from cattle infected with Trypanosoma (Duttonella) vivax and Trypanosoma (Nannomonas) congolense: possible association with severity of anaemia associated with the disease. Parasite Immunol 16 51 54 7908735 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Branch1"><text><SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>38 BranchDRGuilbertLJ 1996 Autocrine regulation of macrophage proliferation by tumor necrosis factor-alpha. Exp Hematol 24 675 681 8635522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Collins1"><text><SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>39 CollinsHLBancroftGJ 1992 Cytokine enhancement of complement-dependent phagocytosis by macrophages: synergy of tumor necrosis factor-alpha and granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor for phagocytosis of Cryptococcus neoformans. Eur J Immunol 22 1447 1454 1601035 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Lay1"><text><SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>40 LayJDTsaoCJChenJYKadinMESuIJ 1997 Upregulation of tumor necrosis factor-alpha gene by Epstein-Barr virus and activation of macrophages in Epstein-Barr virus-infected T cells in the pathogenesis of hemophagocytic syndrome. J Clin Invest 100 1969 1979 9329960 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Hertz1"><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>41 HertzCJFilutowiczHMansfieldJM 1998 Resistance to the African trypanosomes is IFN-gamma dependent. J Immunol 161 6775 6783 9862708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Tabel1"><text><SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>42 TabelHKaushikRSUzonnaJE 2000 Susceptibility and resistance to Trypanosoma congolense infections. Microbes Infect 2 1619 1629 11113381 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Inoue1"><text><SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>43 InoueNNarumiDMbatiPAHirumiKSituakibanzaNT 1998 Susceptibility of severe combined immuno-deficient (SCID) mice to Trypanosoma brucei gambiense and T. b. rhodesiense. Trop Med Int Health 3 408 412 9623947 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="ppat.1000122-Reuner1"><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>44 ReunerBVassellaEYutzyBBoshartM 1997 Cell density triggers slender to stumpy differentiation of Trypanosoma brucei bloodstream forms in culture. Mol Biochem Parasitol 90 269 280 9497048 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
