<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">DNA Res</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">dnares</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">dnares</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>DNA Research: An International Journal for Rapid Publication of Reports on Genes and Genomes</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1340-2838</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1756-1663</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3111233</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/dnares/dsr010</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dsr010</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Full Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Exploration for Functional Nucleotide Sequence Candidates within Coding Regions of Mammalian Genes </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>Rumiko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="AN1">†</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saitou</surname><given-names>Naruya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label><addr-line>Department of Genetics, School of Life Science</addr-line>, <institution>Graduate University for Advanced Studies</institution>, <addr-line>Mishima 411-8540</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label><addr-line>Division of Population Genetics</addr-line>, <institution>National Institute of Genetics</institution>, <addr-line>Mishima 411-8540</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel. +81 559-81-6790. Fax. +81 559-81-6789. E-mail: <email>saitounr@lab.nig.ac.jp</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Edited by Katsumi Isono </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn id="AN1" fn-type="con"><label>†</label><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Present address: Department of Environmental and Preventive Medicine, Oita University, Yufu 879-5593, Japan. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>17</day><month>5</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>177</fpage><lpage>187</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Kazusa DNA Research Institute.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.5</uri>), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="dsr010.pdf"/><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The primary role of a protein coding gene is to encode amino acids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Therefore, synonymous sites of codons, which do not change the encoded amino acid, are regarded as evolving neutrally. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>However, if a certain region of a protein coding gene contains a functional nucleotide element (e.g. splicing signals), synonymous sites in the region may have selective pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The existence of such elements would be detected by searching regions of low nucleotide substitution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We explored invariant nucleotide sequences in 10 790 orthologous genes of six mammalian species (Homo sapiens, Macaca mulatta, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus, Bos taurus, and Canis familiaris), and extracted 4150 sequences whose conservation is significantly stronger than other regions of the gene and named them significantly conserved coding sequences (SCCSs). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>SCCSs are observed in 2273 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>The genes are mainly involved with development, transcriptional regulation, and the neurons, and are expressed in the nervous system and the head and neck organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>No strong influence of conventional factors that affect synonymous substitution was observed in SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>These results imply that SCCSs may have double function as nucleotide element and protein coding sequence and retained in the course of mammalian evolution. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>mammal</kwd><kwd>protein coding</kwd><kwd>nucleotide conservation</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><label>1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The neutral theory of molecular evolution1,2 predicts that synonymous sites of codons are evolving faster than non-synonymous sites because of the smaller selective pressure. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This is true in general; however, several factors are known to influence on a certain region of a coding sequence and suppress synonymous substitution. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>One of the well-known factors is the codon bias towards optimum codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Optimum codons reflect the composition of genomic tRNA pool.3–5 Because optimum codons are advantageous for fast and accurate translation, highly expressed or biologically important genes would have more optimum codons than others.6–8 Changes from an optimum codon to a non-optimum codon will be suppressed in such genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Because optimum codons are similar in closely related species, highly expressed genes tend to show similar codon usage; therefore synonymous substitution is lowered. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>In fact, the requirement for translational efficiency or accuracy enhances the optimum codon usage and suppresses nucleotide changes through purifying selection.5,6,9–11 Codon bias towards optimum codons is strong in fast-growing organisms such as Escherichia coli or Saccharomyces cerevisiae, but generally weak in species with slow growth rate small population size.12,13 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Another factor is exonic splicing enhancer or silencer, which are splicing signals embedded in exons.14,15 Existence of such elements lowers the synonymous substitution.16,17 In addition, ultraconserved elements (UCEs), which majorly reside in non-protein coding regions, sometimes extend to coding regions.18 In mammals, UCEs are reported to exist near to or overlap with genes associated with nucleotide binding, transcriptional regulation, RNA recognition motif, zinc finger domain, and homeobox domain.18–20 Hox genes also contain long conserved nucleotide regions other than UCEs outside the homeobox domain.21 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Although the primary role of protein coding region is to encode amino acids, there may be also functional nucleotide elements embedded within coding regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>For example, transcription-factor-binding sites are found in coding regions,22 messenger RNAs are targeted by various post-transcriptional regulations,23 and the requirement for a specific secondary structure for RNA editing decreases synonymous substitution.24,25 </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Functional nucleotide elements are extensively explored in the non-coding regions,26–30 but less studies have been done to explore probable functional elements within the coding regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>We extracted significantly conserved coding sequences (SCCSs) from orthologous genes of six mammalian species (human, rhesus macaque, mouse, rat, cow, and dog), and compared genes containing SCCSs and genes without SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Analyses on gene ontology (GO), InterPro codes, and KEGG pathways enlighten difference between the two gene groups. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We also investigated RNA secondary structures, codon preference, GC content, exonic splicing signals, and gene expression of SCCSs to survey the influence of these factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><label>2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s2a"><label>2.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Genome data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>We obtained peptide and nucleotide sequences of orthologous genes of six mammalian species (Homo sapiens, Macaca mulatta, Mus musculus, Rattus norvegicus, Bos taurus, and Canis familiaris) from Ensembl database31 version 54 (http://May2009.archive.ensembl.org/index.html). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>These species are selected considering genome data quality and evolutionary diversity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>We selected one-to-one type single copy orthologs and compiled 10 790 orthologous gene sets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dsr010/DC1">Supplementary file S1</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>We then constructed multiple alignments of peptide sequences using ClustalW32 and constructed nucleotide alignments based on the peptide alignments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>From the nucleotide alignments, we extracted sequences that are invariant among all the species. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2b"><label>2.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Identification of SCCSs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>We performed permutation simulation to identify SCCSs, or abbreviated as SCCSs, which are invariant longer than 10 codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>This length is set to confine the permutation run time within a feasible range. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>For an N-codon long alignment, we generated a non-redundant series of random numbers from 1 to N, and permuted codon columns (rows of codons in the same site of the alignment) according to the generated random numbers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>In this process, gap sites are fixed and the rest of the sites are permuted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>Then the length and numbers of invariant sequences in the permuted alignment are counted. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>We repeated this process 500 000 times per ortholog set and took averages of the frequency of invariant sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>We used the length and averaged frequency of invariant sequences obtained from the permutation results as random expectation, and evaluated the probability of invariant sequences in the original alignment based on the expectation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This approach helps identify sequences whose conservation is rare to occur in the substitution background of each alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Multiple testing correction of p-values is done by FDR (false discovery rate).33 Then we identified invariant sequences longer than 10 codons and P &lt; 0.01 as SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2c"><label>2.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Analysis on GO, InterPro, and KEGG pathways </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Protein coding genes that contain at least one SCCS is named SCCS genes and those that do not contain an SCCS is named non-SCCS genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>We used Fatigo web service (http://babelomics.bioinfo.cipf.es/functional.html) to identify GO terms, InterPro codes, and KEGG pathways that are significantly enriched with the SCCS gene group or with the non-SCCS gene group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Fatigo accepts a list of Ensembl gene IDs as input and provides P-values for enrichment of the above terms. P-values are calculated by Fisher's exact test and corrected by FDR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>We used Ensembl gene IDs of H. sapiens as input and performed two-tailed comparison between SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2d"><label>2.4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Analysis on preferred codons and average codon degeneracy of SCCSs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>We defined preferred codons as the most frequently used codons for a given amino acid referring to Codon Usage Database (http://www.kazusa.or.jp/codon/index.html) provided by Kazusa DNA Research Institute. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Because the codon usage pattern was similar among the six species we used, the codon table of human was used as the representative. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>We counted the number of preferred codons in a SCCS and divided it by the codon length of the SCCS, and then used the quotient as the ratio of preferred codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The average codon degeneracy is calculated by summing up the degeneracy of each codon and dividing it by the codon length of the SCCS. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2e"><label>2.5.</label><title><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Prediction of RNA secondary structures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>We computationally predicted secondary structures and free folding energy of SCCSs using Vienna RNA software package34 (http://www.tbi.univie.ac.at/~ivo/RNA/). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Because folding free energy varies depending on the sequence length, we constructed free energy distribution by 1000 randomly chosen sequences for each length (33–246 nucleotides). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The P-value for a given free energy was evaluated based on these distributions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>Multi testing correction is done by FDR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2f"><label>2.6.</label><title><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>Evaluation of exonic splicing enhancer density </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>We obtained 238 hexamers from RESCUE-ESE Web Server34 as candidates of exonic splicing enhancers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>We counted the number of the hexamers in the SCCSs and the rest of the coding regions of the 10 790 genes (human sequences). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We also measured the total nucleotide length of the SCCS and the other regions and applied the chi-square test for the ratio of hexamers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s2g"><label>2.7.</label><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Analysis on gene expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>We used EGenetics (http://www.nhmrc.gov.au/your_health/egenetics/index.htm) to investigate gene expression of SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Human anatomical system data, which give information about in which organs a gene is expressed, were obtained from EGenetics database by Ensemble Biomart. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>We counted how many of SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes are expressed in each organ and divided the numbers by the total number of SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Then we performed the Fisher's exact test to evaluate whether the difference between SCCS and non-SCCS genes is significant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>All P-values were corrected by FDR. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><label>3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s3a"><label>3.1.</label><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Identification of SCCSs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>If an alignment has a high ratio of conservation, long invariant sequences may occur easily, and vice versa. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the rareness of invariant sequences differs depending on the conservation background in each alignment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>To compensate this, we performed permutation simulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>The idea of permutation is to count the length and frequency of invariant sequences after random change of loci and use the result as the random expectation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>We used the frequency distribution of invariant sequences in the permuted alignments as the random expectation and evaluated probability of invariant sequences in the original alignments, and defined invariant sequences longer than 10 codons and whose probability is below 0.01 (corrected by FDR) as SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>In total, 4150 SCCSs (192 306 bp) were obtained from 2273 alignments of 10 790 orthologous gene sets (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dsr010/DC1">Supplementary file S2</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>This occupies 0.94% of the coding region of the 10 790 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Table 1 shows the number of SCCSs per gene and the number of genes that contain that number of SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Figure 1 is a graph of lengths and numbers of SCCSs (grey bars). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Black dots indicate the random expectation obtained from the permuted alignments. Table 1.Number of SCCSs in coding genesNumber of SCCSs (per gene)Number of genesSCCS genes11366247532194105542&gt;566Non-SCCS genes8517 Figure 1.The length and number of SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>X and Y-axes represent the length and frequency of SCCSs, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Grey bars show the length and the number of SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Black dots indicate the number of sequences with probability below 0.01 in the permuted alignments. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>In the permuted alignments, there are 141 sequences (their total length is 5550 bp) whose probability is below 0.01, which means the region size of SCCS is 35-fold larger than this expectation (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dsr010/DC1">Supplementary file S3</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>The χ2 test between SCCSs and the permutation result showed a significant difference (P &lt; 2.2E−16). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>If invariant and variant sites distributed randomly in the original alignment, the frequency of invariant sequences in the permuted alignments would show similar frequency to the original alignment because of the randomness at the start point. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The difference before and after the permutation suggests that the distribution of invariant sites in the original alignments is rather clustered than being random. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3b"><label>3.2.</label><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>GO, InterPro, and KEGG pathways enriched in SCCS containing genes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>We used Fatigo web service to investigate difference in GO, InterPro codes, and KEGG pathways between the SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The difference was evaluated by the two-tailed Fisher's test, and P-values were corrected by FDR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Tables 2 and 3 show GO terms, InterPro codes, and KEGG pathways significantly enriched (P &lt; 0.01) in SCCS genes. Table 2.GO terms significantly (P &lt; 0.01) enriched with SCCS genesTermsP*In SCCS containing genes (%)aIn non-SCCS containing genes (%)bFoldcBiological process GO:0035136: Forelimb morphogenesis7.75E−050.530.0413.25 GO:0035115: Embryonic forelimb morphogenesis2.50E−040.480.0412.00 GO:0060070: Canonical Wnt receptor signalling pathway2.11E−030.40.0410.00 GO:0035137: Hindlimb morphogenesis4.88E−040.530.068.83 GO:0001702: Gastrulation with mouth forming second1.78E−030.440.058.80 GO:0009954: Proximal/distal pattern formation3.80E−040.570.078.14 GO:0031128: Developmental induction1.03E−030.530.077.57 GO:0048593: Camera-type eye morphogenesis1.22E−050.880.136.77 GO:0021510: Spinal cord development2.37E−040.750.135.77 GO:0031016: Pancreas development1.85E−030.620.125.17Cellular components GO:0014704: Intercalated disc8.43E−030.350.048.75 GO:0043198: Dendritic shaft2.38E−030.480.068.00 GO:0030425: Dendrite2.38E−032.291.12.08 GO:0043025: Neuronal cell body2.38E−032.241.112.02 GO:0015629: Actin cytoskeleton1.15E−033.391.81.88 GO:0043005: Neuron projection1.15E−034.092.321.76Molecular function GO:0035254: Glutamate receptor binding3.41E−030.350.0217.50 GO:0005072: Transforming growth factor beta receptor, cytoplasmic mediator activity8.92E−030.310.0215.50 GO:0004843: Ubiquitin-specific protease activity3.71E−030.480.076.86 GO:0031625: Ubiquitin protein ligase binding6.44E−030.620.144.43 GO:0003725: Double-stranded RNA binding6.44E−030.620.144.43 GO:0042054: Histone methyltransferase activity8.64E−030.570.134.38 GO:0050825: Ice binding6.50E−112.860.763.76 GO:0004221: Ubiquitin thiolesterase activity4.18E−041.010.273.74 GO:0005199: Structural constituent of cell wall1.34E−030.920.253.68 GO:0003682: Chromatin binding4.08E−082.150.593.64aThe percentages of SCCS genes that have the GO term.bThe percentages of non-SCCS genes that have the GO term.cThe fold of ‘a’ to ‘b’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Terms are listed in the descending order of the fold difference. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>Terms with the highest 10-folds are shown for Biological Process and Molecular function.*Probability for enrichment of the GO term in the SCCS group. Table 3.InterPro and KEGG terms significantly (P &lt; 0.01) enriched with SCCS genesTermsP*In SCCS containing genes (%)aIn non-SCCS containing genes (%)bFoldcInterProIPR003619: MAD homology 1, Dwarfin-type1.55E−040.440.0144.00 IPR001827: Homeobox protein, antennapedia type, conserved site1.77E−030.440.0411.00 IPR000569: HECT1.26E−050.750.0710.71 IPR002077: Voltage-dependent calcium channel, alpha-1 subunit5.65E−040.530.0510.60 IPR010982: Lambda repressor-like, DNA-binding1.49E−030.480.059.60 IPR002343: Paraneoplastic encephalomyelitis antigen9.91E−050.70.088.75 IPR018359: Bromodomain, conserved site9.75E−040.570.078.14 IPR001487: Bromodomain1.94E−060.970.128.08 IPR017995: Homeobox protein, antennapedia type7.36E−040.620.087.75 IPR004088: K Homology, type 17.36E−040.620.087.75KEGG hsa03018: RNA degradation1.05E−030.920.243.83 hsa04340: Hedgehog signalling pathway6.75E−030.880.293.03 hsa04520: Adherens junction4.55E−031.060.372.86 hsa05211: Renal cell carcinoma9.88E−030.920.332.79 hsa04120: Ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis1.05E−031.50.572.63 hsa04310: Wnt signalling pathway2.22E−042.070.792.62 hsa04360: Axon guidance3.47E−041.80.692.61 hsa04810: Regulation of actin cytoskeleton1.07E−032.070.942.20 hsa04010: MAPK signaling pathway3.23E−043.081.52.05aThe percentages of SCCS genes that have the InterPro or KEGG termbThe percentages of non-SCCS genes that have the InterPro or KEGG term.cThe fold of ‘a’ to ‘b’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Terms are listed in the descending order of the fold difference.*Probability for enrichment of the InterPro or KEGG terms in the SCCS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>The all terms in GO Biological process section is related to developmental process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>One term of Cellular components (GO:0014704) mediate mechanical and electrochemical integration between cardiomyocytes and the rest of the five (GO:0043198, GO:0030425, GO:0043025, GO:0015629, and GO:0043005) have an association with the neuron. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>In the molecular function category, three terms (GO:0004843, GO:0031625, and GO:0004221) are related to the ubiquitin system, two (GO:00042054 and GO:00003682) are associated with chromatin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Ubiquitins are known to be involved not only with protein degeneration but also with signal transduction, chromatin modification, and cell cycle. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Of the ten Interpro codes listed in Table 3, IPR001827 is related to ubiquitin and IPR002077 represents calcium channel and other eight are all associated with DNA or RNA-binding functions that mediate transcriptional regulation or chromatin modification. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Tow KEGG pathways (hsa04340 and hsa04310) in Table 3 are developmental signalling pathways, hsa04120 is related to the ubiquitin system, and hsa04360 is involved in axon guidance, which well corresponds with the GO and Interpro terms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Table 4 shows the terms that are significantly scarce in SCCS genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>In contrast to Tables 2 and 3, majority of the terms are involved with metabolic processes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Fatigo can also explore enrichment of micro RNA target and transcription-factor-binding sites; no significant item was found. Table 4.GO, InterPro and KEGG terms significantly (P &lt; 0.01) scarce in SCCS genesTermsP*In SCCS containing genes (%)aIn non-SCCS containing genes (%)bFoldcBiological processGO:0043039: tRNA aminoacylation6.15E−030.090.630.14 GO:0006725: Cellular aromatic compound metabolic process7.31E−030.481.30.37 GO:0051186: Cofactor metabolic process6.05E−030.661.590.42 GO:0055114: Oxidation-reduction process5.86E−042.113.870.55 GO:0019752: Carboxylic acid metabolic process3.54E−042.424.340.56 GO:0006082: Organic acid metabolic process3.54E−042.424.350.56 GO:0044255: Cellular lipid metabolic process8.60E−033.34.980.66Cellular component GO:0019866: Organelle inner membrane2.38E−030.661.720.38 GO:0044429: Mitochondrial part1.27E−031.633.240.50 GO:0005615: Extracellular space2.87E−032.293.930.58Molecular function GO:0001595: Angiotensin receptor activity8.64E−0300.40.00 GO:0016616: Oxidoreductase activity, acting on the CH-OH group of donors, NAD or NADP as acceptor6.42E−030.180.820.22 GO:0016614: Oxidoreductase activity, acting on CH-OH group of donors8.92E−030.260.970.27Interpro IPR002198: Short-chain dehydrogenase/reductase SDR8.96E−0300.460.00Kegg hsa04060: Cytokine–cytokine receptor interaction2.86E−030.571.560.37aThe percentages of SCCS genes that have the GO, InterPro or KEGG term.bThe percentages of non-SCCS genes that have the GO, InterPro or KEGG term.cThe fold of ‘a’ to ‘b’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Terms are listed in the ascending order of the fold difference.*Probability for enrichment of the GO, InterPro or KEGG terms in the SCCS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3c"><label>3.3.</label><title><text><SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Overlap with UCEs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>UCEs are defined as nucleotide sequences that are absolutely conserved longer than 200 bp between orthologous regions of the human, rat and mouse.18,19 UCEs are found in both coding and non-coding regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Precedent studies report that genes with low synonymous substitution or genes overlapped with UCEs are associated with DNA binding, RNA binding, transcription activity, and Homeobox.18,19 In our 10 790 genes, 4009 bp in 29 genes are found to overlap with UCEs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>In the 4009 bp region, 2835 bp in 22 genes overlap with SCCSs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dsr010/DC1">Supplementary file S4</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Because SCCSs are conserved in six mammalian species, including the three species referred for UCEs, the 2835 bp reflect conservation in other three species (macaque, cow, and dog). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>We surveyed nucleotide sites in the 10 790 genes that are conserved among human, rat, and mouse, and evaluated how many of them are also conserved in macaque, cow, and dog. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>The resulted ratio is 0.751; therefore the expected conservation is 3035 bp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>This matches well with the observation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>The regions overlapped with UCEs make only 1.47% of the entire SCCS regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Other SCCSs convey shorter but deeper conservation than UCEs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3d"><label>3.4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>SCCSs that form stable RNA secondary structures </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>There are cases that a secondary structure of mRNA conveys functions.24,25 We examined secondary structures and free energy of the SCCSs using Vienna RNA package. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>We found three SCCSs whose folding energy were significantly low (Table 5). Table 5.Genes containing SCCS with significantly (P &lt; 0.001) low free folding energyGeneLengthFree energypolgDNA polymerase subunit gamma-136−19.9gal3st3Galactose-3-O-sulfotransferase 336−22.6smarcd3SWI/SNF-related matrix-associated actin-dependent regulator of chromatin subfamily D member39−23.9The gene names are represented by those of human. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Polg encodes a catalytic subunit of mitochondrial DNA polymerase POLG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>The POLG protein is the only polymerase known to be involved in replication of mtDNA. Gal3st3 encodes a member of the galactose-3-O-sulfotransferase protein family. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This protein exists on the membrane of Golgi apparatus. Smarcd3 encodes a protein of SWI/SNF family, whose members display helicase and ATPase activities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>This protein is thought to regulate transcription of target genes by altering the chromatin structure around those genes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 shows the probability density of the folding free energy constructed by randomly extracted sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Each line shows the free energy of the sequences of the same length as the above three SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Gene names on the lines represent free energy of the SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>This figure suggests that these three SCCSs have extremely low free energy and that these regions will form stable secondary structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>These SCCSs may be conserved because of the requirement for the secondary structures. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>However, substitution restriction of this type might be modest because a secondary structure can be retained by another combination of nucleotides as far as the complementarity is maintained. Figure 2.The probability density of the folding free energy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>This graph shows the probability density of the folding free energy for 36 and 39 nucleotide-long sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>The three SCCSs with significantly low free energy are indicated on the graph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Probability density was created using software package R.38 </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3e"><label>3.5.</label><title><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The density of exonic splicing enhancers in SCCSs and in the other coding regions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>One of the well-known functional nucleotide elements in the coding region is splicing signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>We obtained 238 hexamers from RESCUE-ESE Web server as candidates of exonic splicing enhancers, and counted the number of hexamers in SCCSs and non-SCCS regions of the 10 790 genes (Table 6). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Splicing signals in non-SCCS regions are counted on human sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>We observed 20 420 hits of signals in 192 306 bp of SCCS regions and 2 183 544 hits in 205 666 520 of non-SCCS regions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>The number of the signals per nucleotide is both 0.106 for SCCS and non-SCCS, and there was no significant difference (P = 0.99, χ2 test). Table 6.Splicing signals in SCCS and non-SCCS regions of 10 790 genesRegion size (bp)#Splicing signalsPer nucleotideSCCS192 30620 4200.106Non-SCCS20 566 5202 183 5440.106Splicing signals in non-SCCS regions are counted on human sequences. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3f"><label>3.6.</label><title><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Gene expression </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>We investigated the difference of gene expression between SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes referring to anatomical system data of EGenetics, which give qualitative information about in what organs a gene is expressed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>We counted the number of SCCS genes and non-SCCS genes expressed in the organs and performed the Fisher's exact test as described in Materials and method section. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>We compared the percentages of genes that are expressed in each organ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Table 7 shows organs in which significantly higher percentage of SCCS genes are expressed compared with non-SCCS genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>In general, SCCS genes are expressed in a wider variety of organs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>This observation agrees with a previous study.35 Only in medulla oblongata and trophoblast, non-SCCS genes showed significantly higher percentage than SCCS genes (data not shown). Table 7.Organs in which significantly (P &lt; 0.001) higher percentage of SCCS genes are expressed compared with non-SCCS genesOrganP*SCCSNon-SCCSFoldc#ExpressedPercentagea#ExpressedPercentagebAmygdala1.32E−112019.863185.371.84Cochlea1.24E−2243621.3972312.211.75Small intestine5.28E−03492.40861.451.66Amnion1.03E−041025.001833.091.62Amniotic fluid9.12E−071758.593215.421.58Spinal cord7.21E−051296.332434.101.54Artery9.80E−051336.532544.291.52Cerebellum cortex2.74E−03834.071602.701.51Cerebellum3.62E−0827713.595439.171.48Trabecular meshwork1.38E−051999.763996.741.45Frontal lobe1.63E−2889944.11180330.451.45Hypopharynx1.75E−0624612.074978.391.44Pituitary gland1.67E−0942120.6687714.811.39Sympathetic chain9.65E−0627113.305759.711.37Breast5.95E−30113355.59243041.041.35Larynx9.05E−1364231.50138523.391.35Tongue4.55E−0737718.5081613.781.34Smooth muscle1.36E−0530715.0667011.321.33Thyroid3.36E−23107652.80237540.111.32Adrenal gland4.51E−0636217.7680113.531.31aThe percentages of SCCS genes that are expressed in the organ.bThe percentages of non-SCCS genes that are expressed in the organ.cThe fold of ‘a’ to ‘b’ Terms are listed in the descending order of the fold difference.*Probability for enrichment of the expressed genes in the SCCS group. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Seven organs (amygdala, spinal cord, cerebellum cortex, cerebellum, frontal lobe, pituitary grand, and sympathetic chain) in Table 7 are related with the nervous system and six organs (cochlea, trabecular meshwork, hypopharynx, larynx, tongue, and thyroid) are associated with head and neck. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s3g"><label>3.7.</label><title><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Preferred codons, GC content, and codon degeneracy of SCCSs </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Codon usage biases towards optimum codons are known to suppress synonymous substitution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>Optimum codons reflect the composition of the genomic tRNA pool and are advantageous for translation efficiency or accuracy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>As the approximate index of optimum codons, we used preferred codons, or most frequently used codon for an amino acid, and evaluated the preferred codon fraction in SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>In SCCS regions, 28 188 of 64 102 codons are preferred codons and in non-SCCS regions, 2 961 482 of 6 855 505 codons are preferred codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>The ratio of preferred codons in SCCS and non-SCCS regions are 0.440 and 0.432, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The difference is significant at the 0.05 significance level (P = 0.013) but the difference of the ratios is merely 0.008. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>We also observed that the ratio of preferred codon decreases as the length of SCCS increases (Fig. 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Judging from these results, SCCSs are unlikely to be retained solely by codon preference. Figure 3.The ratio of preferred codons in SCCSs. X-axis represents the length of SCCSs, and Y-axis represents the ratio of preferred codon of the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>Classes whose sample size &lt; 20 were combined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent 1 SE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>In mammals, of the influence GC content on nucleotide change as a result of CpG hyper mutability. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>We investigated GC content of SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>GC content in the first (GC1), second (GC2), and third position (GC3) of codons show different patterns along the sequence length (Fig. 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>GC1 is mostly constant but GC2 increases while GC3 decreases as the length of SCCS increases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Because mammalian genomes prefer GC-ending codons, the decrease of GC3 corresponds to the decrease of preferred codons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The decrease of GC3 seems to be complementary with the increase of GC2 because GC content as a whole is constant (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dsr010/DC1">Supplementary Fig. S1</ext-link>). Figure 4.GC content of the first (GC1), the second (GC2), and the third (GC3) position of codons in SCCSs: (A) GC1, (B) GC2, (C) GC3. X-axis represents the length of SCCSs, and Y-axis represents GC content of the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Classes whose sample size &lt; 20 were combined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent 1 SE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>Conservation of SCCSs may occur by chance in a region where amino acid constraint is strong and codon degeneracy is low. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>We investigated codon degeneracy of SCCSs to examine this possibility. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>The average degeneracy is between three and four and increases as the sequence length increases (Fig. 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>This result suggests that even if the first and second positions of codons are restricted, the third position has enough freedom to change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Therefore, it is unlikely that SCCSs are conserved because of the amino acid constraint combined with the low degeneracy of codons. Figure 5.Codon degeneracy of SCCSs. X-axis represents the length of SCCSs and Y-axis represents the averaged codon degeneracy of the sequences. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Classes whose sample size &lt; 20 were combined. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Error bars represent 1 SE. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><label>4.</label><title><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>GO terms, InterPro codes, and KEGG pathways enriched with SCCS genes show a strong commitment to the developmental process, transcriptional regulation, and the neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>Genes associated with transcriptional regulation or the neurons are known to have a low synonymous substitution ratio. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>This phenomenon is discussed in relation with codon biases to improve translational efficiency or accuracy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>However, our analysis on the preferred codons in SCCSs suggests that codon preference is not likely the major factor influencing on the conservation of SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Analyses on the ratio of preferred codons, GC content, and codon degeneracy enlighten the characteristics of SCCSs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>The ratio of preferred codons decreases as the SCCS length increases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Drummond and Wilke36 investigated the correlation between synonymous substitution rate (dS) and fraction of optimum (Fop) codons, and detected negative correlations between dS and Fop in rodents (mouse and rat) and positive correlation in human–dog comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>If the SCCSs have the same trend as the rodents of the previous study, the ratio of preferred codons in SCCSs should be high; however, our result is not. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>There was no factor that would lower nucleotide substitution in GC content and codon degeneracy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Methodological difference is that our research focused on local and complete conservation of nucleotides instead of the dS in the entire region of a gene and that we investigated conservation among the six mammalian species instead of a pair-wise comparison. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The difference of results may suggest that factors underlying local and strong conservation such as SCCS differ from the factors working on the gene-wide conservation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Makalowski et al.37 showed a correlation between synonymous substitution rate (dS) and non-synonymous substitution rate (dN). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Such correlations may occur when the constraint on a certain nucleotide sequence is so strong that dN is also lowered. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>The usage of relatively rare codons and strong local conservation of SCCSs may be preferable as regulatory signals. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>The fraction of SCCSs in the coding region of the 10 790 genes is 0.94%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>This fraction is so small that it would not have an influence on conventional evolutionary analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Although the fraction is small, or because the fraction is small, SCCSs may have potential as regulatory elements. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec id="s5"><title><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/dsr010/DC1">Supplementary Data are available at www.dnaresearch.oxfordjournals.org</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec id="s6"><title><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>This study was supported partly by Grant-in-Aid for scientific research from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology of Japan to N.S. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag>
      <SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
         <title><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
         <supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
            <caption>
               <title><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Data </plain></SENT>
</text></title>
            </caption>
            <media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_18_3_177__index.html"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword" xlink:href="supp_dsr010_dsr010supp.doc"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_dsr010_dsr010supp_table1.xls"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_dsr010_dsr010supp_table2.xls"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_dsr010_dsr010supp_table3.xls"/>
            <media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel" xlink:href="supp_dsr010_dsr010supp_table4.xls"/>
         </supplementary-material>
      </sec></SecTag>
   </body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>We thank Drs Kenta Sumiyama, Kiyoshi Ezawa, and Hiroshi Akashi for their insightful suggestion and discussion. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="DSR010C1"><text><SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>1KimuraM.The Neutral Theory of Molecular Evolution1983CambridgeCambridge University Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C2"><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>2NeiM.Molecular Evolutionary Genetics1987New YorkColumbia Univ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C3"><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>3IkemuraT.Correlation between the abundance of yeast transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in protein genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Differences in synonymous codon choice patterns of yeast and Escherichia coli with reference to the abundance of isoaccepting transfer RNAsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>Biol.198215857397<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0022-2836(82)90250-9">doi:10.1016/0022-2836(82)90250-9</ext-link>6750137 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C4"><text><SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>4IkemuraT.Correlation between the abundance of Escherichia coli transfer RNAs and the occurrence of the respective codons in its protein genes: a proposal for a synonymous codon choice that is optimal for the E. coli translational systemJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>Biol.1981151389409<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0022-2836(81)90003-6">doi:10.1016/0022-2836(81)90003-6</ext-link>6175758 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C5"><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>5KanayaS.YamadaY.KinouchiM.KudoY.,IkemuraT.Codon usage and tRNA genes in eukaryotes: correlation of codon usage diversity with translation efficiency and with CG-dinucleotide usage as assessed by multivariate analysisJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Evol.2001532908<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s002390010219">doi:10.1007/s002390010219</ext-link>11675589 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C6"><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>6AkashiH.Synonymous codon usage in Drosophila melanogaster: natural selection and translational accuracyGenetics1994136927358005445 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C7"><text><SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>7KurlandC.G.Codon bias and gene expressionFEBS Lett.19912851659<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0014-5793(91)80797-7">doi:10.1016/0014-5793(91)80797-7</ext-link>1855585 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C8"><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>8HershbergR.,PetrovD.A.Selection on codon biasAnnu. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Genet.20084228799<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev.genet.42.110807.091442">doi:10.1146/annurev.genet.42.110807.091442</ext-link>18983258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C9"><text><SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>9IkemuraT.Codon usage and tRNA content in unicellular and multicellular organismsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Evol.1985213343916708 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C10"><text><SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>10SharpP.M.,LiW.H.The rate of synonymous substitution in enterobacterial genes is inversely related to codon usage biasMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Evol.19874222303328816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C11"><text><SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>11AkashiH.Translational selection and yeast proteome evolutionGenetics2003164129130312930740 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C12"><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>12Eyre-WalkerA.C.An analysis of codon usage in mammals: selection or mutation bias?J. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Evol.1991334429<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/BF02103136">doi:10.1007/BF02103136</ext-link>1960741 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C13"><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>13SharpP.M.AverofM.LloydA.T.MatassiG.,PedenJ.F.DNA sequence evolution: the sounds of silencePhilos. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>Trans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>R Soc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Lond. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>B Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Sci.19953492417<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1098/rstb.1995.0108">doi:10.1098/rstb.1995.0108</ext-link>8577834 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C14"><text><SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>14ReedR.Initial splice-site recognition and pairing during pre-mRNA splicingCurr. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Opin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>Genet. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Dev.1996621520<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0959-437X(96)80053-0">doi:10.1016/S0959-437X(96)80053-0</ext-link>8722179 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C15"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>15BlencoweB.J.Exonic splicing enhancers: mechanism of action, diversity and role in human genetic diseasesTrends Biochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>Sci20002510610<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0968-0004(00)01549-8">doi:10.1016/S0968-0004(00)01549-8</ext-link>10694877 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C16"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>16TakahashiA.Effect of exonic splicing regulation on synonymous codon usage in alternatively spliced exons of DscamBMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>Biol20099214<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-9-214">doi:10.1186/1471-2148-9-214</ext-link>19709440 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C17"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>17ParmleyJ.L.,HurstL.D.Exonic splicing regulatory elements skew synonymous codon usage near intron-exon boundaries in mammalsMol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>Biol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>Evol20072416003<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msm104">doi:10.1093/molbev/msm104</ext-link>17525472 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C18"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>18BejeranoG.PheasantM.MakuninI.Ultraconserved elements in the human genomeScience200430413215<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1098119">doi:10.1126/science.1098119</ext-link>15131266 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C19"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>19SchattnerP.,DiekhansM.Regions of extreme synonymous codon selection in mammalian genesNucleic Acids Res200634170010<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkl095">doi:10.1093/nar/gkl095</ext-link>16556911 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C20"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>20LareauL.F.InadaM.GreenR.E.WengrodJ.C.,BrennerS.E.Unproductive splicing of SR genes associated with highly conserved and ultraconserved DNA elementsNature20074469269<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature05676">doi:10.1038/nature05676</ext-link>17361132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C21"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>21LinZ.MaH.,NeiM.Ultraconserved coding regions outside the homeobox of mammalian Hox genesBMC Evol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>Biol20088260<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2148-8-260">doi:10.1186/1471-2148-8-260</ext-link>18816392 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C22"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>22LampeX.SamadO.A.GuiguenA.An ultraconserved Hox-Pbx responsive element resides in the coding sequence of Hoxa2 and is active in rhombomere 4Nucleic Acids Res200836321425<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkn148">doi:10.1093/nar/gkn148</ext-link>18417536 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C23"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>23LicatalosiD.D.,DarnellR.B.RNA processing and its regulation: global insights into biological networksNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>Rev. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>Genet2010117587<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nrg2673">doi:10.1038/nrg2673</ext-link>20019688 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C24"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>24BhallaT.RosenthalJ.J.HolmgrenM.,ReenanR.Control of human potassium channel inactivation by editing of a small mRNA hairpinNat. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>Struct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>Biol2004119506<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nsmb825">doi:10.1038/nsmb825</ext-link>15361858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C25"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>25DelgadoM.D.GutierrezP.RichardC.CuadradoM.A.Moreau-GachelinF.,LeonJ.Spi-1/PU.1 proto-oncogene induces opposite effects on monocytic and erythroid differentiation of K562 cellsBiochem. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>Biophys. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>Res. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>Commun199825238391<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/bbrc.1998.9587">doi:10.1006/bbrc.1998.9587</ext-link>9826539 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C26"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>26DonehowerL.A.SlagleB.L.WildeM.DarlingtonG.,ButelJ.S.Identification of a conserved sequence in the non-coding regions of many human genesNucleic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>Acids Res198917699710<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/17.2.699">doi:10.1093/nar/17.2.699</ext-link>2536922 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C27"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>27LipmanD.J.Making (anti)sense of non-coding sequence conservationNucleic Acids Res.19972535803<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/25.18.3580">doi:10.1093/nar/25.18.3580</ext-link>9278476 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C28"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>28LevyS.HannenhalliS.,WorkmanC.Enrichment of regulatory signals in conserved non-coding genomic sequenceBioinformatics2001178717<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/17.10.871">doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/17.10.871</ext-link>11673231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C29"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>29SandelinA.BaileyP.BruceS.Arrays of ultraconserved non-coding regions span the loci of key developmental genes in vertebrate genomesBMC Genomics2004599<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-5-99">doi:10.1186/1471-2164-5-99</ext-link>15613238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C30"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>30KryukovG.V.SchmidtS.,SunyaevS.Small fitness effect of mutations in highly conserved non-coding regionsHum. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>Genet20051422219<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/hmg/ddi226">doi:10.1093/hmg/ddi226</ext-link>15994173 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C31"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>31HubbardT.J.AkenB.L.BealK.Ensembl 2007Nucleic Acids Res200735D6107<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkl996">doi:10.1093/nar/gkl996</ext-link>17148474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C32"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>32ThompsonJ.D.HigginsD.G.,GibsonT.J.CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choiceNucleic Acids Res199422467380<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/22.22.4673">doi:10.1093/nar/22.22.4673</ext-link>7984417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C33"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>33BenjaminiY.DraiD.ElmerG.KafkafiN.,GolaniI.Controlling the false discovery rate in behavior genetics researchBehav. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>Brain Res200112527984<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0166-4328(01)00297-2">doi:10.1016/S0166-4328(01)00297-2</ext-link>11682119 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C34"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>34FairbrotherW.G.YehR.F.SharpP.A.,BurgeC.B.Predictive identification of exonic splicing enhancers in human genesScience2002297100713<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1126/science.1073774">doi:10.1126/science.1073774</ext-link>12114529 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C35"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>35PlotkinJ.B.RobinsH.,LevineA.J.Tissue-specific codon usage and the expression of human genesProc. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>Natl. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>Acad. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>Sci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>USA20041011258891<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0404957101">doi:10.1073/pnas.0404957101</ext-link>15314228 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C36"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>36DrummondD.A.,WilkeC.O.Mistranslation-induced protein misfolding as a dominant constraint on coding-sequence evolutionCell200813434152<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2008.05.042">doi:10.1016/j.cell.2008.05.042</ext-link>18662548 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C37"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>37MakalowskiW.,BoguskiM.S.Synonymous and nonsynonymous substitution distances are correlated in mouse and rat genesJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>Mol. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>Evol19984711921<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/PL00006367">doi:10.1007/PL00006367</ext-link>9694659 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="DSR010C38"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>38IhakaR.,GentlemanR.R: a language for data analysis and graphicsJ. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>Comp. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>Graph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>Stat19965299314<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/1390807">doi:10.2307/1390807</ext-link> </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
