<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ScientificWorldJournal</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">TSWJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Scientific World Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2356-6140</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1537-744X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi Publishing Corporation</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3703906</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2013/174392</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Dual Silencing of Hsp27 and c-FLIP Enhances Doxazosin-Induced Apoptosis in PC-3 Prostate Cancer Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Sang Soo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Hee-Ju</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>Jeong-Man</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Jung Yoon</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Hyun-Won</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoo</surname><given-names>Tag Keun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><sup>1</sup>Eulji Medi-Bio Research Institute, Seoul 139-871, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="I2"><sup>2</sup>Department of Urology, College of Medicine, Eulji University, Hangeulbiseok-gil, Hagye-dong, Nowon-ku, Seoul 139-871, Republic of Korea</aff><aff id="I3"><sup>3</sup>Department of Biotechnology, Seoul Women's University, Seoul 139-871, Republic of Korea</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">*Tag Keun Yoo: <email>ytk5202@eulji.ac.kr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Academic Editors: A. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Tefekli, V. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>Tugcu, and M. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Tunc </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2013</volume><elocation-id>174392</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2013 Sang Soo Kim et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><license xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution,
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>We evaluated effect of dual gene silencing of Hsp27 and c-FLIP in doxazosin-induced apoptosis of PC-3 cell. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>After transfection using Hsp27 and c-FLIP siRNA mixture (dual silencing), doxazosin treatment was done at the concentrations of 1, 10, and 25 μM. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We checked apoptosis of PC-3 cells with and TUNEL staining. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>We also checked interaction between Hsp27 and C-FLIP in the process of apoptosis inhibition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Spontaneous apoptotic index was 5% under single gene silencing of Hsp27 and c-FLIP and 7% under dual silencing of Hsp27 and c-FLIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>When doxazosin treatment was added, apoptotic indices increased in a dose-dependent manner (1, 10, and 25 μM): nonsilencing 10, 27, and 52%; Hsp27-silencing: 14, 35, and 68%; c-FLIP silencing: 21, 46, and 78%; dual silencing: 38, 76, and 92%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>While c-FLIP gene expression decreased in Hsp27- silenced cells, Hsp27 gene expression showed markedly decreased pattern in the cells of c-FLIP silencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The knockout of c-FLIP and Hsp27 genes together enhances apoptosis even under 1 μM, rather than low concentration, of doxazosin in PC-3 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This finding suggests a new strategy of multiple knockout of antiapoptotic and survival factors in the treatment of late-stage prostate cancer refractory to conventional therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Advanced prostate cancers eventually progress to the terminal stage of castration refractory prostate cancer (CRPC) which is not responsive to most of treatment modalities. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>Docetaxel-based chemotherapy has been the mainstay of treatment for this metastatic CRPC, and recently, other anticancer drugs such as cabazitaxel or abiraterone acetate are allowed for use, but their therapeutic benefits are still not that sufficient [1–4]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Researchers consider some defects in apoptotic signaling pathway or abnormal overexpression of antiapoptotic factors as the main causes of treatment resistance in patients with late-stage prostate cancer [5]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Among those antiapoptotic factors, bcl-2 [6], clusterin [7], heat shock prostein 27 (Hsp27) [8, 9], cellular-FLICE inhibitory protein (c-FLIP) [10], and GRP78 [11] have been widely reported. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Overexpression of these factors could be induced by androgen deprivation therapy (ADT), chemotherapy, or other extreme stresses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Recently, new therapeutic ways of blocking these factors are being developed as new drugs, and among them, clusterin ASO is now on Phase 3 clinical trial [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>While knockdown of each factor alone can exert apoptosis inducing effect, blocking several factors which have some different pathways together may enhance apoptosis in prostate cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This concept can be applied to the development of new therapy against prostate cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Hsp27, one of small Hsps, inhibits key effectors of the apoptotic pathway at the pre- and postmitochondria levels [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In prostate cancer, Hsp27 is associated with pathologic stage, Gleason score, lymph node metastasis, shorter biochemical recurrence, and poor clinical outcome [14, 15]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>The c-FLIP is an inhibitor of apoptosis downstream of the death receptors Fas, DE4, and DR5 [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The expression of c-FLIP is closely related to the resistance to tumor necrosis factor-related apoptosis-inducing ligand (TRAIL) and FAS-mediated apoptosis in prostate and bladder cancers [17–19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Therefore, c-FLIP is regarded as a new therapeutic target for relevant cancers [20]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Dual silencing is reported to be effective in augmenting biologic effect on laboratory level and technically feasible [21]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Doxazosin, an quinazoline derivative α1 adrenoreceptor antagonist, has been known to exert antitumor effect via induction of apoptosis in PC-3 cancer cells [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Doxazosin induces apoptosis via not an α1-adrenoceptor-dependent action but a death receptor-mediated pathway [23]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In this present study, we investigated the enhanced effect of double knockout of Hsp27 and c-FLIP genes using siRNA technology in PC-3 prostate cancer cells and also tried to find out whether there is any interactive role between the 2 factors by observing the expression of one factor under silencing of the other factor. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="sec2"><title><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>Materials and Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec2.1"><title><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>2.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Cell Lines </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>PC-3 cells obtained from American Type Culture Collection (Bethesda, MD, USA) were maintained in F-12 medium. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>We compared as group treated scrambled siRNA, AI-LNCaP-scr-siRNA. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title><text><SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>2.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Doxazosin Treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Doxazosin (Sigma Aldrich Korea, Seoul, Korea) was prepared as described in a previous study [7]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Cultures at 80% confluence were changed to fresh media and treated with doxazosin or serum-free media containing 0.25% DMSO as control. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>2.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Transfection with siRNA </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>The mRNA target sequences to Hsp27 (GeneBank Accession no. X54079.1) and c-FLIP (Gene ID: 8837) were designed using a siRNA template design tool (Ambion, Austin, TX, USA), and siRNA was prepared with a Silencer siRNA construction kit (Ambion). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Three oligonucleotides Hsp27-1 (5′-GACCUACCGAGGAGCUUUCdTT-3′), Hsp27-2 (5′-UCGAGGCCCUGUAACUUG-3′), and Hsp27-3 (5′-CAGUAGUUCGGACAAACGAAGA-3′) were designed based on the publicly released Hsp27 DNA sequence and another three oligonucleotides FLIP-1, FLIP-2, and FLIP-3 designed for c-FLIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>The siRNAs were transfected into PC-3 cells with Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen) employing 50 nM in 250 μL Opti-MEM medium/60 mm culture dish. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>The transfected cells were allowed to grow for 24, 48, and 72 h at 37°C in a 5% CO2 incubator. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>2.4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>Total RNA Extraction, Conventional RT-PCR, and Real-Time RT-PCR </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Total RNA was extracted using the TRIzol method (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Cells (5.0 × 105) were mixed in a test tube with 1 mL TRIzol solution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Prepared RNA was denaturated at 65°C for 15 min in a volume of 30 μL and cooled on ice for at least 1 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>2.0 μg of denatured RNA were then annealed by addition of reaction mixture to a total volume of 20 μL (4.0 μL of 5× RT buffer, 10 pmol of primers, 2.0 μL of 25 mM MgCl2, 2.0 μL of 10 mM dNTPs, and 0.2 μL of 1 M DTT in nuclease-free water) and incubated at 42°C for 70 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>The reaction was terminated at 95°C for 5 min, chilled on ice for 5 min and collected by brief centrifugation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>To remove RNA, 1 μL of RNase H was added to each tube followed by incubation at 37°C for 20 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>1 μL of cDNA was used for each PCR reaction. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>PCR was performed with an SLAN real-time PCR detection system (LG Life Science, Korea) and SYBR Green reagents (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Specific primers for human GAPDH, Hsp27, and c-FLIP were designed to work in the same cycling conditions (50°C for 2 min to permit uracil N-glycosylase cleavage, 95°C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 s, and 60°C for 1 min). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>The specificity of the nucleotide sequences chosen was confirmed by conducting basic local alignment search tool searches. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>We used 1.0 μL of the reverse transcriptase product for PCR in a final volume of 25 μL. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>2.5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>Western Blot Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Preparation of total cell lysate and the procedures for Western blot analyses were performed essentially as described previously [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>The antibody against c-FLIP was purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Antibody for Hsp27 was purchased from Millipore (Millipore, MA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The quantity of the applied protein was normalized with anti-actin polyclonal antibody (Sigma Aldrich Korea, Seoul, Korea). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Samples with equal amounts of protein (20 μg) from lysates of cultured PC-3 cells were subjected to SDS-PAGE and then transferred to a PVDF filter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The filters were blocked in TBS containing 5% nonfat milk powder at 4°C overnight and then incubated with each of diluted primary antibodies (Actin: 1 :  10,000; Hsp27: 1 : 1,000; c-FLIP: 1 : 2,000; Santa Cruz, CA, USA) for 1 hour. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.6"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>2.6. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescence and TUNEL Staining </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Cells on coverslips were rinsed with 1× phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and then fixed with ice-cold methanol for 15 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Samples were further permeabilized with PBS containing 0.025% Triton-X detergent (1× PBS-TX) for 10 min and blocked with 3% BSA in 1× PBS for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Cells were incubated with each of the primary antibodies (Hsp27: 1 : 100; c-FLIP: 1 : 50; Santa Cruz, CA, USA) for 1 hour at room temperature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Cells were washed 3 times for 5 mins with 1× PBS-TX and then incubated with green fluorescent- (FITC-) conjugated secondary antibodies (goat anti-mouse IgG and goat anti-rabbit IgG, Santa Cruz, CA, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33258 (Sigma Chemical, St. Louis, MO, USA). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>For TUNEL assays, fixed cells were incubated with an equilibrium buffer for 5 min using the in situ apoptosis detection kit, Fluorescein (ApopTag; Roche, BMS), and then treated in reaction buffer with 10 units of terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase and 1 unit of deoxyuridine triphosphate-digoxigenin at 37°C for 1 hour. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The reaction was terminated by adding stop/wash buffer and then washed twice with Tris buffer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Antidigoxigenin-FITC was added and reacted at 37°C for 30 min. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>After washing with distilled water, nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33258 (Sigma Chemical, St. Louis, MO, USA), and apoptosis in the cells was observed under a fluorescent microscope. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Cells with green fluorescent (FITC) colored nuclei were considered apoptotic. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>For quantifying apoptotic cells, apoptotic and total cells were counted in 5 random fields scoring between 300 and 500 cells, and the numbers of apoptotic cells were expressed as percentages of the total cell population. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Immunofluorescent staining slides and TUNEL staining slides were observed with microscope (TE-300, Nikon, Japan). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec2.7"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>2.7. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Statistical Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Data are expressed as mean ± SD or median (interquartile range). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="sec3.1"><title><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>3.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>Assessment for Hsp27 and c-FLIP RNA Interference with siRNAs in PC-3 Cells </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>For downregulation of Hsp27 expression in PC-3 cells, three different Hsp27-specific siRNAs (Hsp27-1, Hsp27-2, and Hsp27-3) were used for transfection studies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>As a control, cells were transfected with siRNA against scrambled sequence. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>To determine the efficiency of the downregulation of Hsp27 expression in PC-3 cells, mRNA levels of Hsp27 were counted by RT-PCR. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Forty-eight hours after transfection, Hsp27-2 siRNA downregulated Hsp27 mRNA level to approximately 17% of control level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>The downregulation of Hsp27 expression caused by Hsp27-2 siRNA-mediated silencing was maintained until 72 hours (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>Similar to Hsp27, three kinds of siRNAs (c-FLIP-1, c-FLIP-2, and c-FLIP-3) were used for c-FLIP silencing in PC-3 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>c-FLIP-1 siRNA downregulated c-FLIP mRNA level to approximately 14% of control level after 48 hours of transfection. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Among three siRNAs, The c-FLIP-1 siRNA-mediated silencing decreased c-FLIP mRNA expression until 72 hours (Figure 1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>Endogeneous expression of Hsp27 in Hsp27-2 siRNA-transfected PC-3 cells was reduced approximately to 14.6% of control level after 48 hours after transfection when measured by Western blot analysis with an anti-Hsp27 antibody (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Likewise, Western blot analysis for anti-c-FLIP antibody also revealed the reduction of endogeneous c-FLIP expression in c-FLIP-1 siRNA-transfected PC-3 cells in 18.7% after 48 hours and maintained until 72 hours (Figure 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.2"><title><text><SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>3.2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>TUNEL Analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>Figure 3 shows the results of Hoechst and TUNEL fluorescent staining for nuclear morphology and patterns of apoptosis in Hsp27 and c-FLIP gene silenced PC-3 cells when treated with doxazosin (1, 10, and 25 μM) for 24 hours. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Nuclear condensation and fragmentation, characteristic findings of apoptosis, were found in TUNEL-positive cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>In the cells without siRNA transfection, the number of TUNEL-positive cells was minimal under 1 μM of doxazosin treatment, but it increased gradually in a dose-dependent manner, and finally a significant number of apoptotic bodies were observed under 25 μM of doxazosin treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Compared to the nonsilenced cells, in the cells transfected with either siRNA targeting Hsp27 or c-FLIP genes, the numbers of TUNEL-positive cells were increased in all concentrations of doxazosin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>And when they were transfected with both siRNAs targeting Hsp27 and c-FLIP gene together, the number of TUNEL-positive cells was increased more significantly in all concentrations of doxazosin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>In this group of cells, TUNEL-positive cells were visible quite a lot even with 1 μM of doxazosin treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>Spontaneous apoptotic index was 5% under single gene silencing of Hsp27 or c-FLIP and 7% under dual silencing of Hsp27 and c-FLIP genes together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>When doxazosin treatment was added, apoptotic indices increased in the dose-dependent manner (1, 10, and 25 μM): nonsilencing 10, 27, and 52%; Hsp27 silencing: 14, 35, and 68%; c-FLIP silencing: 21, 46, and 78%; dual gene silencing: 38, 76, and 92% (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>Annexin V staining showed similar findings (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="sec3.3"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>3.3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Cross-Checking for Hsp27 and c-FLIP RNA Interference with siRNA for PC-3 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>The interaction between 2 factors is investigated by observing the expression of one factor under silencing of the other factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>When Hsp27 is silenced successfully, c-FLIP gene expression was suppressed, and when c-FLIP was inhibited by siRNA transfection, Hsp27 gene expression was also downregulated (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Similar findings were observed in protein level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Western blot analysis showed that when c-FLIP was inhibited by siRNA transfection, Hsp27 protein expression was downregulated, and protein expression of c-FLIP was suppressed when Hsp27 gene was silenced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>Addition of 1 μM of doxazosin enhanced downregulation of c-FLIP protein expression induced by Hsp27 gene silencing (37.5% → 16.4%) (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The experimental dose of doxazosin, 10–25 μM, is relatively higher than the serum concentration of patients treated with doxazosin for their lower urinary tract symptoms (LUTS) [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>Thus, doxazosin at clinical dose cannot induce significant apoptosis in the patients with prostate cancer. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Therefore, the findings of new mechanisms showing the induction of apoptosis at very low concentrations of doxazosin may provide an evidence to put doxazosin as a new drug candidate for treatment of prostate cancer [25]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Commonly used siRNA introduction techniques are either direct introduction by transfection or introduction via plasmids that express short-hairpin RNA (shRNA) precursors of siRNA [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>In this study, siRNA was introduced by the direct transfection way. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>We selected a proper oligo which could knock out Hsp27 or c-FLIP gene after 48 hours of siRNA transfection. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Rocchi et al. reported the effect of synthetic siRNA targeting Hsp27 in PC-3 and LNCaP cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>According to their reports, 1 nM of siRNA was effective to downregulate Hsp27 in mRNA and protein levels, resulting in 2.4–4-fold increase of apoptotic rates and 40%–76% inhibition of cell growth. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Characteristic cleavage of caspase-3 was also observed [27]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>Day et al. reported c-FLIP knockdown in MCF-7 breast cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>They observed knockdown of c-FLIP gene with siRNA transfection triggering spontaneous apoptosis and inducing FADD-mediated and DR-5-mediated apoptosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>They addressed c-FLIPL not c-FLIPs for having a key role in preventing spontaneous death signaling and suggested c-FLIPL as a therapeutic target for breast cancer [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Similarly, in a report on colorectal cancer cells, Longley et al. observed that siRNA targeting c-FLIPL synergistically enhanced chemotherapy-induced apoptosis [28]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>In our present study, TUNEL-positive apoptotic cells increased twice with each siRNA transfection and increased over 60% after a dual silencing of 2 genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>After single gene silencing of Hsp27, apoptotic index was remarkably increased in 10 and 25 μM of doxazosin treatment condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Similarly, single silencing of c-FLIP gene enhanced doxazosin-induced apoptosis, but the degree of apoptosis was little higher in c-FLIP group compared to Hsp27 group. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>It can be speculated that while both factors are working as antiapoptotic factors significantly, c-FLIP plays bigger role in resisting doxazosin-induced apoptosis in PC-3 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>siRNA technology can be used in combined knockdown of two genes involved in carcinogenesis or cancer progression via dual silencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>Kaulfuβ and colleagues reported that dual silencing of insulin-like growth factor receptor and epidermal growth factor receptor resulted in an increased apoptosis rate and inhibition of cell proliferation in colorectal cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Dual silencing is technically feasible and effective in augmenting biologic effect in laboratory level. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>However, it has not yet been widely established. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>The studies using this method are limited to colorectal and breast cancers and are also limited to the region of growth factor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>As far as we know, there has been no study blocking two different antiapoptotic proteins in prostate cancer cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Both Hsp27 and c-FLIP have been known as strong antiapoptotic mediators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>While c-FLIP manifests its role mainly in extrinsic apoptotic pathway, Hsp27 does mainly in mitochondrial pathway. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>For this reason, we planned to knock out these 2 factors which have different antiapoptotic mechanisms together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>We observed much more amount of apoptotic bodies when these 2 factors are blocked together by siRNA technology than individual silencing of Hsp27 or c-FLIP alone. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, this effect could be seen in low concentration of 1 μM of doxazosin. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>These show that PC-3 cells which could have resisted against apoptosis with the help of 2 survival factors became susceptible to doxazosin treatment when Hsp27 and c-FLIP are effectively knocked down together. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>If applied to clinical situations, this result suggests that multiple block of several antiapoptotic factors which are overexpressed and helped cancer cells to resist to treatment induced apoptosis can augment therapeutic effect even in very low concentration of the drug. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>We also observed that both factors interacted with each other. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>c-Flip knockout downregulated the expression of Hsp27, and similarly, silencing against Hsp27 decreased the expression of c-FLIP in RT-PCR study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>These findings suggest that antiapoptotic functions of c-FLIP and Hsp27 are closely related even when the main pathways are different. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>We previously reported that siRNA targeting androgen receptor reversed the expression of Hsp27, GRP78, clusterin, and c-FLIP in long-term cultured androgen-independent LNCaP cell lines [28, 29]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Through these observations, we can speculate that prostate cancer cells have their own peculiar features of antiapoptotic mechanisms that include close interaction between androgen receptor and several survival factors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="CONCL"><sec id="sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>5. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Dual silencing is technically feasible, and dual silencing of c-Flip and Hsp27 enhances apoptosis even under 1 μM, rather than low concentration, of doxazosin in PC-3 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>This suggests a new strategy of multiple knockout of antiapoptotic and survival factors in the treatment of late-stage prostate cancer refractory to conventional therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>We also preliminarily observed that there was interaction between c-FLIP and Hsp27 expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>Further studies revealing detailed interactions between important survival factors and androgen receptor can make another basis in reinforcing therapeutic armaments combating fatal advanced prostate cancer. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><ack><title>Conflict of Interests</title><p>All authors confirm that they have no conflict of interests.</p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by BumSuk Academic Research Fund of 2010. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="B1"><text><SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>1TannockIFDe WitRBerryWRDocetaxel plus prednisone or mitoxantrone plus prednisone for advanced prostate cancerNew England Journal of Medicine200435115150215122-s2.0-474436627915470213 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B2"><text><SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>2PetrylakDPTangenCMHussainMHADocetaxel and estramustine compared with mitoxantrone and prednisone for advanced refractory prostate cancerNew England Journal of Medicine200435115151315202-s2.0-474433771615470214 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B3"><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>3CheethamPPetrylakDPTubulin-targeted agents including docetaxel and cabazitaxelCancer Journal20131915965 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B4"><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>4SteinMNGoodinSDiPaolaRSAbiraterone in prostate cancer: a new angle to an old problemClinical Cancer Research2012187184818542-s2.0-8485939109822451619 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B5"><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>5BaiJSuiJDemirjianAVollmerCMJr.MarascoWCalleryMPPredominant Bcl-XL knockdown disables antiapoptotic mechanisms: tumor necrosis factor-related apoptosis-inducing ligand-based triple chemotherapy overcomes chemoresistance in pancreatic cancer cells in vitroCancer Research2005656234423522-s2.0-1684438131715781649 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B6"><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>6CatzSDJohnsonJLBCL-2 in prostate cancer: a minireviewApoptosis20038129372-s2.0-003724983312510149 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B7"><text><SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>7YoumYHYangHYoonY-DKimD-YLeeCYooTKDoxazosin-induced clusterin expression and apoptosis in prostate cancer cellsUrologic Oncology20072564834882-s2.0-3634900033518047956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B8"><text><SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>8RocchiPSoAKojimaSHeat shock protein 27 increases after androgen ablation and plays a cytoprotective role in hormone-refractory prostate cancerCancer Research20046418659566022-s2.0-464423733515374973 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B9"><text><SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>9GlaessgenAJonmarkerSLindbergAHeat shock proteins 27, 60 and 70 as prognostic markers of prostate cancerActa Pathologica, Microbiologica, et Immunologica Scandinavica2008116108888952-s2.0-53749093700 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B10"><text><SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>10SafaARDayTWWuC-HCellular FLICE-like inhibitory protein (C-FLIP): a novel target for cancer therapyCurrent Cancer Drug Targets20088137462-s2.0-3904914839718288942 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B11"><text><SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>11PootrakulLDatarRHShiS-RExpression of stress response protein Grp78 is associated with the development of castration-resistant prostate cancerClinical Cancer Research20061220598759932-s2.0-3375070655117062670 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B12"><text><SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>12ZoubeidiAChiKGleaveMTargeting the cytoprotective chaperone, clusterin, for treatment of advanced cancerClinical Cancer Research2010164108810932-s2.0-7674914476620145158 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B13"><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>13LanneauDde ThonelAMaurelSDidelotCGarridoCApoptosis versus cell differentiation: role of heat shock proteins HSP90, HSP70 and HSP27Prion20071153602-s2.0-6234908878919164900 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B14"><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>14CornfordPADodsonARParsonsKFHeat shock protein expression independently predicts clinical outcome in prostate cancerCancer Research20006024709971052-s2.0-003467135811156417 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B15"><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>15LeeSLKimEKKimSSUhSHChaKCYooTKExpression of heat shock protein 27 according to Gleason score and pathologic stage of prostate cancerKorean Journal of Urology20095065475522-s2.0-67650976756 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B16"><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>16DayTWHuangSSafaARc-FLIP knockdown induces ligand-independent DR5-, FADD-, caspase-8-, and caspase-9-dependent apoptosis in breast cancer cellsBiochemical Pharmacology20087612169417042-s2.0-5654911248018840411 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B17"><text><SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>17ZhangXJinT-GYangHDewolfWCKhosravi-FarROlumiAFPersistent c-FLIP(L) expression is necessary and sufficient to maintain resistance to tumor necrosis factor-related apoptosis-inducing ligand-mediated apoptosis in prostate cancerCancer Research20046419708670912-s2.0-494424810915466204 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B18"><text><SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>18KorkolopoulouPSaettaAALevidouGc-FLIP expression in colorectal carcinomas: association with Fas/FasL expression and prognostic implicationsHistopathology20075121501562-s2.0-3444751545217559541 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B19"><text><SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>19KorkolopoulouPGoudopoulouAVoutsinasGc-FLIP expression in bladder urothelial carcinomas: its role in resistance to Fas-mediated apoptosis and clinicopathologic correlationsUrology2004636119812042-s2.0-294260508615183989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B20"><text><SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>20DayTWSinnALHuangSPollokKESanduskyGESafaARC-FLIP gene silencing eliminates tumor cells in breast cancer xenografts without affecting stromal cellsAnticancer Research20092910388338862-s2.0-7194911990319846923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B21"><text><SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>21KaulfußSBurfeindPGaedckeJScharfJ-GDual silencing of insulin-like growth factor-I receptor and epidermal growth factor receptor in colorectal cancer cells is associated with decreased proliferation and enhanced apoptosisMolecular Cancer Therapeutics2009848218332-s2.0-6644909121119372555 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B22"><text><SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>22BenningCMKyprianouNQuinazoline-derived α1-adrenoceptor antagonists induce prostate cancer cell apoptosis via an α1-adrenoceptor-independent actionCancer Research20026225976022-s2.0-003707961411809715 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B23"><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>23GarrisonJBKyprianouNDoxazosin induces apoptosis of benign and malignant prostate cells via a death receptor-mediated pathwayCancer Research20066614644722-s2.0-3154444665916397262 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B24"><text><SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>24KyprianouNVaughanTBMichelMCApoptosis induction by doxazosin and other quinazoline α1-adrenoceptor antagonists: a new mechanism for cancer treatment?Naunyn-Schmiedeberg’s Archives of Pharmacology200938064734772-s2.0-71349084602 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B25"><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>25KyprianouNDoxazosin and terazosin suppress prostate growth by inducing apoptosis: clinical significanceJournal of Urology20031694152015252-s2.0-003737601112629407 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B26"><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>26KimVNRNA interference in functional genomics and medicineJournal of Korean Medical Science20031833093182-s2.0-034643389212808314 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B27"><text><SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>27RocchiPBeraldiEEttingerSIncreased Hsp27 after androgen ablation facilitates androgen-independent progression in prostate cancer via signal transducers and activators of transcription 3-mediated suppression of apoptosisCancer Research2005652311083110932-s2.0-2824445652916322258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B28"><text><SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>28LongleyDBWilsonTRMcEwanMc-FLIP inhibits chemotherapy-induced colorectal cancer cell deathOncogene20062568388482-s2.0-3254443863716247474 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="B29"><text><SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>29KimSSChoHJKangJYKangHKYooTKInhibition of androgen receptor expression with small interfering RNA enhances cancer cell apoptosis by suppressing survival factors in androgen insensitive, late stage LNCaP cellsThe Scientific World Journal201320138 pages519397 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR bands show effective silencing of the heat shock protein 27 (Hsp27) and c-FLIP gene expression in PC-3 cells after small interfering RNA (siRNA) treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-174392.001"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>Immunoblotting shows effective silencing of the heat shock protein 27 (Hsp27) and c-FLIP in PC-3 cells after siRNA treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-174392.002"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>In situ detection of apoptotic cells in siRNA (Hsp27, c-FLIP, dual) transfected PC-3 cells after 48 hours at each dosage of doxazosin treatment (1, 10, and 25 μM). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>In situ detection of apoptotic cells in prostate cancer cells was performed by 3′-end labeling with digoxigenin-dUTP using terminal transferase. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-174392.003"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>Apoptotic indices in siRNA (Hsp27, c-FLIP) transfected cells after 48 hours at each dosage of doxazosin treatment (1, 10, and 25 μM). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-174392.004"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>RT-PCR band of small interfering RNA (siRNA) treatment of the heat shock protein 27 (Hsp27) and c-FLIP after 48 hours in PC-3 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-174392.005"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Electrophoretogram of immunoblot for Hsp27 and c-FLIP expressions at the PC-3 cells. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xlink:href="TSWJ2013-174392.006"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
