<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3676390</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23762280</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-13-09937</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Biochemistry</subject><subj-group><subject>Metabolism</subject><subj-group><subject>Biosynthesis</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Genomics</subject><subj-group><subject>Genome Sequencing</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Mycology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fungi</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Molecular Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Gene Expression</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Plant Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Botany</subject><subj-group><subject>Mycology</subject><subj-group><subject>Fungi</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Complementary and Alternative Medicine</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Profiling and Quantifying Differential Gene Transcription Provide Insights into Ganoderic Acid Biosynthesis in <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> in Response to Methyl Jasmonate</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Profiling Transcription of <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>Ang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Meng-Jiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>Da-Shuai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Ai-Liang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>Qin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Ming-Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<addr-line>Microbiology Department, College of Life Sciences, Nanjing Agricultural University, Key Laboratory of Microbiological Engineering of Agricultural Environment, Ministry of Agriculture, Nanjing, Jiangsu, P.R. China</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>Sung-Hwan</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Soonchunhyang University, Korea, Republic Of</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>mwzhao@njau.edu.cn</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: AR MWZ. Performed the experiments: AR MJL. Analyzed the data: AR LS ALJ. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: AR MJL QH. Wrote the paper: AR DSM MWZ.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e65027</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>3</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>4</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Ren et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ren et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>
<italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> is a mushroom with traditional medicinal properties that has been widely used in China and other countries in Eastern Asia. Ganoderic acids (GA) produced by <italic>G. lucidum</italic> exhibit important pharmacological activities. Previous studies have demonstrated that methyl jasmonate (MeJA) is a potent inducer of GA biosynthesis and the expression of genes involved in the GA biosynthesis pathway in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>. To further explore the mechanism of GA biosynthesis, cDNA-Amplified Fragment Length Polymorphism (cDNA-AFLP) was used to identify genes that are differentially expressed in response to MeJA. Using 64 primer combinations, over 3910 transcriptionally derived fragments (TDFs) were obtained. Reliable sequence data were obtained for 390 of 458 selected TDFs. Ninety of these TDFs were annotated with known functions through BLASTX searching the GenBank database, and 12 annotated TDFs were assigned into secondary metabolic pathways by searching the KEGGPATHWAY database. Twenty-five TDFs were selected for qRT-PCR analysis to confirm the expression patterns observed with cDNA-AFLP. The qRT-PCR results were consistent with the altered patterns of gene expression revealed by the cDNA-AFLP technique. Additionally, the transcript levels of 10 genes were measured at the mycelium, primordia, and fruiting body developmental stages of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>. The greatest expression levels were reached during primordia for all of the genes except cytochrome b2 reached its highest expression level in the mycelium stage. This study not only identifies new candidate genes involved in the regulation of GA biosynthesis but also provides further insight into MeJA-induced gene expression and secondary metabolic response in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (Project No. 30970042), the Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Uni-versities (Project No. KYZ201121), the Chinese National Key Technology R&#x00026;D Program (Project No. 2013BAD16B02) and the Project Funded by the Priority Academic Program Development of Jiangsu Higher Education Institutions. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="12"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Medicinal mushrooms are viewed as a rich source of therapeutically useful biologically active agents. There are approximately 700 species of higher basidiomycetes that have been found to possess significant pharmacological activities <xref rid="pone.0065027-Zhong1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. For several thousand years, <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> (Ling-Zhi in Chinese and Reishi in Japanese) has been widely used in Asia as a home remedy to treat minor disorders and promote vitality and longevity <xref rid="pone.0065027-Lin1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>. Numerous studies have revealed that the primary active ingredients of <italic>G. lucidum</italic> are polysaccharides and the secondary metabolites ganoderic acids (GAs) <xref rid="pone.0065027-Hajjaj1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Joseph1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>. Most GAs have important medicinal value, such as the regulation of osteoclast genesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Miyamoto1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, the inhibition of cholesterol synthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Hajjaj1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> and tumor growth <xref rid="pone.0065027-Jedinak1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>, and protection of the liver <xref rid="pone.0065027-Kimura1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>. However, despite the important pharmacological potential of GAs, low GA yield from both field cultivation and fermentation limits its wide-spread use.</p><p>Many attempts have been made to increase GA biosynthesis. Those works can be divided into two branches. Most reports focus on the environmental conditions during fermentation. The optimal medium (carbon source, nitrogen source, mineral source, and initial pH) was elucidated by an orthogonal design study that tested one factor at a time <xref rid="pone.0065027-Li1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. By studying the effect of the fed-batch fermentation process (pH-shift and dissolved oxygen tension-shift) on the GA content, strategies were identified that resulted in a significant synergistic enhancement of GA accumulation <xref rid="pone.0065027-Tang1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>. Recently, the use of an inducer to enhance the activity components in fungi fermentation has drawn great interest <xref rid="pone.0065027-MachAigner1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Zhang1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>. For GA production, methyl jasmonate, phenobarbital and H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> were added to culture medium to increase the GA content <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0065027-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. However, due to the unclear mechanism of ganoderic acid biosynthesis, determining the optimal fermentation conditions and screening an effective inducer to produce maximum quantities of GA are still a trial-and-error process.</p><p>Isotopic tracer experiments have demonstrated that GA, a type of terpenoid, is synthesized via the mevalonate pathway <xref rid="pone.0065027-Shiao1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Hirotani1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. The genes that encode the proteins involved in the GA biosynthesis pathway have been cloned and characterized, and the regulation of the expression levels of these genes has been investigated under different environmental conditions to determine the relationship between GA biosynthesis and the expression of these genes <xref rid="pone.0065027-Zhao1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0065027-Shang2" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Recent studies have demonstrated that the over-expression of these biosynthetic genes results in an enhanced accumulation of GA in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0065027-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Although these reports indicated that increased GA biosynthesis may result from the up-regulation of GA biosynthesis genes, how specific environmental conditions induce GA biosynthesis through the GA biosynthetic pathway remains unclear. Therefore, research on the GA biosynthesis mechanism has concentrated on the mevalonate pathway.</p><p>MeJA is a ubiquitous small signaling molecule in the plant kingdom. Environmental stresses, such as wounding or pathogen attack, can trigger MeJA production <xref rid="pone.0065027-Creelman1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Choi1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In plants, MeJA induces stomatal closure, monoterpenoid indole alkaloids and isoprenoid biosynthesis, and defense response pathogens by activating reactive oxygen species, the MAPK signal pathway, or the calcium-dependent protein kinase signal pathway <xref rid="pone.0065027-Choi1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0065027-Munemasa1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>. In fungi, MeJA is involved in the modulation of <italic>Cryptococcus laurentii</italic> and <italic>Penicillium expansum</italic> growth <xref rid="pone.0065027-Yao1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref> and the regulation of Aflatoxin B1 biosynthesis by <italic>Aspergillus parasiticus</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0065027-Meimaroglou1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Vergopoulou1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. The same phenomenon is observed in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>; when different concentrations of MeJA were added to the culture, the GA contents were improved <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Moreover, the transcript levels of the genes <italic>hmgr</italic>, <italic>fps</italic>, and <italic>sqs</italic> in the GA biosynthesis pathway were up-regulated in response to MeJA. However, the signaling pathways initiated by MeJA to regulate GA biosynthesis and gene expression remain unknown.</p><p>In this study, differentially expressed transcripts were screened in the MeJA-treated mycelium using cDNA-AFLP to gain insights into the regulatory mechanisms of GA biosynthesis in response to MeJA. The differentially expressed transcripts were sequenced and classified, and their expression patterns were analyzed. For some of the regulated genes, quantitative real-time polymerase chain reaction (qRT-PCR) was used to confirm the expression patterns observed with cDNA-AFLP. In addition, the transcript levels of some of the candidate genes were investigated at various developmental stages of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Results</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Isolation of Differentially Expressed Genes</title><p>To select a suitable restriction enzyme combination for cDNA-AFLP analysis of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>, several enzyme combinations were tested; the combination of <italic>Eco</italic>R I and <italic>Mse</italic> I produced an acceptable range of fragment sizes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g001">Figure 1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0065027-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>cDNA-AFLP analysis of transcripts in response to MeJA treatment in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>.</title><p>cDNA-AFLP silver-stained polyacrylamide gels with 9 primer combinations (PC) amplifying differentially expressed genes in <italic>G. lucidum</italic> treated with 0, 50 and 200 &#x000b5;M MeJA, respectively. The combinations of primers used are indicated according to the codes reported in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s007">Table S4</xref>. The molecular weight marker sizes are indicated on both sides. Arrows indicate some of the differentially expressed transcript-derived fragments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0065027.g001"/></fig><p>A total of 64 primer combinations was used to selectively amplify the expressed genes. Differentially expressed transcript-derived fragments were extracted from the gel and used as templates for re-amplification by PCR. The cDNA-AFLP fragments were highly reproducible, as evidenced by the similar band intensities observed in the three biological replications. All of the visible TDFs between 150 and 800 bp were counted. Of the total 3910 transcript-derived fragments obtained using cDNA-AFLP with 64 primer pairs, 919 (23.5%) displayed altered expression patterns after MeJA induction; 703 were up-regulated, and 216 were down-regulated. Reliable sequences were obtained for 390 TDFs out of 458 TDFs selected for further analysis. Sequence data from this article have been deposited in GenBank, Accession Numbers: JZ163375- JZ163764. According to the genomic sequence of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0065027-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Liu1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>, the distributions of 390 TDFs were analyzed as shown in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s001">Figure S1</xref>. Because our knowledge of gene functions in <italic>G. lucidum</italic> is relatively limited, only 90 of the sequenced genes were associated with known functions, as determined by BLAST searching the GenBank database (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t001">Table 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref>). The sites of known functional TDFs on chromosomes were analyzed as shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s002">Figure S2</xref>. Several differentially expressed genes showed homology to genes encoding transcription factors and genes involved in metabolism, gene regulation, signal transduction, stress defense, protein trafficking and protein degradation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0065027-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Classification of TDFs from the cDNA-AFLP result in functional categories.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0065027-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0065027.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Function</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDFs, %</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U, %</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D, %</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metabolism/energy</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 (9.23)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26 (6.67)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (2.56)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transcription</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14 (3.59)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.79)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7 (1.79)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Protein synthesis/fate</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 (3.85)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 (3.08)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 (0.77)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Signal transduction</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10 (2.56)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.28)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.28)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Transport facilitation</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 (2.82)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6 (1.54)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (1.28)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Defense/cell organization</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.03)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4 (1.03)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified proteins</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151 (38.72)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105 (26.92)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46 (11.79)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149 (38.21)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81 (20.77)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68 (17.44)</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">390 (100.0)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248 (63.59)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142 (36.41)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><p>The number and frequency (in parentheses) of 390 TDFs from the cDNA-AFLP result with defined functional categories annotated is indicated. U, up-regulation; D, down-regulation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone-0065027-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Transcript derived fragments (TDFs) from <italic>G. lucidum</italic> with homologies to other known protein.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0065027-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0065027.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No.</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Size</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Homologue<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max Score<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max ident<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">a</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expression<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">b</xref>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromosomes Site<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">c</xref>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="9" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Metabolism/energy</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF006</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glucosidase I (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-32</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF015</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">468</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NAD-dependent deacetylase (Puccinia graminis )</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-26</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF070</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">466</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ceramidase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">243</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-63</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr13</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF080</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,3-beta-glucan synthase (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-41</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF096</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">275</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aryl-alcohol oxidase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF300</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">375</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">phosphoglycerate kinase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-123</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF138</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">677</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">anthranilate synthase (Coprinopsis scobicola)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-98</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF142</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">494</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">saccharopine dehydrogenase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-59</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF143</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">461</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2-methylcitrate dehydratase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00E-57</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF047</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">612</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome b2 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-43</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF099</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">262</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acetolactate synthase (Neosartorya fischeri)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-15</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF375</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">calcium transporting ATPase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-15</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr13</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF153</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">aspartate ammonia lyase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-88</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF376</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">538</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">lipase/esterase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">155</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-40</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF113</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">600</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-80</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF115</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">biotin-[acetyl-CoA-carboxylase] ligase (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-24</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF160</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">718</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00E-74</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr2</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF161</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">511</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycoside hydrolase family 31 protein (Serpula lacrymans)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-67</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF381</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">309</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">flavin-containing monooxygenase (Aspergillus niger)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-24</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr12</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF313</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">287</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome-b5 reductase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-24</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GaLu96scf_50</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF314</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">327</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hexokinase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-41</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF019</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">265</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome b5 (Phanerochaete chrysosporium)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-34</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF353</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">278</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">heparinase II/III family protein (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-32</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF355</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">219</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-40</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF243</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pyruvate carboxylase (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-38</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF195</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">478</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">fumarase (Scheffersomyces stipitis)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-87</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF322</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytochrome P450 like TBP (Medicago truncatula)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-17</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr10</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF323</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pyruvate kinase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">151</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00E-42</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF325</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">414</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">malate dehydrogenase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-60</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF364</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">552</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cytochrome P450 (Dichomitus squalens)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-77</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr12</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF367</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">288</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">sulfate permease (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-38</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF307</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">239</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">syntaxin-like protein (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-29</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr4</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF256</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">260</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase (Piriformospora indica)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-06</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr2</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF291</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">formaldehyde dehydrogenase (Taiwanofungus camphoratus)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF223</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycoside hydrolase family 3 protein (Serpula lacrymans)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.1</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-15</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr4</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF338</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">209</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP synthase subunit gamma (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.1</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Transcription</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF009</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nucleotide binding protein, putative (Candida dubliniensis)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-21</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF020</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">330</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcription factor (Stereum hirsutum)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-62</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF042</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">271</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pre-mRNA splicing factor prp1 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-23</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF058</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">551</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMP-specific 5&#x02032;-nucleotidase 1 (Uncinocarpus reesii)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">221</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-56</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF081</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">316</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">epsilon DNA polymerase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-37</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF318</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">302</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">eukaryotic translation initiation factor 6 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-46</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr8</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF094</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DNA-directed RNA polymerase II subunit (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">206</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-51</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF114</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">466</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">translation initiation factor 3 subunit 3 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">171</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-41</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF050</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">398</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chromo domain protein MRG15 (Piriformospora indica)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-50</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr12</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF049</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">translation elongation factor 1a (Schizophyllum commune)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-85</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF370</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rRNA intron-encoded homing endonuclease (Medicago truncatula)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">137</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-34</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF341</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">303</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RWD domain-containing protein (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">141</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-40</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF156</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">340</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">argonaute-like protein (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-36</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF390</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">320</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">transcription factor (Stereum hirsutum)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">204</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-60</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Protein synthesis/fate</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF297</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">312</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">peptidylprolyl isomerase (Datisca glomerata)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-59</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr9</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF136</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ubiquitin-protein ligase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">208</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-61</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr4</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF299</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">304</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">histone H2B (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">176</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-54</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr2</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF145</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">561</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60S ribosomal protein L10 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-115</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr10</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF303</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">439</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">profilin (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-58</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr9</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF151</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">501</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SNARE protein SED5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">192</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-58</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF164</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial endopeptidase (Serpula lacrymans)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">198</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-58</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF312</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">272</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">histone H4 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-50</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF383</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal peptidase 21 kDa subunit (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-31</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr11</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF347</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">333</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ubiquitin (Camponotus floridanus)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">246</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-82</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF385</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mitochondrial 50S ribosomal protein L5 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-18</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF321</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">429</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40S ribosomal protein S11 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">263</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-88</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF336</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">505</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60S ribosomal protein L32 (Postia placenta)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-83</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF340</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">240</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p47 protein isoform c (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">107</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-26</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr12</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF293</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">histone deacetylase RPD3 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">152</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-42</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr12</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Signal transduction</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF013</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">297</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMGC/MAPK/JNK protein kinase (Coprinopsis cinerea )</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-21</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr4</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF193</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">736</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rho2 GTP binding protein (Ustilago maydis)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-50</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr2</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF040</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">299</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cAMP-dependent protein kinase Akt (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90.5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00E-17</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF051</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">669</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">histidine kinase (Schizophyllum commune)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-24</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF052</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">547</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">protein kinase activator Mob2 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">203</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-51</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF304</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">299</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">serine/threonine kinase receptor associated protein (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-60</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF158</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">580</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CMGC/GSK protein kinase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">159</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-45</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr4</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF165</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">675</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">rho small monomeric GTPase (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">268</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-89</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr2</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF008</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">848</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ras2 (Cryptococcus neoformans)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-35</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr8</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF333</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">394</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">signal recognition particle binding protein (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">187</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-53</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Transport facilitation</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF078</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">444</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">glycerol uptake facilitator (Talaromyces stipitatus)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-21</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF083</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">copper chaperone TahA (Trametes versicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-25</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr8</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF159</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">548</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vacuolar sorting protein (Ajellomyces capsulatus)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-43</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">79</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF187</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">490</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">oligopeptide transporter (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">266</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-83</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr10</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF342</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">350</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">inorganic phosphate transporter (Laccaria bicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-22</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr8</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">81</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF048</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">218</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nuclear transport factor 2 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">174</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-54</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr10</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF360</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">315</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vacuole protein (Cryptococcus neoformans)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-23</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF327</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">167</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COPII-coated vesicle protein (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF384</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">259</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NifU-like protein c (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-34</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">D</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF316</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">294</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">t-complex protein 1 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-46</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr1</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF264</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">521</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">vacuolar membrane protein (Cryptococcus gattii)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-28</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr4</td></tr><tr><td colspan="9" align="justify" rowspan="1">
<bold>Defense/cell organization</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF122</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">674</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">cell division control protein 23 (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">236</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-60</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">88</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF176</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">hsp70-like protein (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-20</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr10</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF179</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">280</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">microtubule associated protein (Coprinopsis cinerea)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-23</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No hits found</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TDF129</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">448</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">catalase (Trametes versicolor)</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66%</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-63</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">U</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chr3</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label>a</label><p>Based on highest BLASTX match with an E value lower than 1e-<sup>04</sup>.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>b</label><p>U, up-regulation; D, down-regulation.</p></fn><fn id="nt104"><label>c</label><p>The distribution of TDFs on chromosomes in <italic>G. lucidum</italic> genome.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Gene Sequence Analysis</title><p>The annotation approach was based on sequence similarity searches in the GenBank database. The 390 TDFs were subjected to a BLASTX search against the NCBI non-redundant protein database using the default parameters. The results revealed that 241 TDFs (61.8%) had significant sequence similarities to known proteins (eValue&#x02264;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>): 90 TDFs (23.08%) had significant sequence similarity to classified proteins, 151 TDFs (38.72%) had sequence similarity to unclassified proteins; and the remaining 149 TDFs (38.21%) failed to match any proteins in the database. It was noted that the information about the genomes or transcriptomes of this species was needed in-depth analysis. Of the 90 TDFs, 45.6% were homologous to <italic>Coprinopsis cinere</italic>, 11.1% were homologous to <italic>Laccaria bicolor</italic> and 7.8% were homologous to <italic>Postia placenta</italic>.</p><p>Gene ontology (GO) assignments describe gene products in terms of their associated molecular functions, biological processes and cellular components. Blast2GO (B2G) is a bioinformatic tool for GO-based DNA or protein sequence annotation <xref rid="pone.0065027-Conesa1" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>. The 90 TDFs were submitted to Blast2GO, and 75 were successfully annotated (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s004">Table S1</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g002">Figure 2A</xref> shows the percentages of differentially expressed genes in the 90 known functional sequences assigned to various functional categories. Of these, 40.0% of the annotations were related to &#x02018;metabolism/energy&#x02019;, 17.0% were related to &#x02018;protein synthesis/fate&#x02019;, and 16.0% were related to &#x02018;transcription&#x02019;.</p><fig id="pone-0065027-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Percentages of 90 known functional TDFs with functional categories.</title><p>A. The functional classification of transcript-derived fragments (90 TDFs) from <italic>G. lucidum</italic> in response to MeJA. The percentages of differentially expressed genes in the 90 known functional sequences assigned to various functional categories. B. Ninety TDFs in biological function categories showing differential expression patterns in <italic>G</italic>. <italic>lucidum</italic>. The percentages of different functional categories of up- and down-regulated sequences in the 90 known functional sequences were significantly different (P&#x0003c;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0065027.g002"/></fig><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g002">Figure 2B</xref> shows that the percentages of different functional categories of up- and down-regulated sequences in the 90 known functional sequences were significantly different (P&#x0003c;0.05). In the metabolism/energy group and the protein synthesis/fate group, the percentages of up-regulated genes (28.9% and 13.3%, respectively) were increased compared with the percentages of down-regulated genes (11.1% and 3.3%, respectively). In the transcription term and the signal transduction term, the percentages of up-regulated genes (7.8% and 5.6%, respectively) were equal to the percentages of down-regulated genes (7.8% and 5.6%, respectively). Interestingly, all of the differentially expressed genes were up-regulated in the defense/cell organization group (4.4%).</p><p>KEGG provides a reference knowledge base for linking genomes to life through the process of PATHWAY mapping. In this study, the 90 annotated TDFs were blasted against the KEGG database. Thirty of these TDFs were highly homologous to some protein, and 21 were assigned to the metabolic pathways in the database (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s005">Table S2</xref>). Interestingly, 12 TDFs were assigned to secondary metabolic pathways, specifically, the biosynthesis of triterpenes, terpenoids and steroids.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Quantitative RT-PCR Analysis of MeJA-induced Differentially Expressed TDFs in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>
</title><p>Co-expression analysis, which is based on the premise that a set of genes involved in a biological process is co-expressed under given conditions, has been successfully used to identify novel genes involved in secondary metabolism <xref rid="pone.0065027-YonekuraSakakibara1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. To verify the correlation between the expression of differentially expressed TDFs and MeJA induction, quantitative RT-PCR analysis was performed for 25 TDFs, which involved in metabolism (glucosidase I (gls), glutathione-dependent formaldehyde dehydrogenase (gfd), fumarase (fum), NAD-dependent deacetylase (ndd), pyruvate carboxylase (pco), pyruvate kinase (pyr), ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase (ksr), aryl-alcohol oxidase (aao), catalase (cat), cytochrome b2 (cyt) and acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase (aact)), gene regulation (nucleotide binding protein (nbp), histone deacetylase (hd), pre-mRNA splicing factor (prp) and IMP-specific 5&#x02032;-nucleotidase 1 (nuc)), signal transduction (cAMP-dependent protein kinase (apk), CMGC/MAPK/JNK protein kinase (mapk), small monomeric GTPase (rho), histidine kinase (hk) and protein kinase activator (mob)), cell organization (cell division control protein (cdc)) and trafficking (vacuolar membrane protein (vmp), vacuole protein (vac), calcium transporting ATPase (cal) and glycerol uptake facilitator (guf)). In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref>, nbp (TDF009), cal (TDF375), hd (TDF293), gls (TDF080), apk (TDF040), gfd (TDF291), guf (TDF078), prp (TDF042), ndd (TDF015), mapk (TDF013), and rho (TDF165) were down-regulated in response to MeJA treatment, whereas others were up-regulated. For hk (TDF051), mob (TDF052), nuc (TDF058), pyr (TDF323), pco (TDF243), ksr (TDF256), and vmp (TDF264), the highest levels of transcripts were observed with 50 &#x000b5;M MeJA. For aao (TDF096), cdc (TDF122), cat (TDF129), fum (TDF195), vac (TDF360), cyt (TDF047), and aact (TDF113), the highest levels of transcripts were observed with 200 &#x000b5;M MeJA. The qRT-PCR results are consistent with the altered expression patterns observed for these 25 genes using cDNA-AFLP (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s003">Figure S3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0065027-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>qRT-PCR analysis of 25 selected TDFs in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>.</title><p>Expression of 25 selected genes treated with 0, 50 and 200 &#x000b5;M MeJA, respectively. aao (TDF096) aryl-alcohol oxidase, nbp (TDF009) nucleotide binding protein, cdc (TDF122) cell division control protein, cal (TDF375) calcium transporting ATPase, cat (TDF129) catalase, vmp (TDF264) vacuolar membrane protein, hd (TDF293) histone deacetylase, gls (TDF080) glucosidase I, hk (TDF051) histidine kinase, fum (TDF195) fumarase, ksr (TDF256) ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase, apk (TDF040) cAMP-dependent protein kinase, nuc (TDF058) IMP-specific 5&#x02032;-nucleotidase 1, gfd (TDF291) glutathione-dependent formaldehyde dehydrogenase, pyr (TDF323) pyruvate kinase, mob (TDF052) protein kinase activator, pco (TDF243) pyruvate carboxylase, guf (TDF078) glycerol uptake facilitator, prp (TDF042) pre-mRNA splicing factor, vac (TDF360) vacuole protein, aact (TDF113) acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase, ndd (TDF015) NAD-dependent deacetylase, mapk (TDF013) CMGC/MAPK/JNK protein kinase, rho (TDF165) small monomeric GTPase, cyt (TDF047) cytochrome b2. All samples were examined in triplicate. For all genes represented in this figure, the P value was &#x0003c;0.05 or 0.01 (*p&#x0003c;0.05 and **p&#x0003c;0.01).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0065027.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Variations in Gene Expression at Developmental Stages of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>
</title><p>All of TDFs from MeJA-induced library were searched from mycelium or fruiting body EST library reported by Chen et al., 2012 <xref rid="pone.0065027-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s006">Table S3</xref>). In the three EST libraries, there are 260 genes accounted for the majority, including basic metabolism and signal transduction genes. There are 30 genes appeared in both mycelium library and MeJA-induced library, most of which are of unknown function genes. Forty-nine genes appear in both the fruiting EST library and MeJA-induced library, including ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase and cytochrome P450. Fifty genes only exist in MeJA-induced library, indicating that these genes inducing conditions expressed in methyl jasmonate, and may not be expressed or low expressed in mycelium and fruiting bodies, such as pre-mRNA splicing factor and catalase.</p><fig id="pone-0065027-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>The expression of TDF genes in different development stages.</title><p>A. Venn diagrams depicting the genes expressed across MeJA-induction and the different developmental stages. Data are derived from <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s006">Table S3</xref>. B. The transcript levels of TDF genes under the developmental stages of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>. The X axis shows the abbreviation of genes. The full name of each gene is in the <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref> legends. All samples were examined in triplicate. For all genes represented in this figure, the P value was &#x0003c;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0065027.g004"/></fig><p>Varying amounts of GA are observed in different developmental stages in <italic>G. lucidum.</italic> A recent study reported that the GA level is highest during the primordium and fruiting body stages <xref rid="pone.0065027-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. To further study the relationship between the differentially expressed genes and GA biosynthesis, the transcription levels of 10 genes were examined during the mycelium, primordium, and fruiting body developmental stages in <italic>G. lucidum</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g004">Figure 4B</xref>). Expression levels were the highest during primordium for TDF040 (apk, cAMP-dependent protein kinase), TDF096 (aao, aryl-alcohol oxidase), TDF052 (mob, protein kinase activator), TDF256 (ksr, ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase), TDF051 (hk, histidine kinase), TDF013 (mapk, CMGC/MAPK/JNK protein kinase), and TDF165 (rho, small monomeric GTPase). For TDF264 (vmp, vacuolar membrane protein) and TDF009 (nbp, nucleotide binding protein), expression levels were the highest during both the primordium and the fruiting body stages. Only TDF047 (cyt, cytochrome b2) showed a maximum expression level during the mycelium stage.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The biosynthesis of many secondary metabolites is modulated by environmental conditions <xref rid="pone.0065027-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>. Few data are available to elucidate the regulatory mechanisms of the secondary metabolite biosynthesis in response to environmental factors in fungi due to the complex regulatory network and regulatory gene interactions involved <xref rid="pone.0065027-Yu1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0065027-Yin1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. The same challenge exists for understanding the mechanisms governing the regulation of GA biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Shi2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Yu2" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. Despite significant research efforts to understand the influence of environmental factors on the GA biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Shi2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>, the regulatory networks by which environmental factors regulate GA biosynthesis remain unclear. Recent studies on genetically modified GA biosynthesis have focused on the genes restricted to the mevalonate pathway <xref rid="pone.0065027-Shi1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Xu1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Our previous study demonstrated that methyl jasmonate can significantly increase both the amount of GA and the transcription levels of known genes in the GA biosynthesis pathway <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Additional unknown genes may be involved in the regulatory network of GA biosynthesis. Therefore, the screening of differentially expressed genes during MeJA induction may not only identify novel candidate target genes involved in the regulation of GA biosynthesis but may also provide a new perspective for understanding the regulation of GA biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0065027-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0065027.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>Schematic pathway predicting the role of MeJA induced genes in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>.</title><p>Integrated pathway map shows the role of MeJA-induced genes involved in GA biosynthesis, primary metabolism, signaling regulation and transcriptional regulation. Dashed lines indicate the probable pathway involved in GA biosynthesis. Solid lines indicate the result supported by cDNA-AFLP and real time PCR. The ESTs from cDNA-AFLP results are indicated in stars.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0065027.g005"/></fig><p>Among the MeJA up-regulated genes were the acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase gene (TDF113), several members of the cytochrome family (TDF019, TDF047, TDF160, TDF313, TDF322, TDF355, and TDF364), and, most notably, cytochrome P450s (CYPs) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref>). In addition, TDF256, which encodes a 3-keto sterol reductase (<italic>ksr</italic>), was shown to be up-regulated by MeJA induction with both cDNA-AFLP and real-time PCR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref>). In <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic>, <italic>ksr</italic> (Erg27p) is required for oxidosqualene cyclase (Erg7p) activity <xref rid="pone.0065027-Mo1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, which converts oxidosqualene to lanosterol. Those results suggest that the genes in the mevalonate pathway are up-regulated in response to MeJA induction (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g005">Figure 5</xref>). This result is consistent with those of previous studies <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Liang1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and demonstrates that the genes encoding key enzymes in the mevalonate pathway play an important role in GA biosynthesis. Although not all of the differentially expressed genes in the mevalonate pathway have been detected, the cDNA-AFLP approach is effective for screening differentially expressed genes during MeJA induction.</p><p>These results indicate that MeJA induction modulates not only GA biosynthesis-related genes but also related genes in other metabolic pathways, such as glycerol metabolism, pyruvate metabolism, lactate metabolism, sphingolipid metabolism etc. Pyruvate is a precursor of the methylerythritol 4-phosphate (MEP) pathway, and a pyruvate decarboxylase catalyzes the formation of GA <xref rid="pone.0065027-Shi2" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Pyruvate kinase and pyruvate carboxylase are involved in secondary metabolite biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref>). In this study, TDF243 and TDF323 were identified as pyruvate carboxylase and pyruvate kinase, of which up-regulations were detected using cDNA-AFLP and real time PCR (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref>). The result suggested that they were involved in GA biosynthesis. Differential expression of these genes influences a series of metabolic pathways in <italic>G. lucidum</italic> in response to methyl jasmonate (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s005">Table S2</xref>). This is a complex metabolic regulatory network that includes a series of physiological and biochemical reactions involved in primary and secondary metabolism (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>The development stages (fruiting body) and MeJA-treatment improve the GA content <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Chen1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. There are 49 genes in both fruiting body EST library and MeJA-induced library, including ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase and cytochrome P450 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g004">Figure 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s006">Table S3</xref>). Specific expressions of these genes in these two libraries suggest that these genes may not only in response to MeJA but also participate in the developmental process of fruiting body. The investigation of the transcription levels of five genes found that cAMP-dependent protein kinase, aryl-alcohol oxidase, protein kinase activator, ERG27-3-keto sterol reductase, vacuolar membrane protein up-regulated under MeJA treatment and in fruiting body development. The consistent result indicated these five genes may have important roles on the GA biosynthesis. However, there are four genes down-regulated under MeJA treatment and up-regulated in fruiting body development (cAMP-dependent protein kinase, CMGC/MAPK/JNK protein kinase, small monomeric GTPase and nucleotide binding protein) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g004">Figure 4</xref>). Although both MeJA induction and fruiting body stage increased GA content, the regulation mechanism may be difference. These genes may have a variety of physiological functions, especially the regulation of fungal development in development process <xref rid="pone.0065027-Zheng1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Bayram1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. Therefore, these four genes probably regulated not only GA biosynthesis in the fruiting body stage, but also the fruiting body development of <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>.</p><p>Some signaling factors have been reported to regulate both cell developmental processes and secondary metabolite biosynthesis in filamentous fungi <xref rid="pone.0065027-Calvo1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. For example, the small monomeric GTPase rho played an essential role in controlling genes involved in cell polarity, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> generation, asexual sporulation, and mycotoxin production <xref rid="pone.0065027-Zheng1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Raudaskoski1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Song1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>. The rho-GTPase pathway was associated with cholesterol biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Quetglas1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>. In the cDNA-AFLP library, the <italic>G. lucidum</italic> TDF165 gene encodes a protein with sequence similarity to rho (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref>). The qRT-PCR results confirmed that the rho gene is down-regulated in response to MeJA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref>). Furthermore, the down-regulation of the rho expression level through rho gene silencing can increase the GA content (data not shown). These results suggest that the rho small GTPase pathway represses GA biosynthesis in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>.</p><p>A mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) gene (TDF013) was also isolated and characterized from the <italic>G. lucidum</italic> library. The transcription level of the MAPK gene in response to MeJA was 0.20&#x000b1;0.01-fold that of the control. As one of components of the MAPK cascade, a critical signal transduction pathway in eukaryotic organisms, MAPK is essential for regulating growth, differentiation processes and secondary metabolism <xref rid="pone.0065027-Nishida1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Atoui1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. Recently, it was reported that the MAPK cascade played an important role in regulating sterigmatocystin biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Bayram1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. In <italic>G. lucidum</italic>, H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> induced phosphorylation of the proteins Hog-1 and Fus3, which are homologs of the mammalian MAPKs p38 and ERK <xref rid="pone.0065027-You1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>. In contrast, the mammalian JNK homolog in BCRC 36111 was not detected using a JNK-specific antibody <xref rid="pone.0065027-You2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. In this study, the CMGC/MAPK/JNK MAPK is down-regulated after MeJA induction, suggesting that it may play a negative regulatory role in the MeJA signaling pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>The sequences of the TDFs that generated significant matches to sequence databases were most commonly genes involved in stress response and cell organization. Two of these TDFs, TDF122, which encodes cell division control protein, and TDF176, which encodes an hsp70-like protein, may also be involved in cell repair and protection against defense responses. TDF 145 and TDF336, which are derived from putative 60S ribosomal protein genes, have also been implicated in responses to oxidative stress, in addition to protein translation for improving carotenoid biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-MendezAlvarez1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>. Other TDFs, such as <italic>G. lucidum</italic> TDF129 (similar to a catalase), are clearly involved in oxidative stress defense <xref rid="pone.0065027-Rochat1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>. Previous studies reported that H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> increases GA production <xref rid="pone.0065027-Zhang2" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>. Catalase might be involved in prompt neutralization of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub>. The up-regulation of TDF129, a catalase-homologous gene in response to MeJA, indicated that the burst of reactive oxygen species (ROS) triggered by MeJA was most likely involved in GA biosynthesis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g005">Figure 5</xref>).</p><p>Vacuoles and vesicles are known to sequester secondary metabolites to protect host cells from self-toxicity <xref rid="pone.0065027-Sirikantaramas1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>. Enzymes involved in secondary metabolism, including those for the biosynthesis of cyclosporin, penicillin, and aflatoxin in fungi, are often found in vesicles and vacuoles, <xref rid="pone.0065027-Hoppert1" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0065027-Hong1" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. In <italic>Aspergillus parasiticus</italic>, two enzymatic steps in aflatoxin biosynthesis are completed in vesicles, and these organelles also participate in the compartmentalization and export of the end product, aflatoxin <xref rid="pone.0065027-Chanda1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>. A vacuole protein gene (TDF360), a vacuolar membrane protein (TDF264) and a COPII-coated vesicle protein gene (TDF327) were also isolated from the <italic>G. lucidum</italic> library (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref>). The transcription level of the <italic>vmp</italic> gene in response to MeJA induction was 3.10&#x000b1;0.12-fold that of the control (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref>).</p><p>In conclusion, cDNA-AFLP screening has revealed a number of MeJA-responsive genes in <italic>G. lucidum</italic>. Of the 390 successfully sequenced TDFs, 300 unknown or hypothetical proteins require further characterization to determine whether they are novel MeJA-responsive transcripts. Ninety TDFs were annotated with known functions. MeJA-induced genes expression changes in <italic>G. lucidum</italic> are summarized in a schematic pathway (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g005">Figure 5</xref>). Experimental data suggests GA biosynthesis relative genes were up-regulated, which included in acetyl-CoA acetyltransferase gene, several members of the cytochrome P450s family, and 3-keto sterol reductase gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0065027-g003">Figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0065027-t002">Table 2</xref>). We have previously shown that MeJA induces the expression of six genes (<italic>hmgs</italic>, <italic>hmgr</italic>, <italic>mvd</italic>, <italic>fps</italic>, <italic>sqs</italic>, and <italic>lano</italic>) in the GA biosynthesis pathway <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The MeJA induction leads to altered metabolism/energy of <italic>G. lucidum</italic>, which involves changes in primary metabolism and other secondary metabolism, such as glycerol metabolism, pyruvate metabolism, calcium transporting ATPases etc. In previous report found that the calcineurin-signal transduction was significant to GA biosynthesis <xref rid="pone.0065027-Xu2" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>. The GA biosynthetic genes and the Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensor were up-regulated with calcium addition. The changes of CMGC/GSK protein kinase, histidine kinase, serine/threonine kinase receptor associated protein, cAMP-dependent protein kinase, rho small monomeric GTPase, MAPK related ESTs signifies a signaling network probably regulated GA biosynthesis under MeJA treatment. But the proper functional characterizations of such genes are still pending. Thus, further characterization of those genes involved in the regulation of GA biosynthesis would lead to an in-depth understanding of GA biosynthesis regulation network.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Fermentation Conditions and Methyl Jasmonate Elicitation of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>lucidum</italic>
</title><p>
<italic>G. lucidum</italic>, strain HG, was grown at 28&#x000b0;C in potato dextrose agar (PDA) medium. The fermentation conditions of <italic>G. lucidum</italic> were maintained as described <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ren1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. For methyl jasmonate induction, MeJA (Sigma, USA) was dissolved in ethanol and sterilized using a 0.2-&#x000b5;m Supor Membrane Acrodisc Syringe Filter (PALL, USA) before addition to the medium on day 0. The final concentrations of MeJA were 50 and 200 &#x000b5;M. The final ethanol concentration was 2 &#x000b5;L/mL, and equal volumes of ethanol were added to all cultures.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>RNA Extraction Procedure</title><p>For each sample, &#x0223c;0.5 g of mycelia was collected by filtration from the culture media, dehydrated in liquid nitrogen and stored at &#x02013;80&#x000b0;C. Total RNA was extracted using an RNA Isolation Kit (Takara, China) and treated with DNase I (Takara, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>cDNA-AFLP Analysis</title><p>The cDNA-AFLP protocol was described previously by Vuylsteke et al. <xref rid="pone.0065027-Vuylsteke1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. Double-stranded cDNA was synthesized from 2.5 &#x000b5;g of total RNA using an M-MLV RTase cDNA Synthesis Kit (Takara, China) and an oligo-dT primer (Takara, China).</p><p>After pre-amplification, the mixture was diluted 600-fold, and 5 &#x000b5;l was used for selective amplification with each of 64 primer combinations and two selective nucleotides on the MseI primer (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s007">Table S4</xref>). Touchdown PCR was performed using the following conditions: 2 min of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C; 13 cycles of 30 s of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C, 30 s of annealing starting at 65&#x000b0;C and decreasing by 0.7&#x000b0;C per cycle, and 60 s of extension at 72&#x000b0;C; 23 cycles of 30 s of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C, 30 s of annealing at 56&#x000b0;C, and 60 s of extension at 72&#x000b0;C; and 5 min at 72&#x000b0;C. Selective amplification products were separated on a 6% polyacrylamide gel for 2.5 h at 115 W and 50&#x000b0;C. Images of TDFs were developed by silver staining. TDFs that showed clear differences in intensity were visualized by the Quantity One software Version 4.6 (Bio-Rad, Hercules CA) to identify up-regulated or down-regulated TDFs.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Sequence Analysis of cDNA-AFLP Fragments</title><p>The bands corresponding to differentially expressed genes were excised from the gels with a surgical blade, and the eluted DNA was reamplified using the selective amplification primers and the following PCR conditions: denaturation for 15 min at 94&#x000b0;C; 35 cycles of 40 s of denaturation at 94&#x000b0;C, 60 s of annealing at 56&#x000b0;C, and 40 s of extension at 72&#x000b0;C; and 5 min at 72&#x000b0;C. The quantity of each reamplified band was assessed on a 2% agarose gel, and the DNA was purified from the gel and either sequenced directly using the same primers that were used for the re-amplification or cloned into a pMD-18T vector (Takara, China) and sequenced. Nucleotide and protein sequences were compared to sequences in the available public databases by BLAST sequence alignment. Homology searching was performed against the NCBI databases. The sequences were manually assigned to functional categories based on the analysis of the scientific literature and also with the aid of the information reported for each sequence by the Gene Ontology Consortium <xref rid="pone.0065027-Ashburner1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Real-time RT-PCR Analysis</title><p>Real-time RT-PCR was performed on pools of RNA derived from two independent biological experiments. All samples were examined in triplicate. The samples were prepared as described above for the cDNA-AFLP. Total RNA was treated with RNase-free DNase I (Takara, China) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions, and 2.5 &#x000b5;g was then used for reverse transcription with Reverse Transcriptase M-MLV (Takara, China). Then, 5 &#x000b5;l of 1&#x02236;10 diluted cDNA samples was used as the qRT PCR template with 0.5 &#x000b5;M gene-specific primers and 10 &#x000b5;l SYBR <italic>Premix Ex Taq</italic> II (Takara, China) in a total volume of 20 &#x000b5;l. All samples were examined in triplicate. Experiments were performed in a Realplex2 Systems (Eppendorf, Germany) with the following thermal cycling profile: 95&#x000b0;C for 10 min, followed by 40 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 55&#x000b0;C for 30 s, and 72&#x000b0;C for 30 s. Each real-time assay was tested in a dissociation protocol to ensure that each amplicon was a single product. The relative quantification of gene expression was performed using the housekeeping gene 18S rRNA <xref rid="pone.0065027-Mu1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Specific primer pairs were designed for the 25 transcriptionally derived fragments (TDFs) chosen for validation using the Primer 5 software (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0065027.s008">Table S5</xref>). The C<sub>t</sub> was used to calculate the fold changes (FC) in each gene compared to the expression level detected in the control: FC&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2 <sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>, where &#x00394;&#x00394;C<sub>t</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;(C<sub>t target</sub>&#x02212;C<sub>t 18s rRNA</sub>) <sub>treated sample</sub>&#x02212; (C<sub>t target</sub>&#x02212;C<sub>t 18s rRNA</sub>) <sub>control sample</sub>. Gene expression was evaluated by calculating the difference between the C<sub>t</sub> of the gene analyzed and the C<sub>t</sub> of the control 18S rRNA. Post-qRT-PCR calculations analyzing the relative gene expression levels were performed according to the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method described by Livak and Schmittgen <xref rid="pone.0065027-Livak1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4f"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The significance of samples was determined by analysis of variance, and sample means were separated by the Student&#x02019;s t-test. Statistical significance was expressed as P&#x0003c;0.05 or P&#x0003c;0.01.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>The distribution of 390 TDF on chromosomes in </bold>
<bold><italic>G. lucidum</italic></bold>
<bold> genome.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s001.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s002"><label>Figure S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Transcript derived fragments (TDFs) homologies to other known protein found in the </bold>
<bold><italic>G. lucidum</italic></bold>
<bold> genome.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s003"><label>Figure S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>Expression patterns of 25 genes in the cDNA-AFLP results.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s003.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s004"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Gene Functional Annotations according to Gene Ontology (GO).</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s004.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s005"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>Pathway description of TDFs by searching the KEGG PATHWAY database.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s005.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s006"><label>Table S3</label><caption><p>
<bold>The genes expressed across MeJA-induction and the different developmental stages.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s006.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s007"><label>Table S4</label><caption><p>
<bold>Primer sets used for pre-amplified and selective amplified primers.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s007.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0065027.s008"><label>Table S5</label><caption><p>
<bold>Primer sets used for quantitative real-time PCR.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0065027.s008.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the Edible Fungi Institute, Shanghai Academy of Agricultural Science for kind help with <italic>G. lucidum</italic>, strain HG. We also acknowledge helpful comments, suggestions and manuscript reading and English corrections provided by Jing-Wei Jiang.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0065027-Zhong1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Secondary metabolites from higher fungi: discovery, bioactivity, and bioproduction</article-title>. <source>Adv Biochem Eng Biotechnol</source>
<volume>113</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>150</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19475376</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Lin1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>ZB</given-names></name> (<year>1979</year>) <article-title>The current pharmacological research on <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> in China</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharm Sin (in Chinese)</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>192</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Hajjaj1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hajjaj</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Niederberger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Effect of 26-oxygenosterols from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> and their activity as cholesterol synthesis inhibitors</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>71</volume>: <fpage>3653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3658</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16000773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Joseph1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sabulal</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>George</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Antony</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janardhanan</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Antitumor and anti-inflammatory activities of polysaccharides isolated from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Acta Pharm</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21945912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Miyamoto1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kukita</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Regulation of osteoclastogenesis by ganoderic acid DM isolated from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source>
<volume>602</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19026632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Jedinak1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jedinak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thyagarajan-Sahu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sliva</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Ganodermanontriol, a lanostanoid triterpene from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>, suppresses growth of colon cancer cells through ss-catenin signaling</article-title>. <source>Int J Oncol</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>761</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>767</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21225227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Kimura1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Taniguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baba</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Antitumor and antimetastatic effects on liver of triterpenoid fractions of <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>: mechanism of action and isolation of an active substance</article-title>. <source>Anticancer Res</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>3309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3318</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12530080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Li1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>XH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Analysis of Influence of Environmental Conditions on Ganoderic Acid Content in <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> Using Orthogonal Design</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>1940</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1946</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Tang1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Performance analyses of a pH-shift and DOT-shift integrated fed-batch fermentation process for the production of ganoderic acid and Ganoderma polysaccharides by medicinal mushroom <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source>
<volume>100</volume>: <fpage>1852</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1859</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19010665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-MachAigner1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mach-Aigner</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pucher</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>D-Xylose as a repressor or inducer of xylanase expression in <italic>Hypocrea jecorina</italic> (Trichoderma reesei)</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>1770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1776</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20097821</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Zhang1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Use of stimulatory agents to enhance the production of bioactive exopolysaccharide from pleurotus tuber-regium by submerged fermentation</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>59</volume>: <fpage>1210</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1216</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21280626</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Ren1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mu da</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Methyl jasmonate induces ganoderic acid biosynthesis in the basidiomycetous fungus <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Bioresour Technol</source>
<volume>101</volume>: <fpage>6785</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6790</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20395130</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Liang1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>YB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Enhanced biosynthetic gene expressions and production of ganoderic acids in static liquid culture of <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> under phenobarbital induction</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20077112</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Zhang2"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Impact of oxygen level in gaseous phase on gene transcription and ganoderic acid biosynthesis in liquid static cultures of <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Bioprocess Biosyst Eng</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>683</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>690</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19809834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Shiao1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shiao</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Triterpenoid natural products in the fungus <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Chin Chem Soc</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>669</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>674</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Hirotani1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hirotani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Asaka</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furuya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Investigation of the biosynthesis of 3&#x003b1;-hydroxy triterpenoids, ganoderic acids T and S, by application of a feeding experiment using [1, 2&#x02013;<sup>13</sup>C<sub>2</sub>]acetate</article-title>. <source>J Chem Soc Perkin Trans</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>2751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2754</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Zhao1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>WQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Cloning and characterization of squalene synthase (SQS) gene from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>1106</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1112</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18051320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Ding1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>YX</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ou-Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning, characterization, and differential expression of a farnesyl-diphosphate synthase gene from the basidiomycetous fungus <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1579</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18540102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Shang1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ou-Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Cloning and characterization of a gene encoding HMG-CoA reductase from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> and its functional identification in yeast</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>1333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18460810</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Shang2"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning, characterization, and differential expression of a lanosterol synthase gene from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Biosci Biotechnol Biochem</source>
<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>974</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>978</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20460708</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Shi1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Molecular cloning, characterization, and function analysis of a mevalonate pyrophosphate decarboxylase gene from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Rep</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>6149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22203490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Xu1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Enhancement of Ganoderic Acid Accumulation by Overexpression of an N-Terminally Truncated 3-Hydroxy-3-Methylglutaryl Coenzyme A Reductase Gene in the Basidiomycete <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>78</volume>: <fpage>7968</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7976</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22941092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Ren2"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Molecular characterization and expression analysis of GlHMGS, a gene encoding hydroxymethylglutaryl-CoA synthase from <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> (Ling-zhi) in ganoderic acid biosynthesis pathway</article-title>. <source>World J Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>523</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>531</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23138457</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Creelman1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Creelman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tierney</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mullet</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Jasmonic acid/methyl jasmonate accumulate in wounded soybean hypocotyls and modulate wound gene expression</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>89</volume>: <fpage>4938</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4941</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1594598</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Choi1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bostock</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avdiushko</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hildebrand</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name> (<year>1994</year>) <article-title>Lipid-derived signals that discriminate wound- and pathogen-responsive isoprenoid pathways in plants: methyl jasmonate and the fungal elicitor arachidonic acid induce different 3-hydroxy-3-methylglutaryl-coenzyme A reductase genes and antimicrobial isoprenoids in <italic>Solanum tuberosum</italic> L. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</article-title>. <volume>91</volume>: <fpage>2329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2333</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Oh1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Induction of heat shock protein 72 in C6 glioma cells by methyl jasmonate through ROS-dependent heat shock factor 1 activation</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Med</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>833</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>839</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16211252</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Raina1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wankhede</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jaggi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jalmi</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>CrMPK3, a mitogen activated protein kinase from <italic>Catharanthus roseus</italic> and its possible role in stress induced biosynthesis of monoterpenoid indole alkaloids</article-title>. <source>BMC Plant Biol</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>134</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22871174</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Munemasa1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Munemasa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hossain</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Murata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>The Arabidopsis calcium-dependent protein kinase, CPK6, functions as a positive regulator of methyl jasmonate signaling in guard cells</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>155</volume>: <fpage>553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>561</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20978156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Yao1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Effects of a biocontrol agent and methyl jasmonate on postharvest diseases of peach fruit and the possible mechanisms involved</article-title>. <source>J Appl Microbiol</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>941</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>950</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Meimaroglou1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Meimaroglou</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galanopoulou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Markaki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Study of the Effect of Methyl Jasmonate Concentration on Aflatoxin B(1) Biosynthesis by <italic>Aspergillus parasiticus</italic> in Yeast Extract Sucrose Medium</article-title>. <source>Int J Microbiol</source>
<volume>2009</volume>: <fpage>842626</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20016812</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Vergopoulou1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vergopoulou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galanopoulou</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Markaki</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Methyl jasmonate stimulates aflatoxin B1 biosynthesis by <italic>Aspergillus parasiticus</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>3494</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3498</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11453798</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Chen1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Genome sequence of the model medicinal mushroom <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>913</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22735441</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Liu1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The genome of <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> provides insights into triterpenes biosynthesis and wood degradation</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e36146</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22567134</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Conesa1"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garcia-Gomez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Talon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-YonekuraSakakibara1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yonekura-Sakakibara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tohge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakabayashi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Comprehensive flavonol profiling and transcriptome coexpression analysis leading to decoding gene-metabolite correlations in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>2160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2176</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757557</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Yu1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regulation of secondary metabolism in filamentous fungi</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>
<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>437</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16078891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Calvo1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bok</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Relationship between secondary metabolism and fungal development</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12208999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Yin1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>WB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amaike</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wohlbach</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gasch</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>An Aspergillus nidulans bZIP response pathway hardwired for defensive secondary metabolism operates through aflR</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>
<volume>83</volume>: <fpage>1024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1034</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22283524</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Shi2"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Current progress in the study on biosynthesis and regulation of ganoderic acids</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>1243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1251</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20859739</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Yu2"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Deep insight into the <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> by comprehensive analysis of its transcriptome</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e44031</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22952861</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Mo1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milla</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Athenstaedt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Balliano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>In yeast sterol biosynthesis the 3-keto reductase protein (Erg27p) is required for oxidosqualene cyclase (Erg7p) activity</article-title>. <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
<volume>1633</volume>: <fpage>68</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12842197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Zheng1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ke</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A Cdc42 ortholog is required for penetration and virulence of <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Fungal Genet Biol</source>
<volume>46</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>460</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19298860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Bayram1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bayram</surname><given-names>OS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Valerius</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The Aspergillus nidulans MAPK module AnSte11-Ste50-Ste7-Fus3 controls development and secondary metabolism</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002816</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22829779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Raudaskoski1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Raudaskoski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kothe</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Horton</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Ras and Rho small G proteins: insights from the <italic>Schizophyllum commune</italic> genome sequence and comparisons to other fungi</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Genet Eng Rev</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>61</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22616482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Song1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lulla</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Protein kinase D protects against oxidative stress-induced intestinal epithelial cell injury via Rho/ROK/PKC-delta pathway activation</article-title>. <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
<volume>290</volume>: <fpage>C1469</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1476</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16421204</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Quetglas1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Quetglas</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hernaez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galindo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Munoz-Moreno</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cuesta-Geijo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Small rho GTPases and cholesterol biosynthetic pathway intermediates in African swine fever virus infection</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>
<volume>86</volume>: <fpage>1758</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1767</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22114329</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Nishida1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nishida</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gotoh</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>The MAP kinase cascade is essential for diverse signal transduction pathways</article-title>. <source>Trends Biochem Sci</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8388132</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Atoui1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Atoui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grayburn</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Aspergillus nidulans</italic> natural product biosynthesis is regulated by mpkB, a putative pheromone response mitogen-activated protein kinase</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>3596</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3600</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18378656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-You1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>You</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tien</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hsieh</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>A Novel Approach to Enhancing Ganoderic Acid Production by <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic> Using Apoptosis Induction</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e53616</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23326470</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-You2"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>You</surname><given-names>B-J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>W-T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>K-R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>Y-H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C-S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Effect of solid-medium coupled with reactive oxygen species on ganoderic acid biosynthesis and MAP kinase phosphorylation in <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Food Research International</source>
<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>634</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>640</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-MendezAlvarez1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mendez-Alvarez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rufenacht</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Eggen</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>The oxidative stress-sensitive yap1 null strain of Saccharomyces cerevisiae becomes resistant due to increased carotenoid levels upon the introduction of the <italic>Chlamydomonas reinhardtii</italic> cDNA, coding for the 60S ribosomal protein L10a</article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
<volume>267</volume>: <fpage>953</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>959</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10673398</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Rochat1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Rochat</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gratadoux</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gruss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Corthier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maguin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Production of a heterologous nonheme catalase by Lactobacillus casei: an efficient tool for removal of H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2</sub> and protection of <italic>Lactobacillus bulgaricus</italic> from oxidative stress in milk</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>5143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5149</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16885258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Sirikantaramas1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sirikantaramas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms of resistance to self-produced toxic secondary metabolites in plants</article-title>. <source>Phytochemistry Reviews</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Hoppert1"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hoppert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gentzsch</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schorgendorfer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Structure and localization of cyclosporin synthetase, the key enzyme of cyclosporin biosynthesis in <italic>Tolypocladium inflatum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Arch Microbiol</source>
<volume>176</volume>: <fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11685373</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Lendenfeld1"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lendenfeld</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghali</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolschek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubicek-Pranz</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubicek</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Subcellular compartmentation of penicillin biosynthesis in <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum</italic>. The amino acid precursors are derived from the vacuole</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>268</volume>: <fpage>665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>671</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8416970</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Hong1"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linz</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Functional expression and subcellular localization of the aflatoxin pathway enzyme Ver-1 fused to enhanced green fluorescent protein</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>
<volume>74</volume>: <fpage>6385</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6396</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18757582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Chanda1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Chanda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Roze</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Artymovich</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hicks</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>A key role for vesicles in fungal secondary metabolism</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>106</volume>: <fpage>19533</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>19538</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19889978</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Xu2"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhong</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Impacts of calcium signal transduction on the fermentation production of antitumor ganoderic acids by medicinal mushroom <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol Adv</source>
<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>1301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1308</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22036615</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Vuylsteke1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Vuylsteke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peleman</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Eijk</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>AFLP-based transcript profiling (cDNA-AFLP) for genome-wide expression analysis</article-title>. <source>Nat Protoc</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1413</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17545977</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Ashburner1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ashburner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blake</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Botstein</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Gene ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium</article-title>. <source>Nat Genet</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10802651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Mu1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Mu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>The development and application of a multiple gene co-silencing system using endogenous URA3 as a reporter gene in <italic>Ganoderma lucidum</italic>
</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e43737</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22937087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0065027-Livak1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Analysis of relative gene expression data using real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-Delta Delta C(T)) Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>408</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>