<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NPG//DTD XML Article//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName NPG_XML_Article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.7.10?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nature2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">EMBO J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The EMBO Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0261-4189</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2075</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3098484</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">emboj2011112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2011.112</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">21505420</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>The SWI/SNF complex acts to constrain distribution of the centromeric histone variant Cse4 </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="short">SWI/SNF constrains the distribution of Cse4</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gkikopoulos</surname><given-names>Triantaffyllos</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>Vijender</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsui</surname><given-names>Kyle</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>Salma</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Renshaw</surname><given-names>Matthew J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="n1">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Scholfield</surname><given-names>Pieta</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>Geoffrey J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nislow</surname><given-names>Corey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Tomoyuki U</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Owen-Hughes</surname><given-names>Tom</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1">a</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label>1</label><institution>Wellcome Trust Centre for Gene Regulation and Expression, College of Life Sciences, University of Dundee</institution>, Dundee, <country>UK</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Molecular Genetics, The Donnelly Centre, University of Toronto</institution>, Toronto, Ontario, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label>3</label><institution>Division of Biological Chemistry and Drug Discovery, College of Life Sciences, University of Dundee</institution>, Dundee, <country>UK</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1"><label>a</label>Department of Biochemistry, Division of Gene Regulation and Expression, The Wellcome Trust Biocentre, University of Dundee, Dundee DD1 5EH, UK. Tel.: +44 1382 38579; Fax: +44 1382 348072; E-mail: <email>t.a.owenhughes@dundee.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn id="n1"><label>*</label><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Present address: Department of Molecular Genetics, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>18</day><month>05</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>04</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>04</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1919</fpage><lpage>1927</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>08</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>09</day><month>03</month><year>2011</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright © 2011, European Molecular Biology Organization</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><copyright-holder>European Molecular Biology Organization</copyright-holder><license xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial No Derivative Works 3.0 Unported License, which permits distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. This license does not permit commercial exploitation or the creation of derivative works without specific permission.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="hidden-editorial-summary"><title><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>The SWI/SNF complex acts to constrain distribution of the centromeric histone variant Cse4 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>The SWI/SNF complex has an important role in regulating chromatin structure during transcriptional activation and DNA repair. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Here, the SWI/SNF complex is also involved in the organisation of centromeric chromatin and prevention of the ectopic deposition of centromeric histone variants. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><abstract><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>In order to gain insight into the function of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae SWI/SNF complex, we have identified DNA sequences to which it is bound genomewide. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>One surprising observation is that the complex is enriched at the centromeres of each chromosome. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>Deletion of the gene encoding the Snf2 subunit of the complex was found to cause partial redistribution of the centromeric histone variant Cse4 to sites on chromosome arms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Cultures of snf2Δ yeast were found to progress through mitosis slowly. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This was dependent on the mitotic checkpoint protein Mad2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>In the absence of Mad2, defects in chromosome segregation were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>In the absence of Snf2, chromatin organisation at centromeres is less distinct. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>In particular, hypersensitive sites flanking the Cse4 containing nucleosomes are less pronounced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, SWI/SNF complex was found to be especially effective in the dissociation of Cse4 containing chromatin in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>This suggests a role for Snf2 in the maintenance of point centromeres involving the removal of Cse4 from ectopic sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group><kwd>centromere</kwd><kwd>chromatin</kwd><kwd>Cse4</kwd><kwd>nucleosome</kwd><kwd>SWI/SNF</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>The accurate segregation of eukaryotic chromosomes is required to ensure that genetic information is inherited by both daughters following cell division. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>This fundamental process is orchestrated via specialised chromatin structures termed centromeres. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Centromeres serve as the point of attachment for kinetochore proteins, which themselves interact with microtubules during mitosis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>In budding yeast, CEN DNA is made up of a 125-bp sequence consisting of three conserved DNA elements, CDEI, CDEII and CDEIII (Hegemann and Fleig, 1993; Sorger et al, 1995; Cheeseman et al, 2002; Cleveland et al, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Each of these elements is bound by sequence-specific DNA-binding proteins that serve to nucleate the assembly of kinetochores. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Kinetochores consist of inner, central and outer complexes, the latter of which provide sites of microtubule attachment (reviewed by Hyman and Sorger, 1995). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Budding yeast centromeres differ from those in many other species in that the centromeric core is restricted to a nuclease-resistant region spanning ∼200 bp (Furuyama and Biggins, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>This core is flanked on either side by nuclease hypersensitive sites, which are in turn flanked by arrays of positioned nucleosomes (Bloom and Carbon, 1982; Funk et al, 1989; Glowczewski et al, 2000). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>A common feature of centromeric chromatin is the presence of a centromere-specific variant of histone H3 that has a key role in centromere function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>In humans, this variant is known as CenpA, Cid in Drosophila melanogaster, Cnp1 in Schizosaccharomyces pombe and Cse4 in Saccharomyces cerevisiae (Bloom and Carbon, 1982; Palmer et al, 1987; Funk et al, 1989; Schulman and Bloom, 1991; Sullivan et al, 1994; Glowczewski et al, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>These centromeric histone variants have considerable homology with histone H3 (c60% identity within the histone fold region) (Sullivan et al, 1994) and like histone H3 are predicted to adopt a histone fold structure and to interact with histone H4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>The S. cerevisiae CSE4 gene has been identified in several screens for mutants defective in chromosome segregation (Smith et al, 1996; Baker et al, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Cse4 is found to be physically associated with centromeric chromatin both by chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) and immunofluorescence (Meluh et al, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Cse4 differs from centromeric variants in other species in that it includes an N-terminal extension in addition to a core domain with homology to H3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>It is nonetheless found to physically and genetically associate with histone H4 (Glowczewski et al, 2000; Camahort et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Despite some recent reports to the contrary, it remains possible that Cse4 and other centromeric histone variants function as components of an octameric nucleosome-related structure (Camahort et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>In S. cerevisiae, it is known that the inner kinetochore protein Scm3 interacts with Cse4 and is required for recruitment of Cse4 to centromeres (Camahort et al, 2007; Mizuguchi et al, 2007; Stoler et al, 2007; Zhang et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>Mislocalisation of Cse4 has been reported to cause chromosome loss (Au et al, 2008) and in humans this mislocalisation is correlated with colorectal cancer (Tomonaga et al, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>However, overexpression of Cse4 does not necessarily result in mislocalisation to sites out with centromeres (Crotti and Basrai, 2004) raising the possibility that additional mechanisms exist to remove Cse4 that has been misincorporated outwith centromers. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>One such mechanism involves the ubiquitin-mediated proteolysis of ectopically located Cse4 (Collins et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>The structure of chromosomes is regulated throughout their length using a diverse range of strategies. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>These include the post-translational modification of histones (Kouzarides, 2007) and the action of ATP-dependent chromatin remodelling enzymes (Becker and Horz, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>ATP-dependent remodelling enzymes share homology with ATP-dependent DNA translocases and can be classified into many evolutionary conserved subfamilies based on this homology (Flaus et al, 2006). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>One of the first of these proteins to be characterised was the yeast Snf2 protein (Laurent et al, 1991; Hirschhorn et al, 1992). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The Snf2 protein has since been shown to function as the catalytic subunit of the 11 subunit SWI/SNF complex (Smith et al, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>This complex has been shown to be capable of disrupting, repositioning or displacing histones in vitro and in vivo (Côté et al, 1994; Owen-Hughes et al, 1996; Whitehouse et al, 1999; Becker and Horz, 2002). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>Here, we find that the ATP-dependent SWI/SNF chromatin remodelling complex has a role in maintaining the centromeric distribution of Cse4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>SWI/SNF also contributes to the generation of nuclease hypersensitive sites flanking centromeres and acts to dissociate Cse4 containing chromatin in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Our data support a model in which SWI/SNF acts to influence Cse4 distribution via the removal of misincorporated Cse4 rather than via directing incorporation at centromeres. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>Snf2 binding is enriched at yeast centromeres </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>In order to gain insight into the regions of the yeast genome with which the SWI/SNF complex is associated, we isolated DNA fragments bound by Snf2 using ChIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>This DNA was then amplified and hybridised to tiling microarrays with 32 bp resolution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Analysis of these data resulted in the observation of enrichment at several previously reported locations including promoters, Swi4-binding sites and coding regions (Cosma et al, 1999; Schwabish and Struhl, 2007; Venters and Pugh, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>It was also apparent that there was an enrichment of Snf2 within the vicinity of the centromere of each chromosome. Figure 1A shows the enrichment of Snf2 for all yeast chromosomes aligned by their CDEII element. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>A clear enrichment centred over the centromere spanning ∼1000 bp was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>The enrichment within the vicinity of centromeres is also apparent for individual chromosomes as illustrated by the example of CEN16 (Figure 1B). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>To gain confidence that the centromeric distribution we observed was not specific to the array format we were using, we also applied DNA fragments bound by Snf2 to Affymetrix tiling arrays comprised of 25 base oligos tiled every 5 bp (Figure 1C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>A similar pattern of centromeric enrichment was also observed using this platform and was confirmed by quantitative real-time PCR (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>As a role for Snf2 in centromere function had not, to our knowledge been proposed previously, we next sought to investigate the role of Snf2 in maintaining centromere integrity and chromosome segregation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>Snf2 is required to maintain the distribution of the centromeric histone variant Cse4 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>The point centromeres of S. cerevisiae are occupied by a single chromatin particle containing the centromeric histone variant Cse4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>To investigate the genomewide localisation of Cse4, ChIP was used to enrich for bound DNA fragments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Hybridisation to microarrays enabled the distribution to be measured. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Consistent with previous reports, Cse4 was enriched at the centromere of each chromosome with sites on chromosome arms observed occasionally (Figure 2A and C; Supplementary Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>To investigate the role of SWI/SNF in maintaining this distribution, ChIP-chip was also performed in a snf2 deletion strain (Figure 2B and D; Supplementary Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>This shows a reduction in the enrichment at centromeres and considerably increased Cse4 binding at sporadic locations along chromosome arms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>In principle, such a redistribution might in part result from increased expression of Cse4 in a snf2 mutant. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>However, western blotting of whole-cell extracts indicates that the total amount of Cse4 present varies little when SNF2 is deleted (Supplementary Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>However, it was notable that the proportion of Cse4 associated with chromatin increases in a snf2 mutant and that this effect could also be observed following induction of a SNF2 degron (Supplementary Figure S2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with the genomewide location analysis, which also indicates an overall increase in Cse4-enriched sites in a snf2 mutant (Supplementary Figure S1). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>The mitotic checkpoint is unsatisfied in the absence of Snf2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>As Cse4 is required for centromere function, it might be anticipated that snf2 mutant strains display a chromosome segregation defect. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>In order to investigate this further, the fate of an individual centromere was monitored by fluorescence microscopy (Michaelis et al, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>The number of copies of CEN5 visualised as a result of tagging with tet-GFP was compared with spindle poles with the ratio of the two signals proving a means to assess aneuploidy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>In a snf2Δ strain, there was not a major increase in aneuploidy for CEN5 (Figure 3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>However, in synchronised cultures of snf2Δ strains, it is clear that chromosome segregation does not go to completion at the same rate as for the wt strain (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Separation events are observed, but the distance between centromeres oscillates between 1 and 2 μm for a prolonged period prior to anaphase (Supplementary Figure S3A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>One possible explanation for this is that the mitotic checkpoint is abrogated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Defects in the localisation of Cse4 might be anticipated to have this effect as conditional alleles of CSE4 have been observed to have the mitotic checkpoint unsatisfied (Glowczewski et al, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>To investigate this further, the effect of inactivating the mitotic checkpoint through deletion of MAD2 was investigated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>Scoring the proportion of cells in metaphase by fluorescent microscopy indicated a reduction from 31% in snf2Δ to 21% snf2Δ mad2Δ consistent with unsatisfied mitotic checkpoint in the absence of Snf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>This was confirmed by fluorescent-activated cell sorting (FACS) analysis, which indicated a reduction in the proportion of cells with a 2C DNA content from 86% in a snf2Δ strain to 67% in a snf2Δ mad2Δ Figure 3C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, chromosome missegregation was more pronounced in the absence of Snf2 and Mad2 as observed by monitoring segregation of CEN5 (Figure 3A) as an increase in the proportion of cells with DNA content other than 1 or 2C in FACS analysis (Figure 3C and D). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>Finally, degron-mediated depletion of Snf2 was observed to cause a delay in chromosome segregation (Supplementary Figure S3B and C) similar to that observed following deletion of SNF2 (Figure 3B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>This delay was reduced following deletion of MAD2 (Supplementary Figure S3B and C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>In concert, these observations are consistent with mislocalisation of Cse4 causing a proportion of cells to arrest at the mitotic checkpoint until centromere function can be restored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>This may contribute to the previously reported slow growth of snf2 mutants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Snf2 contributes to nucleosome organisation at centromeres </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="85" pm="?"><plain>How does SWI/SNF act to maintain Cse4 localisation? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that SWI/SNF directs incorporation of Cse4 at centromeres, perhaps in a manner similar to the way the Swr1 complex directs incorporation of the histone variant Htz1 (Mizuguchi et al, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>However, we do not find that Cse4 is generally colocalised with SWI/SNF at all sites in the genome (not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, SWI/SNF-related complexes have a stronger activity in the destabilisation of nucleosomes than in their assembly (Owen-Hughes et al, 1996; Bruno et al, 2003; Lorch et al, 2006; Dechassa et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>To investigate the effect of the SWI/SNF complex on centromeric chromatin organisation, we mapped the locations of nucleosomes genomewide using tiled microarrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>In a wild-type (SNF2+) strain, nucleosome alignment for each chromosome with respect to the CDEII element provides a means of viewing the average chromatin organisation at the 16 S. cerevisiae centromeres. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Prominent features include a protected region of some 177 bp spanning the centromere flanked by hypersensitive sites on either side (Figure 4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with previous studies of chromatin organisation at centromeres (Furuyama and Biggins, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>To investigate the role of Snf2 in this region, chromatin was also mapped in a snf2Δ strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>In this case, the hypersensitive sites flanking the centromeric nucleosome are less prominent (Figure 4A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In contrast, hypersensitive sites flanking ARS sequences are not affected (Figure 4B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>This supports a role for SWI/SNF in the organisation of chromatin adjacent to centromeres. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>SWI/SNF destabilises Cse4 containing nucleosomes </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>The SWI/SNF complex has been implicated in the removal of nucleosomes at a number of yeast genes (Barbaric et al, 2007; Schwabish and Struhl, 2007; Bryant et al, 2008; Shivaswamy and Iyer, 2008; Gkikopoulos et al, 2009; Takahata et al, 2009) and to be capable of destabilising nucleosomes in vitro (Owen-Hughes et al, 1996; Bruno et al, 2003; Lorch et al, 2006; Dechassa et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>If SWI/SNF were to have a role in removing Cse4 from noncentromeric sites, it would be anticipated that SWI/SNF should be able to remove Cse4 containing nucleosomes from DNA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>To test this, histone octamers were prepared using recombinant yeast histones H4, H2A and H2B and either histone H3 or Cse4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Octamers prepared in this way could be used to assemble chromatin particles on short DNA fragments that are likely to assume a nucleosomal organisation (Camahort et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Chromatin prepared in this way was used as a substrate for remodelling assays using SWI/SNF complex in the presence or absence of the histone chaperone Nap1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The ATP-dependent action of SWI/SNF in the presence of increasing concentrations of the histone chaperone Nap1 resulted in a reduction in the proportion of DNA assembled as Cse4 containing chromatin and an increase in the amount of free DNA (Figure 5A). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>This shows that the SWI/SNF complex is capable of destabilising chromatin that contains Cse4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, as nucleosomes assembled using H3 were not destabilised following remodelling with SWI/SNF and Nap1, it appears that Cse4 containing chromatin is especially susceptible to SWI/SNF driven dissociation (Figure 5B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>This property of Cse4 containing nucleosomes is not unique to the 601 DNA fragment as similar observations were made with nucleosomes assembled onto a DNA fragment derived from the MMTV promoter (Supplementary Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The susceptibility of Cse4 containing nucleosomes to dissociation is specific to a subset of remodelling enzymes as Chd1 was found not to function in this assay (Supplementary Figure S4). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The observation that SWI/SNF is capable of directing dissociation of Cse4 containing chromatin supports a role for SWI/SNF in the removal of Cse4 from ectopic locations along chromosome arms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>If this is the case then it might be anticipated that deletion of SNF2 would result in accumulation of Cse4 at sites previously bound by Snf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This is, in fact, what we observe. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>In a snf2Δ strain, the strongly enriched ectopic Cse4 sites are found to be enriched for Snf2 in a wild-type strain when compared with an equal number of randomly selected sites (Figure 6). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec disp-level="1"><title><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Following the observation of Snf2 enrichment at centromeres, we discovered that the SWI/SNF complex has an unanticipated role in determining the localisation of the centromeric histone variant Cse4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>SWI/SNF was also found to have a role in the maintenance of nuclease hypersensitive sites flanking centromeres and to be capable of removing Cse4 containing chromatin from DNA in vitro. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>These observations support a model in which SWI/SNF acts to maintain the organisation of S. cerevisiae point centromeres by removing Cse4 misincorporated at ectopic locations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Although we show that Snf2 is enriched at centromeres we do not fully understand how it is recruited. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that the recently reported interactions between components of the SWI/SNF complex and the kinetochore component Ndc80 have a role in this process (Wong et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>However, we have found that Snf2 is still recruited to centromeres when conditional Ndc80 mutants are grown at the nonpermissive temperature (Gkikopoulos, data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>This raises the possibility that additional mechanisms of centromeric recruitment exist. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>One attractive possibility is that Cbf1 acts to recruit SWI/SNF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, we have observed that the enrichment of Snf2 is greater in the vicinity of Cbf1-binding sites in comparison to randomly selected sites genomewide (Supplementary Figure S5). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The SWI/SNF complex is not the only chromatin remodelling complex implicated in centromere function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>In budding yeast, the multi-subunit RSC complex is closely related to SWI/SNF but known to perform distinct functions (Laurent et al, 1992; Cairns et al, 1996). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>Mutations to RSC components also activate the mitotic checkpoint and influence chromatin structure within the vicinity of centromeres (Tsuchiya et al, 1992, 1998; Angus-Hill et al, 2001; Hsu et al, 2003; Yamada et al, 2008) and cause changes in chromosome ploidy (Campsteijn et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>However, depletion of RSC has been reported not to affect the recruitment of Cse4 to centromeres (Hsu et al, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, RSC has additional roles at sites of cohesion along chromosome arms (Huang et al, 2004) perhaps contributing to it's role in chromosome transmission (Wong et al, 2002). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>It is notable that Rsc3 is enriched at centromeres in a similar way to Snf2 (Venters and Pugh, 2009; data not shown) raising the possibility that both RSC and SWI/SNF function in a partially redundant way to destabilise Cse4 containing nucleosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, we find that RSC, like SWI/SNF can destabilise Cse4 containing nucleosomes in vitro (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>An assortment of different ATP-dependent chromatin remodelling enzymes have been implicated in centromere function. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>For example, the Snf2-related ATPase, PICH, is recruited to centromeres and required for recruitment of Mad2 to kinetochores (Baumann et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>Other Snf2 family proteins have been proposed to influence the distribution of centromeric histone variants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>These include the fission yeast Chd1 homologue, Hrp1, which has been shown to have a role in loading the centromeric histone variant Cnp1 at centromeres (Walfridsson et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>Related observations have been made in Chicken and Human cells (Okada et al, 2009), but it has more recently been reported that Chd1 has no role in CenpA deposition in Drosophila (Podhraski et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>Another nucleosome spacing complex, RSF, has been shown to influence CenpA distribution in HeLa cells (Perpelescu et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>In most of these cases, a role for remodelling enzymes in directing deposition has been proposed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>In contrast, we proposed that SWI/SNF acts to maintain the distribution of Cse4 by removing it from ectopic locations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>The accumulation of Cse4 at ectopic locations has been observed previously (Camahort et al, 2009; Lefrancois et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>What defines these ectopic locations is not clear. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>One possibility is that Cse4 is incorporated at sites of high histone turnover (Dion et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>We find a 10% coincidence between sites of ectopic Cse4 and hot nucleosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>This is statistically highly significant, suggesting that histone turnover contributes at a subset of cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>However, additional factors are likely to be involved at locations where there is no coincidence between Cse4 incorporation and histone turnover. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>In vitro we found that the combined action of SWI/SNF and Nap1 acted to preferentially destabilise Cse4 containing nucleosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>Our favoured explanation for how this might occur is that Cse4 containing nucleosomes are inherently less stable than H3 containing nucleosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>We are not aware of any evidence to suggest that Nap1 normally participates in this process, but it is possible that a spectrum of nucleosome destablising activities may be effective in removing Cse4 containing nucleosomes from sites along chromosome arms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="?"><plain>This raises the question of what stabilises Cse4 deposited at the centromere? </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>A possible explanation for this is that association of kinetochore proteins prevents Cse4 containing chromatin from docking within the nucleosome-binding cleft in the SWI/SNF complex (Smith et al, 2003; Dechassa et al, 2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>Consistent with this, previous studies indicate that the Ndc10 kinetochore components are required for localisation of Cse4 to centromeres (Ortiz et al, 1999; Pearson et al, 2003). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>Alternatively, if Scm3 remains associated with Cse4 at centromeres, the resulting chromatin particle may not be a good substrate for SWI/SNF (Mizuguchi et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>The recruitment of Cse4 to centromeres is unlikely by itself to be sufficiently accurate to specify a single nucleosome/chromatin particle. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>However, the action of SWI/SNF and possibly additional nucleosome dissociating activities could help to remove Cse4 that happens to be deposited at locations along chromosome arms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>The degradation of ectopic Cse4 provides an additional means of regulating the localisation of Cse4 (Hewawasam et al, 2010; Ranjitkar et al, 2010). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>The presence of hypersensitive sites flanking the centromere might be anticipated to alter the net contribution of a yeast centromere to DNA topology. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>For example, if a functional centromere consists of one left-handed nucleosome flanked by two nucleosome-depleted regions and inactivation of the centromere results in loss of the nucleosome-free regions, this could result in a net change in linking number of +2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Such a change in linking number has been observed, but has been interpreted as evidence that the centromeric chromatin particle constrains a positive supercoil (Furuyama and Henikoff, 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>It is not clear whether the function of SWI/SNF in removing ectopic Cse4 is restricted to organisms with point centromeres. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>However, it is notable that human SWI/SNF B (PBAF) localises to kinetochores in metaphase (Xue et al, 2000). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, deletion of BRG1 results in the dissolution of pericentromeric heterochromatin, and appearance of micronuclei and an increase in cells undergoing aberrant mitoses (Bourgo et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>Further study will be required to establish whether these observations reflect and activity of BRG1 related to that of SWI/SNF at budding yeast centromeres. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>Our study provides an example of a SWI/SNF-related complex functioning to maintain a nucleosome-depleted region. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>This adds to a list of specific examples in which SWI/SNF has been linked to nucleosome removal (Barbaric et al, 2007; Schwabish and Struhl, 2007; Bryant et al, 2008; Shivaswamy and Iyer, 2008; Gkikopoulos et al, 2009; Takahata et al, 2009) and general correlations between Snf2 localisation and histone occupancy genomewide (Gkikopoulos, data not shown; Dion et al, 2007; Venters and Pugh, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>It is important to point out that while this manuscript has focused on the Snf2-dependent changes to chromatin structure at centromeres, additional changes are evident elsewhere in the genome in our data set (data not shown). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>The closely related RSC complex has also been shown to have a role in the generation of nucleosome-free regions at a significant number of promoters genomewide (Badis et al, 2008; Hartley and Madhani, 2009; Venters and Pugh, 2009). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Regions of high nucleosome turnover that show net depletion of histones are a common feature of many eukaryotic genomes (reviewed by Radman-Livaja and Rando, 2010). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>Our observations linking chromatin disassembly to the distribution of Cse4 lend support to the attractive notion that nucleosome-depleted regions may act to punctuate the genomewide distribution of chromatin marks (Dion et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec disp-level="1" sec-type="materials|methods"><title><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>Yeast growth and manipulation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Standard procedures were used for culture and manipulation of yeast (Amberg et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Strains used in this study are listed in Supplementary Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>Constructs of CEN5-tetOs were previously described (Tanaka et al, 2000). snf2Δ and mad2Δ mutants were constructed according to a PCR-based protocol (Longtine et al, 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Deletion of SWI2 was always carried out as the last step in all snf2Δ strains used in this study. CSE4 was tagged with 3xmyc using the plasmid pYM5 as previously described (Knop et al, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>For the construction of the swi2-degron strains, an auxin-based system was used as previously described (Nishimura et al, 2009). SWI2 was tagged with 9xmyc using the plasmid pYM20 as previously described (Janke et al, 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>To deplete Snf2-aid, starter cultures were grown at 25°C for at least 8 h in YPA medium supplemented with 2% galactose and 2% raffinose. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>Subsequently, cultures were incubated at 30°C and Snf2-aid depletion was induced by addition of IAA at 2 mM final concentration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Chromatin immunoprecipitation </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>ChIP was performed using monoclonal anti-myc antibody (9E10—Millipore) and polyclonal anti-mouse Dynabeads (Dynal) as previously described (Gkikopoulos et al, 2009). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>Chromatin isolation and western blotting </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>To examine Cse4 level in chromatin, extracts were prepared based on previously described protocols (Conradt et al, 1992; Donovan et al, 1997). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>In brief, after spheroplasting and regrowth, cells were washed three times with lysis buffer (0.4 M Sorbitol/150 mM potassium acetate/2 mM magnesium acetate/20 mM Pipes/KOH, pH 6.8/1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride/10 μg/ml leupeptin/1 μg/ml pepstatin A/10 mM benzamidine). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Cells were resuspended in lysis buffer at no more than 8 × 108 cells/ml and lysed by addition of Triton X-100 to a final concentration of 1%. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>The chromatin-enriched fraction was isolated after centrifugation for 15 min at 15 800 g, and the supernatant was carefully removed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>To clean the samples from the DNA, extracts were incubated with three Kunitz units of DNase1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>In all cases, lysates were separated into a supernatant and a pellet as described above after a 5-min incubation on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>For the immunoblot analysis, pellet and supernatant samples were run on 4–12% NUPAGE gels. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>After that, proteins were transferred to nitrocellulose and blocked with 5% dry milk in Tris-buffered saline containing 0.1% Tween 20. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Purified 9E10 (anti-myc) was used at 1:2000 dilution, and immunoreactive bands were visualised with enhanced chemiluminescence (Millipore) according to the manufacturer's instructions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Microarray hybridisation and data analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>For microarray hybridisations, DNA purified by ChIP was amplified using the WGA kit (Sigma). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>Products were applied to Nimblegen tiling arrays (ArrayExpress accession: A-MEXP-1949) according to the manufacturer's specifications except for the data shown in Figures 1C and 4 where Affymetrix PN 520055 arrays were used and processed according to Badis et al (2008). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>Data from hybridisations used in this study has been submitted to ArrayExpress; Accession numbers: E-TABM-1141, E-MEXP-3163. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>For the nucleosome analysis, the raw data from Affymetrix GCOS software (.CEL format) were analysed with Affymetrix Tiling Analysis Software v1.1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>A tiling analysis group (.TAG file) for a two-sample analysis containing the three nucleosomal experiments as the ‘treatment' and the three whole-genome samples as the ‘control' was created in the Tiling Analysis Software. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>The two samples were then quantile normalised and median centred to produce a .txt file. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>ARS coordinates were defined from SGD. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Fold enrichment in Figure 1 was calculated by averaging the mean log2 enrichment ratio per bp across all chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>For the purpose of plotting Figure 2, a threshold was selected and only enrichment values above the threshold were plotted on the graph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>For the selection of ectopic sites in SWI2+, a lower threshold to that applied in snf2Δ data set was used in order to select a similar number of sites. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Enrichment values for Snf2-myc in Figure 6 were calculated by taking the mean signal of a 400-bp long window centred at the assigned location of either the ectopic or the randomly selected site and standard error was plotted. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Fluorescent microscopy techniques </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>Cultures were prepared for microscopy essentially as described previously (Dewar et al, 2004; Tanaka et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>For synchronisation with α factor, cells were grown at 25°C to an OD: 0.2–0.4 and cell synchrony was monitored my bright field microscopy over 2–3 h to achieve at least 90% arrested cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>Release from α factor arrest was achieved by washing cells with 2 × volumes distilled water and cells were subsequently grown at 30°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>Delta T-dishes and Delta T heater (Bioptechs Inc) were used for live cell microscopy at 30°C. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>FACS </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>Cells were fixed using 70% ethanol, then stained with propidium iodide as described (Amberg et al, 2005). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>Aggregates of cells were disrupted by sonication prior to FACS analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Purification of SWI/SNF and Nap1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>SWI/SNF was purified from yeast whole-cell extract by tandem affinity purification (TAP) over two-affinity columns from a Snf6TAP tag strain (Puig et al, 2001). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Nap1 was expressed from a pET15b vector (Novagen) in Escherichia coli and purified by cobalt affinity, anion exchange and gel filtration chromatography. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title><text><SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>Nucleosome reconstitution and remodelling </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Recombinant yeast histones (Cse4, H3, H4, H2A and H2B) were expressed and purified as described (Luger et al, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>Nucleosomes were assembled by mixing equimolar amounts of histone octamer and DNA in high salt and performing continuous dialysis into low salt. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>The DNA fragment used in the assembly has 42 and 47 nucleotides flanking a synthetically selected 601 nucleosome positioning sequence (Thastrom et al, 1999). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>The fragment was PCR amplified with primer labelled with Cy5 dye (Ferreira et al, 2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>In all, 1 pmol of Cse4 and H3 octamers assembled onto Cy5-labelled 42W47 DNA was incubated with SWI/SNF (0.5 pmol) and Nap1 (as indicated) in the presence of 1 mM ATP at 30°C for 1 h. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>The buffer used in reactions contained 50 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris (pH 7.5) and 3 mM MgCl2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>The reactions were stopped using 500 ng of HindIII digested λ phage DNA and adding glycerol to 4% (V/V) and placed on ice. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>The samples were separated on TE (10 mM Tris–HCl pH 8.0, 1 mm EDTA), 5% polyacrylamide gels for 1 h at 300 V at 4°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>Gels were scanned in a Fuji FLA-5100 fluorescent scanner. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="S1"><title><text><SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><supplementary-material id="d31e30" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Supplementary Information </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112s1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="d31e33" content-type="local-data"><caption><title><text><SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Review Process File </plain></SENT>
</text></title></caption><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112s2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"/></supplementary-material></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>We thank Brad Cairns, Andrew Flaus and Philip Korber for histone expression plasmids. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We thank Rosie Clark for assistance with FACS analysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>This work was funded by Wellcome Trust Senior Fellowship 064414 (TG, VS, TOH). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Work in CN's laboratory is supported by the CFI and CIHR (86705). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>We thank the members of the TOH and TT laboratories for informative discussion and suggestions. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><ref id="b1"><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>AmbergDC, BurkeDJ, StrathernJN (2005) Methods in Yeast Genetics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>Cold Spring Harbor, NY: Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b2"><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Angus-HillML, SchlichterA, RobertsD, Erdjument-BromageH, TempstP, CairnsBR (2001) A Rsc3/Rsc30 zinc cluster dimer reveals novel roles for the chromatin remodeler RSC in gene expression and cell cycle control. Mol Cell 7: 741–75111336698 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b3"><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>AuWC, CrispMJ, DeLucaSZ, RandoOJ, BasraiMA (2008) Altered dosage and mislocalization of histone H3 and Cse4p lead to chromosome loss in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Genetics 179: 263–27518458100 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b4"><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>BadisG, ChanET, van BakelH, Pena-CastilloL, TilloD, TsuiK, CarlsonCD, GossettAJ, HasinoffMJ, WarrenCL, GebbiaM, TalukderS, YangA, MnaimnehS, TerterovD, CoburnD, YeoAL, YeoZX, ClarkeND, LiebJD  (2008) A library of yeast transcription factor motifs reveals a widespread function for Rsc3 in targeting nucleosome exclusion at promoters. Mol Cell 32: 878–88719111667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b5"><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>BakerRE, HarrisK, ZhangKM (1998) Mutations synthetically lethal with cep1 target S-cerevisiae kinetochore components. Genetics 149: 73–859584087 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b6"><text><SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>BarbaricS, LuckenbachT, SchmidA, BlaschkeD, HorzW, KorberP (2007) Redundancy of chromatin remodeling pathways for the induction of the yeast PHO5 promoter in vivo. J Biol Chem 282: 27610–2762117631505 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b7"><text><SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>BaumannC, KornerR, HofmannK, NiggEA (2007) PICH, a centromere-associated SNF2 family ATPase, is regulated by Plk1 and required for the spindle checkpoint. Cell 128: 101–11417218258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b8"><text><SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>BeckerPB, HorzW (2002) ATP-dependent nucleosome remodeling. Annu Rev Biochem 71: 247–27312045097 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b9"><text><SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>BloomKS, CarbonJ (1982) Yeast centromere DNA is in a unique and highly ordered structure in chromosomes and small circular minichromosomes. Cell 29: 305–3176288253 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b10"><text><SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>BourgoRJ, SiddiquiH, FoxS, SolomonD, SansamCG, YanivM, MuchardtC, MetzgerD, ChambonP, RobertsCWM, KnudsenES (2009) SWI/SNF deficiency results in aberrant chromatin organization, mitotic failure, and diminished proliferative capacity. Mol Biol Cell 20: 3192–319919458193 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b11"><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>BrunoM, FlausA, StockdaleC, RencurelC, FerreiraH, Owen-HughesT (2003) Histone H2A/H2B dimer exchange by ATP-dependent chromatin remodeling activities. Mol Cell 12: 1599–160614690611 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b12"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>BryantGO, PrabhuV, FloerM, WangX, SpagnaD, SchreiberD, PtashneM (2008) Activator control of nucleosome occupancy in activation and repression of transcription. Plos Biol 6: 2928–293919108605 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b13"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>CairnsBR, LorchY, LiY, ZhangM, LacomisL, Erdjument-BromageH, TempstP, DuJ, LaurentB, KornbergRD (1996) RSC, an essential, abundant chromatin-remodeling complex. Cell 87: 1249–12608980231 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b14"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>CamahortR, LiB, FlorensL, SwansonSK, WashburnMP, GertonJL (2007) Scm3 is essential to recruit the histone H3 variant Cse4 to centromeres and to maintain a functional kinetochore. Mol Cell 26: 853–86517569568 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b15"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>CamahortR, ShivarajuM, MattinglyM, LiB, NakanishiS, ZhuDX, ShilatifardA, WorkmanJL, GertonJL (2009) Cse4 is part of an octameric nucleosome in budding yeast. Mol Cell 35: 794–80519782029 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b16"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>CampsteijnC, Wijnands-CollinAMJ, LogieC (2007) Reverse genetic analysis of the yeast RSC chromatin remodeler reveals a role for RSC3 and SNF5 homolog 1 in ploidy maintenance. Plos Genetics 3: 947–957 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b17"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>CheesemanIM, DrubinDG, BarnesG (2002) Simple centromere, complex kinetochore: linking spindle microtubules and centromeric DNA in budding yeast. J Cell Biol 157: 199–20311956223 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b18"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>ClevelandDW, MaoYH, SullivanKF (2003) Centromeres and kinetochores: from epigenetics to mitotic checkpoint signaling. Cell 112: 407–42112600307 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b19"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>CollinsKA, CastilloAR, TatsutaniSY, BigginsS (2005) De novo kinetochore assembly requires the centromeric histone H3 variant. Mol Biol Cell 16: 5649–566016207811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b20"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>ConradtB, ShawJ, VidaT, EmrS, WicknerW (1992) In vitro reactions of vacuole inheritance in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. J Cell Biol 119: 1469–14791334958 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b21"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>CosmaMP, TanakaT, NasmythK (1999) Ordered recruitment of transcription and chromatin remodeling factors to a cell cycle and developmentally regulated promoter. Cell 97: 299–31110319811 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b22"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>CôtéJ, QuinnJ, WorkmanJL, PetersonCL (1994) Stimulation of GAL4 derivative binding to nucleosomal DNA by the yeast SWI/SNF complex. Science 265: 53–608016655 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b23"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>CrottiLB, BasraiMA (2004) Functional roles for evolutionarily conserved Spt4p at centromeres and heterochromatin in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. EMBO J 23: 1804–181415057281 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b24"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>DechassaML, SabriA, PondugulaS, KassabovSR, ChatterjeeN, KladdeMP, BartholomewB (2010) SWI/SNF has intrinsic nucleosome disassembly activity that is dependent on adjacent nucleosomes. Mol Cell 38: 590–60220513433 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b25"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>DechassaML, ZhangB, Horowitz-SchererR, PersingerJ, WoodcockCL, PetersonCL, BartholomewB (2008) Architecture of the SWI/SNF-nucleosome complex. Mol Cell Biol 28: 6010–602118644858 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b26"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>DewarH, TanakaK, NasmythK, TanakaTU (2004) Tension between two kinetochores suffices for their bi-orientation on the mitotic spindle. Nature 428: 93–9714961024 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b27"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>DionMF, KaplanT, KimM, BuratowskiS, FriedmanN, RandoOJ (2007) Dynamics of replication-independent histone turnover in budding yeast. Science 315: 1405–140817347438 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b28"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>DonovanS, HarwoodJ, DruryLS, DiffleyJFX (1997) Cdc6p-dependent loading of Mcm proteins onto pre-replicative chromatin in budding yeast. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 94: 5611–56169159120 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b29"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>FerreiraH, SomersJ, WebsterR, FlausA, Owen-HughesT (2007) Histone tails and the H3 alphaN helix regulate nucleosome mobility and stability. Mol Cell Biol 27: 4037–404817387148 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b30"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>FlausA, MartinDMA, BartonGJ, Owen-HughesT (2006) Identification of multiple distinct Snf2 subfamilies with conserved structural motifs. Nucl Acids Res 34: 2887–290516738128 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b31"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>FunkM, HegemannJH, PhilippsenP (1989) Chromatin digestion with restriction endonucleases reveals 150--160 bp of protected DNA in the centromere of chromosome-Xiv in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Mol Gen Genet 219: 153–1602693939 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b32"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>FuruyamaS, BigginsS (2007) Centromere identity is specified by a single centromeric nucleosome in budding yeast. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 104: 14706–1471117804787 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b33"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>FuruyamaT, HenikoffS (2009) Centromeric nucleosomes induce positive DNA supercoils. Cell 138: 104–11319596238 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b34"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>GkikopoulosT, HavasKM, DewarH, Owen-HughesT (2009) SWI/SNF and Asf1p cooperate to displace histones during induction of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae HO promoter. Mol Cell Biol 29: 4057–406619470759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b35"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>GlowczewskiL, YangPR, KalashnikovaT, SantistebanMS, SmithMM (2000) Histone-histone interactions and centromere function. Mol Cell Biol 20: 5700–571110891506 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b36"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>HartleyPD, MadhaniHD (2009) Mechanisms that specify promoter nucleosome location and identity. Cell 137: 445–45819410542 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b37"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>HegemannJH, FleigUN (1993) The centromere of budding yeast. Bioessays 15: 451–4608379948 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b38"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>HewawasamG, ShivarajuM, MattinglyM, VenkateshS, Martin-BrownS, FlorensL, WorkmanJL, GertonJL (2010) Psh1 is an E3 ubiquitin ligase that targets the centromeric histone variant Cse4. Mol Cell 40: 444–45421070970 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b39"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>HirschhornJN, BrownSA, ClarkCD, WinstonF (1992) Evidence that SNF2/SWI2 and SNF5 activate transcription in yeast by altering chromatin structure. Genes Dev 6: 2288–22981459453 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b40"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>HsuJM, HuangJ, MeluhPB, LaurentBC (2003) The yeast RSC chromatin-remodeling complex is required for kinetochore function in chromosome segregation. Mol Cell Biol 23: 3202–321512697820 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b41"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>HuangJ, HsuJM, LaurentBC (2004) The RSC nucleosome-remodeling complex is required for Cohesin's association with chromosome arms. Mol Cell 13: 739–75015023343 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b42"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>HymanAA, SorgerPK (1995) Structure and function of kinetochores in budding yeast. Ann Rev Cell Dev Biol 11: 471–4958689566 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b43"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>JankeC, MagieraMM, RathfelderN, TaxisC, ReberS, MaekawaH, Moreno-BorchartA, DoengesG, SchwobE, SchiebelE, KnopM (2004) A versatile toolbox for PCR-based tagging of yeast genes: new fluorescent proteins, more markers and promoter substitution cassettes. Yeast 21: 947–96215334558 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b44"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>KnopM, SiegersK, PereiraG, ZachariaeW, WinsorB, NasmythK, SchiebelE (1999) Epitope tagging of yeast genes using a PCR-based strategy: more tags and improved practical routines. Yeast 15: 963–97210407276 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b45"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>KouzaridesT (2007) Chromatin modifications and their function. Cell 128: 693–70517320507 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b46"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>LaurentBC, TreitelMA, CarlsonM (1991) Functional interdependence of the yeast SNF2, SNF5, and SNF6 proteins in transcriptional activation. Proc Natl Acad Sci 88: 2687–26911901413 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b47"><text><SENT sid="275" pm="."><plain>LaurentBC, YangX, CarlsonM (1992) An essential Saccharomyces cerevisiae gene homologous to SNF2 encodes a helicase-related protein in a new family. Mol Cell Biol 12: 1893–19021549132 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b48"><text><SENT sid="276" pm="."><plain>LeeW, TilloD, BrayN, MorseRH, DavisRW, HughesTR, NislowC (2007) A high-resolution atlas of nucleosome occupancy in yeast. Nat Genet 39: 1235–124417873876 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b49"><text><SENT sid="277" pm="."><plain>LefrancoisP, EuskirchenGM, AuerbachRK, RozowskyJ, GibsonT, YellmanCM, GersteinM, SnyderM (2009) Efficient yeast ChIP-Seq using multiplex short-read DNA sequencing. BMC Genomics 10: 3719159457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b50"><text><SENT sid="278" pm="."><plain>LongtineMS, McKenzieAIII, DemariniDJ, ShahNG, WachA, BrachatA, PhilippsenP, PringleJR (1998) Additional modules for versatile and economical PCR-based gene deletion and modification in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast 14: 953–9619717241 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b51"><text><SENT sid="279" pm="."><plain>LorchY, Maier-DavisB, KornbergRD (2006) Chromatin remodeling by nucleosome disassembly in vitro. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 103: 3090–309316492771 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b52"><text><SENT sid="280" pm="."><plain>LugerK, RechsteinerTJ, RichmondTJ (1999) Preparation of nucleosome core particle from recombinant histones. Methods Enzymol 304: 3–1910372352 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b53"><text><SENT sid="281" pm="."><plain>MeluhPB, YangPR, GlowczewskiL, KoshlandD, SmithMM (1998) Cse4p is a component of the core centromere of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Cell 94: 607–6139741625 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b54"><text><SENT sid="282" pm="."><plain>MichaelisC, CioskR, NasmythK (1997) Cohesins: chromosomal proteins that prevent premature separation of sister chromatids. Cell 91: 35–459335333 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b55"><text><SENT sid="283" pm="."><plain>MizuguchiG, ShenX, LandryJ, WuWH, SenS, WuC (2004) ATP-driven exchange of histone H2AZ variant catalyzed by SWR1 chromatin remodeling complex. Science 303: 343–34814645854 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b56"><text><SENT sid="284" pm="."><plain>MizuguchiG, XiaoH, WisniewskiJ, SmithMM, WuC (2007) Nonhistone Scm3 and histones CenH3-H4 assemble the core of centromere-specific nucleosomes. Cell 129: 1153–116417574026 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b57"><text><SENT sid="285" pm="."><plain>NishimuraK, FukagawaT, TakisawaH, KakimotoT, KanemakiM (2009) An auxin-based degron system for the rapid depletion of proteins in nonplant cells. Nat Methods 6: 917–U97819915560 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b58"><text><SENT sid="286" pm="."><plain>OkadaM, OkawaK, IsobeT, FukagawaT (2009) CENP-H-containing complex facilitates centromere deposition of CENP-A in cooperation with FACT and CHD1. Mol Biol Cell 20: 3986–399519625449 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b59"><text><SENT sid="287" pm="."><plain>OrtizJ, StemmannO, RankS, LechnerJ (1999) A putative protein complex consisting of Ctf19, Mcm21 and Okp1 represents a missing link in the budding yeast kinetochore. Genes Dev 13: 1140–115510323865 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b60"><text><SENT sid="288" pm="."><plain>Owen-HughesT, UtleyRT, CoteJ, PetersonCL, WorkmanJL (1996) Persistent site-specific remodeling of a nucleosome array by transient action of the SWI/SNF complex. Science 273: 513–5168662543 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b61"><text><SENT sid="289" pm="."><plain>PalmerDK, OdayK, WenerMH, AndrewsBS, MargolisRL (1987) A 17-Kd centromere protein (Cenp-a) copurifies with nucleosome core particles and with histones. J Cell Biol 104: 805–8153558482 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b62"><text><SENT sid="290" pm="."><plain>PearsonCG, MaddoxPS, ZarzarTR, SalmonED, BloomK (2003) Yeast kinetochores do not stabilize Stu2p-dependent spindle microtubule dynamics. Mol Biol Cell 14: 4181–419514517328 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b63"><text><SENT sid="291" pm="."><plain>PerpelescuM, NozakiN, ObuseC, YangH, YodaK (2009) Active establishment of centromeric CENP-A chromatin by RSF complex. J Cell Biol 185: 397–40719398759 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b64"><text><SENT sid="292" pm="."><plain>PodhraskiV, Campo-FernandezB, WorleH, PiattiP, NiedereggerH, BockG, FyodorovDV, LusserA (2010) CenH3/CID incorporation is not dependent on the chromatin assembly factor CHD1 in Drosophila. PLoS One 5: e1012020396651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b65"><text><SENT sid="293" pm="."><plain>PuigO, CasparyF, RigautG, RutzB, BouveretE, Bragado-NilssonE, WilmM, SeraphinB (2001) The tandem affinity purification (TAP) method: a general procedure of protein complex purification. Methods 24: 218–22911403571 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b66"><text><SENT sid="294" pm="."><plain>Radman-LivajaM, RandoOJ (2010) Nucleosome positioning: how is it established, and why does it matter? Dev Biol 339: 258–26619527704 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b67"><text><SENT sid="295" pm="."><plain>RanjitkarP, PressMO, YiXH, BakerR, MacCossMJ, BigginsS (2010) An E3 ubiquitin ligase prevents ectopic localization of the centromeric histone H3 variant via the centromere targeting domain. Mol Cell 40: 455–46421070971 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b68"><text><SENT sid="296" pm="."><plain>SchulmanI, BloomKS (1991) Centromeres -- an integrated protein DNA complex required for chromosome movement. Annu Rev Cell Biol 7: 311–3361809349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b69"><text><SENT sid="297" pm="."><plain>SchwabishMA, StruhlK (2007) The Swi/Snf complex is important for histone eviction during transcriptional activation and RNA polymerase II elongation in vivo. Mol Cell Biol 27: 6987–699517709398 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b70"><text><SENT sid="298" pm="."><plain>ShivaswamyS, IyerVR (2008) Stress-dependent dynamics of global chromatin remodeling in yeast: dual role for SWI/SNF in the heat shock stress response. Mol Cell Biol 28: 2221–223418212068 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b71"><text><SENT sid="299" pm="."><plain>SmithCL, Horowitz-SchererR, FlanaganJF, WoodcockCL, PetersonCL (2003) Structural analysis of the yeast SWI/SNF chromatin remodeling complex. Nat Struct Biol 10: 141–14512524530 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b72"><text><SENT sid="300" pm="."><plain>SmithMM, YangPR, SantistebanMS, BoonePW, GoldsteinAT, MegeePC (1996) A novel histone H4 mutant defective in nuclear division and mitotic chromosome transmission. Mol Cell Biol 16: 1017–10268622646 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b73"><text><SENT sid="301" pm="."><plain>SorgerPK, DohenyKF, HieterP, KopskiKM, HuffakerTC, HymanAA (1995) Two genes required for the binding of an essential Saccharomyces cerevisiae kinetochore complex to DNA. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 92: 12026–120308618837 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b74"><text><SENT sid="302" pm="."><plain>StolerS, RogersK, WeitzeS, MoreyL, Fitzgerald-HayesM, BakerRE (2007) Scm3, an essential Saccharomyces cerevisiae centromere protein required for G(2)/M progression and Cse4 localization. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 104: 10571–1057617548816 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b75"><text><SENT sid="303" pm="."><plain>SullivanKF, HechenbergerM, MasriK (1994) Human Cenp-a contains a histone H3 related histone fold domain that is required for targeting to the centromere. J Cell Biol 127: 581–5927962047 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b76"><text><SENT sid="304" pm="."><plain>TakahataS, YuYX, StillmanDJ (2009) FACT and Asf1 regulate nucleosome dynamics and coactivator binding at the HO promoter. Mol Cell 34: 405–41519481521 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b77"><text><SENT sid="305" pm="."><plain>TanakaK, MukaeN, DewarH, van BreugelM, JamesEK, PrescottAR, AntonyC, TanakaTU (2005) Molecular mechanisms of kinetochore capture by spindle microtubules. Nature 434: 987–99415846338 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b78"><text><SENT sid="306" pm="."><plain>TanakaT, FuchsJ, LoidlJ, NasmythK (2000) Cohesin ensures bipolar attachment of microtubules to sister centromeres and resists their precocious separation. Nat Cell Biol 2: 492–49910934469 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b79"><text><SENT sid="307" pm="."><plain>ThastromA, LowaryPT, WidlundHR, CaoH, KubistaM, WidomJ (1999) Sequence motifs and free energies of selected natural and non-natural nucleosome positioning DNA sequences. J Mol Biol 288: 213–22910329138 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b80"><text><SENT sid="308" pm="."><plain>TomonagaT, MatsushitaK, YamaguchiS, OohashiT, ShimadaH, OchiaiT, YodaK, NomuraF (2003) Overexpression and mistargeting of centromere protein-A in human primary colorectal cancer. Cancer Res 63: 3511–351612839935 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b81"><text><SENT sid="309" pm="."><plain>TsuchiyaE, HosotaniT, MiyakawaT (1998) A mutation in NPS1/STH1, an essential gene encoding a component of a novel chromatin-remodeling complex RSC, alters the chromatin structure of Saccharomyces cerevisiae centromeres. Nucleic Acids Res 26: 3286–32929628931 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b82"><text><SENT sid="310" pm="."><plain>TsuchiyaE, UnoM, KiguchiA, MasuokaK, KanemoriY, OkabeS, MikayawaT (1992) The Saccharomyces cerevisiae Nps1 gene, a novel Cdc gene which encodes a 160 Kda nuclear-protein involved in G(2) phase-control. EMBO J 11: 4017–40261396591 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b83"><text><SENT sid="311" pm="."><plain>VentersBJ, PughBF (2009) A canonical promoter organization of the transcription machinery and its regulators in the Saccharomyces genome. Genome Res 19: 360–37119124666 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b84"><text><SENT sid="312" pm="."><plain>WalfridssonJ, BjerlingP, ThalenM, YooEJ, ParkSD, EkwallK (2005) The CHD remodeling factor Hrp1 stimulates CENP-A loading to centromeres. Nucleic Acids Res 33: 2868–287915908586 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b85"><text><SENT sid="313" pm="."><plain>WhitehouseI, FlausA, CairnsBR, WhiteMF, WorkmanJL, Owen-HughesT (1999) Nucleosome mobilization catalysed by the yeast SWI/SNF complex. Nature 400: 784–78710466730 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b86"><text><SENT sid="314" pm="."><plain>WongJ, NakajimaY, WestermannS, ShangC, KangJS, GoodnerC, HoushmandP, FieldsS, ChanCSM, DrubinD, BarnesG, HazbunT (2007) A protein interaction map of the mitotic spindle. Mol Biol Cell 18: 3800–380917634282 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b87"><text><SENT sid="315" pm="."><plain>WongMC, Scott-DrewSR, HayesMJ, HowardPJ, MurrayJA (2002) RSC2, encoding a component of the RSC nucleosome remodeling complex, is essential for 2 microm plasmid maintenance in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Mol Cell Biol 22: 4218–422912024034 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b88"><text><SENT sid="316" pm="."><plain>XueY, CanmanJC, LeeCS, NieZ, YangD, MorenoGT, YoungMK, SalmonED, WangW (2000) The human SWI/SNF-B chromatin-remodeling complex is related to yeast rsc and localizes at kinetochores of mitotic chromosomes. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 97: 13015–1302011078522 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b89"><text><SENT sid="317" pm="."><plain>YamadaK, HirotaK, MizunoK, ShibataT, OhtaK (2008) Essential roles of Snf21, a Swi2/Snf2 family chromatin remodeler, in fission yeast mitosis. Genes Genet Syst 83: 361–37219168987 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b90"><text><SENT sid="318" pm="."><plain>ZhangWG, MelloneBG, KarpenGH (2007) A specialized nucleosome has a ‘point' to make. Cell 129: 1047–104917574019 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><text><SENT sid="319" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group></back><floats-group><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="320" pm="."><plain>Centromeres are enriched for Snf2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="321" pm="."><plain>(A) Enrichment of Snf2-myc associated DNA fragments (solid line) was calculated by averaging enrichment from all chromosomes following hybridisation to Nimblegen tiling arrays aligned by the position of their CDEII element, standard deviation is depicted as dotted line (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="322" pm="."><plain>Input normalised signal for Snf2-myc enrichment at a region spanning 10 000 bp ± the CDEII element of chromosome 16. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="323" pm="."><plain>(C) As in (A) but hybridisation was carried out on an Affymetrix tiling array. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112f1"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="324" pm="."><plain>Deletion of Snf2 alters the genomewide distribution of Cse4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="325" pm="."><plain>Cse4 is predominantly enriched at centromeres in a SNF2+ typical enrichments for chromosomes 14 and 11 (A, C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="326" pm="."><plain>In a snf2Δ, Cse4 is redistributed across the entire chromosome arms at ectopic sites as well as centromeres (B, D). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112f2"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="327" pm="."><plain>Chromosome segregation defects in Snf2 mutants. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="328" pm="."><plain>(A) Anueploidy for CEN5 was assessed by microscopy in a strain in which both CEN5 and Spc42 were fluorescently tagged. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="329" pm="."><plain>Cells in which the ratio of CEN5:Spc42 foci was not 1:1 were scored as anueploid. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="330" pm="."><plain>Cells were cultured at 20°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="331" pm="."><plain>(B) Metaphase-to-anaphase progression was monitored via the separation between fluorescently tagged CEN5 loci. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="332" pm="."><plain>Cultures were arrested using α factor then released and grown at 30°C. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="333" pm="."><plain>The separation between fluorescently tagged CEN5 loci was measured by microscopy at various times following α factor induced cell-cycle arrest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="334" pm="."><plain>Fisher's test P-values are indicated on the graph. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="335" pm="."><plain>(C) Asynchronously grown liquid cultures grown at 20°C were analysed using FACS. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="336" pm="."><plain>The abundance of cells with different DNA content is indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="337" pm="."><plain>In the absence of Snf2 and Mad2, an increase in the proportion of cells with low and high DNA content was observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="338" pm="."><plain>(D) Cultures were grown at 20°C then shifted to 30°C for 3 h and subject to FACS as above. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="339" pm="."><plain>Polyploidy in the mad2Δ snf2Δ strain is more pronounced following growth at the higher temperature. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112f3"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="340" pm="."><plain>Snf2-dependent alterations to chromatin structure adjacent to centromeres. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="341" pm="."><plain>Chromatin structure was mapped genomewide by hybridising nucleosomal DNA to Affymetrix tiling arrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="342" pm="."><plain>(A) Average nucleosome occupancy at all centromeres was aligned by the CDEII element to illustrate the arrangement of chromatin at the centromeres of the 16 chromosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="343" pm="."><plain>Wild-type nucleosome positioning was assessed using data from Lee et al (2007). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="344" pm="."><plain>The data for the snf2 deletion is the average of two repeats made using the same arrays. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="345" pm="."><plain>It is apparent that there are changes to chromatin flanking the centromere and that in particular the nuclease hypersensitive sites flanking centromeres are less pronounced. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="346" pm="."><plain>To illustrate that not all hypersensitive sites in the genome are altered in a snf2Δ strain chromatin was also aligned to ARS elements (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="347" pm="."><plain>Snf2 appears to have a minor role in chromatin organisation at these sites. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112f4"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="348" pm="."><plain>SWI/SNF can dissociate Cse4 containing nucleosomes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="349" pm="."><plain>Chromatin was assembled onto a DNA fragment consisting of the 601 positioning sequence flanked by 42 and 47 bp linker DNA by salt dialysis using either yeast octamers containing Cse4 (A) or octamers containing Histone H3 (B). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="350" pm="."><plain>In all, 1 pmol of nucleosomes were incubated with SWI/SNF (0.5 pmol), Nap1 as indicated in the presence or absence of 1 mM ATP as indicated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="351" pm="."><plain>Increasing amounts of Nap1 in the presence of SWI/SNF cause the Cse4 chromatin to dissociate, resulting in an increase in the free DNA present (A, lanes 5–9). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112f5"/></fig></SecTag><SecTag type="FIG"><fig id="f6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><text><SENT sid="352" pm="."><plain>Deletion of Snf2 results in mislocalisation of Cse4 to sites normally bound by SWI/SNF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="353" pm="."><plain>The top 99 sites showing enrichment for Cse4 in a snf2Δ along with a control set of randomly selected sites were selected. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="354" pm="."><plain>These sites were then scored for enrichment of Snf2 in a wt strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="355" pm="."><plain>It can be seen that there is a significantly increased enrichment for Snf2 at the sites to which Cse4 becomes mislocalised (0.4-fold) in comparison to randomly selected sites (0.05-fold). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="356" pm="."><plain>This enrichment is not observed when comparing the enrichment of Snf2 at ectopic Cse4 sites in a wt strain. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="357" pm="."><plain>These observations support a role for SWI/SNF in the removal of Cse4 from sites on chromosome arms. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="emboj2011112f6"/></fig></SecTag></floats-group></article>
