<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d2 20140930//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Brain</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Brain</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">brainj</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">brain</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Brain</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0006-8950</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1460-2156</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4407186</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awu309</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">awu309</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letters to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Reply: Parkinson’s disease in GTP cyclohydrolase 1 mutation carriers </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mencacci</surname><given-names>Niccolo E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>Alan M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Isaias</surname><given-names>Ioannis U.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF4"><sup>4</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Klebe</surname><given-names>Stephan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>Kailash P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF6"><sup>6</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>Nicholas W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="awu309-AFF1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="awu309-AFF1">1 Department of Molecular Neuroscience, UCL Institute of Neurology, London WC1N 3BG, UK</aff><aff id="awu309-AFF2">2 IRCCS Istituto Auxologico Italiano, Department of Neurology and Laboratory of Neuroscience – Department of Pathophysiology and Transplantation, ‘Dino Ferrari’ Centre, Universita` degli Studi di Milano, 20149 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="awu309-AFF3">3 Reta Lila Weston Institute of Neurological Studies, UCL Institute of Neurology, London WC1N 3BG, UK</aff><aff id="awu309-AFF4">4 Department of Neurology, University Hospital, 97080 Würzburg, Germany</aff><aff id="awu309-AFF5">5 Parkinson Institute, Istituti Clinici di Perfezionamento, 20126 Milan, Italy</aff><aff id="awu309-AFF6">6 Sobell Department of Motor Neuroscience and Movement Disorders, UCL Institute of Neurology, London WC1N 3BG, UK</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence to: Professor Nicholas W. Wood, Department of Molecular Neuroscience, UCL Institute of Neurology, Queen Square, WC1N 3BG London, UK E-mail: <email>n.wood@ucl.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>5</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>11</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>138</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>e352</fpage><lpage>e352</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>© The Author (2014). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Guarantors of Brain.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" license-type="creative-commons"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Sir, </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Thank you for the opportunity to reply to the correspondence concerning our recent publication in Brain, ‘Parkinson’s disease in GTP cyclohydrolase 1 mutation carriers’ (Mencacci et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>We read with great interest these letters and we thank the authors for their insights. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Guella et al. (2014) report the screening of GCH1 in 528 Canadian cases with Parkinson’s disease and atypical parkinsonism and 290 matched controls. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>They identified two variants, the known pathogenic p.K224R (×2) and the novel variant p.A99D (likely pathogenic according to in silico prediction tools and interspecies conservation) in three unrelated cases with Parkinsons’s disease and the two benign variants p.P23L and p.P69L in one single control individual. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The mutational frequency, excluding the aforementioned benign variants, was 0.56% (3/528) in cases versus 0% (0/290) in controls, consistent with the frequency we observed in our study (0.75% in cases versus 0.1% in controls). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>This result is relevant as it represents the first independent confirmation that rare deleterious GCH1 variants are enriched in patients with Parkinson’s disease compared to control subjects. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, they describe the post-mortem findings of one of the mutated patients, who presented at the age of 82 with DOPA-responsive asymmetric rest tremor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>This showed a combination of brainstem Lewy body pathology together with the presence of tau-immunoreactive neurofibrillary tangles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>To date, the only available brain pathology analysis of a GCH1-associated neurodegenerative parkinsonism case showed severe nigral neurodegeneration and Lewy bodies in surviving nigral cells and in the locus coeruleus (Gibb et al., 1991; Segawa et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Further studies are needed to establish if the tauopathy described by Guella et al. (2014) in their case represents simply an incidental finding. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>The finding that GCH1 loss-of-function variants are not only responsible for childhood-onset DOPA-responsive dystonia, but are also associated with adult-onset neurodegenerative parkinsonism, is strengthened by the recent identification, through the meta-analysis of genome-wide association studies (GWAS) data deriving from ∼13 000 cases and 95 000 controls, that GCH1 is also a low-risk susceptibility locus for Parkinson’s disease (Nalls et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>This finding potentially extends the role of GTP cyclohydrolase 1 (GCH1) deficiency in the pathogenesis of Parkinson’s disease beyond carriers of rare deleterious coding mutations. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>The causal link between GCH1 and Parkinson’s disease remains a matter of speculation. Ryan et al. (2014) expand the discussion of our manuscript and add insight into the possible pathogenic mechanisms that predispose GCH1 loss-of-function mutation carriers to nigrostriatal degeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>In our paper we proposed various hypotheses whereby GCH1 and BH4 deficiency and consequent chronic reduction of dopamine levels may predispose carriers of GCH1 mutations to nigral cell degeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Ryan et al. (2014) point out that different cellular mechanisms secondary to BH4 deficiency, other than reduced dopamine levels, could contribute to the death of nigral dopaminergic neurons. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>BH4 acts as an antioxidant itself and is an essential cofactor for nitric oxide synthases (NOS) activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Furthermore decreased BH4 levels have been demonstrated to lead to NOS uncoupling, which results in increased oxidative and nitrative stress (Chen et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>The authors previously described that a haplotype of three SNPs (rs8007267, rs3783641 and rs10483639) at the GCH1 genomic locus influences plasma GCH1 activity and BH4 levels (Antoniades et al., 2008) and identified BH4 as a vascular defence mechanism against inflammation-induced endothelial dysfunction (Antoniades et al., 2011). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Consequently the authors propose that a link between BH4 levels, oxidative stress, and neuroinflammation could represent the mechanism underlying GCH1-associated Parkinson’s disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Fitting well with this model, and possibly supporting Ryan et al.’s view, we found that the GCH1 SNP (rs11158026), recently identified as a risk variant for Parkinson’s disease (Nalls et al., 2014), is in moderate linkage disequilibrium (r2 0.457; D’ 0.932) with the SNPs constituting the functional haplotype. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>This possibly suggests a potential functional basis for the association of this variant to Parkinson’s disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>The authors have also demonstrated the existence of an interaction between α-synuclein, mitochondrial function and GCH1 activity. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Their work may support the compelling hypothesis that a pathogenic cascade occurs in nigral neurons, whereby increased levels of α-synuclein and mitochondrial dysfunction lead to decreased GCH1 activity and BH4 levels, which in turn may result in increased oxidative stress and cell death (Ryan et al., 2014). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>We believe that one of the outstanding questions is whether patients with DOPA-responsive dystonia eventually develop nigral neurodegeneration, or whether neurodegeneration can be avoided by dopaminergic replacement therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>Answering this question will help to understand to what extent low dopamine levels play a role in nigral cell death, with obvious therapeutic implications for asymptomatic carriers of pathogenic variants. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Dopaminergic imaging studies performed in a few cases with classic DOPA-responsive dystonia (mostly genetically not confirmed) have shown no evidence of reduced nigrostriatal innervation (Snow et al., 1993; Jeon et al., 1998). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>This is consistent with post-mortem analysis of four extra cases showing normal nigral cell count (Furukawa et al., 1999; Grotzsch et al., 2002; Segawa et al., 2013). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>However, Sawle et al. (1991) report that six cases with DOPA-responsive dystonia displayed modest but significant reduction in the uptake of 18F-fluorodopa into both caudates and putamen. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, Tadic et al. (2012) report that in DOPA-responsive dystonia cases parkinsonian signs are a relatively common residual motor sign following treatment, possibly suggesting underlying neurodegeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>With regards to this, the case report of Terbeek et al. (2014) is of great interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>They describe a 41-year-old patient carrying a known pathogenic GCH1 variant (p.Y75S) with onset of classic DOPA-responsive dystonia at age 11. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>He was treated with l-DOPA (300 mg/day) from the age of 20 with good and sustained response. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>At age 41, because of rapid recurrence of dystonia after skipping a l-DOPA dose, dopaminergic imaging (123I-FP-CIT SPECT) was performed and showed severe bilateral and asymmetric reduction of putaminal tracer uptake, a pattern typical of idiopathic Parkinson’s disease. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>However, clinical examination, performed after withdrawing l-DOPA, revealed purely dystonic features without any obvious sign of parkinsonism. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>In agreement with the interpretation of Terbeek et al. (2014), we believe that this case may indeed represent a case with overlapping DOPA-responsive dystonia and asymptomatic, as yet, nigrostriatal degeneration, possibly arguing against a neuroprotective role of dopamine replacement in GCH1 mutation carriers. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Lastly, with regards to the letter by Furukawa and Kish (2014), we agree it is not easy to reconcile the evidence of nigral neurodegeneration that we and others have demonstrated in several individuals with GCH1-related parkinsonsim and the intact dopaminergic innervation showed in some other cases (Nygaard et al., 1992; Kang et al., 2004). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>However, the phenotype of these latter cases, characterized by excellent and prolonged response to very small doses of l-DOPA and no motor fluctuations or dyskinesias in spite of decades of treatment, is very different from what we observed in the ‘neurodegenerative’ cases. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>It is therefore possible that there may exist two different types of adult-onset parkinsonism associated with GCH1 mutations; on one side, a benign non-degenerative form, part of the phenotypic spectrum of metabolic GCH1-related striatal dopamine deficiency; on the other, a progressive form of parkinsonism with underlying nigral degeneration. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we anticipate that post-mortem analysis and longitudinal clinical, neuroimaging, and metabolic studies of larger series of GCH1 mutation carriers—including asymptomatic carriers, individuals with classic DOPA-responsive dystonia and cases with adult-onset parkinsonism—will give way to important understandings of the pathogenesis of GCH1–associated Parkinson’s disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>Funding </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>This study was supported by the Wellcome Trust/Medical Research Council (MRC) Joint Call in Neurodegeneration award (WT089698) to the UK Parkinson’s Disease Consortium whose members are from the UCL/Institute of Neurology, the University of Sheffield, and the MRC Protein Phosphorylation Unit at the University of Dundee. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>This project was also supported by the National Institute for Health Research University College London Hospitals Biomedical Research Centre and the Grigioni Foundation for Parkinson Disease. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="awu309-B1"><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>AntoniadesCCunningtonCAntonopoulosANevilleMMargaritisMDemosthenousMInduction of vascular GTP-cyclohydrolase I and endogenous tetrahydrobiopterin synthesis protect against inflammation-induced endothelial dysfunction in human atherosclerosisCirculation201112418607021969008 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B2"><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>AntoniadesCShirodariaCVan AsscheTCunningtonCTegederILotschJGCH1 haplotype determines vascular and plasma biopterin availability in coronary artery disease effects on vascular superoxide production and endothelial functionJ Am Coll Cardiol2008521586518598896 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B3"><text><SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>ChenDDChenLYXieJBShuCYangTZhouSTetrahydrobiopterin regulation of eNOS redox functionCurr Pharm Design201420355462 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B19"><text><SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>FurukawaYKishSJParkinsonism in GTP cyclohydrolase 1-deficient DOPA-responsive dystoniaBrain2015138e351 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B4"><text><SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>FurukawaYNygaardTGGutlichMRajputAHPiflCDiStefanoLStriatal biopterin and tyrosine hydroxylase protein reduction in dopa-responsive dystoniaNeurology19995310324110496263 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B5"><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>GibbWRNarabayashiHYokochiMIizukaRLeesAJNew pathologic observations in juvenile onset parkinsonism with dystoniaNeurology19914182022046923 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B6"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>GrotzschHPizzolatoGPGhikaJSchorderetDVingerhoetsFJLandisTNeuropathology of a case of dopa-responsive dystonia associated with a new genetic locus, DYT14Neurology20025818394212084887 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B20"><text><SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>GuellaIShermanHEAppel-CresswellSRajputARajputAHFarrerMJParkinson’s disease in GTP cyclohydrolase 1 mutation carriersBrain2015138e349 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B7"><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>JeonBSJeongJMParkSSKimJMChangYSSongHCDopamine transporter density measured by [123I]beta-CIT single-photon emission computed tomography is normal in dopa-responsive dystoniaAnn Neurol1998437928009629849 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B8"><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>KangJHKangSYKangHKKohYSImJHLeeMCA novel missense mutation of the GTP cyclohydrolase I gene in a Korean family with hereditary progressive dystonia/dopa-responsive dystoniaBrain Dev2004262879115165667 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B9"><text><SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>MencacciNEIsaiasIUReichMMGanosCPlagnolVPolkeJMParkinson's disease in GTP cyclohydrolase 1 mutation carriersBrain201413724809224993959 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B10"><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>NallsMAPankratzNLillCMDoCBHernandezDGSaadMLarge-scale meta-analysis of genome-wide association data identifies six new risk loci for Parkinson's diseaseNat Genet2014469899325064009 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B11"><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>NygaardTGTakahashiHHeimanGASnowBJFahnSCalneDBLong-term treatment response and fluorodopa positron emission tomographic scanning of parkinsonism in a family with dopa-responsive dystoniaAnn Neurol19923260381449240 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B18"><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>RyanBJCrabtreeMJChannonKMWade-MartinsRParkinson’s disease in GTP cyclohydrolase 1 mutation carriersBrain2015138e348 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B12"><text><SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>RyanBJLourenco-VendaLLCrabtreeMJHaleABChannonKMWade-MartinsRα-Synuclein and mitochondrial bioenergetics regulate tetrahydrobiopterin levels in a human dopaminergic model of Parkinson diseaseFree Radic Biol Med201467586824148766 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B13"><text><SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>SawleGVLeendersKLBrooksDJHarwoodGLeesAJFrackowiakRSDopa-responsive dystonia: [18F]dopa positron emission tomographyAnn Neurol19913024301681782 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B14"><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>SegawaMNomuraYHayashiMDopa-responsive dystonia is caused by particular impairment of nigrostriatal dopamine neurons different from those involved in Parkinson disease: evidence observed in studies on Segawa diseaseNeuropediatrics20134461623468278 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B15"><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>SegawaMNomuraYYukishitaSNishiyamaNYokochiMIs phenotypic variation of hereditary progressive dystonia with marked diurnal fluctuation/dopa-responsive dystonia (HPD/DRD) caused by the difference of the locus of mutation on the GTP cyclohydrolase 1 (GCH-1) gene?Adv Neurol2004942172314509676 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B16"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>SnowBJNygaardTGTakahashiHCalneDBPositron emission tomographic studies of dopa-responsive dystonia and early-onset idiopathic parkinsonismAnn Neurol19933473388239569 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B17"><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>TadicVKastenMBruggemannNStillerSHagenahJKleinCDopa-responsive dystonia revisited: diagnostic delay, residual signs, and nonmotor signsArch Neurol20126915586222986512 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="awu309-B21"><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>TerbeekJHermansSLaereKVVandenbergheWParkinson’s disease in GTP cyclohydrolase 1 mutation carriersBrain2015138e350 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
