<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4070555</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24912499</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">6133</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-15-450</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Methodology Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>REGNET: mining context-specific human transcription networks using composite genomic information </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chi</surname><given-names>Sang-Mun</given-names></name><address><email>smchiks@ks.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff16"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Young-Kyo</given-names></name><address><email>ykseo@unist.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff17"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Young-Kyu</given-names></name><address><email>youngkyu-park@bmlaboratories.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>Sora</given-names></name><address><email>yoonsora@unist.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff17"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Chan Young</given-names></name><address><email>cypark@unist.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff17"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Yong Sung</given-names></name><address><email>yongsung@kribb.re.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Seon-Young</given-names></name><address><email>kimsy@kribb.re.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff18"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nam</surname><given-names>Dougu</given-names></name><address><email>dougnam@unist.ac.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff17"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff19"/></contrib><aff id="Aff16"><label/>School of Computer Science and Engineering, Kyungsung University, Busan, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff17"><label/>School of Life Sciences, UNIST, Ulsan, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff18"><label/>Medical Genomics Research Center, Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology, Daejeon, Republic of Korea </aff><aff id="Aff19"><label/>Division of Mathematical Sciences, UNIST, Ulsan, Republic of Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>450</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>8</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© Chi et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. 2014</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Genome-wide expression profiles reflect the transcriptional networks specific to the given cell context. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>However, most statistical models try to estimate the average connectivity of the networks from a collection of gene expression data, and are unable to characterize the context-specific transcriptional regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>We propose an approach for mining context-specific transcription networks from a large collection of gene expression fold-change profiles and composite gene-set information. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>Using a composite gene-set analysis method, we combine the information of transcription factor binding sites, Gene Ontology or pathway gene sets and gene expression fold-change profiles for a variety of cell conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>We then collected all the significant patterns and constructed a database of context-specific transcription networks for human (REGNET). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>As a result, context-specific roles of transcription factors as well as their functional targets are readily explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>To validate the approach, nine predicted targets of E2F1 in HeLa cells were tested using chromatin immunoprecipitation assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Among them, five (Gadd45b, Dusp6, Mll5, Bmp2 and E2f3) were successfully bound by E2F1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>c-JUN and the EMT transcription networks were also validated from literature. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>REGNET is a useful tool for exploring the ternary relationships among the transcription factors, their functional targets and the corresponding cell conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>It is able to provide useful clues for novel cell-specific transcriptional regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>The REGNET database is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mgrc.kribb.re.kr/regnet">http://mgrc.kribb.re.kr/regnet</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The online version of this article (doi: 10.1186/1471-2164-15-450) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Composite gene-set analysis</kwd><kwd>Microarray</kwd><kwd>Transcription network</kwd><kwd>TFBS</kwd><kwd>Gene Ontology</kwd><kwd>KEGG</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>© The Author(s) 2014</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="Sec1"><title><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>Cells alter the process of transcriptional regulation so as to adjust to or drive changes in the cellular conditions between different stages of the cell cycle, stem cell differentiation or cancer development. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>Such changes in the transcriptional networks between different cell conditions are represented in the transcriptome data that are obtained using microarrays or high-throughput sequencing. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>However, elucidating the complex transcription networks (TNs) has been a daunting task in spite of the remarkable advances in both computational modeling and high-throughput experimental technologies [1–8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>One main reason for the difficulty is the dynamic nature of the networks: Transcription factors (TFs) not only regulate different targets depending on the cell conditions, but their effects on these targets can also change. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>Therefore, statistical models that estimate the average connectivity of the networks from a large collection of transcriptome data may confer limited accuracy. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Taking these issues into account, we have developed an approach for identifying the context-specific TNs from a large collection of gene expression fold-change profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>Toward this end, we collected 2,482 paired (test/control) human microarray datasets encompassing a variety of cell conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="?"><plain>Using a composite gene-set analysis method (ADGO) [9, 10], we combined the information of TF binding site (TFBS), Gene Ontology or KEGG pathway gene sets, and the gene expression fold-change profiles, and thereby tried to address the fundamental but largely open question of which TFs regulate which functions or pathways under differing cell conditions? </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>Since the majority of TFBSs are potentially false positives, we applied the following filtering criteria to identify reliable TNs as follows. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>(A) A TFBS gene set (genes that share a common TFBS in their promoters) is required to have a significant overlap with a functional gene set (genes that share a common annotation in GO or KEGG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>(B) The genes that overlap, as a whole, should exhibit significant expression changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>(C) Such changes should be observed across many microarray conditions (e.g. ten or more). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>If the above three criteria are satisfied between a TFBS gene set and a functional gene set, we say the corresponding TF is associated with the functional gene set (Figure 1a), and the associated pairs as well as the corresponding conditions are output as context-specific TNs.Figure 1 Overview of REGNET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>(a) Association of a TF and functional gene set. (b) Ternary relationships explored by REGNET. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>We collected all of the 12,149,291 significant triples (TF, functional gene set, condition; q-values for the two conditions (A) and (B) &lt;0.05) in order to construct a context-specific TN database, dubbed REGNET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>It is used for exploring the ternary relationships among the TFs, their functional targets and the corresponding cell conditions (Figure 1b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>Each TF or function (or pathway) name can be used as a query, and REGNET provides corresponding context-specific TNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>Using this database, we analyzed TNs for two TFs, E2F1 and c-JUN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Many known target genes as well as corresponding microarray conditions were identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>REGNET also included many predictions for novel targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>For example, we selected nine candidate targets of E2F1 predicted for HeLa cells and tested them using a ChIP assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>Among them, five (Gadd45b, Dusp6, Mll5, Bmp2 and E2f3) were successfully bound by E2F1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>We also validated the TNs for c-JUN and the ‘epithelial to mesenchymal transition (EMT)’ gene set from the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>REGNET is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mgrc.kribb.re.kr/regnet">http://mgrc.kribb.re.kr/regnet</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods"><title><text><SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec3"><title><text><SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>Collection of data </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>Human gene expression microarray datasets of the same platform ‘HG-U133 Plus 2’ were downloaded from 839 Gene Expression Omnibus [11] series. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>In each series dataset, we manually identified the test/control sample groups to collect log fold-change profiles. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>Many datasets contained multiple test groups, and hence 2,482 fold-change profiles were collected in total. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Probe values that correspond to the same gene were averaged to yield gene-based fold-change profiles (20,361 genes). human TFBS gene sets were obtained from MSigDB [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>For functional gene sets, the three categories of GO and KEGG pathways were used. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>GO gene sets were obtained from a gene product association file downloaded from a ftp site (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.geneontology.org/gene-associations/">http://www.geneontology.org/gene-associations/</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Both the electronic and non-electronic annotations were used to maximize the coverage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>KEGG gene sets were downloaded from MSigDB. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>All the offspring terms are again included in their parent terms. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>All the gene-sets with not less than 10 and not more than 500 genes are included in the analysis and the system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title><text><SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Identification of context-specific transcription networks </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>We applied the following three filtering criteria to identify reliable TNs: </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>(A) Overlap significance: the significance of overlap for every pair of a TFBS gene set and functional gene set is assessed using the hypergeometric distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>The genes that overlap, if significant (default: FDR q-value &lt; =0.02), are regarded as candidate targets of the TF, and may be interpreted as the channel through which the TF regulates the function (or pathway). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>Such overlapping sets constitute the candidate TNs to be further examined throughout gene expression datasets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>(B) Expression significance: For each pair of TFBS-functional gene sets that overlap significantly, another filtering criterion using a fold-change expression dataset is applied: The Z-statistic on the gene expression fold-change values is computed for each of the TFBS set, functional set and their overlapping set, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>If the FDR q-value of the overlapping set is less than or equal to 0.02 (default value) and the q-values for the two individual sets are larger than 0.05 (default value), we assume the corresponding TN is activated on the given microarray condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>In other words, expression changes in the overlapping genes should be pronounced compared to the two individual sets [9]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>(C) Number of conditions: Only TNs that satisfy the above two criteria (A) and (B) across k (default number =10) or more microarray conditions are regarded as reliable transcription patterns. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>If all these criteria are satisfied between a TFBS gene set and functional gene set, the TF, candidate targets as well as the corresponding conditions are output as context-specific TN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Among the overlap set identified through (A) ~ (C), we can further select individual candidate targets that show some high fold expression changes (e.g. ±1.5 of higher) across a number of conditions (e.g., more than 0.3 ×k conditions). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>All the threshold values including q-values and k can be changed by the user for more thorough exploration of the transcriptional regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>Figure 2 summarizes the context-specific TNs queried by TF and functional gene set, respectively.Figure 2 Context-specific transcription networks for the query of a TF or functional gene set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>(a) For the query of a TF, multiple functional gene sets are associated. C l, C 2, …, C k represent the microarray conditions of the fold-change profiles for which the genes in the overlap parts significantly altered their expressions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>The collection of the genes in the overlap parts are used for a global assessment. (b) For the query of a functional gene set, multiple TF’s are associated. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Chromatin Immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assay for E2F1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>ChIP assays for E2F1 in HeLa cells were performed following the protocol represented at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genomics.ucdavis.edu/farnham">http://genomics.ucdavis.edu/farnham</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>HeLa cells were crosslinked for 10 min by adding formaldehyde to a final concentration of 1% with mild agitation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>Crosslinking was stopped by the addition of glycine to a final concentration of 125 mM, and cells were washed three times with ice-cold PBS prior to harvesting by scraping of the plates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>Chromatid were fragmented for 20 min (10 sec on pulse and 20 sec off pulse) to produce fragments ~500 nt in size using the Bioruptor sonicator (Diagenode). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>Antibody (SC251X; Santa Cruz Biotech) to E2F1 was used to pull down target chromatid from 1 × 108 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Genomic DNAs were isolated from proteinase K-treated (45°C for 1 h) samples and purified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>ChIP samples were tested by PCR using positive and negative control primer sets shown in Additional file 1: Table S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>The quantitative real-time PCR for ChIP is described in Supplementary Material. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results"><title><text><SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec7"><title><text><SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>REGNET database </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>REGNET is an intuitive and easy to use database developed for exploring context-specific TNs (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mgrc.kribb.re.kr/regnet">http://mgrc.kribb.re.kr/regnet</ext-link>). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>REGNET accepts two kinds of queries, i.e. TF and function (or pathway, localization) names, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>It provides a webpage presenting all the TF names analyzed, so that investigators can simply choose the TF of their interest. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>Each TF name indicates a TFBS gene set to which the TF can bind. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>Because a TF can have different TFBSs, many of the TF names are represented multiple times. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>Among them, ‘(TF name)_all’ is linked to the TNs that can be captured only by taking the union of all the TFBS sets of their common TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>For example, AHR_all links to the TNs that can be captured only by using the union of the four different TFBS sets (V$AHRARNT_01, V$AHRARNT_02, V$AHR_01 and V$AHR_Q5).Each TF name is linked to a list of functional gene sets associated with the TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>Each line on the list is then linked to the corresponding target genes, descriptions for the TFBS and functional gene sets and the microarray conditions under which the target genes exhibit significant changes in expression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>The ‘number of conditions’ leads to a table of the corresponding test/control microarray conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>At the bottom of the table, a heat map of the log fold-change values of the target genes is displayed, summarizing the information for the associated pair of the TF and functional gene set (Figure 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>From this heat map, investigators can easily identify candidate targets that exhibit large expression changes across a number of conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>The fold-change values of the TF itself are also provided on the right-end column of the heat map, for the activity of certain TFs can be usefully inferred from their transcript levels.Figure 3 Condition table and heat maps for transcription networks of E2F1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>(a) The condition table and heat map for the association between E2F1 and the gene set ‘transcription activator activity (GO:0016563)’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Several targets exhibit clear activations across a number of virus treated HeLa cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>Seven genes, Bmp2, E2f3, Epc1, Fosl1, Mll5, Myc and Nr4a3 are chosen for validation using a ChIP assay. (b) The heat map for the association between E2F1 and the gene set ‘negative regulation of protein kinase activity (GO:0006469)’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>A part of the 55 conditions that associate E2F1 and the GO gene set are shown. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>Among the targets, Gadd45b and Dusp6 exhibit clear expression changes across a variety of microarray conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Both genes are tested using a ChIP assay. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>When querying for a functional gene set, a keyword is required for searching. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>For example, if the investigators want to identify TNs related to the ‘epithelial to mesenchymal transition’ process, entering ‘mesen’ is sufficient. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Then, the names of functional gene sets that contain ‘mesen’ are all displayed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>From among them, investigators can choose the exact gene set of their interest, and then all the TFs associated with that functional gene set are listed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>As in the case of the TF query, each line is linked to detailed information on the target genes, TFBS sets and the queried gene set as well as the corresponding microarray conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>More detailed information on the REGNET database may be seen from our web site. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><text><SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Analysis results for E2F1 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>We used the human TFBS gene sets from the Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) [12]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>The MSigDB provides five E2F1 TFBS sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>The predicted results for E2F1 are accessible by choosing ‘E’ in the ‘TF-based browsing’ webpage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>As expected, many cell-cycle related functional gene sets were found to be related to most of the TFBS gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>For example, the ‘DNA replication (GO:0006260)’ and ‘G1/S transition of mitotic cell cycle (GO:0000082)’ are associated with four of the five TFBS sets while the ‘cell cycle (KEGG)’ and ‘cell cycle checkpoint (GO:0000075)’ are associated with three. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>For each gene set, many conditions likely to activate cell cycle progression were observed, e.g. iPS or diverse cancer cell conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>For the union of all the E2F1 TFBS gene sets (E2F1_all), the ‘transcription activator activity (GO:0016563)’ set is captured and several of the putative targets exhibit high expression fold-changes for a number of the HeLa cell conditions treated with vaccinia virus (GSE 11238): Bmp2, E2f3, Epc1, Fosl1, Mll5, Myc and Nr4a3 (Figure 3a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Another target set, ‘negative regulation of protein kinase activity (GO:0006469)’ is found to be associated with the E2F1_all set through 55 conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>Among the targets, in particular, Dusp6 and Gadd45b exhibit high expression fold-changes across dozens of heterogeneous conditions (Figure 3b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>Although these 55 conditions do not include the HeLa cells, it was found that both genes display more than two-fold increases in their expression levels in most of the virus-treated HeLa conditions (GSE 11238). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>To validate the regulatory relationships, therefore, we performed a ChIP assay on HeLa cells, as described in Methods, for the nine candidate targets selected from the two associated sets ‘transcription activator activity’ and ‘negative regulation of protein kinase activity’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>To this end, we activated E2F1 via the CDK4-Rb-E2F1 pathway [13] as described in Additional file 1: Figure S1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>We used Gapdh as a control. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>The ChIP results are shown in Figure 4. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Among the targets tested, five exhibited positive results: The binding of E2F1 to Gadd45b, Dusp6 and Mll5 was pronounced with six or higher fold-changes compared to a control IgG, and the binding to Bmp2 and E2f3 exhibited approximate five and three-fold increases, respectively.Figure 4 Chromatin IP experimental results for E2F1. The nine candidate targets of E2F1 were chosen for validation by gene-specific ChIP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>The fold change (FC) is the fold increase of the signal from E2F1 antibody (black)–enriched chromatin relative to a control IgG (open). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>The negative control Gapdh exhibited no enrichment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>Analysis results for c-JUN </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>The MSigDB provides eleven c-JUN TFBS sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>The predicted results for c-JUN are accessible by choosing ‘J’ in the TF-based browsing webpage. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>The first TFBS set named ‘TGANTCA_V$AP1_C’ contains 866 genes, and 129 GO or KEGG gene sets are associated with this TFBS set as the result of satisfying the three filtering criteria (A) ~ (C). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>Among them, we identified two cell conditions for which c-JUN targets are most clearly activated. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>For example, the ‘response to steroid hormone stimulus (GO:0048545)’ gene set is associated with the c-JUN TFBS set for 56 microarray conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>Among them, the HeLa cells treated with vaccinia virus (GSE 11238) clearly exhibits activation in five targets: Adm, F3, Fosl1, Il6 and Thbs1 (Additional file 1: Figure S2a). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>The latter four genes are known targets of c-JUN [14, 15]. Thbs1 is known to be repressed by c-JUN in rat embryo fibroblasts [16], but it is also known to be activated by c-JUN in human hepatocarcinoma cell lines [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>ADM is reported to induce the phosphorylation of c-JUN in glioblastoma cells [17], but is also a candidate target of c-JUN in our prediction. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>Because the known targets of c-JUN as well as Jun itself display high expression fold changes, we infer that viral infection to HeLa cells strongly increases the activity of c-JUN. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>In the ‘pathways in cancer (KEGG)’ gene set, we found another group of known c-JUN targets, i.e. Il6, Lamb3, Lamc2, Mmp1 and Mmp9[14], that are strongly activated for the conditions of ‘engineered human skin’ (GSE 17539) [18] and ‘low dose treatment of 5-aza-2-deoxycytidine on an non-small cell lung cancer cell line’ (GSE 6695) [19] (Additional file 1: Figure S2b). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>If another TFBS set V$AP1FJ_Q2 is chosen, the well-known c-JUN interacting partner Fos as well as Il6 are captured in the ‘pathways in cancer (KEGG)’ gene set, and Fos exhibits a very strong co-expression pattern with Jun in many of the virus-treated HeLa cell conditions (Additional file 1: Figure S2c). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>Summarizing the results for all the c-JUN TFBS gene sets, in total 156 functional gene sets are associated with at least one of the eleven TFBS gene sets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>Of them, 52 functional gene sets (approximately 33%) are associated with two or more. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>This suggests that c-JUN binds to a variety of different TFBSs in order to ensure the regulation of its target pathways. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>For example, ‘pathways in cancer (KEGG)’ is associated with eight different c-JUN TFBS gene sets, highlighting the role of c-JUN as a key factor of cancer progression. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>The representative gene sets associated with three or more c-JUN TFBS sets are shown in Table 1.Table 1 Functional gene sets associated with c-JUN Functional gene set codesFunctional gene set names#TFBS sets*KEGG PATHWAYS IN CANCER (KEGG)Pathways in cancer8GO:0000165 (GOBP)MAPKKK cascade6GO:0043086 (GOBP)Negative regulation of catalytic activity5GO:0031012 (GOCC)Extracellular matrix4GO:0045859 (GOBP)Regulation of protein kinase activity4KEGG MAPK SIGNALING PATHWAY (KEGG)MAPK signaling pathway4GO:0001501 (GOBP)Skeletal system development3GO:0001525 (GOBP)Angiogenesis3GO:0007409 (GOBP)Axonogenesis3GO:0018193 (GOBP)Peptidyl-amino acid modification3GO:0030334 (GOBP)Regulation of cell migration3GO:0032270 (GOBP)Positive regulation of cellular protein metabolic process3GO:0043066 (GOBP)Negative regulation of apoptosis3GO:0048812 (GOBP)Neuron projection morphogenesis3*The number of c-JUN TFBS gene sets associated with each functional gene set. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>Analysis results for the EMT gene set </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>We now illustrate how to analyze a functional gene set using REGNET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>Entering the keyword ‘mesen’ from the ‘Keyword Search’ page, nine similar functional gene sets were presented. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Among them, we chose the first one, i.e. the ‘epithelial to mesenchymal transition (GO:0001837)’. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="144" pm="."><plain>This set is associated with eight TFs (MAZ, FOXO4, PITX2, SP1, NFAT, PAX4, ZEB1 and LEF1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="145" pm="."><plain>Except for MAZ and PAX4, each TF is reported to regulate EMT process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="146" pm="."><plain>We then investigated the conditions under which each TF might regulate the EMT process. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="147" pm="."><plain>Many putative conditions that are likely to trigger EMT were observed. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="148" pm="."><plain>For example, PCDH24-expressing HCT116 cells shown to abolish tumor formation in vivo have ~2000 differentially expressed genes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="149" pm="."><plain>These expression changes have been confirmed to be quite similar to EMT via further proteomics analysis using 2-DE/MS (GSE10650). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="150" pm="."><plain>Our predictions on EMT suggest MAZ as a candidate TF to regulate EMT in the HCT116 cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="151" pm="."><plain>Among the candidate targets of MAZ in the EMT gene set, Bmp7, Col1a1, Sfrp2, Wnt2 and Wnt5a exhibit two or higher expression fold-changes. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="152" pm="."><plain>Interestingly, four of the targets except for Sfrp2 were also captured among the PAX4 results for the same cell condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="153" pm="."><plain>This indicates PAX4 and MAZ possibly cooperate on their four common targets to regulate EMT in the HCT cells. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="154" pm="."><plain>For another example, the embroid body cells (GSE9196) the differentiation of which is known to accompany EMT [20] also exhibit clear activation in many of the MAZ targets (Additional file 1: Figure S3a). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="155" pm="."><plain>Among the conditions, HUVECs treated with TNF-alpha are captured by five of the eight TF results (Additional file 1: Figure S3b-e). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="156" pm="."><plain>By mapping each TF to the targets that exhibit two or higher fold-changes, the EMT transcription networks in HUVECs treated with TNF-alpha were constructed that comprised five TFs and six target genes (Figure 5). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="157" pm="."><plain>TNF-alpha is a key cytokine involved in inflammation and cancer, and is known to induce EMT [21]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="158" pm="."><plain>Because HUVECs do not contain epithelial cells, such EMT signals may indicate ‘endothelial’ to mesenchymal transitions.Figure 5 EMT transcription networks in HUVECs inferred from REGNET. The sun symbols indicate the corresponding TFs or TF-target relationships have strong supports from the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="159" pm="."><plain>The circle symbols indicate weak supports from the literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="160" pm="."><plain>The evidences from the literature are all summarized in Additional file 1: Table S2. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="161" pm="."><plain>The graph is depicted using the Graphviz software. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="162" pm="."><plain>Although each regulatory relationship in the networks needs to be validated, it is noteworthy that the predicted edges of the networks were evenly distributed among the five TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="163" pm="."><plain>This implies that the EMT in HUVECs is processed by a tight cooperation of these regulators. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="164" pm="."><plain>Some of the reports for the predicted regulatory relationships are provided in Additional file 1: Table S2. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title><text><SENT sid="165" pm="."><plain>A global assessment of REGNET </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="166" pm="."><plain>Because the predicted TNs in REGNET are context-specific (the targets or effects of a TF can change depending on the cell conditions), reliable gold-standard TNs for a global assessment are rarely available. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="167" pm="."><plain>For example, each ChIP-seq or ChIP-chip dataset is also obtained under a specific cell condition and may not serve as a general gold-standard set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="168" pm="."><plain>Therefore, instead of considering individual cell conditions, we merged all the context-specific targets of a TF for our prediction set (the union of the intersection parts in Figure 2a), and merged multiple ChIP-seq or ChIP-chip data for gold-standard targets of a TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="169" pm="."><plain>Among the prediction set, we further selected candidate targets that exhibited ±1.5 or higher fold expression changes across 0.3 ×k conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="170" pm="."><plain>We validated the predicted targets of E2F1, JUN and TP53. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="171" pm="."><plain>Because these TFs have multiple known binding sites in MSigDB, we merged all the corresponding targets for each TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="172" pm="."><plain>The targets reported from ChIP data are downloaded from ChEA curated database [22]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="173" pm="."><plain>Three, one and six ChIP datasets were available for E2F1, JUN and TP53, respectively and corresponding targets were merged for each TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="174" pm="."><plain>These targets with known TFBS were further selected for true positive gold standard sets. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="175" pm="."><plain>Among the 564 genes with an E2F1 binding site, 65 were the predicted as context-specific targets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="176" pm="."><plain>Among the 270 true positive set, 39 were included in the 65 predicted set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="177" pm="."><plain>This corresponds to specificity 0.9116 and sensitivity 0.1444 with a significant p-value 0.0256 against a random prediction (hypergeometric distribution). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="178" pm="."><plain>The true positive set used here is obtained from a collection of high-throughput ChIP datasets and is missing the three targets Dusp6, Mll5 and Gadd45b, while these targets were identified from our ChIP assay. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="179" pm="."><plain>If we include these three in the positive set, we have an improved sensitivity 0.1538 with a significant p-value 0.0039. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="180" pm="."><plain>Unfortunately, JUN had only one ChIP data in ChEA database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="181" pm="."><plain>Based on this single ChIP dataset, we had specificity 0.7853, sensitivity 0.2593 but with a less significant p-value 0.1734. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="182" pm="."><plain>Lastly, TP53 had six ChIP datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="183" pm="."><plain>Among the 426 genes with an P53 binding site, 142 were true positives and the 50 predicted targets included 25 true positives. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="184" pm="."><plain>This corresponds to specificity 0.9120, sensitivity 0.1761 and a significant p-value 0.0071. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="185" pm="."><plain>In summary, REGNET provides highly specific predictions for context-specific transcriptional regulations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="186" pm="."><plain>Though less sensitive, they still contain a number of novel regulatory relationships as shown in our ChIP assay and the EMT networks. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title><text><SENT sid="187" pm="."><plain>Assessment for extended GO and KEGG annotations </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="188" pm="."><plain>Because many genes are still unannotated in GO and KEGG, transcriptional regulations for such genes are not covered by REGNET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="189" pm="."><plain>To ameliorate the problem, we extended GO and KEGG annotations using protein-protein interaction networks [23], and tested how the extended annotations affect the predictions in REGNET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="190" pm="."><plain>The annotations are extended as follows: For each gene gi (protein), we identified the set of interacting proteins Li from the BioGrid database [24]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="191" pm="."><plain>For each functional gene set (GO or KEGG annotation), say Fj, we assessed the significance of overlap between Li and Fj using hypergeometric distribution. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="192" pm="."><plain>If an overlap p-value ≤ p0, we assign the annotation Fj to the gene gi. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="193" pm="."><plain>In the original GO and KEGG annotations, 2,409 GO biological process terms (GO-BP), 369 GO cellular component terms (GO-CC), 186 GO molecular function terms (GO-MF) and 666 KEGG terms are used to annotate genes 164,562, 26,270, 12,875 and 41,063 times respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="194" pm="."><plain>When a threshold p0 = 10E-4 is applied, GO-BP, GO-CC, GO-MF and KEGG terms are used 233,878, 37,455, 23,370 and 54,142 times exhibiting overall 29.8% increase. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="195" pm="."><plain>Using these extended annotations, we regenerated significant patterns in REGNET and extracted context-specific targets of E2F1 and TP53, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="196" pm="."><plain>With the original annotations, 65 and 50 context-specific targets were identified for E2F1 and TP53, but the extended annotations increased these numbers to 183 and 71, respectively. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="197" pm="."><plain>The extended predictions, as expected, exhibited somewhat reduced specificities 0.7313 and 0.8627, and increased sensitivities 0.3852 and 0.2253 for E2F1 and TP53, respectively. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="198" pm="."><plain>Here, we illustrated how current annotations can be extended using protein interaction data and how such extension could affect the predictions in REGNET, but such extensions are not included in the current REGNET system. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS,CONCL"><sec id="Sec13"><title><text><SENT sid="199" pm="."><plain>Discussion and conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><text><SENT sid="200" pm="."><plain>For a given TF or a functional gene set, REGNET provides the associated TNs as well as the corresponding conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="201" pm="."><plain>From the heat map provided for each of the associated pairs of a TF and functional gene set, investigators can select putative targets that exhibit large expression changes across a number of different conditions. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="202" pm="."><plain>We note that the transcription networks inferred in our approach have multiple lines of evidences and a substantial portion of such predictions are highly likely true as validated by reports in the literature and the ChIP assay in the finding reported here. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="203" pm="."><plain>For a global validation, we pooled targets from multiple ChIP datasets and pooled context-specific predictions for each of three TFs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="204" pm="."><plain>As expected, predictions in REGNET were highly specific and less sensitive. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="205" pm="."><plain>For example, REGNET provides 65 context-specific targets of E2F1, 42 of which were actually bound by the TF. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="206" pm="."><plain>More importantly, REGNET suggests the cell conditions in which such regulation patterns occur. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="207" pm="."><plain>Despite the high specificity, predictions by REGNET included many novel targets providing useful clues for unraveling cellular processes. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="208" pm="."><plain>Because many microarray datasets have only a small number of samples, we applied a gene randomizing gene set analysis method [25, 26] to assess the overall expression changes in each gene set. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="209" pm="."><plain>Most gene-randomizing methods, however, suffer from increased false-positives [26]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="210" pm="."><plain>To reduce false positives, we applied an auxiliary filter that requires a significant regulation pattern to be observed across a number of different conditions. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="211" pm="."><plain>Specifically, REGNET deploys a composite gene-set analysis method [9, 10] to combine three sources of genomic information: TFBS gene set, functional gene set and gene expression fold-change profile. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="212" pm="."><plain>As a result, three-dimensional information among the TFs, their functional targets and cell conditions are readily explored. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="213" pm="."><plain>Most other approaches including DAVID [27], the Molecular Concept Map [28] and ConceptGen [29] investigate the ‘binary’ relationships between a TFBS gene set and another gene list. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="214" pm="."><plain>One may apply the overlap of gene-sets once more to investigate such three-dimensional relationships, but the repeated use of gene-set overlaps may cause a serious loss of power due to the use of threshold values [26, 30]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="215" pm="."><plain>Because the activity of a TF is estimated by the overall pattern of expression change in its target genes, REGNET is most useful for finding relatively strong transcriptional activities in which a TF regulates multiple target genes simultaneously. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="216" pm="."><plain>On the other hand, specific regulation of one or two targets that have only small expression changes might be missed in this approach. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="217" pm="."><plain>Another limitation is that by using the TFBS information instead of genome-wide ChIP data, which are mostly unavailable, we only consider the sequence-specific transcriptional regulation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="218" pm="."><plain>Furthermore, many gene functions are still unknown and remain unannotated in GO or KEGG. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="219" pm="."><plain>We here demonstrated a method to extend annotation gene-sets using protein interaction data and its effect on the performance of REGNET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="220" pm="."><plain>More reliable extension of gene annotation may be possible by integrating diverse types of genomic data and network information which may help identifying missing transcriptional associations in REGNET [31–33]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="221" pm="."><plain>Over the last decade, more than a million gene expression microarray datasets have been deposited in public databases [11, 34, 35], covering virtually all of the cell conditions of interest including a broad range of tissues, diseases, development and treatments. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="222" pm="."><plain>Most of them are made up of test and control samples, and their fold-change values provide information on the TNs specific to each condition. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="223" pm="."><plain>For this reason, we have collected the fold-change profiles for a diverse array of cell conditions in order to identify context-specific TNs. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="224" pm="."><plain>We have collected 2,482 human expression fold-change profiles in our current database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="225" pm="."><plain>As this number increases, it is expected that more specific TNs are newly identified. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="226" pm="."><plain>Moreover, developing a similar system for other species would be valuable for the purpose of comparative analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title><text><SENT sid="227" pm="."><plain>Electronic supplementary material </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="Sec14"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="12864_2013_6133_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p><text><SENT sid="228" pm="."><plain>Additional file 1: The description on ChIP assay and EMT networks. Figure S1. ChIP assay design. Figure S2. Heat maps associated with c-JUN. Figure S3. EMT transcription networks by five TFs. Table S1. Oligos used for ChIP assays. Table S2. Evidences of the EMT transcription networks from literature. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="229" pm="."><plain>(PDF 1 MB) </plain></SENT>
</text></p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="ABBR"><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-list><def-item><term>TF</term><def><p>Transcription factor</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TFBS</term><def><p>Transcription factor binding site</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>TN</term><def><p>Transcription network</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>ChIP</term><def><p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>GO</term><def><p>Gene ontology</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KEGG</term><def><p>Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MSigDB</term><def><p>Molecular signature database</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>EMT</term><def><p>Epithelial to mesenchymal transition.</p></def></def-item></def-list></def-list></glossary></SecTag><fn-group><fn><p><text><SENT sid="230" pm="."><plain>Competing interests </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="231" pm="."><plain>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn><fn><p><text><SENT sid="232" pm="."><plain>Authors’ contributions </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p><text><SENT sid="233" pm="."><plain>SMC and YKP developed the database, YKS did ChIP assay and CYP confirmed the result. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="234" pm="."><plain>SY aided literature study. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="235" pm="."><plain>SYK, DN and YSK co-supervised the development of database. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="236" pm="."><plain>SYK collected microarray datasets. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="237" pm="."><plain>DN wrote the manuscript. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="238" pm="."><plain>All authors read and approved the final manuscript. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></fn-group><SecTag type="ACK_FUND"><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p><text4fund><text><SENT sid="239" pm="."><plain>This work was supported by Basic Science Research Program through a National Research Foundation (NRF) grants funded by the Korean government (MEST) (No. 2012–0003589 and No. 2011-0020163) to DN, and by genomics (2012M3A9D1054670) program of the National Research Foundation of Korea funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (MEST) to SYK. </plain></SENT>
</text></text4fund></p></ack></SecTag><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><text><SENT sid="240" pm="."><plain>1.BansalMBelcastroVAmbesi-ImpiombatoAdi BernardoDHow to infer gene networks from expression profilesMol Syst Biol200737810.1038/msb4100158<?supplied-pmid 17299415?>17299415 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR2"><text><SENT sid="241" pm="."><plain>2.HarbisonCTGordonDBLeeTIRinaldiNJMacisaacKDDanfordTWHannettNMTagneJBReynoldsDBYooJJenningsEGZeitlingerJPokholokDKKellisMRolfePATakusagawaKTLanderESGiffordDKFraenkelEYoungRATranscriptional regulatory code of a eukaryotic genomeNature200443170049910410.1038/nature02800<?supplied-pmid 15343339?>15343339 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR3"><text><SENT sid="242" pm="."><plain>3.ChenXXuHYuanPFangFHussMVegaVBWongEOrlovYLZhangWJiangJLohYHYeoHCYeoZXNarangVGovindarajanKRLeongBShahabARuanYBourqueGSungWKClarkeNDWeiCLNgHHIntegration of external signaling pathways with the core transcriptional network in embryonic stem cellsCell200813361106111710.1016/j.cell.2008.04.043<?supplied-pmid 18555785?>18555785 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR4"><text><SENT sid="243" pm="."><plain>4.HeFBallingRZengAPReverse engineering and verification of gene networks: principles, assumptions, and limitations of present methods and future perspectivesJ Biotechnol2009144319020310.1016/j.jbiotec.2009.07.013<?supplied-pmid 19631244?>19631244 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR5"><text><SENT sid="244" pm="."><plain>5.WingenderEChenXFrickeEGeffersRHehlRLiebichIKrullMMatysVMichaelHOhnhauserRPrüssMSchachererFThieleSUrbachSThe TRANSFAC system on gene expression regulationNucleic Acids Res200129128128310.1093/nar/29.1.281<?supplied-pmid 11125113?>11125113 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR6"><text><SENT sid="245" pm="."><plain>6.WassermanWWSandelinAApplied bioinformatics for the identification of regulatory elementsNat Rev Genet20045427628710.1038/nrg1315<?supplied-pmid 15131651?>15131651 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR7"><text><SENT sid="246" pm="."><plain>7.KatoMHataNBanerjeeNFutcherBZhangMQIdentifying combinatorial regulation of transcription factors and binding motifsGenome Biol200458R5610.1186/gb-2004-5-8-r56<?supplied-pmid 15287978?>15287978 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR8"><text><SENT sid="247" pm="."><plain>8.GaoFFoatBCBussemakerHJDefining transcriptional networks through integrative modeling of mRNA expression and transcription factor binding dataBMC Bioinformatics200453110.1186/1471-2105-5-31<?supplied-pmid 15113405?>15113405 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR9"><text><SENT sid="248" pm="."><plain>9.ChiSMKimJKimSYNamDADGO 2.0: interpreting microarray data and list of genes using composite annotationsNucleic Acids Res201139W30230610.1093/nar/gkr392<?supplied-pmid 21624890?>21624890 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR10"><text><SENT sid="249" pm="."><plain>10.NamDKimSBKimSKYangSKimSYChuISADGO: analysis of differentially expressed gene sets using composite GO annotationBioinformatics200622182249225310.1093/bioinformatics/btl378<?supplied-pmid 16837524?>16837524 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR11"><text><SENT sid="250" pm="."><plain>11.BarrettTWilhiteSELedouxPEvangelistaCKimIFTomashevskyMMarshallKAPhillippyKHShermanPMHolkoMYefanovALeeHZhangNRobertsonCLSerovaNDavisSSobolevaANCBI GEO: archive for functional genomics data sets–updateNucleic Acids Res201341Database issueD99199510.1093/nar/gks1193<?supplied-pmid 23193258?>23193258 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR12"><text><SENT sid="251" pm="."><plain>12.LiberzonASubramanianAPinchbackRThorvaldsdottirHTamayoPMesirovJPMolecular signatures database (MSigDB) 3.0Bioinformatics201127121739174010.1093/bioinformatics/btr260<?supplied-pmid 21546393?>21546393 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR13"><text><SENT sid="252" pm="."><plain>13.SatyanarayanaAKaldisPMammalian cell-cycle regulation: several Cdks, numerous cyclins and diverse compensatory mechanismsOncogene200928332925293910.1038/onc.2009.170<?supplied-pmid 19561645?>19561645 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR14"><text><SENT sid="253" pm="."><plain>14.LeeJSHeoJLibbrechtLChuISKaposi-NovakPCalvisiDFMikaelyanARobertsLRDemetrisAJSunZNevensFRoskamsTThorgeirssonSSA novel prognostic subtype of human hepatocellular carcinoma derived from hepatic progenitor cellsNat Med200612441041610.1038/nm1377<?supplied-pmid 16532004?>16532004 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR15"><text><SENT sid="254" pm="."><plain>15.KimSAUmSJKangJHHongKJExpression of thrombospondin-1 in human hepatocarcinoma cell lines and its regulation by transcription factor Jun/AP-1Mol Cell Biochem20012161–2212910.1023/A:1011022822077<?supplied-pmid 11216860?>11216860 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR16"><text><SENT sid="255" pm="."><plain>16.MettouchiACabonFMontreauNVernierPMercierGBlangyDTricoireHVigierPBinetruyBSPARC and thrombospondin genes are repressed by the c-jun oncogene in rat embryo fibroblastsEMBO J1994132356685678<?supplied-pmid 7988564?>7988564 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR17"><text><SENT sid="256" pm="."><plain>17.OuafikLBerenguer-DaizeCBerthoisYAdrenomedullin promotes cell cycle transit and up-regulates cyclin D1 protein level in human glioblastoma cells through the activation of c-Jun/JNK/AP-1 signal transduction pathwayCell Signal200921459760810.1016/j.cellsig.2009.01.001<?supplied-pmid 19166930?>19166930 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR18"><text><SENT sid="257" pm="."><plain>18.KlingenbergJMMcFarlandKLFriedmanAJBoyceSTAronowBJSuppDMEngineered human skin substitutes undergo large-scale genomic reprogramming and normal skin-like maturation after transplantation to athymic miceJ Invest Dermatol2010130258760110.1038/jid.2009.295<?supplied-pmid 19798058?>19798058 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR19"><text><SENT sid="258" pm="."><plain>19.ShamesDSGirardLGaoBSatoMLewisCMShivapurkarNJiangAPerouCMKimYHPollackJRFongKMLamCLWongMShyrYNandaROlopadeOIGeraldWEuhusDMShayJWGazdarAFMinnaJDA genome-wide screen for promoter methylation in lung cancer identifies novel methylation markers for multiple malignanciesPLoS Med2006312e48610.1371/journal.pmed.0030486<?supplied-pmid 17194187?>17194187 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR20"><text><SENT sid="259" pm="."><plain>20.ten BergeDKooleWFuererCFishMErogluENusseRWnt signaling mediates self-organization and axis formation in embryoid bodiesCell Stem Cell20083550851810.1016/j.stem.2008.09.013<?supplied-pmid 18983966?>18983966 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR21"><text><SENT sid="260" pm="."><plain>21.WuYZhouBPTNF-alpha/NF-kappaB/Snail pathway in cancer cell migration and invasionBr J Cancer2010102463964410.1038/sj.bjc.6605530<?supplied-pmid 20087353?>20087353 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR22"><text><SENT sid="261" pm="."><plain>22.LachmannAXuHKrishnanJBergerSIMazloomARMa’ayanAChEA: transcription factor regulation inferred from integrating genome-wide ChIP-X experimentsBioinformatics201026192438244410.1093/bioinformatics/btq466<?supplied-pmid 20709693?>20709693 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR23"><text><SENT sid="262" pm="."><plain>23.JansenRYuHGreenbaumDKlugerYKroganNJChungSEmiliASnyderMGreenblattJFGersteinMA Bayesian networks approach for predicting protein-protein interactions from genomic dataScience2003302564444945310.1126/science.1087361<?supplied-pmid 14564010?>14564010 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR24"><text><SENT sid="263" pm="."><plain>24.Chatr-AryamontriABreitkreutzBJHeinickeSBoucherLWinterAStarkCNixonJRamageLKolasNO’DonnellLRegulyTBreitkreutzASellamAChenDChangCRustJLivstoneMOughtredRDolinskiKTyersMThe BioGRID interaction database: 2013 updateNucleic Acids Res201341Database issueD81682310.1093/nar/gks1158<?supplied-pmid 23203989?>23203989 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR25"><text><SENT sid="264" pm="."><plain>25.KimSYVolskyDJPAGE: parametric analysis of gene set enrichmentBMC Bioinformatics2005614410.1186/1471-2105-6-144<?supplied-pmid 15941488?>15941488 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR26"><text><SENT sid="265" pm="."><plain>26.NamDKimSYGene-set approach for expression pattern analysisBrief Bioinform20089318919710.1093/bib/bbn001<?supplied-pmid 18202032?>18202032 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR27"><text><SENT sid="266" pm="."><plain>27.da HuangWShermanBTLempickiRASystematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resourcesNat Protoc200941445710.1038/nprot.2008.211<?supplied-pmid 19131956?>19131956 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR28"><text><SENT sid="267" pm="."><plain>28.RhodesDRKalyana-SundaramSTomlinsSAMahavisnoVKasperNVaramballyRBarretteTRGhoshDVaramballySChinnaiyanAMMolecular concepts analysis links tumors, pathways, mechanisms, and drugsNeoplasia20079544345410.1593/neo.07292<?supplied-pmid 17534450?>17534450 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR29"><text><SENT sid="268" pm="."><plain>29.SartorMAMahavisnoVKeshamouniVGCavalcoliJWrightZKarnovskyAKuickRJagadishHVMirelBWeymouthTAtheyBOmennGSConceptGen: a gene set enrichment and gene set relation mapping toolBioinformatics201026445646310.1093/bioinformatics/btp683<?supplied-pmid 20007254?>20007254 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR30"><text><SENT sid="269" pm="."><plain>30.MoothaVKLindgrenCMErikssonKFSubramanianASihagSLeharJPuigserverPCarlssonERidderstraleMLaurilaEHoustisNDalyMJPattersonNMesirovJPGolubTRTamayoPSpiegelmanBLanderESHirschhornJNAltshulerDGroopLCPGC-1alpha-responsive genes involved in oxidative phosphorylation are coordinately downregulated in human diabetesNat Genet200334326727310.1038/ng1180<?supplied-pmid 12808457?>12808457 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR31"><text><SENT sid="270" pm="."><plain>31.WangPIHwangSKincaidRPSullivanCSLeeIMarcotteEMRIDDLE: reflective diffusion and local extension reveal functional associations for unannotated gene sets via proximity in a gene networkGenome Biol20121312R12510.1186/gb-2012-13-12-r125<?supplied-pmid 23268829?>23268829 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR32"><text><SENT sid="271" pm="."><plain>32.DutkowskiJKramerMSurmaMABalakrishnanRCherryJMKroganNJIdekerTA gene ontology inferred from molecular networksNat Biotechnol2013311384510.1038/nbt.2463<?supplied-pmid 23242164?>23242164 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR33"><text><SENT sid="272" pm="."><plain>33.ChuaHNSungWKWongLAn efficient strategy for extensive integration of diverse biological data for protein function predictionBioinformatics200723243364337310.1093/bioinformatics/btm520<?supplied-pmid 18048396?>18048396 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR34"><text><SENT sid="273" pm="."><plain>34.RusticiGKolesnikovNBrandiziMBurdettTDylagMEmamIFarneAHastingsEIsonJKeaysMKurbatovaNMaloneJManiRMupoAPedro PereiraRPilichevaERungJSharmaATangYATernentTTikhonovAWelterDWilliamsEBrazmaAParkinsonHSarkansUArrayExpress update–trends in database growth and links to data analysis toolsNucleic Acids Res201341Database issueD98799010.1093/nar/gks1174<?supplied-pmid 23193272?>23193272 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="CR35"><text><SENT sid="274" pm="."><plain>35.DemeterJBeauheimCGollubJHernandez-BoussardTJinHMaierDMateseJCNitzbergMWymoreFZachariahZKBrownPOSherlockGBallCAThe Stanford microarray database: implementation of new analysis tools and open source release of softwareNucleic Acids Res200735Database issueD76677010.1093/nar/gkl1019<?supplied-pmid 17182626?>17182626 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag></back></article>
