<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.4.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art540.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.4.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_CTRO28 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 pdf ?><?FILEmmc2 doc ?><?FILEmmc3 doc ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Transl Radiat Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Clin Transl Radiat Oncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Clinical and Translational Radiation Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2405-6308</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5833918</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2405-6308(17)30012-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctro.2017.04.001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><SecTag type="TITLE"><text><SENT sid="0" pm="."><plain>Association of lung fluorodeoxyglucose uptake with radiation pneumonitis after concurrent chemoradiation for non-small cell lung cancer </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Jinbo</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McKeever</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sio</surname><given-names>Terence T.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af020" ref-type="aff">d</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Ting</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huo</surname><given-names>Jinhai</given-names></name><xref rid="af025" ref-type="aff">e</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Qiuling</given-names></name><xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>Quynh-Nhu</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Komaki</surname><given-names>Ritsuko</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>Daniel R.</given-names></name><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Tinsu</given-names></name><xref rid="af035" ref-type="aff">g</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xin Shelley</given-names></name><xref rid="af030" ref-type="aff">f</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Zhongxing</given-names></name><email>zliao@mdanderson.org</email><xref rid="af005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">⁎</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af005"><label>a</label>Department of Radiation Oncology, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</aff><aff id="af010"><label>b</label>Department of Radiation Oncology, Shandong Cancer Hospital and Institute, Jinan, Shandong, China</aff><aff id="af015"><label>c</label>UT Southwestern Medical School, Dallas, TX, USA</aff><aff id="af020"><label>d</label>Department of Radiation Oncology, Mayo Clinic, Scottsdale, AZ, USA</aff><aff id="af025"><label>e</label>Department of Health Services Research, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</aff><aff id="af030"><label>f</label>Department of Symptom Research, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</aff><aff id="af035"><label>g</label>Department of Imaging Physics, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, TX, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>⁎</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Radiation Oncology, Unit 1422, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, 1400 Pressler St., Houston, TX 77030, USA.Department of Radiation OncologyUnit 1422The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center1400 Pressler St.HoustonTX77030USA <email>zliao@mdanderson.org</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>8</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>© 2017 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab005"><sec><title><text><SENT sid="1" pm="."><plain>Background </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="2" pm="."><plain>Increased uptake of fluorodeoxyglucose (FDG) by lung tissue could reflect inflammatory changes related to radiation pneumonitis (RP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="3" pm="."><plain>In this secondary analysis of a clinical trial, we examined potential associations between posttreatment lung FDG uptake and RP severity in patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) for up to 12 months after concurrent chemoradiation (CRT). </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="4" pm="."><plain>Methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="5" pm="."><plain>Subjects were 152 patients with NSCLC who had received concurrent CRT as part of the prospective trial NCT00915005. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="6" pm="."><plain>The following lung FDG variables were evaluated after CRT: maximum, mean, and peak standardized uptake values (SUVmax, SUVmean, SUVpeak) and global lung glycolysis (GLG; lung SUVmean × lung volume). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="7" pm="."><plain>RP severity was scored with the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events v3.0. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="8" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="9" pm="."><plain>Significant associations were noted between PET findings and RP severity at 1–6 months (all P &lt; 0.05), but not at 7–12 months after therapy (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="10" pm="."><plain>Lung FDG uptake at 1–3 months after treatment predicted later development of grade ≥2 RP (all P &lt; 0.05), with cutoff values as follows: 4.54 for SUVmax, 3.69 for SUVpeak, 0.78 for SUVmean, and 2295 for GLG. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec><sec><title><text><SENT sid="11" pm="."><plain>Conclusions </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p><SecTag type="ABS"><text><SENT sid="12" pm="."><plain>Lung FDG uptake correlated significantly with RP severity during the first 6 months after CRT. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="13" pm="."><plain>The cutoff values seem clinically meaningful for identifying patients at risk of developing RP after such therapy. </plain></SENT>
</text></SecTag></p></sec></abstract><SecTag type="KEYWORD"><kwd-group id="kg005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>FDG PET</kwd><kwd>Radiation pneumonitis</kwd><kwd>Clinician-rated toxicity</kwd><kwd>Non-small cell lung cancer</kwd><kwd>Radiotherapy</kwd></kwd-group></SecTag></article-meta></front><body><SecTag type="INTRO"><sec id="s0005"><title><text><SENT sid="14" pm="."><plain>Introduction </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0005"><text><SENT sid="15" pm="."><plain>Radiation pneumonitis (RP) is a common and potentially fatal complication among patients with locally advanced non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) treated with radiation therapy. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="16" pm="."><plain>On a cellular level, the acute phase of RP is characterized by the movement of inflammatory mononuclear cells from the vascular compartment to the alveolar space [1]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="17" pm="."><plain>The ability to detect RP early by using advanced imaging modalities could provide significant clinical benefits to affected patients by allowing supportive care to be implemented promptly. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0010"><text><SENT sid="18" pm="."><plain>However, the clinical diagnosis of RP can be challenging. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="19" pm="."><plain>On images of irradiated lungs, RP can manifest as consolidation, ground glass opacities, or both. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="20" pm="."><plain>For patients with preexisting lung disease, the uncertainty in diagnosing RP is even greater, with studies reporting rates of diagnostic uncertainty ranging from 28% to 48% [2], [3]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="21" pm="."><plain>Computed tomography (CT) has low sensitivity and suboptimal specificity for detecting early tissue injury and inflammation in the lung parenchyma because of its inability to distinguish RP imaging findings from those of other pulmonary disease processes [4]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="22" pm="."><plain>Thus, the ability of molecular imaging to detect the inflammatory process associated with RP before the development of any visible structural manifestation makes it a potentially effective method for studying RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="23" pm="."><plain>RP manifests on 2-fluoro-2-deoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG PET) as increased FDG uptake, and such increases allow quantitative assessment of pneumonitis [5], [6]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="24" pm="."><plain>Thus, lung parenchymal FDG uptake on PET/CT could be a useful biomarker to quantify and predict lung inflammation after thoracic radiation [7], [8]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="25" pm="."><plain>However, no study has yet explored the longitudinal and cross-sectional relationships between molecular imaging and radiation-induced RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="26" pm="."><plain>In the current study, we obtained serial FDG PET scans during the first 12 months after treatment for patients with NSCLC participating in a prospective clinical protocol, and we correlated these findings with RP grade assessed by clinicians. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="27" pm="."><plain>We further aimed to identify the potential value of post-treatment FDG PET for assessing and predicting the severity of lung RP after thoracic radiation. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="METHODS"><sec id="s0010"><title><text><SENT sid="28" pm="."><plain>Materials and methods </plain></SENT>
</text></title><sec id="s0015"><title><text><SENT sid="29" pm="."><plain>Patients </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0015"><text><SENT sid="30" pm="."><plain>The study was secondary analysis of randomized patient groups in a prospective clinical trial (NCT00915005) conducted from June 2009 through April 2014 at The University of Texas M.D. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="31" pm="."><plain>Anderson Cancer Center in Houston, Texas, USA. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="32" pm="."><plain>Eligibility criteria for patients included having pathologic confirmation of NSCLC, being at least 18 years old, having unresectable disease, and being scheduled to receive curative-intent concurrent chemoradiation therapy (CRT) with either carboplatin and paclitaxel, or etoposide and cisplatin or pemetrexed for patients with lung adenocarcinoma. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="33" pm="."><plain>This study was approved by the appropriate institutional review board, and all participants gave written informed consent to participate. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0020"><title><text><SENT sid="34" pm="."><plain>FDG PET image analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0020"><text><SENT sid="35" pm="."><plain>FDG PET scans were obtained from patients before treatment and at 1–3 months, 4–6 months, 7–9 months, and 10–12 months after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="36" pm="."><plain>All patients had fasted for a minimum of 6 h and had a blood glucose level of 80–120 mg/dL (4.4–6.6 mmol/L) before intravenous administration of 18F-FDG (555–740 MBq [15–20 mCi]). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="37" pm="."><plain>Data were acquired 60 min after radiotracer injection, with 3 min per bed in 2D acquisition mode, from the orbit to the mid-thigh, with a GE Discovery ST PET/CT scanner. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="38" pm="."><plain>No CT contrast was injected for the CT component of the PET/CT scan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="39" pm="."><plain>PET/CT images were processed and evaluated by a clinical investigator and an experienced nuclear medicine physician using Mirada XD3 software (Mirada Medical, Denver, CO, USA). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="40" pm="."><plain>The region of interest was the volume of both lungs with the following corrections. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="41" pm="."><plain>First, the volume was restricted to areas on the CT scan with a radiodensity of −400 Hounsfield units; then both lungs were outlined manually on the post-treatment PET/CT fusion scans, excluding the gross tumor volume (GTV) and central airway, and parenchymal changes thought to be related to treatment (e.g., ground glass opacities, interstitial infiltrates, homogeneous or patchy consolidation, and reticulation) were marked (Fig. 1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="42" pm="."><plain>PET spill-over artifacts attributable to heart, tumor, and liver activity were manually contoured and carefully excluded from the segmented lung volume [9]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="43" pm="."><plain>The FDG uptake variables for the region of interest (volume of both lungs, excluding GTV) were generated automatically with the XD3 software, including maximum standardized uptake value [SUVmax], SUVmean, SUVpeak, and global lung glycolysis (GLG). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="44" pm="."><plain>SUVpeak was defined as the average SUV within a 1-cm3 sphere centered in the lung region having the highest uptake [10]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="45" pm="."><plain>GLG was defined as the SUVmean for both lungs (excluding the GTV) multiplied by the volume of both lungs (also excluding GTV) [4].Fig. 1PET/CT fusion scans from a patient showing inflammatory infiltration of the lungs, with interstitial infiltrates, ground glass opacities, homogeneous consolidation, and patchy consolidation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="46" pm="."><plain>(A) Scan obtained before treatment; the bright yellow area inside the white outline is the primary lung tumor. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="47" pm="."><plain>(B) Scan obtained 2 months after treatment; the bright yellow area inside the white outline represents interstitial infiltrates. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="48" pm="."><plain>Scans obtained at 4 months (C), 7 months (D), and 10 months after treatment (E) illustrate the course of interstitial infiltration over time. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0025"><title><text><SENT sid="49" pm="."><plain>Clinician-rated toxicity </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0025"><text><SENT sid="50" pm="."><plain>RP was systematically recorded and scored during the trial according to the National Cancer Institute’s Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 3 (CTCAE v3) [11].The score (grade) was determined on the basis of both lung radiographic findings and RP symptoms (obtained from clinic notes made by the treating clinicians and from other consultations). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="51" pm="."><plain>Grade 1 is associated with no symptoms; grade 2, with symptoms that do not interfere with activities of daily living; grade 3, with symptoms that do interfere with activities of daily living; grade 4, with symptoms that are life-threatening, and grade 5, with death. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0030"><title><text><SENT sid="52" pm="."><plain>Statistical analysis </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0030"><text><SENT sid="53" pm="."><plain>Patient characteristics were evaluated with descriptive statistics. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="54" pm="."><plain>Cross-sectional correlations between the post-treatment PET variables and CTCAE RP grade were assessed with Spearman correlation coefficients. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="55" pm="."><plain>Mixed effect models were used to examine the longitudinal relationships between lung SUVmean and CTCAE RP score over the four specified time periods (1–3 months, 4–6 months, 7–9 months, and 10–12 months after treatment); ordinal logistic regression was used to calculate the cumulative probability of association of SUV variables across various levels of CTCAE RP grade. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="56" pm="."><plain>The predictive value of post-treatment PET findings with regard to CTCAE RP (grade ≥ 2 vs. 0–1) was analyzed with binary logistic models. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="57" pm="."><plain>To simplify the application of these values in clinical practice, we used receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve regression analysis to identify cutoff values that were the most sensitive for identifying RP grades 2–4 at after therapy (Suppl Fig. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="58" pm="."><plain>S1). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="59" pm="."><plain>The best cutoff value was determined using the criteria of minimal distance to (0/1) for candidate predictors such as lung SUVmax, SUVpeak, SUVmean, and GLG after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="60" pm="."><plain>Statistical analyses were done with SAS version 9.4. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="RESULTS"><sec id="s0035"><title><text><SENT sid="61" pm="."><plain>Results </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0035"><text><SENT sid="62" pm="."><plain>Patient, tumor, and treatment characteristics are shown in Table 1. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="63" pm="."><plain>All 152 patients completed the protocol-dictated treatment regimen (concurrent CRT). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="64" pm="."><plain>Most patients had stage III disease and good performance status. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="65" pm="."><plain>Twenty-six patients (17%) had four PET/CT scans, 50 (33%) had 3 scans, 50 (33%) had 3 scans, and 26 (17%) had one scan. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="66" pm="."><plain>Between 14% and 31% had RP symptoms during any measurement period. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="67" pm="."><plain>No patient had grade 4 or 5 RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="68" pm="."><plain>Values of SUVmax, SUVpeak, SUVmean, and GLG at each measurement point are shown in Supplementary Table S1.Table 1Patient characteristics.CharacteristicNo. of patients%Age, years Median (range): 66 (33–85)  Sex Male8153 Female7147  Race White13488 Other1812  Disease stage II117.0 III12482 IV74.5 Recurrence106.5  Tumor histology Adenocarcinoma8355 SCC4832 Other2113  Zubrod performance score 010.8 114092 2117.2  Induction chemotherapy No10066 Yes5234  Adjuvant chemotherapy No12280 Yes3020  Modality IMRT9160 PSPT6140  Total tumor dose, Gy Median (range): 74 (62–74)  Highest-grade toxicity after treatment* 04026.3 14730.9 25838.2 374.6 400  RPGrade 1 1–3 Months after treatment5033 4–6 Months after treatment5335 7–9 Months after treatment3523 10–12 Months after treatment3322  Grade 2 1–3 Months after treatment3523 4–6 Months after treatment4328 7–9 Months after treatment2718 10–12 Months after treatment2114  Grade 3 1–3 Months after treatment53.3 4–6 Months after treatment32.0 7–9 Months after treatment32.0 10–12 Months after treatment10.6  Symptomatic RP# 1–3 Months after treatment4127 4–6 Months after treatment4731 7–9 Months after treatment3020 10–12 Months after treatment2214GTV, median (range), cm315270 (4.8–686)Total tumor dose, median (range), Gy15270 (60–87)Mean lung dose, Gy15217.25 (4.2–23.7)Abbreviations: SCC, squamous cell carcinoma; GTV, gross tumor volume; SUVmean, mean standardized uptake value; CTCAE, Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events; PSPT, passively scattered proton therapy; IMRT, intensity-modulated photon radiation therapy.*Toxicity was assessed with the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events V 3.0.#Symptoms considered to indicate RP included coughing and shortness of breath (which would also be characterized as CTCAE RP grade 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><sec id="s0040"><title><text><SENT sid="69" pm="."><plain>Cross-sectional correlation between RP grade and PET variables </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0040"><text><SENT sid="70" pm="."><plain>Spearman correlation analysis showed that SUVmax, SUVmean, SUVpeak all correlated with RP grade at the 1–3 months and 4–6 months measurement periods (all P &lt; 0.05), but not at the 7–9 months or 10–12 months periods (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="71" pm="."><plain>GLG correlated with RP grade at the 1–3 months period but not at the 4–6 months, 7–9 months, and 10–12 months periods (all P ≥ 0.05) (Table 2).Table 2Associations between FDG PET variables and the development of radiation pneumonitis at various times after treatment.SUVmaxSUVpeakSUVmeanGLGEstimateOR (95% CI)PEstimateOR (95% CI)PEstimateOR (95% CI)PEstimateOR (95% CI)P1–3 mo after treatment0.892.45 (1.87–3.19)0.010.952.60 (1.93–3.50)0.014.37.07 (1.38–16.38)0.010.0011.001 (1.001–1.002)0.014–6 mo after treatment0.441.55 (1.23–1.97)0.010.501.66 (1.26–2.20)0.014.47.96 (1.03–20.18)0.010.0011.000 (1.000–1.001)0.197–9 mo after treatment0.071.08 (0.76–1.53)0.670.131.15 (0.74–1.79)0.550.762.13 (0.07–64.78)0.660.0011.000 (0.999–1.002)0.4510–12 mo after treatment−0.030.97 (0.75–1.26)0.81−0.030.96 (0.68–1.36)0.830.181.20 (0.05–28.24)0.91−0.0010.999 (0.998–1.000)0.06Abbreviations: SUV, standardized uptake value; GLG, global lung glycolysis; mo, month; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0045"><title><text><SENT sid="72" pm="."><plain>Longitudinal correlations between RP grade and PET variables </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0045"><text><SENT sid="73" pm="."><plain>In a mixed-effect longitudinal model, patients with grade 2 or 3 RP had significantly higher SUVmax, SUVmean, SUVpeak, and GLG values than those with grade 0 or 1 RP at 1–3 months and 4–6 months after treatment (all P &lt; 0.001), but not at the 7–9 months and 10–12 months period (P &gt; 0.05) (Fig. 2).Fig. 2Longitudinal correlations between SUV variables and radiation pneumonitis (RP). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="74" pm="."><plain>All four variables studied [(A) SUVmax, (B) SUVpeak, (C) SUVmean, and (D) global lung glycolysis {GLG}] showed significant correlations with RP of grade 0–1 and 2–3 during the first 6 months after therapy, but not thereafter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="75" pm="."><plain>All four of these variables were higher in patients with CTCAE RP grade ≥2 than in patients with CTCAE RP 0–1 during the first 6 months after treatment, but not thereafter. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="76" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: SUV, standardized uptake value; GLG, global lung glycolysis; CTCAE, Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events version 3; post 1, 1–3 months after treatment; post 2, 4–6 months after treatment; post 3, 7–9 months after treatment; post 4, 10–12 months after treatment. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0050"><title><text><SENT sid="77" pm="."><plain>PET variables and RP severity after treatment </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0050"><text><SENT sid="78" pm="."><plain>Like the mixed-effect longitudinal results reported above, an ordinal logistic regression model also showed that higher lung SUVmax, SUVpeak, and SUVmean values were associated with more severe RP (grade 2–3 by CTCAE v3) at 1–3 months and 4–6 months after treatment (all P &lt; 0.01), but not afterwards (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="79" pm="."><plain>Higher lung GLG was associated with more severe RP at 1–3 months after treatment (P &lt; 0.01), but not afterwards (all P &gt; 0.05) (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="80" pm="."><plain>The cumulative probabilities of SUV variables after treatment for RP severity (by CTCAE grade) are shown in Fig. 3.Fig. 3Cumulative probabilities of developing grade 0, 1, 2, or 3 radiation pneumonitis (RP) according to FDG uptake variables on PET. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="81" pm="."><plain>Panels A and B, SUVmean; panels C and D, SUVmax; panels E and F, SUVpeak; panels G and H, global lung glycolysis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="82" pm="."><plain>Abbreviations: SUV, standardized uptake value; post1, 1–3 months after treatment; post2, 4–6 months after treatment.Table 3Predictive value of FDG uptake variables at 1–3 or 4–6 months for subsequent development of grade ≥2 radiation pneumonitis.Predictive variablesTime point for RP (grade ≥ 2 vs. 0–1)Odds ratio (95% CI)P ValueSUVmax at 1–3 mo4–6 mo1.31 (1.05–1.63)0.0157–9 mo—0.45710–12 mo—0.055SUVmean at 1–3 mo4–6 mo3.18 (1.52–6.65)0.0037–9 mo—0.23710–12 mo—0.051SUVpeak at 1–3 mo4–6 mo1.33 (1.04–1.70)0.0227–9 mo—0.38610–12 mo—0.059GLG at 1–3 mo4–6 mo1.35 (1.03–1.80)0.0437–9 mo—0.68410–12 mo—0.836SUVmax at 4–6 mo7–9 mo—0.15710–12 mo—0.874SUVmean at 4–6 mo7–9 mo—0.20910–12 mo—0.926SUVpeak at 4–6 mo7–9 mo—0.17110–12 mo—0.929GLG at 4–6 mo.7–9 mo—0.17610–12 mo—0.121Abbreviations: RP, radiation pneumonitis; SUV, standardized uptake value; GLG, global lung glycolysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec><sec id="s0055"><title><text><SENT sid="83" pm="."><plain>Predictive value of lung PET variables at 1–3 or 4–6 months for subsequent development of RP grade ≥2 </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0055"><text><SENT sid="84" pm="."><plain>In a binary logistic model, lung FDG uptake variables at 1–3 months after treatment predicted CTCAE RP grade ≥2 at 4–6 months after treatment (all P &lt; 0.05), but not afterwards (all P &gt; 0.05). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="85" pm="."><plain>In contrast, lung FDG uptake variables at 4–6 months could not predict CTCAE RP grade ≥2 at 7–9 months or 10–12 months after treatment (Table 3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="86" pm="."><plain>The identified predictive cutoff values of lung FDG uptake in 1–3 months for RP grade ≥2 at 4–6 months after treatment were 0.54 for SUVmax; 3.69 for SUVpeak; 0.78 for SUVmean; and 2295 for GLG (Supplementary Table S2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="DISCUSS"><sec id="s0060"><title><text><SENT sid="87" pm="."><plain>Discussion </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0060"><text><SENT sid="88" pm="."><plain>In this study, we observed significant associations between lung FDG uptake after CRT for NSCLC and the incidence and severity of subsequent RP, graded according to the CTCAE v3. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="89" pm="."><plain>We further found that higher lung FDG uptake variables during the first 1–3 months after treatment predicted the subsequent development of grade ≥2 RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="90" pm="."><plain>We also defined optimal cut-off values for the FDG uptake variables that corresponded to the risk of CTCAE grade 2–4 RP. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0065"><text><SENT sid="91" pm="."><plain>Our results confirmed that the intensity of FDG uptake on PET can be used to objectively grade established pneumonitis and perhaps to identify patients at higher risk of developing high-grade pneumonitis [12], [13]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="92" pm="."><plain>In another study of 101 patients with esophageal cancer [14], the authors found that higher mean lung doses were associated with greater risk of pneumonitis, and another variable, “pulmonary metabolic radiation response,” was also associated with increased risk of pneumonitis. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="93" pm="."><plain>Our data demonstrated that lung SUVmax, SUVpeak, and SUVmean, i.e., the intensity of FDG uptake in pulmonary tissue after CRT, correlated with the incidence and severity of RP at 1–6 months after treatment, which is consistent with previous reports [12], [13], [15]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="94" pm="."><plain>Although GLG did not correlate with RP at 4–6 months after treatment in our cross-sectional analysis, it did correlate with RP at 1–6 months after treatment in our longitudinal analysis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0070"><text><SENT sid="95" pm="."><plain>In another study of 20 patients with stage III NSCLC who had undergone FDG PET/CT imaging before and after thoracic irradiation [4], the authors suggested that lung SUVmean and GLG after treatment were potentially useful biomarkers for quantifying lung inflammation. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="96" pm="."><plain>A potential drawback of using SUVmax as a biomarker is that the reported values may reflect the presence of only one or a few “hot” pixels [16]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="97" pm="."><plain>By contrast, SUVpeak measurements (a circular volume of a fixed diameter [e.g., 1 cm] in the hottest area) are more reproducible, because they reflect the mean value of a larger number of pixels that are directly involved in and surrounding the “hottest” (highest-uptake) area. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="98" pm="."><plain>Thus SUVmean may be similar to SUVmax in terms of representing the area of highest metabolism, but it avoids the statistical fluctuations of SUVmax by incorporating larger numbers of pixels within the hottest tumor area [17]. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0075"><text><SENT sid="99" pm="."><plain>The greatest strength of our study is our analysis of serial FDG PET scans obtained from the beginning of treatment until 12 months after treatment and our ability to correlate FDG uptake variables with RP severity (graded by CTCAE v3). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="100" pm="."><plain>Our longitudinal analysis indicated that SUVmax, SUVpeak, SUVmean, and GLG all showed similar trends from the completion of treatment to 12 months later (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="101" pm="."><plain>Patients with CTCAE RP grade 2–3 experienced detrimental symptoms and had higher values of all FDG PET variables within the first 6 months after treatment relative to those with grade 0–1 RP, but this association was not observed past the sixth month after treatment (Fig. 2). </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0080"><text><SENT sid="102" pm="."><plain>Our results are consistent with clinical findings on the development of RP, which in its most severe forms is characterized on imaging by an acute exudative phase and a chronic fibrosis phase [18], [19]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="103" pm="."><plain>The former usually occurs within the first 6 months after treatment and the latter afterward [20]. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="104" pm="."><plain>Radiation fibrosis, which occurs &gt;6 months after radiotherapy, may cause less FDG uptake than the acute/exudative inflammation during the first few months. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="105" pm="."><plain>Thus FDG PET may be more valuable for predicting RP within the first 6 months after treatment rather than afterward. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0085"><text><SENT sid="106" pm="."><plain>Further, the association of FDG uptake variables with RP grade from our logistic regression models (Table 3) suggests that the SUVmax, SUVpeak, SUVmean, and GLG values for a specific patient soon after treatment could reflect the likelihood of that patient subsequently developing clinically significant RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="107" pm="."><plain>To the best of our knowledge, no studies have evaluated using FDG PET after treatment to predict the subsequent development of RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="108" pm="."><plain>Several other studies have attempted to identify predictors of RP from images obtained before treatment; in one such study, a retrospective analysis of 100 patients who had FDG PET/CT images available before treatment [9], pretreatment pulmonary FDG uptake, quantified by SUV95, could predict clinician-rated RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="109" pm="."><plain>However, the SUVmean, SUVmax, SUVpeak, and GLG as reported here are easier to measure than SUV95, and using the proposed cut-off values (taken from median data) of SUVmax ≥4.54, SUVpeak ≥3.69, SUVmean ≥0.78, and GLG ≥2295 after treatment could be useful for identifying patients who may be at higher risk of subsequent development of severe lung toxicity and thus may require more intensive management of RP or perhaps prophylaxis. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0090"><text><SENT sid="110" pm="."><plain>This study did have some limitations. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="111" pm="."><plain>First, although FDG-PET scans to assess and predict the development of RP were a secondary endpoint in the clinical trial, and the scans were obtained prospectively according to the protocol for that trial, there were some missing data in some of the time points. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="112" pm="."><plain>Second, FDG uptake can be affected by several kinds of factors including injection time, body weight, the decision to order imaging based on RP-related symptoms, and available scanning time. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="113" pm="."><plain>Third, not every patient was evaluated at each period, and so the numbers of patients in each time interval varied. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="114" pm="."><plain>However, 83% patients in this study had at least 2 FDG PET scans, and 50% patients had 3 or more FDG PET scans. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="115" pm="."><plain>For the patients with 4 FDG PET scans, we obtained both cross-sectional and longitudinal correlations between CTCAE grade and PET variables and got the same results. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="116" pm="."><plain>Our power analyses indicated that having power of 80% to detect an effect size of 0.78 [(µ2 − µ1)/σ] at 4 time points, as shown in the SUVmean analysis, with correlation of the repeated measures of 0.487, our study needed only 16 patients for each group, and therefore our sample was large enough for these longitudinal analyses. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="117" pm="."><plain>Finally, although our patients were participating in a prospective randomized trial and scans were obtained prospectively, this analysis was retrospective and subject to all of the limitation of post hoc analyses. </plain></SENT>
</text></p><p id="p0095"><text><SENT sid="118" pm="."><plain>In conclusion, we have demonstrated in this study that the uptake of FDG by normal lung tissue during the first 3 months after completion of CRT correlated with the severity of RP during the first 6 months after treatment. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="119" pm="."><plain>We found that higher lung FDG uptake variables in the early intervals after treatment predicted higher-grade subsequent RP. </plain></SENT>
<SENT sid="120" pm="."><plain>Our cutoff values for FDG uptake after treatment (4.54 for SUVmax, 3.69 for SUVpeak, 0.78 for SUVmean, and 2295 for GLG) may be clinically meaningful for identifying patients at risk of developing radiation-related pneumonitis, one of the most important factors limiting radiation doses to thoracic tumors. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="COMP_INT"><sec id="s0065"><title><text><SENT sid="121" pm="."><plain>Conflicts of interest </plain></SENT>
</text></title><p id="p0100"><text><SENT sid="122" pm="."><plain>None. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></sec></SecTag></body><back><SecTag type="REF"><ref-list id="bi005"><title>References</title><ref id="b0005"><text><SENT sid="123" pm="."><plain>1ChenY.WilliamsJ.DingI.Radiation pneumonitis and early circulatory cytokine markersSemin Nucl Med1220022633 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0010"><text><SENT sid="124" pm="."><plain>2YirmibesogluE.HigginsonD.S.FaydaM.Challenges scoring radiation pneumonitis in patients irradiated for lung cancerLung Cancer76201235035322230037 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0015"><text><SENT sid="125" pm="."><plain>3KocakZ.EvansE.S.ZhouS.-M.Challenges in defining radiation pneumonitis in patients with lung cancerInt J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys62200563563815936538 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0020"><text><SENT sid="126" pm="."><plain>4AbdullaS.SalavatiA.SabouryB.BasuS.TorigianD.A.AlaviA.Quantitative assessment of global lung inflammation following radiation therapy using FDG PET/CT: a pilot studyEur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging41201435035624085504 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0025"><text><SENT sid="127" pm="."><plain>5BasuS.ChryssikosT.Moghadam-KiaS.ZhuangH.TorigianD.A.AlaviA.Positron emission tomography as a diagnostic tool in infection: present role and future possibilitiesSemin Nucl Med392009365119038599 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0030"><text><SENT sid="128" pm="."><plain>6AlaviA.GuptaN.AlberiniJ.-L.Positron emission tomography imaging in nonmalignant thoracic disordersSemin Nucl Med32200229332112524653 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0035"><text><SENT sid="129" pm="."><plain>7CastilloR.PhamN.AnsariS.Pre-radiotherapy FDG PET predicts radiation pneumonitis in lung cancerRadiat Oncol920147424625207 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0040"><text><SENT sid="130" pm="."><plain>8BasuS.ZhuangH.TorigianD.A.RosenbaumJ.ChenW.AlaviA.Functional imaging of inflammatory diseases using nuclear medicine techniquesSemin Nucl Med39200912414519187805 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0045"><text><SENT sid="131" pm="."><plain>9CastilloR.PhamN.AnsariS.Pre-radiotherapy FDG PET predicts radiation pneumonitis in lung cancerRadiat Oncol92014124382205 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0050"><text><SENT sid="132" pm="."><plain>10WahlR.L.JaceneH.KasamonY.LodgeM.A.From RECIST to PERCIST: evolving considerations for PET response criteria in solid tumorsJ Nucl Med502009122S150S19403881 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0055"><text><SENT sid="133" pm="."><plain>11YamashitaH.Kobayashi-ShibataS.TeraharaA.Research prescreening based on the presence of CT-scan abnormalities and biomarkers (KL-6 and SP-D) may reduce severe radiation pneumonitis after stereotactic radiotherapyRadiat Oncol520103220459699 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0060"><text><SENT sid="134" pm="."><plain>12HicksR.J.Mac ManusM.P.MatthewsJ.P.Early FDG-PET imaging after radical radiotherapy for non–small-cell lung cancer: inflammatory changes in normal tissues correlate with tumor response and do not confound therapeutic response evaluationInt J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys60200441241815380574 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0065"><text><SENT sid="135" pm="."><plain>13Mac ManusM.P.DingZ.HoggA.Association between pulmonary uptake of fluorodeoxyglucose detected by positron emission tomography scanning after radiation therapy for non-small-cell lung cancer and radiation pneumonitisInt J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys8020111365137120675076 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0070"><text><SENT sid="136" pm="."><plain>14HartJ.P.McCurdyM.R.EzhilM.Radiation pneumonitis: correlation of toxicity with pulmonary metabolic radiation responseInt J Radiat Oncol Biol Phys71200896797118495373 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0075"><text><SENT sid="137" pm="."><plain>15McCurdyM.R.CastilloR.MartinezJ.[18 F]-FDG uptake dose–response correlates with radiation pneumonitis in lung cancer patientsRadiother Oncol1042012525722578806 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0080"><text><SENT sid="138" pm="."><plain>16KinehanP.FletcherJ.PET/CT standardized uptake values (SUVs) in clinical practice and assessing response to therapySemin Ultrasound CT MR31201049650521147377 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0085"><text><SENT sid="139" pm="."><plain>17LodgeM.A.ChaudhryM.A.WahlR.L.Noise considerations for PET quantification using maximum and peak standardized uptake valueJ Nucl Med5320121041104722627001 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0090"><text><SENT sid="140" pm="."><plain>18ParkK.J.ChungJ.Y.ChunM.S.SuhJ.H.Radiation-induced lung disease and the impact of radiation methods on imaging featuresRadiographics202000839810682774 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0095"><text><SENT sid="141" pm="."><plain>19DavisS.D.YankelevitzD.F.HenschkeC.I.Radiation effects on the lung: clinical features, pathology, and imaging findingsAm J Roentgenol1591992115711641442375 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref><ref id="b0100"><text><SENT sid="142" pm="."><plain>20ChoiY.W.MundenR.F.ErasmusJ.J.Effects of radiation therapy on the lung: radiologic appearances and differential diagnosisRadiographics24200498599715256622 </plain></SENT>
</text></ref></ref-list></SecTag><SecTag type="SUPPL"><sec id="s0075" sec-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><title>Supplementary data</title><p id="p0115"><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0005"><caption><title>Supplementary data 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.pdf"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0010"><caption><title>Supplementary data 2</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc2.doc"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="m0015"><caption><title>Supplementary data 3</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc3.doc"/></supplementary-material></p></sec></SecTag><SecTag type="AUTH_CONT"><ack id="ak005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors extend special thanks to Christine F. Wogan for her contributions in manuscript development and editing. The research was supported in part by <funding-source id="gp005">US National Cancer Institute</funding-source> grants P01 CA021230.</p></ack></SecTag><fn-group><SecTag type="SUPPL"><fn id="s0070" fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Appendix A</label><p id="p0110"><text><SENT sid="143" pm="."><plain>Supplementary data associated with this article can be found, in the online version, at <ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1016/j.ctro.2017.04.001" id="ir005">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ctro.2017.04.001</ext-link>. </plain></SENT>
</text></p></fn></SecTag></fn-group></back></article>
