<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4051653</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">24915541</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-03256</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathology and Laboratory Medicine</subject><subj-group><subject>Pathogenesis</subject><subj-group><subject>Host-Pathogen Interactions</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Cell Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Cellular Types</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune Cells</subject><subj-group><subject>Antigen-Presenting Cells</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Immune System</subject><subj-group><subject>Innate Immune System</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Immunity</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbial Pathogens</subject><subj-group><subject>Bacterial Pathogens</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Systems Biology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intracellular Bacteria Interfere with Dendritic Cell Functions: Role of the Type I Interferon Pathway</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Intracellular Bacteria and Dendritic Cells</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names>Laurent</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Textoris</surname><given-names>Julien</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>Romain</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ben Amara</surname><given-names>Amira</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tantibhedhyangkul</surname><given-names>Wiwit</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>von Bargen</surname><given-names>Kristin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ka</surname><given-names>Mignane B.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Capo</surname><given-names>Christian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>Eric</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names>Jean-Pierre</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>Jean-Louis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique UMR 7278, IRD198, INSERM U1095, Aix-Marseille Universit&#x000e9;, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>Baylor Institute for Immunology Research, Dallas, Texas, United States of America</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<addr-line>Centre d'Immunologie de Marseille-Luminy (CIML), Aix-Marseille University, UM2, INSERM, U1104, CNRS, UMR7280, Marseille, France</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<addr-line>Department of Immunology, Faculty of Medicine, Siriraj Hospital, Mahidol University, Bangkok, Thailand</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Neyrolles</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Institut de Pharmacologie et de Biologie Structurale, France</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>jean-louis.mege@univ-amu.fr</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: EG JPG JLM. Performed the experiments: LG ABA WT KVB MBK. Analyzed the data: JT RB CC EG JPG. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: RB ABA WT KVB MBK. Wrote the paper: LG JT CC JLM.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>e99420</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 Gorvel et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Gorvel et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Dendritic cells (DCs) orchestrate host defenses against microorganisms. In infectious diseases due to intracellular bacteria, the inefficiency of the immune system to eradicate microorganisms has been attributed to the hijacking of DC functions. In this study, we selected intracellular bacterial pathogens with distinct lifestyles and explored the responses of monocyte-derived DCs (moDCs). Using lipopolysaccharide as a control, we found that <italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic>, the causative agent of scrub typhus that survives in the cytosol of target cells, induced moDC maturation, as assessed by decreased endocytosis activity, the ability to induce lymphocyte proliferation and the membrane expression of phenotypic markers. In contrast, <italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic>, the agent of Q fever, and <italic>Brucella abortus</italic>, the agent of brucellosis, both of which reside in vacuolar compartments, only partly induced the maturation of moDCs, as demonstrated by a phenotypic analysis. To analyze the mechanisms used by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> to alter moDC activation, we performed microarray and found that <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> induced a specific signature consisting of <italic>TLR4</italic>, <italic>TLR3</italic>, <italic>STAT1</italic> and interferon response genes. These genes were down-modulated in response to <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> but up-modulated in moDCs activated by lipopolysaccharide and <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>. This transcriptional alteration was associated with the defective interferon-&#x003b2; production. This study demonstrates that intracellular bacteria specifically affect moDC responses and emphasizes how <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> interfere with moDC activation and the antimicrobial immune response. We believe that comparing infection by several bacterial species may be useful for defining new pathways and biomarkers and for developing new treatment strategies.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Dendritic cells (DCs) are specialized antigen-processing and -presenting cells that act as sentinels at the interface between innate and adaptive immunity <xref rid="pone.0099420-Banchereau1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>. In peripheral tissues, DCs are considered to be immature and are characterized by a high endocytic activity, the inability to activate T-cells and the intracellular expression of major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class II molecules <xref rid="pone.0099420-Shortman1" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Palucka1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. However, encounters with microorganisms or bacterial ligands, such as lipopolysaccharide (LPS), triggers the maturation of immature DCs <xref rid="pone.0099420-Alvarez1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, a process that is associated <italic>in vivo</italic> with their migration to secondary lymphoid organs where they interact with T-cells to orchestrate adaptive immune responses <xref rid="pone.0099420-Banchereau1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Alvarez1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Thus, the prevention of DC maturation and/or migration may be a relevant strategy for intracellular bacteria to avoid efficient immune responses, as illustrated by some examples of bacterial infections. <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhimurium interferes with the migration of intestinal DCs and hinders antigen presentation via the ubiquitination and degradation of MHC class II molecules, which prevents bacterial killing <xref rid="pone.0099420-Zenk1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Wei1" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>. <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> replicates within autophagosomes and retains cytosolic MHC class II molecules; <italic>H. pylori</italic> also prevents interleukin (IL)-12 production and induces IL-10 secretion, thereby inhibiting the anti-microbial Th1 response <xref rid="pone.0099420-Andres1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Wang1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>. <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> interferes with Toll-like receptor (TLR) signaling through its binding to CD209, also known as the C-type lectin dendritic cell-specific intercellular adhesion molecule-3-grabbing non-integrin (DC-SIGN), blocking DC maturation and IL-12 production <xref rid="pone.0099420-Balboa1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Geijtenbeek1" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Additionally, <italic>Chlamydia trachomatis</italic> and <italic>C. psittaci</italic> release molecules that delay antigen presentation by MHC class II molecules <xref rid="pone.0099420-Ojcius1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>.</p><p>Unfortunately, most of these reports are based on the comparison of na&#x000ef;ve DCs and DCs stimulated by only one type of microorganism <xref rid="pone.0099420-Zenk1" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0099420-Andres1" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Balboa1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0099420-Ojcius1" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref>, and such an approach cannot identify the elements common to microorganisms sharing cellular targets and the relative level of DC impairment. Therefore, we selected four intracellular bacteria responsible for infectious diseases in humans and that exhibit distinct lifestyles within target cells. These four bacteria, namely, <italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic>, <italic>Brucella abortus</italic>, <italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic> and <italic>Tropheryma whipplei</italic>, are known to target myeloid cells and to be pathogenic for humans: <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>, the agent of scub typhus, lives in a cytosolic <xref rid="pone.0099420-Choi1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref> compartment, whereas <italic>C. burnetii</italic>, the agent of Q fever, <italic>B. abortus</italic>, the agent of brucellosis, and <italic>T. whipplei</italic>, the agent of the Whipple's disease, are found in vacuolar compartments <xref rid="pone.0099420-Barry1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0099420-Desnues1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>. <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> induces a strong inflammatory response, including the type I interferon (IFN) response, in monocytes <xref rid="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref> and macrophages <xref rid="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. It has been demonstrated <italic>in vivo</italic> that <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> is preferentially located in dermal DCs from the eschars of patients with scrub typhus <xref rid="pone.0099420-Paris1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. <italic>T. whipplei</italic> is a Gram-positive bacterium; this pathogen infects macrophages, inducing apoptosis <xref rid="pone.0099420-Gorvel1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref> and an M2 non-microbicidal profile <xref rid="pone.0099420-Desnues2" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. <italic>C. burnetii</italic>, the Gram-negative bacterium infects and resides within monocytes and macrophages. This bacterium induces an M1 inflammatory profile in monocytes and an M2 immunoregulatory profile <xref rid="pone.0099420-Benoit1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref> and also infects monocyte-derived DCs (moDCs) <italic>in vitro</italic>, appearing to prevent their maturation <xref rid="pone.0099420-Shannon1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. <italic>B. abortus</italic>, a Gram-negative bacterium, is known to infect macrophages and evade killing via the VirB type IV secretion system <xref rid="pone.0099420-Celli2" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. <italic>B. abortus</italic>, also infects DCs <xref rid="pone.0099420-Salcedo1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, and it has been shown that the bacterial btp1 protein partially inhibits the maturation of mouse bone marrow-derived DCs by inhibiting the Toll-like receptor (TLR)-2 and TLR4 pathways <xref rid="pone.0099420-Salcedo1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>.</p><p>Here, we investigate the functions of moDCs infected with four intracellular bacterial pathogens to reappraise the concept of DC activation within the context of infectious diseases. Although <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> induced moDC maturation, as did LPS, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> were less efficient. A transcriptional analysis identified an alteration of the IFN response pathway in moDCs infected with <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>, whereas this pathway was fully operative in <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>-infected moDCs. These results demonstrate that <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> both interfere with the activation of human moDCs at the level of the IFN response, thus positioning this pathway in the pathogenesis of Q fever and brucellosis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The experimental protocol was approved by the institutional animal care and use committee of Aix-Marseille University (d&#x000e9;cret N&#x000b0; 8 87&#x02013;848, October 19, 1987, Paris). Blood was obtained from the Etablissement Fran&#x000e7;ais du Sang. It is a commercial product and the Ethics Committee agreement is not required.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Bacteria</title><p>
<italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> strain Kato (CSUR R163) was propagated in L929 cells, as previously described <xref rid="pone.0099420-Choi1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. Briefly, highly infected cells were sonicated, or lysed using glass beads for <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>, and centrifuged at 500&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 10 minutes to remove the cell debris. The supernatants were collected and centrifuged at 10,000&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 10 minutes to pellet the bacteria. The live bacteria were quantified using infected cell-counting units. <italic>C. burnetii</italic> organisms (RSA493 Nile Mile strain) were obtained by passage in BALB/c mice and culture in L929 cells. The concentration of organisms was determined by immunofluorescence using specific antibodies (Abs) and/or PCR using known concentrations of bacterial DNA. The quantification of organisms was performed as previously described <xref rid="pone.0099420-Barry1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. Bacterial viability was assessed using the LIVE/DEAD BacLight bacterial viability kit (Invitrogen, Cergy Pontoise, France) <xref rid="pone.0099420-BenAmara1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. <italic>B. abortus</italic> strain 2308 was grown on tryptic soy agar (Sigma-Aldrich, Saint-Quentin Fallavier, France) at 37&#x000b0;C for 4&#x02013;5 days, as previously described <xref rid="pone.0099420-PizarroCerd1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. The Twist-Marseille (CNCM I-2202) strain of <italic>Tropheryma whipplei</italic>, a bacterium known to live in macrophages, was cultured in HEL cells and purified as described elsewhere. The quantification of inocula was performed by measuring the percentage of infected cells by immunofluorescence, as previously described <xref rid="pone.0099420-Gorvel1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Isolation and stimulation of moDCs</title><p>Blood from healthy donors was obtained from the Etablissement Fran&#x000e7;ais du Sang. Peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) from buffy coats were recovered from the Ficoll-Hypaque interface after centrifugation at 700&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 20 minutes. Monocytes and T-lymphocytes were isolated from PBMCs using magnetic beads coupled to Abs specific for CD14 and CD3, respectively, as described by the manufacturer (Miltenyi Biotec, Paris, France). The purity of the monocyte and T-cell preparations was assessed by flow cytometry and was greater than 98%. The monocytes were then incubated in RPMI 1640 containing 20 mM HEPES, 2 mM glutamine, 10% fetal calf serum (FCS) (Invitrogen), 0.1 ng/mL IL-4 and 1 ng/mL granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor (GM-CSF) (R&#x00026;D Systems, Lille, France) for 7 days to obtain moDCs. The T-lymphocytes were frozen in a medium containing 10% dimethylsulfoxide. The moDCs were stimulated by 100 ng/mL <italic>Escherichia coli</italic> LPS (Sigma-Aldrich) or 20 bacterial cells per moDC. For the microarray experiments, 300 <italic>B. abortus</italic> cells per moDC were used to maximize the infection of moDCs. In some experiments, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> LPS, kindly provided by Dr. R. Toman) <xref rid="pone.0099420-Barry1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> LPS <xref rid="pone.0099420-Martirosyan1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref> were used at 1 &#x000b5;g/mL.</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Functional activity of moDCs</title><p>The endocytic activity of moDCs was examined by measuring the uptake of fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-coupled albumin. moDCs were cultured in 6-well plates (10<sup>6</sup> cells per well) in RPMI 1640 containing 10% FCS and stimulated with pathogens, or LPS as a control of maturation, for 24 hours at 37&#x000b0;C. After washing in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), the moDCs were incubated with 20 &#x000b5;g/mL FITC-coupled albumin (Invitrogen) for 1 hour; the moDCs were then washed, scraped and fixed in 3% paraformaldehyde (PFA) for 15 minutes. The cell fluorescence was analyzed by flow cytometry using the FACS Canto II flow cytometer (BD Biosciences, Le Pont de Claix, France). The mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) was recorded, and the results are expressed relative to the fluorescence of unstimulated DCs.</p><p>The ability of moDCs to induce T-cell proliferation was investigated as follows. moDCs (2&#x000d7;10<sup>5</sup>/mL) were cultured in 12-well plates and stimulated with bacteria or LPS for 24 hours. Autologous T-lymphocytes (10<sup>6</sup> cells/mL) were labeled in 500 &#x000b5;L of PBS containing 10% of bovine serum albumin and 10 &#x000b5;M carboxyfluorescein diacetate succinimidyl ester (CFSE) (Invitrogen) for 15 minutes. The T-lymphocytes were co-cultured with moDCs (ratio of 5&#x02236;1) for 5 days, and the fluorescence of the T-lymphocytes was analyzed by flow cytometry. The T-lymphocyte proliferation was determined as the percentage of cells with decreased CFSE fluorescence. The results are expressed relative to the fluorescence of unstimulated moDCs.</p></sec><sec id="s2e"><title>Expression of DC maturation markers</title><p>moDCs were stimulated in 6-well plates (10<sup>6</sup> cells) in RPMI 1640 containing 10% FCS with bacterial pathogens or LPS extracted from <italic>E. coli</italic>, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> or <italic>B. abortus</italic> for 24 hours. The moDCs were scraped, centrifuged at 400&#x000d7; <italic>g</italic> for 5 minutes and incubated with conjugated with FITC-CD80, phycoerythrin (PE)-CD83, PE-CD86 and FITC-HLA-DR for 30 minutes. The moDCs were fixed with 3% PFA for 20 minutes, washed and incubated in 500 &#x000b5;L of PBS prior to the flow cytometry analysis. The fluorescence of 20,000 cells per sample was quantified using the FACS Canto II flow cytometer (BD Biosciences). The results are expressed as the fold change (FC) defined as the MFI of stimulated moDCs and the MFI of unstimulated moDCs.</p></sec><sec id="s2f"><title>Microarrays</title><p>moDCs (5&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> cells per well) were plated in 6-well plates and stimulated with bacteria (MOI of 20&#x02236;1, except for <italic>B. abortus</italic> at an MOI of 300&#x02236;1) or LPS for 6 hours, and total RNA was then extracted using the RNeasy minikit (Qiagen, Courtaboeuf, France) and DNase treatment. This study utilized the 4X44k Human Whole Genome microarrays (Agilent Technologies, Les Ulis, France), representing 44,000 probes, as recently described <xref rid="pone.0099420-BenAmara1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Reverse transcription, sample labeling and hybridization were performed according to the protocols specified by the manufacturer (One-Color Microarray-Based Gene Expression Analysis). Three samples per experimental condition were included in the analysis. The slides were scanned at a 2-&#x000b5;m resolution with a G2505C DNA microarray scanner (Agilent Technologies). The data were generated in compliance with the Minimum Information About a Microarray Experiment (MIAME) guidelines and were deposited in the Gene Expression Omnibus of the National Center for Biotechnology Information (accession number: GSE49016).</p><p>Image analysis and intra-array signal corrections were performed using Agilent Feature Extractor Software A.9.1.3. The microarray data analysis was performed using R (v.3.0.1) and the Bioconductor software suite, and the raw data were filtered and normalized using the Agi4x44PreProcess library. Unsupervised and supervised analyses were performed using hierarchical clustering and a principal component analysis (PCA) (<italic>made4</italic> library <xref rid="pone.0099420-Culhane1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref> and Linear Models for Microarray Analysis (<italic>limma</italic> library) <xref rid="pone.0099420-LpezRomero1" ref-type="bibr">[29]</xref>). Genes were considered to be differentially expressed if the False Discovery Rate (FDR) <xref rid="pone.0099420-Hochberg1" ref-type="bibr">[30]</xref> was below 0.1% and the absolute fold change (FC) was above 2.0. The core program of the moDCs induced by <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> was annotated using the DAVID annotation tool <xref rid="pone.0099420-Dennis1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref> and Kyoto Encyclopedia of Gene and Genome (KEGG) pathways <xref rid="pone.0099420-Okuda1" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The integration and rendering of the pathway-based data were performed using the library <italic>pathview</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0099420-Luo1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2g"><title>Real-time RT-PCR</title><p>The genes in the IFN pathway that were identified by the microarray as being modulated were selected and validated by quantitative real-time reverse transcriptase PCR (qRT-PCR), as previously described <xref rid="pone.0099420-BenAmara1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. In brief, reverse transcription of 150 ng of RNA was performed using an Moloney murine leukemia virus (MMLV) RT kit (Invitrogen). The first-strand cDNA was obtained using oligo(dT) primers and MMLV RT (Invitrogen), and the qPCR experiments were performed using SYBR Green Fast Master Mix (Roche Diagnostics, Meylan, France) and an ABI7900 Fast Real-Time PCR System (Life Technologies). The primers were designed using Primer3. The results were normalized to the housekeeping gene &#x003b2;-actin and are expressed as the median of fold change (FC) &#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup>, where &#x00394;&#x00394;Ct &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; (Ct<sub>Target</sub> &#x02212; Ct<sub>Actin</sub>)<sub>stimulated</sub> &#x02212; (Ct<sub>Target</sub> &#x02212; Ct<sub>Actin</sub>)<sub>unstimulated</sub>, as previously described <xref rid="pone.0099420-BenAmara2" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2h"><title>Phosphorylation of p38</title><p>moDCs were stimulated with 1 &#x000b5;g/mL <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS or pathogens for different periods. The activation of the mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) p38 was determined by immunoblotting using Abs specific for phospho-p38 (1/1000 dilution, Cell Signaling). The expression of activated p38 was quantified by densitometric scanning after normalization with structural p38. The results are expressed in relative intensities.</p></sec><sec id="s2i"><title>IFN-&#x003b2; immunoassay</title><p>moDCs (10<sup>5</sup> cells/mL) plated in 24-well plates were stimulated with pathogens or different concentrations of <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS for 16 hours, and the supernatants were centrifuged at 1000&#x000d7;<italic>g</italic> for 10 minutes and frozen at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. The Verikine Human IFN-&#x003b2; ELISA kit (R&#x00026;D Systems) was used to determine IFN-&#x003b2; production by the moDCs; the sensitivity of the kit was 3 pg/ml, and the inter- and intra-assay specificity was &#x02264; 8%.</p></sec><sec id="s2j"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The results are expressed as the means &#x000b1; SEM and were compared using Student's <italic>t</italic>-test. When the comparisons involved more than two conditions, the analysis was made with ANOVA test. <italic>P</italic> values less than 0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>
<italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> partly induce moDC maturation</title><p>We investigated the maturation of moDCs in response to the cytoplasmic bacterial pathogen <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and three vacuolar bacteria, <italic>C. burnetii</italic>, <italic>B. abortus</italic> and <italic>T. whipplei</italic>, using three criteria: the loss of endocytosis, the ability to induce lymphocyte proliferation and the expression of CD83. First, the endocytosis activity of the moDCs stimulated with <italic>T. whipplei</italic> was not different (80% &#x000b1; 8%) from that of unstimulated cells (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1A</bold>
<bold>, a and f</bold>
</xref>). In contrast, the endocytosis activity of the moDCs stimulated with <italic>B. abortus C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> was dramatically reduced compared to the control moDCs (21% &#x000b1; 3%, 18% &#x000b1; 2% and 17% &#x000b1; 5%, respectively, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1A</bold>
<bold>, b&#x02013;d and f</bold>
</xref>). Note that the endocytosis activity of the moDCs stimulated with <italic>B. abortus</italic>, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> was similar to that observed in moDCs stimulated with <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS (18% &#x000b1; 2%, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1</bold>
<bold>, e and f</bold>
</xref>). Second, the ability of moDCs to induce proliferation of autologous T-cells after moDC infection was assessed by flow cytometry. We found that <italic>T. whipplei</italic> was unable to affect T-cell proliferation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1B</bold>
<bold>, a and f</bold>
</xref>), as recorded by CFSE fluorescence. In contrast, <italic>B. abortus</italic>, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> induced a significant T-cell proliferation compared to the unstimulated moDCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1B</bold>
<bold>, b, c, d and f</bold>
</xref>): T-cell proliferation was similar to that observed in LPS-stimulated moDCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1B</bold>
<bold>, e and f</bold>
</xref>). Third, we found that the measurement of CD83 expression was more discriminative than the two other features of moDC maturation. <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> induced a strong CD83 expression (when compared to the unstimulated condition, the FC of MFI values was &#x0003e;80) that was similar to that induced by LPS (MFI FC&#x0003e;75). In contrast, CD83 was only weakly expressed in the <italic>C. burnetii</italic>-stimulated moDCs (MFI FC&#x0003c;10) and was absent in the moDCs stimulated by <italic>B. abortu</italic>s or <italic>T. whipplei</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g001">
<bold>Figure 1C</bold>
<bold>, a and b</bold>
</xref>). Taken together, these results demonstrate that <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> was fully efficient to induce the maturation of moDCs whereas <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> partly induce moDC maturation.</p><fig id="pone-0099420-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Functional study of moDC maturation.</title><p>
<bold>A</bold>, moDCs were stimulated with <italic>T. whipplei</italic> (a), <italic>B. abortus</italic> (b), <italic>C. burnetii</italic> (c), <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> (d) or <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS (e) for 24 hours and then incubated with FITC-albumin (1 mg/mL) for 1 hour. The fluorescence intensities of unstimulated moDCs and stimulated moDCs were determined by flow cytometry. The results are expressed as the ratio of stimulated moDC fluorescence over unstimulated moDC fluorescence (f). They represent the mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments. ***p&#x0003c;0.001 represents the comparison of stimulated moDCs vs unstimulated DCs using Student's t-test. <bold>B</bold>, moDCs stimulated with <italic>T. whipplei</italic> (a), <italic>B. abortus</italic> (b), <italic>C. burnetii</italic> (c), <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> (d) or <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS (e) were co-cultured with CFSE-labeled autologous T-lymphocytes for 5 days. The gating strategy used to determine lymphocyte proliferation is shown for each stimulation (a&#x02013;e). The results are expressed as the percentage of new T-cells (cells with decreased fluorescence intensity) in the total T-cell population (f). They represent the mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments. **p&#x0003c;0.02 represents the comparison of stimulated moDCs vs unstimulated DCs using Student's t-test. <bold>C</bold>, The membrane expression of CD83 by moDCs incubated with bacterial pathogens or LPS for 24 hours was determined by flow cytometry using PE-coupled anti-CD83 Abs (a). The histograms are representative of three different experiments. The FC of MFI values after stimulation was compared to unstimulated condition (b). *p&#x0003c;0.03 represents the comparison of stimulated moDCs vs unstimulated DCs using Student's t-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099420.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>
<italic>B. abortus</italic> and <italic>C. burnetii</italic> did not share the same ability to activate moDCs</title><p>As the expression of CD83 was differently affected by pathogens, we addressed whether these bacteria affected other features of moDC maturation, including the membrane expression of such costimulation molecules as CD80 and CD86 and that of HLA-DR, a MHC class II molecule. In agreement with its ability to induce the maturation of moDCs, we found that <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> markedly increased the expression of CD80 (MFI FC of 10), CD86 (MFI FC of 10) and HLA-DR (MFI FC of 12), as did LPS. In contrast, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> only slightly affected the membrane expression of CD80 (MFI FC of 5), CD86 (MFI FC of 8) and HLA-DR (MFI FC of 8); <italic>B. abortus</italic> also poorly affected the expression of CD80 (MFI FC of 2) and CD86 (MFI FC of 4) but not that of HLA-DR. It should be noted that <italic>T. whipplei</italic> had a limited effect on the expression of CD80, CD86 and HLA-DR (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g002">
<bold>Figure 2</bold>
</xref>). Taken together, these results emphasize the profound deficiency of <italic>B. abortus</italic>-stimulated moDCs and the relative alteration of <italic>C. burnetii</italic>-stimulated moDCs to express activation markers.</p><fig id="pone-0099420-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Phenotypic study of moDC maturation.</title><p>moDCs were stimulated with bacterial pathogens or <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS for 24 hours. The cells were then incubated with FITC-coupled anti-CD80 (A), PE-coupled anti-CD86 (B) and FITC-coupled anti-HLA-DR (C) Abs for 30 minutes and analyzed by flow cytometry. The histograms are representative of three different experiments. The bar charts represent the MFI FC values of stimulated moDCs compared with unstimulated moDCs. *p&#x0003c;h0.05.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099420.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Microarray analysis reveals specific responses to intracellular bacteria</title><p>We used a systems biology approach to investigate the mechanisms leading to the different patterns of activation in response to LPS, <italic>C. burnetii</italic>, <italic>B. abortus</italic> and <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and found that the stimulated moDCs were present in a cluster that was different from that of the unstimulated moDCs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g003">
<bold>Figure 3A</bold>
</xref>), with 3,610 modulated probes (2,609 distinct genes). We removed <italic>T. whipplei</italic>-stimulated moDCs from the analysis because we were unable to identify a transcriptional signature that was not different from background analysis. Hierarchical clustering and PCA also discriminated the global transcriptional signature of each bacterium; note that the global signatures induced by <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and LPS were largely different from those induced by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g003">
<bold>Figure 3B</bold>
</xref>). Using Venn diagrams, we identified a core response to LPS and pathogens: this core response included 62 genes (55 up-modulated and 7 down-modulated). We also identified specific signatures for LPS and each bacterium (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g003">
<bold>Figure 3C and 3D</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0099420-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Transcriptional program of stimulated moDCs.</title><p>moDCs were stimulated with <italic>B. abortus</italic>, <italic>C. burnetii</italic>, <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> or <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS for 6 hours. RNA was extracted, and a microarray was performed. <bold>A</bold>, A heatmap representation of the 3,610 modulated probes in stimulated moDCs compared to unstimulated moDCs (NS). The probes are shown in the rows and the samples in the columns. The expression levels are color coded from blue to red. <bold>B</bold>, Graphical representation of the samples based on the correspondence analysis of the modulated probes. The samples are colored according to the stimulus. <bold>C</bold>&#x02013;<bold>D</bold>, Venn diagrams highlighting the core and specific signatures induced in moDCs stimulated with LPS and pathogens, showing up-modulated probes (C) and down-modulated probes (D). <bold>E</bold>, Summary of the pathways in moDCs modulated by intracellular bacteria. Ba: <italic>B. abortus</italic>; Cb: <italic>C. burnetii</italic>; Ot: <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099420.g003"/></fig><p>We then analyzed the gene pathways stimulated by LPS and bacterial pathogens. Among the 2,609 genes modulated, we found that 469 genes (20%) were implicated in several canonical immune response pathways (extracted from the KEGG database, <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0099420-t001">
<bold>Table 1</bold>
</xref>), such as recognition pathways (the TLR signaling pathway, NOD-like signaling pathway, RIG-I-like signaling pathway and cytosolic DNA-sensing pathway), signal processing (the Jak-STAT and MAPK signaling pathways) or functions (cytokine-cytokine receptor interaction, chemokine signaling pathway and apoptosis) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g003">
<bold>Figure 3E</bold>
</xref>). The analysis of each pathway revealed numerous differences, which were specific for each bacterium (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099420.s004">Results S1</xref></bold>). Taken together, these results showed that, in addition to a core program related to the immune response, each microorganism is able to specifically modulate this response.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0099420-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>KEGG pathways identified in stimulated moDCs.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0099420-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0099420.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KEGG pathway name (#ID)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of genes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corrected <italic>P</italic> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytokine-cytokine receptor interaction (#04060)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;18</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jak-STAT signaling pathway (#04630)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.0&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RIG-I-like receptor signaling pathway (#04622)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.5&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NOD-like receptor signaling pathway (#04621)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.5&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cytosolic DNA-sensing pathway (#04623)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.3&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chemokine signaling pathway (#04062)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Toll-like receptor signaling pathway (#04620)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.5&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Apoptosis (#04210)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.8&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P53 signaling pathway (#04115)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.8&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAPK signaling pathway (#04010)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.3&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Focal adhesion (#04510)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.4&#x000d7;10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>
</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>moDCs were stimulated with <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS or bacterial pathogens for 6 hours. RNAs were extracted, and microarrays were performed. The modulated genes were analyzed using the KEGG database. The KEGG pathways, the number of modulated genes and <italic>P</italic> values are shown.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>
<italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> interfere with the type I IFN response pathway</title><p>Although each microorganism elicited a specific signature in moDCs, the <italic>C. burnetii</italic>- and <italic>B. abortus</italic>-stimulated responses were clearly distinct from the <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>- and LPS-stimulated responses, suggesting major differences between those agonists that induced full maturation and the others. By selecting the genes that were up-modulated by LPS and <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and down-modulated by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>, we identified a series of genes implicated in apoptosis regulation, innate immune response and type I IFN &#x0201c;antiviral&#x0201d; response (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0099420-t002">
<bold>Table 2</bold>
</xref>). A set of genes involved in the IFN pathway and that were down-modulated in response to <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> was confirmed by qRT-PCR (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099420.s002">Table S1</xref></bold>). In addition, a comparison of the KEGG &#x0201c;Influenza&#x0201d; pathway (which summarizes the main modules of the type I IFN response pathway) in the stimulated moDCs highlighted three nodes that were down-modulated by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g004">
<bold>Figure 4</bold>
</xref>), corresponding to the genes encoding TLR3/TLR4, the transcription factor Stat1 and such antiviral response genes as <italic>MX1, MX2, OAS1, IFI44</italic> and <italic>ADAR</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0099420-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.g004</object-id><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Activation of the type I IFN response pathway by bacteria.</title><p>The KEGG pathway hsa05164 of influenza response was modified to represent the type I IFN response. The genes depicted on this pathway are colored according to the modulation induced by <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS (A), <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> (B), <italic>C. burnetii</italic> (C) or <italic>B. abortus</italic> (D).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099420.g004"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0099420-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Genes differentially expressed by bacterial pathogens.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0099420-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0099420.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Symbol</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>C. burnetii</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. abortus</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">LPS</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ATP10A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BRIP1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.85</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CCL2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">FAM59A</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.89</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GMPR</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>HERC5</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HSH2D</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>IFI44</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>MX1</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>MX2</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR52K3P</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P2RY6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SAMD9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SH2D1B</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SIX1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TRIL</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<underline>USP18</underline>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XAF1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt102"><label/><p>moDCs were stimulated with bacterial pathogens or <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS for 6 hours. RNAs were extracted, and microarrays were performed. The genes that were up-modulated by <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and LPS and down-modulated by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> are listed in alphabetic order. The values of FC are presented and IFN response genes are underlined.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The transcriptional alterations in the moDCs stimulated by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> were associated with defective activation of the MAPK p38. Hence, the phosphorylation of p38, 15 and 30 minutes after <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> stimulation, was lower that observed in the moDCs stimulated with LPS or <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g005">
<bold>Figure 5</bold>
</xref>
<bold>, A and B</bold>). The transcriptional alterations induced by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> were also associated with defective IFN-&#x003b2; production Indeed, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> was unable to induce the release of IFN-&#x003b2;, a type I IFN, from the moDCs. Similarly, <italic>B. abortus</italic>-stimulated moDCs released low levels of IFN-&#x003b2;. In contrast, <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> induced the release of high levels of IFN-&#x003b2; from the moDCs. LPS, which induces type I IFN genes, induced the release of IFN-&#x003b2; in a dose-dependent manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0099420-g005">
<bold>Figure 5C</bold>
</xref>). These results demonstrate that the defective maturation of moDCs in response to <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> is associated with defective gene expression within the type I IFN pathway, defective p38 activation and defective IFN-&#x003b2; production.</p><fig id="pone-0099420-g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0099420.g005</object-id><label>Figure 5</label><caption><title>p38 phosphorylation and IFN-&#x003b2; release.</title><p>
<bold>A</bold>, moDCs were stimulated with bacterial pathogens or <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS for different durations, ranging from 15 minutes to 4 hours, and immunoblotting was used to assess MAPK p38 phosphorylation. <bold>B</bold>, Densitometric scanning was used to quantify phosphorylation changes of p38 and the results are the mean &#x000b1; SD of three experiments. <bold>C</bold>, moDCs were stimulated with bacterial pathogens or different concentrations of LPS for 16 hours. The release of IFN-&#x003b2; by moDCs was determined by ELISA. The results are expressed in pg/mL and represent the mean &#x000b1; SD of three independent experiments.*p&#x0003c;0.03.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0099420.g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study addressed how intracellular bacteria responsible for human infectious diseases affect the response of moDCs, thereby creating an immune environment that is favorable to bacterial survival. We selected two intraphagosomal bacteria, <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>, and one intracytosolic microorganism, <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>. Although each pathogen has specificity in metabolism, virulence and replication rate, these bacteria share the ability to target myeloid cells <xref rid="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Paris1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Benoit1" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Shannon1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Salcedo1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>; the former two cause infectious diseases with a risk of chronic evolution, whereas the latter is responsible for acute infections. Such observations suggest that the immune mechanisms, including DC activation, induced by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> are different from those induced by <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>. The combined use of functional tests of maturation and the measurement of activation marker membrane expression revealed that the responses of moDCs to <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> were similar to those induced by LPS, corresponding to DC maturation. It has also been reported that <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> activates moDCs and drives the proliferation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cells <xref rid="pone.0099420-Choi1" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Paris1" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>. The combined approach in the present study showed that <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> partly induce the maturation of moDCs, with <italic>B. abortus</italic> being less efficient than <italic>C. burnetii</italic>. These findings are consistent with previous reports showing that <italic>C. burnetii</italic> partially impairs the maturation of moDCs <xref rid="pone.0099420-Shannon1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref> and that <italic>B. abortus</italic> inhibits DC maturation in a murine model of infection <xref rid="pone.0099420-Salcedo1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>. Our results demonstrate that the use of whole functional tests, including the loss of endocytic activity and T-cell proliferation, were not sufficiently accurate to discriminate among the responses of DCs to bacteria. These assays might also lead to erroneous conclusions, as <italic>O. tsutsugamushi, C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> share the ability to induce the loss of endocytosis and T-cell proliferation. The discrepancy between the expression of membrane antigens and functional tests of maturation has been described in <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> infection. Indeed, the subsets of DCs that are infected at high frequency poorly stimulate <italic>M. tuberculosis</italic> antigen-specific CD4<sup>+</sup> T-cells, despite the expression of surface MHC class II molecules and costimulatory molecules <xref rid="pone.0099420-Wolf1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref>. Alternatively, the production of IL-2 and IL-15 by DCs in response to infectious stimuli may be involved in T-cell proliferation <xref rid="pone.0099420-Feau1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Granucci1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. We analyzed the microarray data from stimulated moDCs and found that the <italic>IL15</italic> gene was overexpressed in response to <italic>C. burnetii, O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and LPS. Similarly, the <italic>IL2</italic> gene was upmodulated in response to <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and LPS while the <italic>IL2RA</italic> gene was overexpressed in response to <italic>O. tsutsugamushi, C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099420.s003">Table S2</xref></bold>). These findings are consistent with the hypothesis that the expression of IL-2 and IL-15 pathways is sufficient to induce T-cell proliferation whereas the modulation of membrane molecules requires additional signals.</p><p>As our phenotypic assays identified defective moDC maturation in response to <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>, we used a high-throughput transcriptional approach to characterize the underlying mechanisms. We used the <italic>E. coli</italic> LPS signature and the signature induced by <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> as positive controls of maturation. The absence of LPS from the cell wall of <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> rules out wall LPS as stimulating <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>-induced full DC maturation, which is emphasized by the failure of LPS-expressing <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> to fully induce the maturation of DCs. Nevertheless, the LPS of these bacteria are atypical. <italic>C. burnetii</italic> LPS is poorly endotoxinic and exhibits a specific molecular composition with two unusual sugars: virenose and dihydroxystreptose <xref rid="pone.0099420-Barry1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. The treatment of moDCs with <italic>C. burnetii</italic> LPS up-regulated the expression of CD86 and HLA-DR but not that of CD80 and CD83, suggesting that bacterial LPS contributes to the phenotype of <italic>C. burnetii</italic>-stimulated DCs (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099420.s001">Figure S1</xref></bold>). However, these results do not support the hypothesis of Shannon <italic>et al.</italic> that <italic>C. burnetii</italic> LPS interferes with <italic>C. burnetii</italic>-activated DCs <xref rid="pone.0099420-Shannon1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. We found that <italic>B. abortus</italic> LPS induced an moDC phenotype similar to that induced by the entire bacterium, as only CD80 and CD86 were expressed at the moDC membrane (<bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0099420.s001">Figure S1</xref></bold>), suggesting that <italic>B. abortus</italic> LPS is unable to fully activate moDCs. Indeed, <italic>B. abortus</italic> LPS might act along with the btp1 protein <xref rid="pone.0099420-Salcedo1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> to prevent the proper DC-driven immune response. Here, we confirm that the LPSs from <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> are not sufficient to activate moDC responses.</p><p>We focused on the moDC responses induced by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>. The activation of the MAPK p38 was defective in response to <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>. The defective activation of p38 by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> has been reported in macrophages and related to the escape of bacteria to degradative compartments <xref rid="pone.0099420-Barry1" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>. The modulation of p38 by <italic>Brucella</italic> sp. is debated. The LPS O chain from <italic>Brucella</italic> sp. restricts the activation of p38 <xref rid="pone.0099420-JimenezdeBaquies1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref> and the intracellular replication of <italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> is mainly dependent of p38 <xref rid="pone.0099420-Demitrakopoulos1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. In contrast, <italic>B. abortus</italic> activates p38 in murine astrocytes <xref rid="pone.0099420-Miraglia1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>. The transcriptional signature induced by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> compared to that induced by <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> and LPS was composed of a series of down-modulated genes. The comparison of the KEGG &#x0201c;Influenza&#x0201d; response pathway led to the identification of nodes targeted by <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> to down-modulate <italic>TLR4</italic>/<italic>TLR3</italic>, <italic>STAT1</italic> and type I IFN-responsive genes. We recently explored the transcriptional datasets that are deposited in public repertories, such as the Gene Expression Omnibus, and we focused the main transductional pathways that lead to the type I IFN response during bacterial infections. We found that the type I IFN pattern induced by vacuolar bacteria is completely different from the signatures induced by viruses and cytosolic bacteria <xref rid="pone.0099420-Textoris1" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>. The IFN response pathway has been described in transcriptomics analysis of tuberculosis in which it remains silent in latent tuberculosis and was fully active in patients with active tuberculosis <xref rid="pone.0099420-Berry1" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. As <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> share the ability to cause a chronic evolution of disease and bacterial persistence, such a strategy may be operative for their persistence. <italic>C. burnetii</italic> was unable to stimulate the release of IFN-&#x003b2;, and <italic>B. abortus</italic> only induced the release of low levels of IFN-&#x003b2; compared to <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>. It has been recently demonstrated that <italic>B. abortus</italic> induced the production of IFN-&#x003b2; by moDCs in mice <xref rid="pone.0099420-deAlmeida1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>. The recognition of <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> by cytosolic sensors and the activation of the type I IFN signaling pathway <xref rid="pone.0099420-Boldrick1" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref> may be related to the ability of <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> to escape phagosomes and enter the cytosol <xref rid="pone.0099420-Ge1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, as found for <italic>Francisella tularensis</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0099420-BarHaim1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref> and <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0099420-Edelson1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Tam1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>. IFN-&#x003b2; was also reported to be produced by monocytes and macrophages in response to <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul1" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul2" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, suggesting that the intracellular lifestyle of <italic>O. tsutsugamushi</italic> is critical for the production of type I IFN.</p><p>In conclusion, we showed that intracellular bacteria, such as <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic>, are able to modulate the maturation of moDCs. The classical functional tests of DC maturation are not sufficiently accurate to detect impaired DC responses. However, using a systems biology approach, we found that <italic>C. burnetii</italic> and <italic>B. abortus</italic> dampen the type I IFN response. This effect may lead to inefficient immune response and bacterial persistence within the host, conferring a critical role for the type I IFN pathway in antibacterial immunity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0099420.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Phenotypic study of moDC maturation.</bold> moDCs were stimulated with <italic>C. burnetii</italic>-LPS, <italic>B. abortus</italic>-LPS or <italic>E. coli</italic>-LPS for 24 hours. The cells were then incubated with FITC-coupled anti-CD80, PE-coupled anti-CD83, PE-coupled anti-CD86 and FITC-coupled anti-HLA-DR Abs for 30 minutes and analyzed by flow cytometry. The curves are representative of three different experiments.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0099420.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0099420.s002"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>qRT-PCR validation of genes involved in the IFN pathway.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0099420.s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0099420.s003"><label>Table S2</label><caption><p>
<bold>IL-15 and IL-12-associated genes.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0099420.s003.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0099420.s004"><label>Results S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Pathway analysis of transcriptional modulation of moDC by intracellular bacteria.</bold>
</p><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0099420.s004.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to Catherine L&#x000e9;polard for her technical expertise.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0099420-Banchereau1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Dendritic cells and the control of immunity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>392</volume>: <fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>252</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9521319</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Shortman1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shortman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Mouse and human dendritic cell subtypes</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>161</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11913066</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Palucka1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Palucka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banchereau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mellman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Designing vaccines based on biology of human dendritic cell subsets</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>478</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21029958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Alvarez1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vollmann</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Andrian</surname><given-names>UH</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Mechanisms and consequences of dendritic cell migration</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>325</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>342</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18799141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Zenk1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Zenk</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jantsch</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hensel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Role of <italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> lipopolysaccharide in activation of dendritic cell functions and bacterial containment</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>183</volume>: <fpage>2697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2707</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625639</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Wei1"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Salmonella enterica</italic> serovar Typhi plasmid impairs dendritic cell responses to infection</article-title>. <source>Curr Microbiol</source>
<volume>65</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>140</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22569891</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Andres1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HMA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rhen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maeurer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> defines local immune response through interaction with dendritic cells</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol Med Microbiol</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21175878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Wang1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>When <italic>Helicobacter pylori</italic> invades and replicates in the cells</article-title>. <source>Autophagy</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>540</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>542</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19270492</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Balboa1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Balboa</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yokobori</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schierloh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Geffner</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> impairs dendritic cell response by altering CD1b, DC-SIGN and MR profile</article-title>. <source>Immunol Cell Biol</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20212510</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Geijtenbeek1"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Geijtenbeek</surname><given-names>TBH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Van Vliet</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Koppel</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanchez-Hernandez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vandenbroucke-Grauls</surname><given-names>CMJE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Mycobacteria</italic> target DC-SIGN to suppress dendritic cell function</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>197</volume>: <fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12515809</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Ojcius1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ojcius</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bravo de Alba</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kanellopoulos</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hawkins</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Internalization of <italic>Chlamydia</italic> by dendritic cells and stimulation of <italic>Chlamydia</italic>-specific T cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>160</volume>: <fpage>1297</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1303</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9570547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Choi1"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cheong</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic> subverts dendritic cell functions by escaping from autophagy and impairing their migration</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e1981</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23301113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Barry1"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Barry</surname><given-names>AO</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boucherit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mottola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vadovic</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trouplin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Impaired stimulation of p38&#x003b1;-MAPK/Vps41-HOPS by LPS from pathogenic <italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic> prevents trafficking to microbicidal phagolysosomes</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>751</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>763</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23245320</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Celli1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Celli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Surviving inside a macrophage: the many ways of <italic>Brucella</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Res Microbiol</source>
<volume>157</volume>: <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364608</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Desnues1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Desnues</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>IL-16 is critical for <italic>Tropheryma whipplei</italic> replication in Whipple's disease</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>175</volume>: <fpage>4575</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4582</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16177102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul1"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tantibhedhyangkul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prachason</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Waywa</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>El Filali</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic> stimulates an original gene expression program in monocytes: relationship with gene expression in patients with scrub typhus</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1028</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21610853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Tantibhedhyangkul2"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tantibhedhyangkul</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ben Amara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Textoris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic>, the causative agent of scrub typhus, induces an inflammatory program in human macrophages</article-title>. <source>Microb Pathog</source>
<volume>55</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23088884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Paris1"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Paris</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Phetsouvanh</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanganuchitcharnchai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jenjaroen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic> in human scrub typhus eschars shows tropism for dendritic cells and monocytes rather than endothelium</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1466</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22253938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Gorvel1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Al Moussawi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Capo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Tropheryma whipplei</italic>, the Whipple's disease bacillus, induces macrophage apoptosis through the extrinsic pathway</article-title>. <source>Cell Death Dis</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>e34</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21364641</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Desnues2"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Desnues</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lepidi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Whipple disease: intestinal infiltrating cells exhibit a transcriptional pattern of M2/alternatively activated macrophages</article-title>. <source>J Infect Dis</source>
<volume>192</volume>: <fpage>1642</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1646</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16206080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Benoit1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Benoit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barbarat</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bernard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Olive</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic>, the agent of Q fever, stimulates an atypical M2 activation program in human macrophages</article-title>. <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>1065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1070</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18350541</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Shannon1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinzen</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Virulent <italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic> does not activate human dendritic cells: role of lipopolysaccharide as a shielding molecule</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>8722</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8727</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15939879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Celli2"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Celli</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>de Chastellier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Franchini</surname><given-names>D-M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pizarro-Cerda</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Brucella</italic> evades macrophage killing via VirB-dependent sustained interactions with the endoplasmic reticulum</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>198</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>556</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12925673</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Salcedo1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Salcedo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Marchesini</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lelouard</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fugier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jolly</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Brucella</italic> control of dendritic cell maturation is dependent on the TIR-containing protein Btp1</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e21</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18266466</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-BenAmara1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ben Amara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ghigo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Le Priol</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>L&#x000e9;polard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Salcedo</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Coxiella burnetii</italic>, the agent of Q fever, replicates within trophoblasts and induces a unique transcriptional response</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e15315</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21179488</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-PizarroCerd1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Pizarro-Cerd&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#x000e9;resse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parton</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van der Goot</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sola-Landa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Brucella abortus</italic> transits through the autophagic pathway and replicates in the endoplasmic reticulum of nonprofessional phagocytes</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>5711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5724</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9826346</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Martirosyan1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Martirosyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ohne</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Degos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moriy&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Lipopolysaccharides with acylation defects potentiate TLR4 signaling and shape T cell responses</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e55117</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23390517</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Culhane1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Culhane</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thioulouse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perri&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>MADE4: an R package for multivariate analysis of gene expression data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>2789</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2790</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15797915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-LpezRomero1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Romero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Pre-processing and differential expression analysis of Agilent microRNA arrays using the AgiMicroRna Bioconductor library</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>64</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21269452</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Hochberg1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>More powerful procedures for multiple significance testing</article-title>. <source>Stat Med</source>
<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>818</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2218183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Dennis1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>G</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>, <name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hosack</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>DAVID: Database for annotation, visualization, and integrated discovery</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>P3</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12734009</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Okuda1"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Okuda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hamajima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>KEGG Atlas mapping for global analysis of metabolic pathways</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>W423</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>426</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18477636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Luo1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brouwer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Pathview: an R/Bioconductor package for pathway-based data integration and visualization</article-title>. <source>Bioinformics</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1831</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-BenAmara2"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ben Amara</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gorvel</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baulan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Derain-Court</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Buffat</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Placental macrophages are impaired in chorioamnionitis, an infectious pathology of the placenta</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>191</volume>: <fpage>5501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5514</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24163411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Wolf1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trevejo-Nu&#x000f1;ez</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kincaid</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> infects dendritic cells with high frequency and impairs their function in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>179</volume>: <fpage>2509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2519</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17675513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Feau1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Feau</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Facchinetti</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Granucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Citterio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jarrossay</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Dendritic cell-derived IL-2 production is regulated by IL-15 in humans and in mice</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<volume>105</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15353479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Granucci1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Granucci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Degli-Esposti</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ricciardi-Casragnoli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>IL-2 mediates adjuvant effect of dendritic cells</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>171</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11923103</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-JimenezdeBaquies1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jimenez de Baquies</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terraza</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dornand</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Regulation of the mitogen-activated protein kinases by <italic>Brucella</italic> spp. expressing a smooth and rough phenotype: relationship to pathogen invasiveness</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>3178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15845529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Demitrakopoulos1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Demitrakopoulos</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liopeta</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dimitracopoulos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paliogianni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>Replication of <italic>Brucella melitensis</italic> inside primary human monocytes depends on mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>450</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>460</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23628412</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Miraglia1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Miraglia</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scian</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Samartino</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barrionuevo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2013</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Brucella abortus</italic> induces TNF-&#x003b1;-dependent astroglial MMP-9 secretion through mitogen-activated protein kinases</article-title>. <source>J Neuroinflammation</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Textoris1"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Textoris</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Capo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mege</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Type I interferons and bacterial infectious diseases: new features</article-title>. <source>Recent Res Devel Immunology</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Berry1"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>MPR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McNab</surname><given-names>FW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bloch</surname><given-names>SAA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>An interferon-inducible neutrophil-driven blood transcriptional signature in human tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>466</volume>: <fpage>973</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>977</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20725040</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-deAlmeida1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>de Almeida</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carvalho</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lacerda</surname><given-names>TLS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vasconcelos</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>MyD88 and STING signaling pathways are required for IRF3-mediated IFN-&#x003b2; induction in response to <italic>Brucella abortus</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e23135</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21829705</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Boldrick1"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Boldrick</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diehn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudoit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Stereotyped and specific gene expression programs in human innate immune responses to bacteria</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>99</volume>: <fpage>972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>977</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11805339</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Ge1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rikihisa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Subversion of host cell signaling by <italic>Orientia tsutsugamushi</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Microbes Infect</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>638</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>648</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21458586</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-BarHaim1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bar-Haim</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gat</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Markel</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shafferman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Interrelationship between dendritic cell trafficking and <italic>Francisella tularensis</italic> dissemination following airway infection</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e1000211</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19023422</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Edelson1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Edelson</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name> (<year>2012</year>) <article-title>Dendritic cells in <italic>Listeria monocytogenes</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Adv Immunol</source>
<volume>113</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22244578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0099420-Tam1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wick</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Dendritic cells and immunity to <italic>Listeria</italic>: TipDCs are a new recruit</article-title>. <source>Trends Immunol</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15207498</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>