<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5670217</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">14808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-14808-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Antibiotics induce polarization of pleural macrophages to M2-like phenotype in patients with tuberculous pleuritis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Sisi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Jian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sui</surname><given-names>Liyan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Hao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Piao</surname><given-names>Qianling</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Xinglong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Dan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Liping</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Shucheng</given-names></name><address><email>shuchenghua@eyou.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-1828-0509</contrib-id><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Guangan</given-names></name><address><email>gahu@mit.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Jianzhu</given-names></name><address><email>jchen@mit.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 5735</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.64924.3d</institution-id><institution>Department of Translational Medicine, The First Hospital, Jilin University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changchun, 130061 China </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>The Infectious Disease Hospital of Changchun, Changchun, Jilin, Changchun, 130123 China </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1760 5735</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.64924.3d</institution-id><institution>Department of Respiratory Medicine, The First Hospital, Jilin University, </institution></institution-wrap>Changchun, 130021 China </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2341 2786</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.116068.8</institution-id><institution>Koch Institute for Integrative Cancer Research and Department of Biology, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 77 Massachusetts Avenue, </institution></institution-wrap>Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139 USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>3</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>14982</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Pleural macrophages play critical roles in pathogenesis of tuberculous pleuritis, but very little is known about their response to anti-tuberculosis antibiotics treatment. Here, we examined whether and how pleural macrophages change in phenotype, transcription and function following antibiotics treatment in patients with tuberculous pleuritis. Results show pro-inflammatory cytokines were down-regulated significantly post antibiotic treatment in the pleural effusions and pleural macrophages up-regulated markers characteristic of M2 macrophages such as CD163 and CD206. Differential expression analysis of transcriptomes from four paired samples before and after treatment identified 230 treatment-specific responsive genes in pleural macrophages. Functional analysis identified interferon-related pathway to be the most responsive genes and further confirmed macrophage polarization to M2-like phenotype. We further demonstrate that expression of a significant fraction of responsive genes was modulated directly by antibiotics in pleural macrophages <italic>in vitro</italic>. Our results conclude that pleural macrophages polarize from M1-like to M2-like phenotype within a mean of 3.5 days post antibiotics treatment, which is dependent on both pleural cytokine environment and direct modulatory effects of antibiotics. The treatment-specific genes could be used to study the roles of pleural macrophages in the pathogenesis of tuberculous pleuritis and to monitor the response to antibiotics treatment.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Tuberculosis (TB) is caused by infection of <italic>Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> in the lung and is a major public health problem in the world because of its prevalence and high mortality<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Around 20% of TB patients develop tuberculous pleural effusion (TPE), an accumulation of excess fluid in the pleural cavity, due to tuberculous pleuritis, i.e., inflammation of the pleura<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Tuberculous pleuritis usually presents as an acute illness with fever, cough and pleuritic chest pain, and is diagnosed by elevated levels of adenosine deaminase (ADA) and interferon-gamma (IFN&#x003b3;) in the pleural fluid<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Tuberculous pleuritis is caused by delayed type hypersensitivity responses to mycobacterial antigens in the pleural space with low bacterial burden<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. Although ~70% pleural fluid cells are T cells, pleural macrophages are also known to contribute to the pathogenesis of tuberculous pleuritis and the outcome of different clinic forms of TB<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par3">Macrophages are the first line of defense against invading microbes and mediate innate immune responses through pathogen recognition and activation of inflammatory reactions. Depending on the stimulations and microenvironment, macrophages polarize to different functional states, including the classically activated M1 and the alternatively activated M2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. The M1 phenotype is associated with secretion of large quantities of pro-inflammatory cytokines and killing of microbes. The M2 type of macrophages exhibits immunoregulatory, phagocytosis, and tissue remodeling and repair functions. In TB patients, alveolar macrophages in the lungs are directly infected by <italic>M</italic>. <italic>tuberculosis</italic>. Depending on the stage of infection and disease development, macrophages can produce either pro-inflammatory and microbicidal responses or immunosuppressive and tissue repairing responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. For example, in newly onset TB patients and during the early phase of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>tuberculosis</italic> infection, macrophages exhibit an M1-like phenotype producing pro-inflammatory cytokines and contributing to the development of TPE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">The frontline treatment of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>tuberculosis</italic> infection is a combination of four antibiotics: isoniazid, rifampicin, pyrazinamide and ethambutol (HRZE). Antibiotics treatment significantly eliminates the bacterial load and inhibits the formation of TPE. Although antibiotics are most widely known for their direct microbicidal activity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, increasing evidence suggests that many antibiotics also modulate activities of immune cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. For example, rifampicin is known to induce the expression of CD1 in human T cells and monocytes and therefore immune responses to various infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Isoniazid eliminates antigen-specific T cells by inducing apoptosis in TB animal models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>, and also regulates both adaptive and innate immune responses during its induction of liver injury<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Pyrazinamide modulates the host immune response to infection by reducing pro-inflammatory cytokines IL6 and TNF&#x003b1; production<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, and activates the mouse macrophage by inducing expression of CD80, CD86 and MHCII<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Isoniazid and pyrazinamide together robustly activate autophagy through reactive oxygen species in mycobacterial-infected murine macrophages<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>. A pertinent question is whether and how antibiotics treatment in TB patients modulates macrophage polarization and function.</p><p id="Par5">Recently, O&#x02019;Garra and colleagues have started to address this question by transcriptional profiling of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) from TB patients before and after antibiotics treatment. They report the identification of a whole-blood host-response-specific 393-transcript signature, which reflects mycobacterial infection, and a whole-blood treatment-specific 320-transcript signature for monitoring the efficiency of antibiotics treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Because total PBMCs were used, their studies did not define the contribution of specific immune cell types. Furthermore, compared to TPE, although peripheral blood is more accessible but it is farther removed from the primary site of mycobacterial infection. Whether and how antibiotics treatment in TB patients affects specific immune cell types, such as macrophages, in the proximal site of infection has not been investigated.</p><p id="Par6">In this study we have examined changes in phenotype and function of pleural macrophages in TB patients before and after antibiotics treatment by assaying their expression of surface markers, transcription profiles and phagocytosis activities. Our results show that pleural macrophages are polarized from M1-like to M2-like phenotype as early as 2 days post antibiotics treatment. A signature of 230 genes was identified to reflect the treatment-specific response in pleural macrophages. Among these genes, some were modulated by direct antibiotics treatment of purified pleural macrophages <italic>in vitro</italic>. Our study defines responses of pleural macrophages to antibiotics treatment in TB patients and raises the possibility of therapeutic efficacy of antibiotics in treating tuberculous pleuritis by modulating activities of pleural macrophages.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Pleural macrophages are polarized in response to antibiotics treatment</title><p id="Par7">We enrolled 171 patients with tuberculous pleuritis for studying the effect of antibiotics on macrophage polarization. After excluding patients with other lung diseases, HIV co-infection, or contraindications to pleural effusion puncture, 135 patients remained (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Pleural fluids were collected from 36 patients before and 2 to 10 days after HRZE treatment (paired samples). In the remaining 99 patients, pleural fluids were collected either before or after treatment only (unpaired samples). The frequency and phenotype of various immune cells in the pleural fluids were determined by flow cytometry using commonly used lymphocyte and macrophage markers (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). Overall, CD3<sup>+</sup> T cells were most abundant in the pleural fluids with a CD4<sup>+</sup> to CD8<sup>+</sup> ratio of ~3 to 1, similar to a previous report<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The proportion of macrophages in the pleural fluids varied from patients to patients with an average of 8.5% (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The frequencies of CD4<sup>+</sup> or CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells, B cells, nature killer cells (NK) and macrophages did not change significantly before and after antibiotics treatment in the paired and unpaired analysis (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). However, expression of M2 markers, including CD163 and CD206, was significantly elevated in pleural macrophages in both paired (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>) and unpaired (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>) samples following antibiotics treatment, although expression of M1 markers CD80 and CD86 were also increased slightly. The phagocytic activities of pleural macrophages to engulf fluorescent beads were decreased following antibiotics treatment with a <italic>P</italic>-value of&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.056 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>). These data suggest that pleural macrophages are polarized following antibiotics treatment in patients with tuberculous pleuritis.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Clinical characteristics of patients.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Characteristics</th><th align="left">Statistics</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Male/Female</td><td>89/46</td></tr><tr><td>Ages (years)</td><td>35.6 (17~83)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Pleural fluid</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;WBC (6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>9</sup>/L)</td><td>4.5 (0.6~23)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Mononecluear cells (%)</td><td>72.3 (39~94)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;CD4+</td><td>58.6 (29.8~82.3)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;CD8+</td><td>19.5 (6.9~34.6)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;B</td><td>5.7 (0.3~26.9)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;NK</td><td>6.3 (0.4~21.4)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Macrophages</td><td>8.5 (0.2~53.6)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Multinuclear cells (%)</td><td>27.7 (6~61)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;ADA (U/L)</td><td>84.9 (37~145)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;LDH (U/L)</td><td>782.2 (199~1462)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Protein (g/L)</td><td>52.2 (26~88)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Rivalta test</td><td>+</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2">Serum</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;ESR (mm/h)</td><td>48.7 (8~76)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;CRP (mg/L)</td><td>65.7 (19~121.8)</td></tr><tr><td>CDU</td><td>66.6 (27~123)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of surface marker expression by pleural macrophages before and after antibiotics treatment. (<bold>A</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of CD80, CD86, CD163 and CD206 expression by CD14<sup>+</sup> pleural macrophages before (BT) and after (AT) antibiotics treatment from a representative patient. Shaded histograms show cells stained with isotype control antibody. The numbers indicate percentages of cells within the gated regions. (<bold>B</bold>&#x02013;<bold>C</bold>) Aggregated data from paired samples (B, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;29) and unpaired samples (C, n&#x02009;=&#x02009;128) showing mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) of CD80, CD86 and CD163 expression and percentages of CD206<sup>+</sup> cells. P values are shown between BT and AT. (<bold>D</bold>) Comparison of phagocytosis of five paired pleural macrophage samples before and after antibiotics treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_14808_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e668"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Antibiotics inhibit pro-inflammatory cytokine production</title><p id="Par8">We measured the levels of cytokines IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL4, IL6, IL10, IL1&#x003b2;, TGF&#x003b2;, GM-CSF, IFN&#x003b1; and IFN&#x003b2; in the paired pleural fluids by ELISA. The levels of IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL6 and IL10 were significantly decreased following antibiotics treatment while the rest did not change significantly (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Intracellular IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL6 and IL10 were assayed in various cell types after <italic>in vitro</italic> stimulation with PMA plus ionomycin. Consistently, the percentages of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells positive for intracellular IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL6 and IL10 decreased and the percentages of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells positive for intracellular IFN&#x003b3; and TNF&#x003b1; also decreased (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3A</xref>, <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3B</xref>). Similarly, the percentages of non-T cells positive for intracellular TNF&#x003b1; also decreased. RT-qPCR showed that in pleural macrophages the level of IL6 and IFN&#x003b3; transcripts was significantly decreased following antibiotics treatment (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3C</xref>). In the paired samples, change in cytokine levels in pleural fluids was negative correlated with change of macrophage markers (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). For example, IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL6 and IL10 level was negatively correlated with the expression of CD80 and CD163, whereas TGF&#x003b2; and GM-CSF level was negatively correlated with CD206. Taken together, antibiotics treatment reduces cytokine levels in the pleural fluid by modulating functionality of not only T cells but also non-T cells such as macrophages.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Comparison of cytokine levels in pleural fluids from patients with tuberculous pleuritis before and after antibiotics treatment. The indicated cytokines were assayed by ELISA in pleural fluids of 28 patients. <italic>P</italic> values by paired <italic>t</italic>-test are indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_14808_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e714"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Pleural macrophages polarize to an M2-like phenotype following antibiotics treatment</title><p id="Par9">To better understand the effect of antibiotics on pleural macrophages, we determined the transcription profiles of pleural macrophages before and after HRZE treatment by RNA-Seq of four pairs of pleural macrophage samples with yielding high quality of total RNA. Based on the overall transcription profiles, principle component analysis (PCA) grouped samples before treatment together and samples after treatment together (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>), suggesting the sufficient samples to capture the treatment response. Differential expression analysis revealed that 156 genes were up-regulated and 74 genes were down-regulated significantly after antibiotics treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). The differentially expressed genes were enriched with immune regulation and stress response pathways (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref> and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>), including response to chemical stimulus (37 genes, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.91e-6), immune response (25 genes, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.97e-6), response to stress (42 genes, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.86e-5), and immunity and defense (36 genes, <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.2e-6). Regardless of the enriched category, up-regulated genes were enriched with vascular development and extracellular matrix remodeling, while down-regulated genes were enriched with interferon-mediated immunity (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Moreover, most M1 marker genes, such as <italic>IL6</italic>, <italic>IL23A</italic>, <italic>IDO</italic>, <italic>CCL8</italic> and <italic>CXCL10</italic>/11, were down-regulated whereas M2 marker genes, such as <italic>IL10</italic>, <italic>IRF4</italic>, <italic>CD163</italic>, <italic>IL4R</italic>, <italic>MRC1</italic>/2 and <italic>CCL18</italic>, were up-regulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). These results suggest that at the genome level, pleural macrophages are polarized to an M2-like phenotype following HRZE treatment.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Pleural macrophages are polarized to an M2-like phenotype by antibiotics treatment. (<bold>A</bold>) Principal component analysis of transcriptional profiles of pleural macrophages from four patients (red, orange, blue and green) before (circle) and after (triangle) antibiotics treatment. (<bold>B</bold>) Heatmap showing differentially expressed genes in four pairs of samples. (<bold>C</bold>) List of the most significantly enriched pathways of differentially expressed genes. (<bold>D</bold>) Heatmap of M1 and M2 gene expression in pleural macrophages before and after antibiotics treatment. (<bold>E</bold>) Comparison of differentially expressed genes to gene signatures of hMDMs stimulated by 23 different stimuli (Xue <italic>et al</italic>. 2014). Shown are number of differentially expressed genes in pleural macrophages that are either positively (orange bar) or negatively (blue bar) correlated with the corresponding gene expression in hMDMs following indicated stimulation. (<bold>F</bold>) List of top 10 transcription factors that were identified to regulate the differentially expressed genes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_14808_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e820"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par10">Twenty-two of the 74 down-regulated genes were also down-regulated in previous transcriptional analysis of peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) in TB patients post antibiotics treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, whereas only 4 of the 156 up-regulated genes were up-regulated in PBMCs. The 22 down-regulated genes were enriched with interferon-mediated immunity (7 genes, P&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.2e-10) and immunity and defense (10 genes, P&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.0e-6), including OAS (2&#x02032;-5&#x02032;-oligoadenylate synthetase) and IFIT (Interferon-induced protein with tetratricopeptide repeats) family members. We also compared expression profiles in pleural macrophages to the gene expression modules in human monocyte-derived macrophage (hMDMs) stimulated by various stimuli<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. Most differentially expressed genes in pleural macrophages before and after antibiotics treatment were negatively correlated with IFN&#x003b3;/TNF&#x003b1; stimulating modules and positively correlated with P3C or TNF_PGE2_P3C (TPP) simulating modules through TLR2 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3E</xref>). Based on master regulation analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> of the signature genes and genome-wide regulatory network by Xu <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, 7 of the top 10 identified transcription factors (TFs) were interferon responsive, including STAT1, FOXO3 and IRF9 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3F</xref>). These results suggest that while IFN&#x003b3; and TNF&#x003b1; exert significant effect on pleural macrophage polarization, antibiotics may exert separate effect.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Antibiotics exert direct effect on pleural macrophages</title><p id="Par11">Gene expression changes in pleural macrophages after antibiotics treatment are enriched in GO term of &#x0201c;response to chemical stimulus&#x0201d; and most of these up-regulated genes were not captured in the whole-blood treatment-specific signature, raising the possibility that antibiotics exert direct effect on macrophage polarization. To test this possibility, we purified pleural macrophages from patients before antibiotics treatment but treated these macrophages with antibiotics <italic>in vitro</italic>. We selected 8 signature genes (<italic>COLEC12</italic>, <italic>HSPA1B</italic>, <italic>TREM1</italic>, <italic>CCL18</italic>, <italic>OAS3</italic>, <italic>IFIT3</italic>, <italic>CXCL16</italic>, <italic>CXCL10</italic>) to monitor the change of gene expression by real-time PCR. These genes not only belonged to &#x0201c;response to chemical stimulus&#x0201d; but to other functional categories such as &#x0201c;immune response&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;response to stress&#x0201d;. Expression of five genes was altered by antibiotics treatment <italic>in vitro</italic>: The levels of <italic>COLEC12</italic>, <italic>HSPA1B</italic> and <italic>TREM1</italic> transcripts were up-regulated, whereas the two IFN&#x003b3;-mediated antiviral genes <italic>OAS3</italic> and <italic>IFIT3</italic> were down-regulated (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), consistent with the <italic>in vivo</italic> results. However, <italic>CCL18</italic>, a typical M2 marker, was down-regulated <italic>in vitro</italic> but up-regulated <italic>in vivo</italic> following antibiotics treatment, and <italic>CXCL16</italic> and <italic>CXCL10</italic>, typical M1 markers and known IFN&#x003b3;-responsive genes, were not significantly changed <italic>in vitro</italic>. These results show that anti-TB antibiotics directly modulate differentiation status of pleural macrophages.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Comparison of gene expression in pleural macrophages with and without antibiotics treatment <italic>in vitro</italic>. Pleural macrophages were isolated from five patients before antibiotics treatment and cultured <italic>in vitro</italic> for 36&#x02009;hours with or without antibiotics. Cells were collected for RNA isolation and real-time PCR to quantify the transcript level of the indicted genes. Transcript level of each gene was normalized to GAPDH (ct). The ratio of ct with and without antibiotics is shown. Error bar, SEM; *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_14808_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e951"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par12">TPE is one of the most common forms of extrapulmonary tuberculosis. Pleural macrophages exhibit an M1-like phenotype producing pro-inflammatory cytokines and contribute to the initiation and development of TPE<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. No study has investigated the treatment-specific response of pleural macrophages in patients with tuberculous pleuritis. Here we examine the phenotypic and functional changes of pleural macrophages post antibiotics treatment by assaying their expression of surface markers, phagocytic function, secretion of cytokines and genome-wide transcriptional profiles. Our results from different analyses show that pleural macrophages are rapidly polarized from M1-like to M2-like phenotype after antibiotics treatment <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p id="Par13">Differentiating monocytes or macrophages express higher level of CD14 and HLA-DR than circulating or resident monocytes. The higher expression level of CD14 and HLA-DR in pleural macrophages comparing to monocytes (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5A,D</xref>), suggests pleural macrophages are not monocytes. However, pleural macrophages before treatment have lower FSC/SSC comparing to pleural macrophages post treatment (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5D</xref>), suggesting pleural macrophages before treatment tend to be in intermediate status during monocytes to macrophage differentiation. Since the total number or proportion of pleural macrophages did not change before and post antibiotic treatment (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1G</xref>), additionally the expression levels of CD14+ were slightly elevated post treatment (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5B,C</xref>) and CD206<sup>low</sup> pleural macrophages had lower FSC/SSC comparing to CD206<sup>hi</sup> pleural macrophages (Supplementary Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5E</xref>), these results suggest that CD206 expression changes are most likely due to the differentiation of pleural macrophages induced by antibiotics treatment but not the reduction of monocytes with low expression of CD206.</p><p id="Par14">Our transcription analysis of pleural macrophages before and after antibiotics treatment identified a treatment-specific signature of 230 genes, which significantly enriched a down-regulated functional pathway of &#x0201c;interferon-mediated immunity&#x0201d;, such as the interferon-related antiviral gene families<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, IFIT (<italic>IFIT1</italic>, <italic>IFIT2</italic>, <italic>IFIT3</italic>, <italic>IFIT5</italic> and <italic>IFITM1</italic>) and OAS (<italic>OAS1</italic>, <italic>OAS2</italic> and <italic>OAS3</italic>). In previous studies, gene expression analysis of the whole blood of TB patients also showed interferon signaling and innate immune response genes were gradually down-regulated post antibiotics treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, consistent with the decreased level of IFN&#x003b3; in the patient serum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. These results indicate interferon-mediated genes are significantly responsive to antibiotics treatment not only in the peripheral blood but also in the TPE. Moreover, differential expressed genes are negatively correlated with IFN&#x003b3; and/or TNF&#x003b1; stimulating modules and regulated by interferon responsive TFs, indicating the decrease of IFN&#x003b3; and TNF&#x003b1; in the TPE exerts significant effect on pleural macrophage polarization post antibiotics treatment. However, a significant fraction of treatment-specific genes was modulated by direct antibiotics treatment of purified pleural macrophages <italic>in vitro</italic>, demonstrating antibiotics may exert independent effects on the pleural macrophage polarization.</p><p id="Par15">Studies have suggested that single anti-TB antibiotics exerts direct immunomodulatory effect on immune cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Among the treatment-specific 230 signature genes, most of them were not present in the whole-blood treatment-specific signature<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup> nor IFN&#x003b3; and/or TNF&#x003b1; stimulating modules, suggesting anti-TB antibiotics might directly regulate gene expression in pleural macrophages. As shown by <italic>in vitro</italic> antibiotics treatment of purified pleural macrophages, the expression of five out of eight selected genes was significantly changed. <italic>COLEC12</italic>, <italic>HSPA1B</italic> and <italic>TREM1</italic> were up-regulated as in <italic>in vivo</italic>. <italic>COLEC12</italic> is a C-lectin scavenger receptor associated with host defense by binding to and removal of microorganisms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. <italic>HSPA1B</italic> encodes a 70&#x02009;kDa heat shock protein and has been reported to activate macrophages and enhance phagocytosis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. <italic>TREM1</italic> plays a crucial role in fine-tuning of inflammatory response by enhancing or inhibiting TLR signals through NF&#x003ba;B and PU.1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. TREM1-related signaling was identified as the most important activated pathway during active TB disease in blood transcriptome analysis from multiple data sets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. Two antiviral genes <italic>IFIT3</italic> and <italic>OAS3</italic>, IL10-inducing and IFN&#x003b3;-suppressing gene <italic>CCL18</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> were down-regulated, while strong IFN&#x003b3;-inducing genes <italic>CXCL10</italic> and <italic>CXCL16</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> were not changed. <italic>IFIT3</italic> and <italic>OAS3</italic> can be induced by interferon signal or Pattern Recognition Receptors (PRRs) activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Interestingly, comparing to expression profiles of human monocyte-derived macrophages (hMDMs) to various stimuli, the most positively correlated stimulus is the TLR2 ligand P3C (Pam3Cys) and combination of LPS and Immune Complex (LPS_IC). Anti-TB antibiotics treatment induced the <italic>TLR2</italic> and <italic>TLR4</italic> expression in lymphocytes and CD14<sup>+</sup> monocytes in pulmonary tuberculous patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. These results suggest that anti-TB antibiotics might directly modulate the TLR signaling to regulate the gene expression in pleural macrophages. The master regulation analysis also identified several non-interferon or TNF responsive TFs that regulate the differentially expressed genes, such as <italic>MAFA</italic>, <italic>MTF1</italic> and <italic>MEF2D</italic>. These non-interferon or TNF responsive TFs could play a key role in modulating pleural macrophages response to anti-TB antibiotics. Thus, the efficacy of antibiotics in treating tuberculous pleuritis may depend not only on direct killing of mycobacteria but also on modulating the function of pleural macrophages. Consistent with this notion, differentiation of pleural macrophages to M2-like phenotype may promote tissue repair.</p><p id="Par16">Current management of TB treatment lacks robust tools to monitor the treatment efficiency in the early stage during the long-term antibiotics treatment, especially for the treatment of multidrug-resistant TB patients<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. We show that the pro-inflammatory mediators IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1; and IL6 in TPE were decreased significantly post antibiotics treatment as short as 2~3 days. The reduction of these pro-inflammatory cytokines was also observed in the serum, but not until 2~4 months post treatment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Because TPE is more proximal to the site of mycobacterial infection, the more rapid change of pleural cytokines as well as pleural macrophage phenotype could be valuable prognostic biomarkers to monitor the efficiency of antibiotics treatment in TB patients with tuberculous pleuritis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec9"><title>Patients and study design</title><p id="Par17">A total 171 adult patients with tuberculous pleuritis were enrolled in this study. Participants were recruited from the Infectious Disease Hospital of Changchun, China. Thirty-six patients with serious comorbidities, encapsulated pleural effusion, other lung diseases, HIV co-infection, or contraindications to pleural effusion puncture were excluded from this study. All patients received a full 2 months of combination antibiotics treatment (HRZE) with standard doses of isoniazid (H, 300&#x02009;mg/d), rifampicin (R, 450&#x02009;mg/d), pyrazinamide (Z, 1500&#x02009;mg/d) and ethambutol (E, 750&#x02009;mg/d) followed by 4-month HR treatment without steroid therapy. Patients underwent thoracentesis (diagnostic and therapeutic) before chemotherapy and/or after 2~10 days of chemotherapy before pleural effusion disappeared. The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the Infectious Disease Hospital of Changchun and The First Hospital of Jilin University. All experiments were performed in accordance with the relevant guidelines and regulations. In addition, written informed consent was obtained from each subject.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Sample acquisition</title><p id="Par18">TPE was obtained by thoracocentesis under conscious sedation and local anaesthesia using a 14&#x02009;G Klatskin needle. 50~150&#x02009;ml of urokinase-anticoagulated TPE was immediately deposited in 50&#x02009;ml tube and centrifuged at 1500&#x02009;rpm at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;minutes. The cell-free PE was collected and stored at &#x02212;80&#x02009;&#x000b0;C before use. Pleural effusion mononuclear cells (PEMCs) were separated immediately on Lymphoprep (Fresenius Kabi Norge AS, Norway) density gradients from cell pellet.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Cell surface and intracellular cytokine staining</title><p id="Par19">After pre-incubation with human Fc-receptor binding inhibitor (eBioscience, USA) for 15&#x02009;minutes on ice, fresh PEMCs were stained with fluorochrome-conjugated antibodies of CD14, CD80, CD86, CD163, CD206, CD3, CD4, CD8, CD20 and CD56 (BD Biosciences, USA) at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the dark for 20&#x02009;minutes. Cells were washed, centrifuged and resuspended in cold FACS Buffer (PBS containing 0.1% BSA and 0.01% sodium azide) plus PI before flow cytometry analysis. For intracellular cytokine staining, PEMCs were first plated and stimulated with 50&#x02009;ng/ml PMA and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;M Ionomycin (Sigma-Aldrich) supplement with GolgiStop&#x02122; (BD Biosciences) for 4&#x02009;hours or 18&#x02009;hours. Cells were stained with Live/Dead<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> Fixable Dead Cell green fluorescent reactive dye (Invitrogen, USA), then fixed and stained with IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL6, IL10, IL4 and IL2 using Cytofix/Cytoperm Kit (BD Biosciences). Flow cytometry was performed using a LSR Fortessa cytometer (BD Biosciences) and data were analyzed using Flowjo7.6.1 software.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>ELISA</title><p id="Par20">TPE supernatant were harvested and assayed for IFN&#x003b1;, IFN&#x003b2;, IFN&#x003b3;, TNF&#x003b1;, IL-1&#x003b2;, IL-4, IL-6, IL-10, TGF&#x003b2;, and GM-CSF production by ELISA according to the manufacturers&#x02019; protocol from eBioscience, R&#x00026;D, Abcam, Elabscience and Dakewe Biotech Co.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Pleural macrophage purification, RNA isolation, RNA-sequencing and data analysis</title><p id="Par21">Pleural macrophages were purified from freshly isolated PEMCs using human CD14 MicroBeads (Miltenyi Biotec, USA). Briefly, cells were passed through a magnetic column as CD14-depleted cells. Labeled cells were collected as purified macrophages. Macrophages were further purified by seeding in 60-mm dish in complete RPMI 1640 medium (Gibco, USA) containing 10% FBS (BI, Israel), 100 U/ml of penicillin and streptomycin. Cells were incubated at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 20&#x02009;minutes and washed off the unattached cells. The purity of macrophages were assessed by Giemsa staining to ensure &#x0003e;90% purity. 0.5~1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> macrophages were collected into 1&#x02009;ml of TRIzol (Ambion, USA) for RNA extraction.</p><p id="Par22">The quality and quantity of total RNA were assessed with a RNA-6000 Nano LabChip on a 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Inc., USA). cDNA libraries were prepared with SMARTer Universal Low Input RNA Kit (Clontech, USA). The libraries were sequenced by HiSeq. 2000 100 PE (Illumina, USA). Paired sequences were aligned to the human genome (version hg19) using Tophat2<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Raw counts of each gene for each sample were calculated by HTseq<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Differentially expressed genes between paired samples before and after treatment were performed using edgeR at <italic>P</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 with a cutoff of 2-fold change<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Differentially expressed genes were annotated using online functional enrichment analysis tool DAVID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. RNA-seq data are available in GEO database under accession code GSE85037.</p><p id="Par23">To compare to the spectrum of human macrophage activation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>, signature genes of each stimulus were matched to our 230 treatment-specific signature genes based on their expression change trends. Master regulation analysis was performed as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. The spectrum data<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> was used to construct an information-based regulatory network and applied to search for the key transcription factors that regulate the 230 treatment-specific signature genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> anti-TB drug treatment</title><p id="Par24">A combined dose of HRZE for <italic>in vitro</italic> treatment was used to mimic the <italic>in vivo</italic> treatment based on the maximum human blood plasma concentrations (Cmax) of approximately 12.4&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml H, 4.0&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml R, 58&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml Z and 4.3&#x02009;&#x000b5;g/ml E during chemotherapy respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Pleural macrophages were purified from PEMCs as described above and incubated with or without HRZE in a 6-well plate at a concentration of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells/well for 36&#x02009;hours.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Real time RT-PCR</title><p id="Par25">Pleural macrophages from <italic>in vitro</italic> treatment were collected to isolate total RNA using TRIzol. cDNA was reverse-transcribed using Maxima FirstStrand cDNA Synthesis Kit (Thermo, USA) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. RT-qPCR was performed in ABI Plus one (Applied Biosystems, USA) using FastStart Universal SYBR Green Master (Roche, Germany). Either the 18S ribosomal RNA (forward: GCGGCTTTGGTGACTCTA, reverse: CTGCCTTCCTTGGATGTG) or <italic>GAPDH</italic> (forward: CGGATTTGGTCGTATTGGG, reverse: CGGATTTGGTCGTATTGGG) was used as an internal control for normalization. The gene-specific primer sets were purchased from Qiagen as following: <italic>COLEC12</italic> (Cat. QT00080192), <italic>HSPA1B</italic> (Cat. QT01668212), <italic>CCL18</italic> (Cat. QT00024066), <italic>CXCL10</italic> (Cat. QT01003065), <italic>IFIT3</italic> (Cat. QT00100030) and <italic>OAS3</italic> (Cat. QT01005277) or synthesized as <italic>CXCL16</italic> (forward and reverse primers: AAACCACCATTCACACTGCG and AGCCACAGTTTACCCTCACAA), <italic>TREM1</italic> (AAGCTCCACCCAAGTCAACTG, and CATCCTCTCAGCACACAGACT), <italic>IL1&#x003b2;</italic> (CAGAAGTACCTGAGCTCGCC, and AGATTCGTAGCTGGATGCCG), <italic>IL6</italic> (GAACTCCTTCTCCACAAGCG and GAAGAGGTGAGTGGCTGTCTG), <italic>IL10</italic> (GGGAGAACCTGAAGACCCTCA and TGCTCTTGTTTTCACAGGGAAG), <italic>IFN&#x003b3;</italic> (CATCCAAGTGATGGCTGAACTG and TCGAAACAGCATCTGACTCCTTT), <italic>TNF&#x003b1;</italic> (ATCCTGGGGGACCCAATGTA, and AAAAGAAGGCACAGAGGCCA), <italic>TGF&#x003b2;</italic> (CTGTATTTAAGGACACCCGTGC, and ATGACACAGAGATCCGCAGTC), <italic>GM-CSF</italic> (CAGCCCTGGGAGCATGTG and CATCTCAGCAGCAGTGTCTCTAC).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Statistical method</title><p id="Par26">in the method as following &#x0201c;Data for flow cytometry and qPCR were presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. Statistical analysis was performed with Prism5 (GraphPad Software, San Diego, CA). Statistical significance between before and after treatment groups was defined as <italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, and obtained with a paired or unpaired two-tailed t-test for paired and unpaired samples, respectively. Differences are noted as *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec17"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2017_14808_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary figures and tables</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p>Sisi Wang and Jian Zhang contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>
<bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-017-14808-9.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank assistance of doctors Zhiyong Zhang, Yanbin Xu, Miao Wang, Weili Chen, Xuesong Tan, Jisi Sun, Mingguang Zhou, Zhi Shao and Hui Jia from Hospital of Infectious Diseases of Changchun to collect TPF samples. This work was supported by the First Hospital of Jilin University, National High-tech Research and Development Projects (863) (2014AA021603) and Scientific Research Foundation in the Science and Technology Development Plan of Jilin Province (20150520142JH).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>S.W., J.Z., L.Su., H.X., and Q.P. performed the experiments. J.Z., X.Q., L.So., Y.L., Y.S., D.L. and L.P. performed TPF sample collection. S.W. and G.H. analyzed the data. G.H., S.H. and J.C. wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par27">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. Global tuberculosis reports; (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Light</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update on tuberculous pleural effusion</article-title><source>Respirology</source><year>2010</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1843.2010.01723.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20345583?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20345583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wolfgang, F. Tuberculous Pleural Effusion. In: Mahboub, B. (ed). <italic>Tuberculosis - Current Issues in Diagnosis and Management</italic>. InTech: InTech (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vorster</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Allwood</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name><name><surname>Diacon</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Koegelenberg</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tuberculous pleural effusions: advances and controversies</article-title><source>Journal of thoracic disease</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>981</fpage><lpage>991</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26150911?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26150911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greco</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Girardi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Masciangelo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Capoccetta</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Saltini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adenosine deaminase and interferon gamma measurements for the diagnosis of tuberculous pleurisy: a meta-analysis</article-title><source>Int J Tuberc Lung Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>777</fpage><lpage>786</lpage><?supplied-pmid 12921155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12921155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Porcel</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tuberculous pleural effusion</article-title><source>Lung</source><year>2009</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>263</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00408-009-9165-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19672657?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19672657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stead</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichenholz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stauss</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Operative and pathologic findings in twenty-four patients with syndrome of idiopathic pleurisy with effusion, presumably tuberculous</article-title><source>Am Rev Tuberc</source><year>1955</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>502</lpage><?supplied-pmid 14361964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14361964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>GX</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Different subsets of macrophages in patients with new onset tuberculous pleural effusion</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e88343</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0088343</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24520370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24520370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thuong</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of tuberculosis susceptibility genes with human macrophage gene expression profiles</article-title><source>PLoS Pathog</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>e1000229</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000229</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19057661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19057661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name><name><surname>Helming</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alternative activation of macrophages: an immunologic functional perspective</article-title><source>Annu Rev Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.021908.132532</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19105661?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19105661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Etna</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Giacomini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Severa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coccia</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pro- and anti-inflammatory cytokines in tuberculosis: a two-edged sword in TB pathogenesis</article-title><source>Semin Immunol</source><year>2014</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.smim.2014.09.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25453229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25453229</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchison</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity and penetration of antituberculosis drugs in mouse peritoneal macrophages infected with Mycobacterium microti OV254</article-title><source>Antimicrobial agents and chemotherapy</source><year>1989</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.33.8.1255</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2802553?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2802553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rey-Jurado</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Tudo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Soy</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Martin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activity and interactions of levofloxacin, linezolid, ethambutol and amikacin in three-drug combinations against Mycobacterium tuberculosis isolates in a human macrophage model</article-title><source>Int J Antimicrob Agents</source><year>2013</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>524</fpage><lpage>530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2013.07.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24080479?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24080479</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minic</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunomodulatory actions of antibiotics</article-title><source>Med Pregl</source><year>2009</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2298/MPNS0908327M</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19902783?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19902783</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giuliani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effect of rifampin on CD1b expression and double-negative T cell responses against mycobacteria-derived glycolipid antigen</article-title><source>Life Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>985</fpage><lpage>994</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0024-3205(98)00360-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9749821?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9749821</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tentori</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Rifampin increases cytokine-induced expression of the CD1b molecule in human peripheral blood monocytes</article-title><source>Antimicrobial agents and chemotherapy</source><year>1998</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>550</fpage><lpage>554</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/42.4.550</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9517931?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9517931</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tousif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isoniazid induces apoptosis of activated CD4+ T cells: implications for post-therapy tuberculosis reactivation and reinfection</article-title><source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source><year>2014</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>30190</fpage><lpage>30195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.C114.598946</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25202011?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25202011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Metushi</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name><name><surname>Uetrecht</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoniazid-induced liver injury and immune response in mice</article-title><source>J Immunotoxicol</source><year>2014</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>392</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/1547691X.2013.860644</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24303880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24303880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Manca</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Host targeted activity of pyrazinamide in Mycobacterium tuberculosis infection</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e74082</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0074082</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24015316?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24015316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The antituberculosis drug pyrazinamide affects the course of cutaneous leishmaniasis <italic>in vivo</italic> and increases activation of macrophages and dendritic cells</article-title><source>Antimicrobial agents and chemotherapy</source><year>2009</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>5114</fpage><lpage>5121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.01146-09</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19770283?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19770283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Host cell autophagy activated by antibiotics is required for their effective antimycobacterial drug action</article-title><source>Cell Host Microbe</source><year>2012</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>468</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chom.2012.03.008</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22607799?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22607799</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berry</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An interferon-inducible neutrophil-driven blood transcriptional signature in human tuberculosis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>466</volume><fpage>973</fpage><lpage>977</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09247</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20725040?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20725040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bloom</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detectable changes in the blood transcriptome are present after two weeks of antituberculosis therapy</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e46191</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0046191</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23056259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23056259</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baganha</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pego</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaspar</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Cordeiro</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum and pleural adenosine deaminase</article-title><source>Correlation with lymphocytic populations. Chest</source><year>1990</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>610</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1689629?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1689629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-based network analysis reveals a spectrum model of human macrophage activation</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2014</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2014.01.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24530056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24530056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-wide regulatory network identifies key transcription factors for memory CD8(&#x02009;+&#x02009;) T-cell development</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>2830</fpage><?supplied-pmid 24335726?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24335726</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antony</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahn</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Antony</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Repine</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title> Bacillus Calmette-Guerin-stimulated neutrophils release chemotaxins for monocytes in rabbit pleural spaces and <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Invest</source><year>1985</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>1514</fpage><lpage>1521</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI112131</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3902892?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3902892</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnes</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compartmentalization of a CD4+ T lymphocyte subpopulation in tuberculous pleuritis</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>1989</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1114</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2464638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2464638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Farzan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The broad-spectrum antiviral functions of IFIT and IFITM proteins</article-title><source>Nature reviews. Immunology</source><year>2013</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3344</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23237964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23237964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Deveci</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbulut</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Turgut</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Muz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in serum cytokine levels in active tuberculosis with treatment</article-title><source>Mediators of inflammation</source><year>2005</year><volume>2005</volume><fpage>256</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/MI.2005.256</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16258192?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16258192</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of neutrophil granule glycoproteins as Lewis(x)-containing ligands cleared by the scavenger receptor C-type lectin</article-title><source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source><year>2011</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>24336</fpage><lpage>24349</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M111.244772</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21561871?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21561871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohtani</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The membrane-type collectin CL-P1 is a scavenger receptor on vascular endothelial cells</article-title><source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source><year>2001</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>44222</fpage><lpage>44228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M103942200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11564734?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11564734</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Town</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gokarn</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Flavell</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandawarkar</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HSP70 enhances macrophage phagocytosis by interaction with lipid raft-associated TLR-7 and upregulating p38 MAPK and PI3K pathways</article-title><source>The Journal of surgical research</source><year>2006</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jss.2006.06.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16979664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16979664</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Asea</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>HSP70 stimulates cytokine production through a CD14-dependant pathway, demonstrating its dual role as a chaperone and cytokine</article-title><source>Nature medicine</source><year>2000</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/74697</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10742151?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10742151</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ornatowska</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sadikot</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TREM-1 expression in macrophages is regulated at transcriptional level by NF-kappaB and PU.1</article-title><source>European journal of immunology</source><year>2007</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>2300</fpage><lpage>2308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.200737270</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17634956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17634956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells 1 (TREM-1)-mediated Bcl-2 induction prolongs macrophage survival</article-title><source>The Journal of biological chemistry</source><year>2014</year><volume>289</volume><fpage>15118</fpage><lpage>15129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M113.536490</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24711453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24711453</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>McVicar</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TREM and TREM-like receptors in inflammation and disease</article-title><source>Current opinion in immunology</source><year>2009</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>38</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coi.2009.01.009</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19230638?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19230638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joosten</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottenhoff</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A helicopter perspective on TB biomarkers: pathway and process based analysis of gene expression data provides new insight into TB pathogenesis</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e73230</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073230</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24066041?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24066041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vulcano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unique regulation of CCL18 production by maturing dendritic cells</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>3843</fpage><lpage>3849</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.170.7.3843</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12646652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12646652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Analysis of Toll-like receptors, iNOS and cytokine profiles in patients with pulmonary tuberculosis during anti-tuberculosis treatment</article-title><source>PloS one</source><year>2014</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>e88572</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0088572</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24558401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24558401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TopHat-Fusion: an algorithm for discovery of novel fusion transcripts</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2011</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>R72</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2011-12-8-r72</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21835007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21835007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyl</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HTSeq&#x02013;a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>169</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25260700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>edgeR: a Bioconductor package for differential expression analysis of digital gene expression data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btp616</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19910308?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19910308</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang da</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempicki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2009</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2008.211</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19131956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19131956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Oral bioavailability of rifampicin, isoniazid, ethambutol, and pyrazinamide in a 4-drug fixed-dose combination compared with the separate formulations in healthy Chinese male volunteers</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>2013</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.clinthera.2013.01.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23410999?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23410999</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>