<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Springerplus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Springerplus</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>SpringerPlus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2193-1801</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer International Publishing</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cham</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3736078</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">426</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2193-1801-2-362</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of leptospira isolates from animals and humans: phylogenetic analysis identifies the prevalence of intermediate species in India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Balamurugan</surname><given-names>Vinayagamurthy</given-names></name><address><email>balavirol@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>Nidaghatta L</given-names></name><address><email>nlgangadhar@rediffmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mohandoss</surname><given-names>Nagalingam</given-names></name><address><email>nagar75@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thirumalesh</surname><given-names>Sushma Rahim Assadi</given-names></name><address><email>assadi.sushma@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dhar</surname><given-names>Moushumi</given-names></name><address><email>drmdutta2003@yahoo.co.in</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shome</surname><given-names>Rajeswari</given-names></name><address><email>raji_shome1@rediffmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krishnamoorthy</surname><given-names>Paramanandham</given-names></name><address><email>krishvet@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Prabhudas</surname><given-names>Krishnamsetty</given-names></name><address><email>prabhudask@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>Habibur</given-names></name><address><email>hricar@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7"/></contrib><aff id="Aff7">Project Directorate on Animal Disease Monitoring and Surveillance (PD_ADMAS), Hebbal, HA Farm Post, Bengaluru, 560 024 Karnataka India </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>30</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>362</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>29</day><month>7</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Balamurugan et al.; licensee Springer. 2013</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This article is published under license to BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p>In this study, 191 culture isolates were recovered from suspected samples of animals and humans in Ellinghausen McCullough Johnson and Harris (EMJH) medium and assessed for its morphological features by dark field microscopy. Extracted DNA from individual culture was subjected to different PCR assays for identification and characterization of leptospira. Out of 99 positive leptospira cultures, 52 pathogenic leptospira isolates were characterized at species level by using partial RNA polymerase &#x003b2;-subunit (<italic>rpoB)</italic> gene sequences. Phylogenetic analysis of the nucleotide sequences revealed that 30, 8, and 14 isolates belong to <italic>L. borgpetersenii / L. interrogans</italic>, <italic>L. kirschneri</italic>, and <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species, respectively. Based on analysis of 99 leptospira isolates, the prevalent <italic>Leptospira</italic> species were <italic>L. borgpetersenii</italic> or <italic>L. interrogans</italic> (30.30%), <italic>L. kirschneri</italic> (8%) and <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species (14.14%) in animals and humans. To the best of authors knowledge, this is the first study to use <italic>rpoB</italic> gene nucleotide sequence based phylogenetic analysis to identify/detect <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species (<italic>L. wolffii</italic>) in animals and humans in India. Hence, the prevalence of this species will surely emphasize the importance of consideration of <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species and formulate a way for further studies especially in understanding the newly emerging <italic>Leptospira</italic> in animals and humans and to combat the problem associated with the disease conditions.</p></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Leptospira</kwd><kwd>Animals</kwd><kwd>Human</kwd><kwd>Characterization</kwd><kwd>Prevalence</kwd><kwd>Intermediate species</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2013</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Leptospirosis is an important re-emerging zoonotic disease in tropical and subtropical regions of the world with various animal species acting as carriers. It is considered as an emerging global public health problem (Bharti et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2003</xref>), caused by different pathogenic species of leptospira and is difficult to control and eradicate in tropical developing countries like India. Hence, early detection of leptospira in the host, prompt treatment as well as creating awareness in the public are the steps that could be taken to reduce the extent of problem and the economical losses associated with it.</p><p>Diagnosis of leptospirosis is usually achieved by serological investigation particularly by microscopic agglutination test (MAT), a gold standard test. The MAT is a well proven, accepted and widely used serological test for the detection of leptospiral antibodies in animals and humans. It is very useful in the demonstration of a four-fold change in antibody titers in paired acute and convalescent sera and is of significant value in diagnosing recent infection. However, in case of animals, getting paired sera is difficult, in such case while testing of single serum in MAT, it is essential to correlate the results with clinical signs of the affected animal. Generally, very high MAT titres with a consistent clinical features are conclusive of leptospirosis.</p><p>In any particular geographical region, various leptospiral serovars are prevalent and are associated with one or more maintenance host(s) that serves as reservoir of infection. <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. are traditionally classified into 29 serogroups and over 300 serovars (Levett <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2001</xref>). Further, genotypic methods like DNA-DNA hybridization have identified 20 <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. to date (Cerqueira and Picardeau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2009</xref>). However, antigenically related serovars are classified in two or more different species and a serogroup is often found in several species of leptospira. Serovar identification of isolates are essential to understand the prevalence of leptospira in the epidemiology of this disease, but few laboratories perform Cross Agglutination Absorption Test (CAAT) (Terpstra et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1985</xref>) and most isolates are therefore not identified at serovar level. Serogroups identified using the MAT have no official taxonomic status, can serve as practical purpose of grouping common antigens together. With the emergence of molecular typing methods, it has become increasingly clearer that the concept of a &#x0201c;serovar&#x0201d; is no longer fully satisfactory as it may fail to define epidemiologically important strains/isolates in an adequate manner (Cerqueira and Picardeau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2009</xref>). For example, molecular typing has been shown to give better discrimination of strains of the Grippotyphosa serogroup than serological typing (Steinen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1992</xref>; Hartskeerl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">2004</xref>).</p><p>Phylogenetic analysis identifies three major groups of leptospira with few exceptions, based on the pathogenicity such as pathogenic, saprophytic and intermediate strains of unclear pathogenicity (Paster et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1991</xref>; (Matthias et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2008</xref>). Genes used to discriminate between species within the genus <italic>Leptospira</italic> include RNA polymerase &#x003b2;-subunit (<italic>rpoB)</italic> (La Scola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2006</xref>), DNA gyrase subunit B <italic>(gyrB)</italic> (Slack et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">2006</xref>) and leptospiral immunoglobulin-like protein (<italic>ligB)</italic> (Cerqueira et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2009</xref>). All the proposed taxonomic markers generate results consistent with those obtained with the 16S rRNA sequences in terms of clustering of the strains into three major groups.</p><p>The research activities in leptospirosis since inception of Project Directorate on Animal Disease Monitoring and Surveillance (PD_ADMAS) has led to isolation of <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. from diverse animals and humans and their maintenance in the repository, development of a simple leptospira staining kit and recording of the leptospiral abortions in bovines and other animal species (Gangadhar and Rajashekar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1998</xref>; Gangadhar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>). It is imperative to know the circulating <italic>Leptospira</italic> species/serovars in animals and humans in different geographical locations in order to investigate the prevalence of <italic>Leptospira</italic> species during monitoring of the leptospirosis. This helps in appropriate use of panel of leptospira serovars in the MAT for providing proper diagnostic without false negative results. Hence, the preliminary study was undertaken to investigate the prevalence of <italic>Leptospira</italic> species in animals and humans using the archived cultural isolates recovered from suspected samples of animals and humans in different geographical locality of India collected during different periods up to the species level by using <italic>rpoB gene-</italic> based sequence and phylogenetic analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Culture media</title><p>A modified Ellinghausen McCullough Johnson and Harris (EMJH) liquid medium containing bovine serum albumin fraction V (Ellis <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1986</xref>) was prepared as per standard bacteriological procedure with 200 &#x003bc;g of 5-fluorouracil per mL of medium.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Clinical samples</title><p>Clinical samples such as blood, serum, urine and other materials such as kidney, tissues and fluids from aborted fetus collected from suspected animals and humans [most of cases-pyrexia of unknown origin (PUO)] from different geographical locations of India collected either by the ADMAS team or obtained through various organizations such as state animal husbandry laboratories, research institutes and from organized farms which were submitted to the laboratory for leptospira diagnosis. The details of the species from which the samples were collected and the area of origin with brief history of samples and designation of cultural isolates are presented in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The majority of clinical materials were from the states of Karnataka, Maharashtra and Gujarat. The animals and human beings from which samples were collected and submitted for diagnosis had clinical signs consistent with leptospira infection especially in humans.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p><bold>Details of characterized leptospira isolates from animals and humans</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">ADMAS No.</th><th align="left">Source of sample</th><th align="left">Brief history of samples/specimens, place, year of collection</th><th align="left">GenBank Acc. No.</th></tr><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left"/><th>Karnataka state</th><th align="left"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">Kidney</td><td align="left">Pregnant female rat trapped at military dairy farm, Bangalore, May,1994.#</td><td align="left">JN388643&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">121</td><td align="left">Kidney</td><td align="left">Female rat trapped in dairy farm at Malleshwaram, Bangalore, August, 1994.#</td><td align="left">JN388654&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">421</td><td align="left">Blood/Serum</td><td align="left">Repeat breeder cow from University of Agricultural Sciences dairy farm, Bangalore, July,1995.#</td><td align="left">JN388636&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">737</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Referred human case with fever from Bowring and Lady Curzon Hospital, Bangalore, February, 1997.*</td><td align="left">HM046992&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">840</td><td align="left">Urine</td><td align="left">Rat from small animal house at Institute of Animal Health and Veterinary Biological, Bangalore, October, 1997.#</td><td align="left">JN388655&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">843</td><td align="left">Kidney</td><td align="left">"</td><td align="left">JN388644&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">930</td><td align="left">CSF</td><td align="left">4 &#x000bd; years old girl with pyogenic mengitis, Bangalore, March,1998.*</td><td align="left">JN388645&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">950</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Referred human case aged 21years male with fever &#x00026; myalgia from Victoria Hospital, Bangalore, April,1998.*</td><td align="left">JN388646&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">966</td><td align="left">Urine</td><td align="left">Referred human case aged 28 years male with fever, jaundice and hematuria from Bangalore Medical college, June, 1998.*</td><td align="left">JN388627&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1003</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Buffalo calf with pyrexia, Hassan, August, 1998,*</td><td align="left">JN388656&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1063</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Referred human case aged 30 years male with heptorenal syndrome and leptospira serology positive from NIMHANS, Bangalore, October,1998.*</td><td align="left">HM046989&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1147</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Referred human case aged 14 years male with icteric discolouration of eye with heptomegally from St. Marthas Hospital, Bangalore, July,1999.</td><td align="left">JN388634&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1178</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Referred human case aged 6 years female with pyrexia for one week from, Bowring and Lady Curzon Hospital, Bangalore, October, 1999.*</td><td align="left">HM046997&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1175</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Bullock with fever from State Breeding and Training Centre, Hassarghatta, October, 1999.*</td><td align="left">JN388616&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">107</td><td align="left">Kidney</td><td align="left">Adult male rat trapped from SPCA(Animal Shelter), Kennel, Bangalore, February, 1995.#</td><td align="left">JN388629&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1190</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Alcoholic male aged 40 years from Gowribidanur with fever for 8 days (Temperature 104&#x000b0;C), August, 2000.*</td><td align="left">JN388628&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">58</td><td align="left">Blood/ Serum</td><td align="left">Female with pyrexia of unknown origin, February, 2010.*</td><td align="left">JN388620&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G202</td><td align="left">Foetal peritoneal fluid</td><td align="left">Aborted foetus from cow with fever, Kengeri, March, 2007.#</td><td align="left">JN388621&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G229</td><td align="left">Foetal heart blood</td><td align="left">Aborted foetus from cow with fever, Devanahalli, June, 2007.#</td><td align="left">JN388622&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1345</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">HF cross breed cow with pyrexia and diahhroea, Hosodi, Shimoga, September,2001.#</td><td align="left">HM046993&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1332</td><td align="left">Urine</td><td align="left">Urine from the bladder of rat tapped from Veterinary Hospital, Husudi area, Shimoga, September, 2001.#</td><td align="left">JN388633&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1590</td><td align="left">Serum/Blood</td><td align="left">Repeat breeder cow with pyrexia from Veterinary Hospital, Mysore Road Bangalore, March, 2004.*</td><td align="left">HM046994&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3233</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Referred human case of adult male with weakness of the left side body for15 days without pyrexia from KIMS Hospital, Bangalore, March, 2007.*</td><td align="left">JN388652&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3647</td><td align="left">Heart Blood</td><td align="left">Rat trapped at Poultry farm, Veterinary College, Bangalore May 2009.*</td><td align="left">JN388657&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>Gujarat state</bold></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">2421</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Cow with fever from Animal Disease Investigation, Ramveri, Surat, Gujarat, September, 2006.*</td><td align="left">JN388631&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2475</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Following incidence of leptospirosis samples were collected from Deputy Director of Animal Husbandry, Ambavadi, Ahmedabad, Gujarat, October, 2006.*<break/>- Cow, Gandhinagar</td><td align="left">JN388635&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2757</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Cow, Maninagar</td><td align="left">JN388639&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2882</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Cow, Amaraiwadi</td><td align="left">JN388642&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2480</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Cow, Raipur</td><td align="left">JN388647&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2636</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Dog, Ghatlodiya</td><td align="left">JN388648&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2667</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Dog, Khadiya</td><td align="left">JN388649&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2713</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Buffalo, NavaVadaj</td><td align="left">JN388650&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2779</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Cow, Maninagar</td><td align="left">JN388651&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3334</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">6 &#x000bd; years old HF cross breed cow with pyrexia from Veterinary dispensary, Badekhan Chakla. Kazimaidair, Gopipur, Surat, Gujarat,August, 2007.*</td><td align="left">JN388640&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3360</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Following incidence of leptospirosis, cow samples were collected from Paldi village, Kakanj Tal Daskroi District, Ahemadabad, Gujarat,September, 2007.*</td><td align="left">JN388637&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3377</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">"</td><td align="left">JN388653&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td/><td/><td align="center"><bold>Maharashtra state</bold></td><td/></tr><tr><td align="left">1215</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Following incidence of leptospirosis, samples were collected from Disease Investigation Section (DIS),WRDDL, Aundh, Pune.* ^Thane-August, 2000;<sup>&#x000b1;</sup>Pune-August, 2005.<break/>- Goat^</td><td align="left">HM046995&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1194</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Dog^</td><td align="left">JN388615&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1856</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">-Cow<sup>&#x000b1;</sup></td><td align="left">JN388632&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1756</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">-Buffalo<sup>&#x000b1;</sup></td><td align="left">JN388625&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1761</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">-Buffalo<sup>&#x000b1;</sup></td><td align="left">JN388630&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1762</td><td align="left">Serum/Blood</td><td align="left">-Buffalo<sup>&#x000b1;</sup></td><td align="left">JN388618&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3395</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Following incidence of leptospirosis, samples were collected from DIS, WRDDL, Pune, September 2007.*<break/>- Goat, Rajapur</td><td align="left">JN388638&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3394</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Goat, Rajapur</td><td align="left">JN388624&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3398</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Goat, Rajapur</td><td align="left">JN388626&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3397</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">- Goat, Pune</td><td align="left">JN388641&#x02663;</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4"><bold>Other states</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left">1183</td><td align="left">Blood</td><td align="left">Male elephant aged 70 years having fever from Department of Medicine, Veterinary college, Mannuthy Kerala, June, 2000.*</td><td align="left">HM046990&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1228</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">4 years old cow having pyrexia from District Medical office, Leptospira cell, Thodupuzha, Idukki. Kerala, June, 2001.*</td><td align="left">JN388619&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">1256</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">Dog with fever and Jaundice, Guwahati, Assam, July, 2001.*</td><td align="left">HM046991&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G70</td><td align="left">Blood/Serum</td><td align="left">3 years old repeat breeding cow, Goa, January 2006.#</td><td align="left">JN388617&#x025c6;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G73</td><td align="left">Serum</td><td align="left">6 years old pregnant cow with pyrexia, Goa, January, 2006.#</td><td align="left">HM046996&#x02660;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G90</td><td align="left">Serum/Blood</td><td align="left">Repeat breeding cow, Goa, September, 2006.#</td><td align="left">JN388623&#x025c6;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Suspected samples received for leptospirosis diagnosis. # Randomly collected samples for leptsospira study. <italic>Leptospira</italic> species identified &#x025c6; <italic>L.interrogans or L.borgpetersenii</italic> species, &#x02660; <italic>L.krischneri</italic> species, &#x02663; <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species group.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Isolation</title><p>For isolation of leptospira, the serum/blood/urine samples that were collected from the suspected animal were inoculated (1&#x02013;2 drops) directly to the transport EMJH medium containing 500 &#x003bc;g of 5-fluorouracil per mL in the field level laboratory or veterinary dispensary or on the site of collection and transported to the laboratory at room temperature. Samples received from the messenger or by post either in the transport medium for isolation or submission of serum/blood samples on ice pack for diagnosis of leptospirosis, upon receipt all the samples were stored at 4&#x000b0;C and were further used when required. It was directly inoculated into EMJH medium for isolation. The collected urine, tissue/kidney and fetal fluid/tissues were transported to laboratory either on ice pack or on transport medium, upon receipt the particular pieces of tissues especially kidney were rinsed thoroughly in media and teased the cortex and medulla region with sterile needle using media and suspension was prepared by mincing the specimen in pestle and mortar in biosafety cabinet and inoculated into culture medium containing 5-fluorouracil for isolation of leptospira organism and to prevent contamination of other bacteria. After incubation at 30&#x000b0;C in the laboratory for 4&#x02013;5 days, the culture were filtered through 0.2 &#x003bc;m membrane filter and subcultured periodically from 8 to 10 weeks. On successful isolation the cultures were stored in the semisolid EMJH medium for long-term storage as archived culture with periodical subculturing every 2 to 3 months for the viability of the organism.</p><p>In this study, 191 archived culture isolates from the samples that were collected from various hosts (Human-31; Cattle-82; Buffalo-11; Goat-11; Horse-8; Rat-25; Elephant-1; Dog-16 and water bodies-6), from different geographical locations of the country were taken for analysis to identify the isolated organisms initially as leptospira and further to characterize the pathogenic culture up to species level. These stored archived individual culture were revived again in liquid medium, for isolation of DNA for its molecular characterization along with the leptospira reference culture in liquid medium as the agarose present in the semi solid media will interfere in the pelleting of the leptospira organisms.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Identification of the causative agent by PCR</title><p>Genomic DNA was extracted from these cultures along with reference culture serovars using QIamp DNA mini kit (Qiagen, Germany) as per manufacturer&#x02019;s procedure. Initially, <italic>Leptospira</italic> genus-specific PCR was carried out using reported Lept 1 and Lept 2 primers as per method described by Merien et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1992</xref>) to differentiate the leptospira from other spirochetes. Then, 16S rRNA gene-based PCR using E1 and E2 primers was performed which would amplify the 571 bp amplicon from pathogenic leptospira (Faber et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2000</xref>). Then, <italic>secY</italic> gene (translocase)-based PCR was also employed using the G1 and G2 primer set, which would amplify the 285 bp product from pathogenic <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. (Gravekamp et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1993</xref>). Further, pathogenic isolates were characterized by <italic>rpoB</italic> gene-specific PCR, which was carried out using reported <italic>rpoB</italic> Lept 1,900f and 2,500r primers to amplify the partial gene sequences (&#x02248;600 bp product) for species identification (La Scola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2006</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Cloning, sequencing and phylogenetic analysis</title><p>The <italic>rpoB</italic> PCR amplicons were purified using QIA quick gel extraction Kit (Qiagen, Germany) as per manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol and cloned into pGEM-T Easy vector (Promega, USA) following standard molecular procedures using Top10F&#x02019; <italic>E. coli</italic> host. The recombinant plasmid DNA was isolated and confirmed by PCR and restriction endonuclease analysis. The sequencing of plasmid was carried out commercially in an automated DNA sequencer. Nucleotide (nt) sequence analysis was performed with published <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequences of other <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. by using NCBI BLAST (Altschul et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1997</xref>). Further, comparative analysis of nt sequences were carried out by using the clustal W program alignment in MEGALIGN of Lasergene 6.0 (DNASTAR Inc., USA) package and sequence identity among all intermediate species was determined.</p><p>Phylogenetic tree was constructed based on partial nucleotide sequences of <italic>rpoB</italic> gene by using Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) version 4 (Tamura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2007</xref>). The alignment gaps were excluded from pair wise distance estimations. The tree topologies were evaluated by using bootstrap test of phylogeny in the neighbor-joining method and the bootstrap P-values were obtained after 1000 replicates of the dataset. The tree is drawn to scale, with branch lengths in the same units as those of the evolutionary distances used to infer the phylogenetic tree. The bootstrap consensus tree inferred from 1000 replicates was taken to represent the evolutionary history of the isolates analyzed. Branches corresponding to partitions reproduced in less than 50% bootstrap replicates were collapsed. The percentage of replicate trees in which the associated isolates clustered together in the bootstrap test were shown next to the branches. The evolutionary distances were computed using the Maximum Composite Likelihood (MCL) method and were in the units of the number of base substitutions per site. For comparison, available <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequences of <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp<italic>.</italic> were retrieved from GenBank, NCBI database for identifying the species of isolates, which clustered in to respective genenomospecies of the <italic>Leptospira</italic> genus.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Results and discussion</title><p>Several molecular techniques have been evaluated for the identification and characterization of <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. and DNA&#x02013;DNA hybridization identified 20 <italic>Leptospira</italic> species to date with nine pathogenic <italic>Leptospira</italic> species (Cerqueira and Picardeau <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2009</xref>). This species assignment is consistent with the results of the phylogenetic analysis based on the <italic>rrs (16S)</italic> gene, which codes for the 16S rRNA (Postic et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2000</xref>). La Scola et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2003</xref>) reported that analysis of a segment of <italic>rpoB</italic> may be useful as an initial screening test for the identification of a new isolate of leptospira using a system of similarity cut-off to define species. This technique may be useful for the detection as well as identification of leptospira in clinical or environmental samples but not for serovar determination in <italic>L. interrogans</italic> species (La Scola et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2006</xref>).</p><p>In this study, out of 191 revived cultures, 99 were found positive in leptospira genus-specific PCR. The remaining 92 cultures may be other spirochete organisms namely <italic>Borrelia, Treponema, Leptonema,</italic> etc., as these organism looks like a spiral under dark field microscopy examination and staining (Gangadhar and Rajashekar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1998</xref>; Gangadhar et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2005</xref>). Of these 99 positive leptospira cultures, 52 isolates were identified as pathogenic, when tested by different type of PCR assays as described in materials and methods. These 52 isolates were further characterized by <italic>rpoB</italic> gene-based nucleotide sequences and phylogenetic analyses, which revealed the prevalence of four <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. {<italic>L. borgpetersenii</italic> or <italic>L. interrogans</italic> (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;30), <italic>L. kirschneri</italic> (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;8) and <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species group (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;14)} from animals and humans in India. <italic>Leptospira</italic> genus-specific PCR amplified 331bp products from the leptospira organism and different PCR assays detected 52 pathogenic organism, which also gave expected size of the PCR products from pathogenic isolates as described earlier. The remaining 47 culture isolates might be non pathogenic leptospira, which may require further study to classify these isolates using complete 16S rRNA sequencing. Further, <italic>rpoB</italic> gene-specific amplicons were cloned into plasmid vector, characterized and sequenced. The characterized leptospira isolates were from different species (Human-10; Cattle-21; Buffalo-4; Goat-5; Rat-7; Elephant-1; Dog-4). The partial <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequences of the leptospira isolates were obtained (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) after editing the primer sequences and submitted to the GenBank database (HM046989 to HM046997; JN388615 to JN388667).</p><p>By sequence analysis, the isolates showed identity with published sequences of various leptospires. <italic>L. interrogans</italic> was the most prevalent species among the examined samples of human and animals. In general, isolates belonging to either <italic>L. interrogans</italic>/<italic>L. borgpetersenii</italic> species showed 99 to 100% identity with reported sequences<italic>.</italic> Similarly, isolates belonging to <italic>L. kirschneri</italic> species had 98&#x02013;99% identity. However, isolates belonging to intermediate species showed only 77.9% to 78.3% and 78.1 to 78.5% identity with reported sequences of <italic>L. inadai</italic> and <italic>L. fainei</italic> species, respectively. La Scola et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2006</xref>) described the convention of identification in practice ie., if the partial <italic>rpoB</italic> similarity of a test isolate or strain is lower than 92%, it should be regarded as a new species. If such a value goes above 97%, then the isolate under scrutiny should be regarded as being representative of a known species. Surprisingly, 14 isolates belonging to intermediate species group showed identities from 99.1 to 99.6% with only one leptospira strain so far reported from Thailand {<italic>L. wolffii</italic> serovar Khorat strain Khorat-H2 sequence-NZ_AKWX02000023} (Slack et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2008</xref>). This molecular characterization indicates prevalence of the <italic>L. wolffii</italic> intermediate species in India. In India, earlier sporadic human case reports with <italic>L. inadai</italic> infection and circulation of <italic>L. inadai</italic> in reservoir hosts have been reported (Gangadhar et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>).</p><p>Further, phylogenetic analysis (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) of 52 isolates based on <italic>rpoB</italic> gene nucleotide sequences revealed that 30 isolates belong to either <italic>L. interrogans</italic> or <italic>L. borgpetersenii</italic> species and eight belongs to <italic>L. kirschneri</italic> species. However, clustering of 14 leptospira isolates branched into a separate group under intermediate species (namely <italic>L. wolffii</italic> species). Surprisingly, when analyzing in MEGALIGN, these isolates branch into a separate group under <italic>L. wolffii</italic> species and showed two to three different branching pattern within this group namely 8 isolates in one branch, 4 isolates in another and 2 isolates (ADMAS No. 2779 and 3334) in other separate branches. This may clearly indicate some of the isolates, which belong to particular serovars among this species. This is to be confirmed by further analysis using the referral panel of antigen and antibodies procuring from world reference laboratory.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Phylogenetic tree showing clustering of</bold><bold><italic>Leptospira</italic></bold><bold>constructed based on the nucleotide sequence of partial</bold><bold><italic>rpoB</italic></bold><bold>gene by bootstrap test of phylogeny using neighbor-joining method in MEGA-4 program.</bold> The values of major clusters are indicated in the <italic>node or branch</italic> in tree, which represent the bootstrap confidence tested on using 1000 replicates of the data set. Bar represents the genetic distance i.e., number of substitutions per site.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="40064_2013_426_Fig1_HTML" id="d30e1428"/></fig></p><p>Based on the present study, the major prevalent pathogenic species of <italic>Leptospira</italic> in animals and human were <italic>L. borgpetersenii / L. interrogans</italic> (30.3%)<italic>,</italic> intermediate species (14.14%) and <italic>L. krischneri</italic> (8%) in India. Similarly, in the bovine population, the percentage prevalence of aforementioned species among pathogenic isolates was 56% (14/25), 36% (9/25) and 8% (2/25), respectively. In Karnataka, the prevalence rate of these species among pathogenic isolates was found to be 62.25% (15/24), 25% (6/24) and 12.5% (3/24), respectively (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The intermediate species requires further study to determine the exact serovars or new species, as recently more classification of new isolates was made for this intermediate species (Levett et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2006</xref>; Matthias et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2008</xref>). Similarly, <italic>L. wolffii</italic>, a potential pathogenic leptospira species detected in human, sheep and dog as intermediate species (Slack et al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2008</xref>; Zakeri et. al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2010a</xref><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">b</xref>). The presence of <italic>L. wolffii</italic> with 100% identity in clinical human samples and animals suspected with leptospira may provide evidence for circulation of <italic>L. wolffii</italic> and its role in transmission cycle within human and animal hosts in Iran (Zakeri et. al., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2010a</xref>). To establish the possible seroprevalence of this species in the population, the inclusion of intermediate species serovars representative of all the serogroups in the panel of leptospira cultural serovars besides regular serovars used in MAT for seroepidemiological studies in animals and humans as recommended earlier (Gangadhar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>Characterized</bold><bold><italic>Leptospira</italic></bold><bold>species from animals and humans in different states of India</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>State</th><th>Species</th><th><bold><italic>L. borgpetersenii or L. interrogans</italic></bold>species</th><th><bold><italic>Leptospira</italic></bold>intermediate species</th><th><bold><italic>L. krischneri</italic></bold>species</th><th>Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="4">Karnataka</td><td>Cattle</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">6</td></tr><tr><td>Buffalo</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td>Human</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">10</td></tr><tr><td>Rodents</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Gujarat</td><td>Cattle</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">5</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">9</td></tr><tr><td>Buffalo</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td>Dog</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4">Maharashtra</td><td>Cattle</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td>Buffalo</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td></tr><tr><td>Dog</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td>Goat</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">5</td></tr><tr><td>Goa</td><td>Cattle</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">3</td></tr><tr><td>Kerala</td><td>Elephant</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Cattle</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td>Assam</td><td>Dog</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">1</td></tr><tr><td/><td><bold>Total</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>30</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>14</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>8</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>52</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p><p>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to use <italic>rpoB</italic> gene-based phylogenetic analysis to identify or detect <italic>Leptospira</italic> intermediate species in animals and humans in India. Isolation and characterization of leptospires from the samples collected from different hosts, clearly suggested a possible leptospiral infection / or carrier status. Isolation of leptospires from blood samples of cows with either history of abortions or reproductive disorders does not necessarily incriminate leptospira as the etiology of the disorder but only serve as a possible indicator to the existence of the infection. Role of leptospira infection in abortions and reproductive disorders is well established by earlier workers including our earlier studies (Ellis et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1976</xref>; Poonacha et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1993</xref>; Gangadhar et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2008</xref>). Infected cattle are known to be maintenance host resulting in illness leading to abortion, stillbirth, infertility and mastitis or clinically normal but harbour infection and act as a potential source of infection (Higgins et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1980</xref>).</p><p>Leptospira and its maintenance hosts appear to undergo adaptation to their environment, and the preference and pathogenicity of these hosts can change with time and geographic region. Transmission of the infection among maintenance hosts (which remains largely asymptomatic) is efficient and the incidence of infection in humans are relatively high as they are incidental hosts or accidental hosts (which develop clinical disease). Because of the wide spectrum of animal species that serve as reservoirs/maintenance hosts, leptospirosis is considered as the most widely spread zoonotic disease.</p><p>The significance of intermediate species in public health and animal reproduction is neither clearly understood nor documented much in literature. It is imperative to identify the species prevalence as well as to know the pathogenic nature and its virulence factors, drug resistance etc. In order to understand the newly emerging leptospira in animals and humans by employing various techniques and to combat the problem associated with the disease conditions. Further studies should be carried out on characterization, identification by pulse field gel electrophoresis and hybridization techniques and pathological studies using hamster model in order to identify the exact <italic>Leptospira</italic> species.</p><p>The disease is of public health importance and warrants bio-safety measures in handling the organism and/or disease. Prevalence of intermediate species identified, will surely emphasize the importance of consideration of this species in India for further studies especially to understand the newly emerging leptospira in animals and humans and to combat the problem associated with the disease conditions if any. Therefore, it is important to increase attention about this disease among physicians and to strengthen laboratory capacity for its diagnosis. However, systematic random screening of the samples from different animals and at-risk personnel is required to know the exact prevalence rate in particular geographical locality, which again depends on the various epidemiological factors influencing leptospirosis occurrence and its spread. This could be useful in the selection of panel of serovars to be used in the MAT at different geographical location to provide proper diagnosis in animals and humans, which in turn will lead to development of specific diagnostics and also to determine the exact prevalence of leptospirosis in different species. Further, a large systematic epidemiology survey would be needed to define the presence and the prevalence of this pathogenic intermediate species in endemic regions of India.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Competing interests</bold></p><p>The authors declares that they have no competing interests.</p></fn><fn><p><bold>Authors&#x02019; contributions</bold></p><p>VB and NM-conceptualized and planned the study. VB designed and performed the work, molecular genetic studies, participated in the sequence alignment and drafted the manuscript. NLG -samples collection, isolation and revival of culture isolates of leptospira. SRAT and MD- PCR amplification and cloning of the <italic>rpoB</italic> gene sequences from revived culture isolates. RS and PK-cataloguing and revival of culture isolates of leptospira. KP and HR -guided the research throughout the study and arranged facility to complete this work. VB and NM wrote and revised the paper and approved the submission of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Authors wish to thank Deputy Director General (Animal Sciences) and Assistant Director General (Animal Health), Indian Council of Agricultural Research (ICAR), New Delhi, India, for financial support and encouragement. The authors also thank the Directors of the state Animal Husbandry Departments and human hospitals for sending the samples to the PD_ADMAS for providing diagnosis of leptopsirosis. The authors also thank Dr. P.Vijayachari, Director, Regional Medical Research Centre (ICMR), Port Blair, for providing the leptospira reference cultures and also for his constant support and encouragement.</p></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>AA</surname><given-names>S a</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>3389</fpage><lpage>3402</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/25.17.3389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bharti</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nally</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricaldi</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovett</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Willig</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotuzzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinetz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospirosis: a zoonotic disease of global importance</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>3</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(03)00830-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14652202</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerqueira</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Picardeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A century of Leptospira strain typing</article-title><source>Infect Genet Evol</source><year>2009</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>760</fpage><lpage>768</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2009.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19540362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerqueira</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>AJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Picardeau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellagostin</surname><given-names>OA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of the Leptospiral immunoglobulinlike (Lig) genes in pathogenic Leptospira spp. and application of ligB to typing leptospiral isolates</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2009</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1173</fpage><lpage>1181</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.009175-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19528180</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The present status of leptospirosis diagnosis and control</article-title><source>The diagnosis of Leptospirosis in farm animals</source><year>1986</year><publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Martinous Nijhoff publishers</publisher-name><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>31</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Obrien</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Neill</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Henna</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The isolation of a <italic>Leptospira</italic> from an aborted fetus</article-title><source>Vet Rec</source><year>1976</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.99.23.458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">997199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faber</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>LeFebvre</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Buyukmihci</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Madigan</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Willits</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of <italic>Leptospira spp.</italic> in the aqueous humor of horses with naturally acquired recurrent uveitis</article-title><source>J Clinic Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>38</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>2731</fpage><lpage>2733</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajasekhar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohnt</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reservoir hosts of <italic>Leptospira</italic> inadai in India</article-title><source>Rev Sci Tech OIE</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>793</fpage><lpage>799</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajashekar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified silver impregnation staining for <italic>Leptospira</italic></article-title><source>Indian Vet J</source><year>1998</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>351</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhudas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhushan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sulthana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbuddhe</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rhaman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Leptospira</italic> infection in animals and humans: a potential public health risk in India</article-title><source>Rev Sci Tech OIE</source><year>2008</year><volume>27</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>892</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhudas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gajendragad</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Shashibhushan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kakoli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospirosis: an enigma of Zoonosis for the developing world</article-title><source>Infect Dis J Pakistan</source><year>2006</year><volume>15</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gangadhar</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rajasekhar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Prabhudas</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation of Leptonema from rodents and cattle in India</article-title><source>Indian J Anim Science</source><year>2005</year><volume>75</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>508</fpage><lpage>510</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gravekamp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Van de Kemp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Franzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoone</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Eys</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Everard</surname><given-names>CO</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartskeerl</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Terpstra</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of seven species of pathogenic leptospires by PCR using two sets of primers</article-title><source>J Gen Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>1691</fpage><lpage>1700</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-139-8-1691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8409911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hartskeerl</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goris</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopp</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerhards</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wollanke</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of leptospira from the eyes of horses suffering from recurrent uveitis</article-title><source>J Vet Med B</source><year>2004</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0450.2004.00740.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbourne</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>TWA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mastitis and abortion in dairy cattle associated with <italic>Leptospira</italic> of the serotype hardjo</article-title><source>Vet Rec</source><year>1980</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/vr.107.13.307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7210429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Scola</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Khamis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Partial rpoB gene sequencing for identification of <italic>Leptospira</italic> species</article-title><source>FEMS Microbiol Lett</source><year>2006</year><volume>263</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.2006.00377.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978348</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>La Scola</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeaiter</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Khamis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene-sequence-based criteria for species definition in bacteriology: the Bartonella paradigm</article-title><source>Trends Microbiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>11</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>318</fpage><lpage>321</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0966-842X(03)00143-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12875815</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospirosis</article-title><source>Clinic Microbiol Rev</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>326</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.14.2.296-326.2001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Morey</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Steigerwalt</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospira broomii sp. nov., isolated from humans with leptospirosis</article-title><source>Int J Syst Evol Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>56</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>671</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.63783-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16514048</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matthias</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricaldi</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Cespedes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Saito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Steigerwalt</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Patra</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ore</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotuzzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilman</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Levett</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Vinetz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human leptospirosis caused by a new, antigenically unique <italic>Leptospira</italic> associated with a Rattus species reservoir in the Peruvian Amazon</article-title><source>PLoS Negligible Tropical Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merien</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Amouriauz</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perolat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saint Girons</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polymerase chain reaction for detection of <italic>Leptospira</italic> spp. in clinical samples</article-title><source>J Clinic Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>2219</fpage><lpage>2224</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paster</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dewhirst</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisburg</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Tordoff</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fraser</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hespell</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zablen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandelco</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Woese</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of the spirochetes</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1991</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>6101</fpage><lpage>6109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1917844</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poonacha</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrites-murphy</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Swerczek</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tramont</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuttle</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospires in equine fetuses, stillborn foals and placentas</article-title><source>Vet Pathol</source><year>1993</year><volume>30</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/030098589303000405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8212458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Postic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Riquelme-Sertour</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Merien</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Perolat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baranton</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interest of partial 16S rDNA gene sequences to resolve heterogeneities between Leptospira collections: application to <italic>L. meyeri</italic></article-title><source>Res Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>151</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0923-2508(00)00156-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10919513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalambaheti</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohnt</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Galloway</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Steigerwalt</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaicumpa</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunyaraksyotin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Harrower</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospira wolffii sp. nov., isolated from a human with suspected leptospirosis in Thailand</article-title><source>Int J System Evol Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>2305</fpage><lpage>2308</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/ijs.0.64947-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18842846</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Symonds</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Dohnt</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Smythe</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of pathogenic Leptospira species by conventional or real-time PCR and sequencing of the DNA gyrase subunit B encoding gene</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>95</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-6-95</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17067399</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinen</surname><given-names>ACM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuurman</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gravekamp</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Korver</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Terpstra</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Muskrats as carriers of pathogenic leptospires in The Netherlands</article-title><source>Anton Van Leeuwonhook</source><year>1992</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00572121</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2007</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1596</fpage><lpage>1599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msm092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17488738</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Terpstra</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Korver</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Leeuwen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Klatser</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolk</surname><given-names>AHJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The classification of Sejroe group serovars of Leptospira interrogans with monoclonal antibodies</article-title><source>Zentralbl Bakteriol Mikrobiol Hygiene</source><year>1985</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>498</fpage><lpage>506</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zakeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Khorami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganji</surname><given-names>ZF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepahian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Malmasi</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouya</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Djadid</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leptospira wolffii, a potential new pathogenic Leptospira species detected in human, sheep and dog</article-title><source>Infect Genet Evol</source><year>2010</year><volume>10</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>277</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.meegid.2010.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20074666</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zakeri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sepahian</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Afsharpad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Esfandiari</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziapour</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Djadid</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular epidemiology of leptospirosis in northern Iran by nested polymerase chain reaction/restriction fragment length polymorphism and sequencing methods</article-title><source>American J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>2010</year><volume>82</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>899</fpage><lpage>903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2010.09-0721</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>