<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1474-7596</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1474-760X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4901439</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-016-0990-4</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Functional genomics analyses of RNA-binding proteins reveal the splicing regulator SNRPB as an oncogenic candidate in glioblastoma</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>Bruna R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Araujo</surname><given-names>Patricia Rosa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qiao</surname><given-names>Mei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Burns</surname><given-names>Suzanne C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schlegel</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>Seema</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Galante</surname><given-names>Pedro A. F.</given-names></name><address><email>pgalante@mochsl.org.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Penalva</surname><given-names>Luiz O. F.</given-names></name><address><email>penalva@uthscsa.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label/>Centro de Oncologia Molecular, Hospital S&#x000ed;rio-Liban&#x000ea;s, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label/>Children&#x02019;s Cancer Research Institute, UTHSCSA, San Antonio, TX USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label/>Georgetown University Medical Center, Washington, DC USA </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label/>Department of Cellular and Structural Biology, UTHSCSA, San Antonio, TX USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>17</volume><elocation-id>125</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2016</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p>Glioblastoma (GBM) is the most common and aggressive type of brain tumor. Currently, GBM has an extremely poor outcome and there is no effective treatment. In this context, genomic and transcriptomic analyses have become important tools to identify new avenues for therapies. RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) are master regulators of co- and post-transcriptional events; however, their role in GBM remains poorly understood. To further our knowledge of novel regulatory pathways that could contribute to gliomagenesis, we have conducted a systematic study of RBPs in GBM.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>By measuring expression levels of 1542 human RBPs in GBM samples and glioma stem cell samples, we identified 58 consistently upregulated RBPs. Survival analysis revealed that increased expression of 21 RBPs was also associated with a poor prognosis. To assess the functional impact of those RBPs, we modulated their expression in GBM cell lines and performed viability, proliferation, and apoptosis assays. Combined results revealed a prominent oncogenic candidate, <italic>SNRPB</italic>, which encodes core spliceosome machinery components. To reveal the impact of SNRPB on splicing and gene expression, we performed its knockdown in a GBM cell line followed by RNA sequencing. We found that the affected genes were involved in RNA processing, DNA repair, and chromatin remodeling. Additionally, genes and pathways already associated with gliomagenesis, as well as a set of general cancer genes, also presented with splicing and expression alterations.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Our study provides new insights into how RBPs, and specifically SNRPB, regulate gene expression and directly impact GBM development.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s13059-016-0990-4) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>RNA-binding proteins</kwd><kwd>Glioblastoma</kwd><kwd>Glioma stem cells</kwd><kwd>SNRPB</kwd><kwd>Splicing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100001807</institution-id><institution>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de S&#x000e3;o Paulo</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>2013/25483-4</award-id><award-id>2013/07159-5</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Correa</surname><given-names>Bruna R.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100003593</institution-id><institution>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>400262/2014-2</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Galante</surname><given-names>Pedro A. F.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100004917</institution-id><institution>Cancer Prevention and Research Institute of Texas</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>RP140105</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>de Araujo</surname><given-names>Patricia Rosa</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</institution-id><institution>National Institutes of Health</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>5R21CA205475-02</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Penalva</surname><given-names>Luiz O. F.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Background</title><p>Glioblastoma (GBM) is the most common and lethal tumor type of the central nervous system, with 16,000 new cases per year in the US alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. GBM is highly heterogenic, invasive, and refractory to the current standard of care, which is a combination of surgical resection, adjuvant radiotherapy, and temozolomide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Despite decades of research, the overall outcome for patients with GBM remains extremely poor, with an average survival of approximately 15 months after diagnosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p>To identify new targets for therapy, The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) consortium produced a comprehensive somatic landscape of GBM through a set of genomic, epigenomic, transcriptomic, and proteomic analyses, combining molecular and clinical data for 543 patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. These analyses have improved our understanding of GBM pathobiology, emphasizing that gliomagenesis is driven by signaling networks with functional redundancy, which allows adaptation in response to therapy. Because novel therapeutic strategies based on these findings have not yet become a reality, it is necessary to investigate additional pathways of gene deregulation in GBM. Equally important is the study of glioma stem cells (GSCs), which are particularly relevant to tumor initiation and resistance to treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Unveiling individual genes and pathways that contribute to GSC survival and phenotype maintenance might enable the design of novel therapeutic strategies against GBM.</p><p>RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) are master regulators of co- and post-transcriptional mechanisms, including RNA processing (splicing, capping, and polyadenylation), transport, decay, localization, and translation. They are still a poorly characterized class of regulators, with hundreds of new members only recently identified via novel experimental high-throughput approaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The most updated human RBP catalog includes 1542 genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], which represents ~7.5 % of human coding genes (GENCODE version 19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]). Mutations and alterations in RBP expression levels, which have been observed in many tumor tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], are known to impact large gene sets and to contribute to tumor initiation and growth. In fact, numerous well-characterized RBPs such as HuR, Musashi1, Sam68, and eIF4E have been implicated in multiple tumor types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In the context of neural tissue, the number of tissue-specific RBPs and alternative splicing isoforms is particularly high compared with other tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Hence, RBPs play key roles in this biological context and their alteration is expected to be a major contributor to gliomagenesis. Some important players include Musashi1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], HuR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], hnRNP proteins (H and A2/B1) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and PTB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].</p><p>In order to identify novel RBPs potentially implicated in GBM development, we conducted a combination of transcriptomic analyses followed by functional screenings. We found 58 genes with oncogenic potential, defined as those with high expression in GBM and GSC samples relative to their normal counterparts. Twenty-one of these genes are also associated with a poor prognosis and were further selected for functional analyses. <italic>SNRPB</italic>, which encodes core components of the spliceosome complex SmB/B&#x02019;, showed the strongest impact on viability, proliferation, and apoptosis. We determined that changes in SNRPB expression levels have a large impact on expression and splicing regulation and preferentially affect alternative exons and introns. RNA processing, DNA repair, and chromatin remodeling are among the biological processes with the highest number of genes affected by SNRPB at expression and splicing levels. Moreover, several genes in pathways relevant to GBM initiation and development, such as <italic>RTK</italic>, <italic>PI3K</italic>, <italic>RAS</italic>, <italic>MAPK</italic>, <italic>AKT</italic>, <italic>RB</italic>, and <italic>p53</italic>, as well as a set of additional cancer genes, displayed alterations in their splicing and expression profiles upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Several RBPs are aberrantly expressed in GBM and GSCs</title><p>To identify RBPs potentially involved in GBM development, we examined the expression profiles of all 1542 human catalogued RBP coding genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] in two different contexts: GBM samples from TCGA versus normal brain; and GSCs versus normal neural progenitor cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). We obtained raw RNA sequencing (RNA-Seq) data for 170 GBM samples from TCGA database (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1) and compared them with 14 normal brain samples: eight samples from two studies available in the Sequence Read Archive (SRA), one sample from the Human Body Map, and five samples from TCGA (see &#x02018;Methods&#x02019;; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). This approach allowed the identification of 223 upregulated and 135 downregulated RBPs in tumors compared to normal samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref> top panel; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S2). Next, we looked at the expression of these differentially expressed RBPs, classifying all samples according to the four molecular GBM subtypes (classical, neural, proneural, and mesenchymal) to identify particular associations (if any). Results indicated that the overall expression profile was very similar among subtypes, with no differentially expressed RBPs showing drastic changes across subtypes (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S1).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Experimental design and RNA-binding protein (<italic>RBP</italic>) expression profile in glioblastoma (<italic>GBM</italic>) and glioma stem cells (<italic>GSCs</italic>). <bold>a</bold> Gene expression results from GBM and GSC samples were combined to identify upregulated RBPs. Those RBPs were evaluated regarding their association with survival decrease, and their functional impact in GBM was assayed by a set of functional assays. <bold>b</bold> Heatmaps show all differentially expressed RBPs in GBM samples from The Cancer Genome Atlas compared to normal brain samples and in GSC samples compared to a normal neural progenitor cell line. <bold>c</bold> Venn diagram shows the intersection between gene expression analyses</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_990_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p><p>GSCs constitute a unique subpopulation within the tumor and display features similar to normal stem cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Their association with tumor relapse is often linked to their tumor-initiating capacity as well as radio- and chemoresistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Therefore, identifying regulators that maintain GSC phenotypes and/or contribute to their survival is critical for designing novel therapeutic strategies. We examined the microarray dataset of Mao et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] to identify differentially expressed RBPs in GSCs in comparison to normal neural progenitor cells. This analysis revealed a total of 275 upregulated and 85 downregulated RBPs in GSCs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref> bottom panel; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S3).</p><p>We focused next on the identification of &#x0201c;pro-oncogenic RBPs.&#x0201d; We selected these RBPs because they tend to be more attractive targets in therapeutic contexts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and they are easier to handle in screening studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Results from both transcriptomic studies were merged: 58 genes were determined to be upregulated in both GBM and GSC samples (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>), which represents a highly significant overlap (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0006; hypergeometric test). Those 58 genes were selected for further analyses.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Upregulation of RBPs is associated with decreased survival and is prevalent in higher grade gliomas</title><p>To determine whether our set of 58 pro-oncogenic RBPs exhibits an association with poor prognosis in gliomas, we used clinical and expression data from the REMBRANDT database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. We built Kaplan-Meier survival curves comparing samples with increased expression of the selected RBPs to all other samples. Twenty-one out of the 58 upregulated RBPs showed an association with survival reduction when overexpressed (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; log-rank test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S2). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> presents a summary of the selected RBPs and their results in survival analysis.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Candidates&#x02019; selection and characterization. <bold>a</bold> Circos plot shows 58 upregulated RNA-binding proteins (<italic>RBPs</italic>) in glioblastoma (<italic>GBM</italic>) samples from The Cancer Genome Atlas (<italic>TCGA</italic>) and glioma stem cell (<italic>GSC</italic>) lines. Fold-changes and corrected <italic>p</italic>-values were extracted from the RNA-Seq analysis (<italic>GBM TCGA</italic>). Twenty-one RBPs were also associated with survival reduction and were further investigated. <bold>b</bold> RBPs exhibited higher expression levels in GBMs compared with lower grade gliomas</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_990_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p><p>We also evaluated gene expression levels of these RBPs using a large cohort of normal brain samples generated by the Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) Project [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. By comparing expression levels of the 21 RBPs in 222 normal brain samples from GTEx with 170 GBM samples from TCGA, we were able to confirm the overexpression of our selected RBPs in GBM samples (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S4).</p><p>Finally, to corroborate the relevance of these 21 selected RBPs in an additional context, we evaluated their expression levels in 167 GBM samples (grade IV glioma) versus 218 lower grade glioma samples (grades II and III astrocytomas and oligodendrogliomas) from TCGA. In general, analyzed RBPs exhibited higher expression levels in GBM samples than in lower grade glioma samples (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S5). The only exception was RNASET2, which presented no significant difference in one comparison (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1428 for GBMs versus grade III astrocytomas; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S5).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Analysis of regulatory elements potentially triggering overexpression of RBPs in GBM</title><p>To try to identify mechanisms responsible for the upregulation of RBPs in tumor samples, we evaluated whether the 21 selected RBPs are targeted by frequently downregulated miRNAs in GBM (tumor suppressor miRNAs). Using a list of tumor suppressor miRNAs compiled by Hermansen and Kristensen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>], we found that 18 of those miRNAs potentially target 15 out of the 21 RBPs. We observed a significant enrichment for miR-124, which presented the highest number of targets: six RBPs in total (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0099; hypergeometric test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S3).</p><p>We also evaluated whether the 21 RBPs presented mutations and/or copy-number alterations (CNA) in GBM samples from TCGA. We analyzed 273 GBM samples with exome sequencing and CNA data available in cBioPortal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Only 10 % of the samples displayed alterations in at least one of our selected RBPs. CNA, missense mutations, and/or truncating mutations were present in 17 out of 21 evaluated RBPs, not different from randomly selected RBPs sets (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.1; simulation with 100,000 sets of 21 randomly selected RBPs; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S4).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>RBPs impact cellular viability, proliferation, and apoptosis in GBM</title><p>The 21 selected RBPs were then evaluated in a functional screening. Transient knockdowns were performed with siRNAs (median knockdown efficiency ~90 %; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S6) in U251 and U343 GBM cells and their impact on viability (MTS assay), proliferation (IncuCyte), and apoptosis (Caspase-3/7 assay) were evaluated. Results of these three assays are summarized in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and represented in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figures S5&#x02013;S7. Out of the 21 investigated RBPs, 15 showed significant effect in at least one assay in one or both cell lines.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of functional assays results</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">#</th><th rowspan="2">Ensemble ID</th><th rowspan="2">Gene symbol</th><th colspan="2">Viability (MTS)</th><th colspan="2">Proliferation (IncuCyte)</th><th colspan="2">Apoptosis (Caspase-3/7)</th></tr><tr><th>U251</th><th>U343</th><th>U251</th><th>U343</th><th>U251</th><th>U343</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>ENSG00000106305</td><td>
<italic>AIMP2</italic>
</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>ENSG00000183684</td><td>
<italic>ALYREF</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>ENSG00000179218</td><td>
<italic>CALR</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>ENSG00000174371</td><td>
<italic>EXO1</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>ENSG00000172183</td><td>
<italic>ISG20</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>ENSG00000162385</td><td>
<italic>MAGOH</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>ENSG00000111196</td><td>
<italic>MAGOHB</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>ENSG00000128626</td><td>
<italic>MRPS12</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>ENSG00000090263</td><td>
<italic>MRPS33</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>ENSG00000132603</td><td>
<italic>NIP7</italic>
</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>ENSG00000132661</td><td>
<italic>NXT1</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>ENSG00000111331</td><td>
<italic>OAS3</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>ENSG00000171960</td><td>
<italic>PPIH</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>ENSG00000153250</td><td>
<italic>RBMS1</italic>
</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>15</td><td>ENSG00000104889</td><td>
<italic>RNASEH2A</italic>
</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>16</td><td>ENSG00000026297</td><td>
<italic>RNASET2</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>17</td><td>ENSG00000175792</td><td>
<italic>RUVBL1</italic>
</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>18</td><td>ENSG00000125835</td><td>
<italic>SNRPB</italic>
</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td></tr><tr><td>19</td><td>ENSG00000143977</td><td>
<italic>SNRPG</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>20</td><td>ENSG00000060138</td><td>
<italic>YBX3</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>21</td><td>ENSG00000088930</td><td>
<italic>XRN2</italic>
</td><td>-</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>&#x02713;</td><td>-</td><td>-</td><td>-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x02713;&#x02009;=&#x02009;significant difference compared to control (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p><p>-&#x02009;=&#x02009;no significant difference compared to control (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;0.05)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title><italic>SNRPB</italic> as a potential new oncogenic candidate in GBM</title><p>Overall, <italic>SNRPB</italic>, which encodes core spliceosome components SmB/B&#x02019;, exhibited the most consistent results in the functional screening: knockdown of this gene decreased viability (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a</xref>), increased apoptosis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b</xref>), and decreased proliferation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>) in both U251 and U343 cell lines.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>
<italic>SNRPB</italic> impacts cancer-relevant processes. <bold>a</bold> Cellular viability was assayed by MTS and shows that <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown caused a significant reduction of viability in U251 (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002; Wilcoxon rank-sum test) and U343 cells (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; Wilcoxon rank-sum test), compared to control transfected cell lines (<italic>siCtrl</italic>). <bold>b</bold> Caspase-3/7 assay shows an increase in apoptosis in siSNRPB compared to siCtrl in both cell lines (U251 <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.011; U343 <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.007; Wilcoxon rank-sum test). <bold>c</bold> Plots show confluence percentage monitored by IncuCyte over 96 hours, comparing siSNRPB with siCtrl. Proliferation reduction was observed in both cell lines upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown (U251 <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; U343 <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; ANOVA). <italic>Right</italic> panel shows U251 cellular profile at time zero and after 96 hours of transfection with siCtrl and siSNRPB. <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown resulted in a strong reduction in cell proliferation compared to control. <bold>d</bold> Downregulation of <italic>SNRPB</italic> by siRNA leads to inhibition of cell growth and cell detachment in two glioma stem cell lines. The percentage of the normalized cell index was calculated with respect to control. Results represent an average of two (line 326) or three (line 83) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] individual experiments and each experiment was done in triplicate. <italic>Red arrowheads</italic> indicate the floated round up cell colonies on the plates where <italic>SNRPB</italic> siRNA was transfected. <bold>e</bold>
<italic>SNRPB</italic> expression in mouse neural stem cells (<italic>NSCs</italic>) was compared to differentiated neural cells after 4 days by RNA-Seq. <italic>SNRPB</italic> expression was higher in undifferentiated cells (log<sub>2</sub> fold change&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.599347, FDR-adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_990_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p><p>We conducted additional experiments to determine the impact of <italic>SNRPB</italic> on the growth of GSC cultures. Lines 326 and 83 were described in a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. We knocked down the expression of <italic>SNRPB</italic> in these two GSC lines grown as conditionally reprogrammed cells (CRCs). CRCs have been shown to better recapitulate the characteristics of original tumor cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. In both cell lines, <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown led to inhibition of cell growth and to cell detachment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). Additionally, because GBMs are known to be highly undifferentiated tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], we checked <italic>SNRPB</italic> expression in mouse neural stem cells versus differentiated neural cells and determined that <italic>SNRPB</italic> expression was higher in undifferentiated cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title><italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown impacts the expression and processing of RNA splicing machinery components</title><p>To assess the contribution of <italic>SNRPB</italic> to GBM development, we performed its knockdown (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S8) followed by RNA-Seq analysis in U251 cells. We then mapped changes in transcriptomic profiles and splicing events compared to control samples.</p><p>At the expression level, we found 7118 differentially expressed genes (log<sub>2</sub> fold change&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;|1| and Benjamini-Hochberg corrected <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown (3171 upregulated and 3947 downregulated genes; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S7). Among the upregulated genes, we observed strong enrichment for biological processes related to RNA processing and metabolism, splicing, and several cellular processes like differentiation, development, proliferation, migration, and signal transduction (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S9A; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S8). Downregulated genes were enriched for processes related to DNA repair, DNA metabolism and replication (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S9B; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S8).</p><p>At the splicing level, we found that 18,105 splicing events were altered upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown (difference in percentage spliced in (&#x00394;PSI)&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;|0.1| and FDR-adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05), affecting a total of 5692 genes. Events were classified in five categories: exon skipping (SE), mutually exclusive exons (MXE), alternative 5&#x02032; splice site (A5SS), alternative 3&#x02032; splice site (A3SS), or intron retention (RI). A summary showing results classified by event type is presented in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S9.</p><p>Similar to what was observed in the transcriptomic analysis, we determined that genes affected at the splicing level by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown are preferentially associated with biological processes such as RNA processing and metabolism, splicing, DNA metabolism, and DNA repair (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S10). Additional cancer relevant processes like chromatin remodeling were also identified (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S10). In the particular case of RNA processing and splicing, we determined that core members of the small nuclear ribonucleic proteins (snRNPs), U1, U2, U4/U6, and U5, were greatly affected by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown, especially at the splicing level: almost 60 % of them exhibited splicing alterations, which represents a strong enrichment when this gene set is compared to all multi-exon genes presenting at least one read on exon-exon junctions (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.521199e-13; hypergeometric test; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). These results suggest that SNRPB coordinates the splicing of spliceosome components.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Gene Ontology (<italic>GO</italic>) annotation of genes presenting splicing alterations upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. Network shows interaction between GO terms. <italic>Colors</italic> represent node significance. Top enriched terms were related to RNA processing, DNA metabolism and repair, chromatin modification, and cellular protein catabolism</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_990_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>
<italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown impacts core spliceosome components. More than 20 % of the core spliceosome components were differentially expressed upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown; meanwhile, almost 60 % of them presented splicing alterations. <italic>EJC</italic> exon-junction complex, <italic>&#x00394;PSI</italic> percentage spliced in. Adapted from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114">114</xref>]</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_990_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title><italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown impacts expression and processing of cancer genes and pathways already associated with gliomagenesis</title><p>We also evaluated a set of 368 well-established cancer genes, manually curated from three different large-scale studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>]. Out of 368 genes, 94 presented differential expression (57 upregulated and 37 downregulated). At the splicing level, ~50 % of the cancer genes presented at least one alteration. Enrichment for alterations at expression and splicing levels in this gene set were observed when compared to all expressed genes analyzed and all multi-exon genes&#x000a0;presenting at least one read on exon-exon junctions, respectively (expression: <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.04123; splicing: <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.45815e-52; hypergeometric test; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, b</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>SNRPB impact on cancer genes and on alternative/constitutive exons/introns. <bold>a</bold> Sashimi plots highlighting two splicing events differentially regulated in siSNRPB compared with siCtrl: an exon skipping event in K-RAS (<italic>top panel</italic>) and an intron retention in H-RAS (<italic>bottom panel</italic>). <bold>b</bold> A total of 368 cancer genes were evaluated. Only genes presenting differential expression (upregulated or downregulated) or at least one splicing alteration [exon skipping (<italic>SE</italic>), mutually exclusive exons (<italic>MXE</italic>), alternative 5&#x02032; splice site (<italic>A5SS</italic>), alternative 3&#x02032; splice site (<italic>A3SS</italic>), or intron retention (<italic>RI</italic>)] are shown. <bold>c</bold> Alternative exons and introns are more affected by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown than constitutive exons and introns</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13059_2016_990_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p><p>We then specifically checked for alterations in genes involved in critical GBM pathways defined by TCGA: <italic>RTK</italic>, <italic>PI3K</italic>, <italic>RAS</italic>, <italic>MAPK</italic>, <italic>AKT</italic>, <italic>RB</italic>, and <italic>p53</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. All pathways were affected by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. At the expression level, 8 out of 33 evaluated genes were differentially expressed: four of them were upregulated (<italic>HRAS</italic>, <italic>MET</italic>, <italic>NF1</italic>, and <italic>TP53</italic>) and four downregulated upon knockdown (<italic>AKT1</italic>, <italic>AKT2</italic>, <italic>FGFR3</italic>, <italic>PDGFRA</italic>). No enrichment was observed when this category of genes was compared to all expressed genes exhibiting differential expression (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.4250002; hypergeometric test). At the splicing level, 18 out of those 33 genes presented at least one differentially regulated splicing event (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S10), showing strong enrichment for splicing alterations in this specific gene set when compared to all multi-exon genes having at least one read on exon-exon junctions (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.409015e-07; hypergeometric test).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Characteristics of exons/introns affected by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown</title><p>SE and RI were two of the categories with the highest number of differentially regulated events and therefore were further investigated.</p><p>Knockdown of <italic>SNRPB</italic> reduced the inclusion levels of several exons (12,030 events with exons more included in control samples versus 462 events with exons more included in knockdown; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S8). Exons with higher exclusion levels upon knockdown were shorter than the ones with higher exclusion levels in control (median knockdown&#x02009;=&#x02009;106 nucleotides, median control&#x02009;=&#x02009;148 nucleotides; <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16; Wilcoxon-rank sum test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S11 left panel). With respect to GC content, exons whose inclusion in mature transcripts decreased upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown exhibited a lower percentage of GC when compared to the ones showing the opposite behavior (median knockdown&#x02009;=&#x02009;47.25 %; median control&#x02009;=&#x02009;50.57 %; <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.936e-07; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S12 left panel). We also examined the strength of 3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032; splice sites (3&#x02032;ss and 5&#x02032;ss) associated with exons affected by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown using the MaxEntScan approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. Exons with higher exclusion levels upon knockdown were associated with stronger 3&#x02032;ss and 5&#x02032;ss compared to control (3&#x02032;ss <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16; 5&#x02032;ss <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.092e-14; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S13 top panel).</p><p>Regarding introns, we observed that <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown favored the retention of introns in mature transcripts (835 intron retention events in knockdown compared to 116 in control samples; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S8). Introns showing increased retention in mature transcripts upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown were determined to be shorter than the ones preferentially retained in control samples (median knockdown&#x02009;=&#x02009;483 nucleotides; median control&#x02009;=&#x02009;1144 nucleotides; <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S11 right panel). Considering the GC content, introns more retained upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown presented a higher percentage of GC compared to the ones more retained in control (median knockdown&#x02009;=&#x02009;59.07 %; median control&#x02009;=&#x02009;43.96 %; <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S12 right panel). No significant difference was observed in the strength of 5&#x02032;ss 3&#x02032;ss associated with differentially regulated introns (3&#x02032;ss <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.4464; 5&#x02032;ss <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.9095; Wilcoxon rank-sum test; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>: Figure S13 bottom panel).</p><p>We also determined the effect of <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown on &#x0201c;constitutive&#x0201d; versus &#x0201c;alternative&#x0201d; exons and introns. Constitutive exons and introns were defined as those presenting with a PSI value&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 and PSI&#x02009;=&#x02009;0 in the control samples, respectively, whereas alternative exons and introns were defined as those with a PSI value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1 (for exons) and PSI value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0 (for introns) in control samples. In total, 5.6 % of the constitutive exons were affected by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown, while 20.1 % of alternative exons showed changes (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16; proportion test; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref> top panel). Regarding introns, 12.5 % of the constitutive ones were affected, while 26.4 % of the alternative introns presented alterations (<italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;2.2e-16; proportion test; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref> bottom panel).</p><p>In summary, exons with higher exclusion levels upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown were shorter, and had lower GC content, and stronger 3&#x02032;ss and 5&#x02032;ss, whereas introns with higher retention levels upon knockdown were shorter, and exhibited higher GC content and no difference in 3&#x02032;ss and 5&#x02032;ss strength compared to the ones more retained in control samples.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Major changes in the expression of RBP coding genes are a noteworthy phenomena in multiple tumor tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Here, we have corroborated this scenario in GBM. By comparing tumor samples (GBM samples from TCGA and GSC lines) to normal samples, we identified a set of 21 upregulated RBPs that also exhibited an impact on patient survival. We also found the expression levels of those RBPs was higher in GBMs than in lower grade gliomas, suggesting their potential impact on tumor progression and aggressiveness. To explore mechanisms that could contribute to the upregulation of those RBPs, we analyzed non-synonymous mutations, CNAs, and targeting by tumor suppressor miRNAs. We observed a modest contribution of mutations and CNAs. Because GBM does not exhibit a high mutational load compared to other tumor types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>], and has only 71 genes that are frequently mutated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>], the low number of samples harboring mutations in a small set of RBPs was expected. Regarding the tumor suppressor miRNAs, we found 18 of them targeting 15 out of 21 RBPs. Notably, miR-124 alone targets six RBPs. miR-124 is an important player in GBMs and impacts proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>], tumor growth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>], migration, and invasion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].</p><p>The impact of RBP alterations in cancer is still poorly appreciated. One of the main reasons is that most available datasets include only mRNA expression levels, preventing any type of analysis to measure changes in splicing, mRNA decay, and translation. However, this scenario is improving, especially with the advent of functional genomics methods, like ribosomal profiling and more sensitive proteomics platforms. In addition, the transcriptomics field is moving away from microarray towards RNA-Seq, which provides an opportunity to investigate global changes in splicing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. Recent investigations of alternative splicing across multiple cancer types have revealed splicing as an important source of transcriptional diversity in many cancers and allowed the identification of a common set of cancer-specific splicing events, which can potentially be used as novel biomarkers with application in molecular diagnosis and prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>].</p><p>We identified an interesting subset of aberrantly expressed RBPs implicated in splicing, pointing to an additional layer of alterations that could contribute to GBM development. Involvement of splicing proteins in cancer and other disorders is capturing the interest of the scientific community. One of the most studied cases is <italic>SF3B1</italic>, which is mutated in ~20 % of patients with myelodysplastic syndromes (MDS). Other splicing regulators, including <italic>PRPF40B</italic>, <italic>SRSF2</italic>, <italic>SF3A1</italic>, <italic>U2AF1</italic>, and <italic>ZRSR2</italic>, also display a high mutation frequency in MDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Studies of hematological malignancies showed similar results. For instance, <italic>SF3B1</italic>, <italic>SRSF1</italic>, <italic>U2AF65</italic>, and <italic>CELF4</italic> are often mutated in chronic lymphocytic leukemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>]. Subsequent reports revealed that alterations in splicing factors occur in solid tumors, including neuroblastomas, pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma, lung cancer, melanoma, colon cancer, and estrogen receptor-positive breast tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>]. In GBM, the splicing factors PTB, hnRNP H and A2/B1, and WTAP have been shown to regulate several biological processes relevant to cancer development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>]. Moreover, numerous examples of cancer-relevant genes affected at the splicing level (e.g. <italic>ANXA7</italic>, <italic>GLI1</italic>, <italic>MAX</italic>, <italic>KLF6</italic>) have been reported in GBM [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. Besides contributing to tumorigenesis via splicing regulation, splicing factors can have additional routes of action. For instance, genomic instability, a common feature in cancer, can be induced by RNA processing defects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>].</p><p><italic>SNRPB</italic>, which encodes core members of the spliceosome machinery, SmB/B&#x02019;, was the main focus of our study. Its knockdown decreased viability, increased apoptosis, and decreased proliferation in both U251 and U343 cell lines. One would expect that alterations in core splicing proteins, such as the ones encoded by <italic>SNRPB</italic>, could cause major disruptions in RNA processing, affecting the entire transcriptome in a global and homogeneous manner. However, a different scenario has been observed, with splicing regulators impacting distinct sets of events when their expression levels are altered. For instance, in a recent study, 270 core splicing proteins and other RNA-related factors were systematically knocked down and the impact on splicing of 38 genes associated with proliferation and apoptosis was investigated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. It was observed that each splicing factor regulated a specific set of events, and factors involved in the same splicing step tended to affect the same group of events. Results were corroborated by RNA-Seq studies in which specific changes in splicing, mainly in alternative exons, were observed upon knockdown of core splicing proteins, including SNRPB [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>].</p><p>In addition to its essential role in splicing, mutations in <italic>SNRPB</italic> are known to cause cerebro-costo-mandibular syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. Furthermore, a screening for genes required for cell division revealed <italic>SNRPB</italic> along with other splicing factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. However, <italic>SNRPB</italic> is relatively poorly characterized in terms of contributions to tumorigenesis. Its expression is altered in non-small cell lung cancer along with other genes involved in RNA metabolism and is correlated with a poor prognosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>]. In a mouse allograft model of prostate cancer (NE-10), <italic>SNRPB</italic> was identified as a candidate metastasis suppressor gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. Quantitative expression analysis confirmed decreased expression of SNRPB in the metastasizing compared to non-metastasizing tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. These data along with ours suggest that SNRPB can have different roles in tumorigenesis depending on context.</p><p>Alternative splicing events can result in transcript isoforms with reading frame disruption, lower stability, and improper localization in comparison to constitutive isoforms. Our RNA-Seq analysis determined some trends in terms of splicing events upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. Alternative exons and introns were more affected than the constitutive ones, suggesting SNRPB functions to help the recognition of exons and introns containing weaker regulatory elements, such as alternative exons.</p><p>Gene ontology enrichment analysis of gene expression and splicing data revealed that <italic>SNRPB</italic> influences a large number of biological processes with relevance to cancer, such as RNA processing and DNA repair. Alterations in a large number of RNA processing/splicing genes places <italic>SNRPB</italic> as a central regulator and suggests that several of the splicing alterations we observed upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown might be in fact a secondary effect. Radio-resistance, which is largely influenced by genes in the DNA repair pathway, is a major problem in cancer treatment and it is particularly relevant to GBM. Splicing alterations have been described for a large number of DNA repair genes, including several that we determined to be influenced by SNRPB levels (<italic>BRAC1</italic>, <italic>BARD1</italic>, <italic>MSH2</italic>, <italic>RAD50</italic>, <italic>CHEK1</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86">86</xref>]. Additionally, we observed that knockdown of <italic>SNRPB</italic> altered multiple genes associated with critical genes/pathways relevant to GBM development (<italic>RTK</italic>, <italic>PI3K</italic>, <italic>MAPK</italic>, <italic>RAS</italic>, <italic>AKT</italic>, <italic>RB</italic>, and <italic>p53</italic>) and other cancer genes.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Despite the need for a more detailed analysis to determine how alterations identified here affect protein function in specific ways to contribute to tumor initiation and growth, we conclude that our data suggest diverse routes by which SNRPB influences GBM development.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Gene expression analysis of GBM RNA-Seq data from TCGA</title><p>RNA-Seq raw reads from 170 samples of GBM from TCGA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>] were downloaded from Cancer Genomics Hub (CGHub [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88">88</xref>]; Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). Normal brain samples were downloaded from the SRA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89">89</xref>] database [SRA: SRP028705 and ERP003613], Human Body Map [SRA: ERR030882], and TCGA (Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S1). Reads were mapped against the human genome (version hg19/GRCh37 &#x02013; UCSC Genome Browser [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90">90</xref>]) using GSNAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] (version 2014-05-15). Mapped reads with quality (Q)&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;20 (Phred scale) were selected using SAMtools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. Read counts per gene were defined using HTSeq [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93">93</xref>] and GENCODE (version 19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]) as the reference transcriptome. Differential expression analysis was performed using DESeq2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>] comparing tumor samples to normal samples. All genes differentially expressed between tumor and normal samples (Benjamini-Hochberg corrected <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and log<sub>2</sub> fold change&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;|1|) were selected. The catalog containing 1542 human RBPs from Gerstberger et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] was used as a reference to identify all differentially expressed RBPs.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Gene expression analysis of GSCs microarray data</title><p>Microarray data (Affymetrix platform: Human U219) of 10 glioma stem cell lines and one normal neural progenitor cell line, in triplicate, were obtained from Mao et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Data were normalized using Robust Multichip Average (RMA; Affy package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]). Differentially expressed RBPs between normal and GSC samples (Benjamini-Hochberg corrected <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) were identified using the LIMMA package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Survival analysis</title><p>The REMBRANDT dataset (REpository for Molecular BRAin Neoplasia DaTa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]) was used to evaluate whether increased expression of the selected RBPs was associated with a poorer prognosis in brain neoplasia. Samples with increased expression of selected RBPs (log<sub>2</sub> fold change&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1) were compared to all other samples. Kaplan-Meier survival curves were built and then compared using a log-rank test. Differences resulting in a <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were considered significant.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Comparison of normal brain samples from GTEx with GBM samples from TCGA</title><p>Read counts per gene of 222 samples from normal brain (cortex and frontal cortex) were downloaded from the GTEx portal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. Those samples were compared to 170 GBM samples from TCGA. Read counts per gene of GBM samples were generated as described previously. Differential expression analysis was performed using DESeq2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94">94</xref>], comparing tumor to normal samples, and the expression levels of 21 RBPs were analyzed. RBPs presenting Benjamini-Hochberg corrected <italic>p</italic>-values&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were considered to be differentially expressed.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>RBPs expression in lower and higher grade gliomas</title><p>Level 3 normalized expression data from 167 grade IV gliomas (GBMs) and 218 lower grade gliomas (LGG: 31 grade II astrocytomas, 73 grade II oligodendrogliomas, 68 grade III astrocytomas, and 46 grade III oligodendrogliomas) were downloaded from TCGA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87">87</xref>]. Expression levels of 21 RBPs in LGG were compared with GBM samples using Wilcoxon rank-sum test.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Mutation and CNA analysis</title><p>All 273 GBM samples with exome sequencing and CNA data available in cBioPortal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] were evaluated (dataset: Glioblastoma Multiforme &#x02013; TCGA, Provisional). The gene set containing 21 selected RBPs was analyzed and all samples containing at least one alteration in one or more of these RBPs were identified and presented. A simulation with 100,000 random sets of 21 out of 1542 RBPs was performed to determine if our selected set presented enrichment for CNA and mutations. Mutation and CNA data for all RBPs were retrieved from cBioPortal using the CDGS-R package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Tumor suppressor miRNAs targeting RBPs</title><p>A list containing frequently downregulated miRNAs in GBM (tumor suppressor miRNAs) was downloaded from Hermansen and Kristensen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. We then used the miRTarBase database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>] to select all genes targeted by those tumor suppressor miRNAs. Next, we identified which of those miRNAs target at least one of the 21 selected RBPs. Enrichment was calculated using a hypergeometric test.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Functional annotation</title><p>Functional annotation analyses (Gene Ontology and KEGG pathways) were performed using DAVID [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>], using <italic>Homo sapiens</italic> genes as background. Terms with Benjamini-Hochberg corrected <italic>p</italic>-values&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 were determined as enriched. Redundant GO terms were summarized using REViGO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100">100</xref>]. Networks of GO terms were built using Cytoscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Cell growth and transfection</title><p>U251 and U343 GBM cells (from American Type Culture Collection, Manassas, VA, USA) were grown in Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle medium with 10 % fetal bovine serum. Cells were synchronized through serum starvation for 48 hours. siRNAs (ON-TARGETplus SMARTpool; Dharmacon) for 21 RBPs and one siRNA control were transfected using Lipofectamine RNAiMax reagent (Invitrogen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. All following experiments were performed in triplicate.</p><p>We established serum-free 3D cultures from two individual GSC lines (326 and 83) previously obtained by Dr Ichiro Nakano [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] during his time at The Ohio State University. Information regarding the Human Protocol and patient consent are described in the original publication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Cells were trypsinized using TrypLE (Invitrogen) and plated in a collagen-coated T-25 flask with 10,000 irradiated (3000 rad) human mesenchymal stem cells (Lonza) in a conditionally reprogrammed FY medium [3:1 (v/v) F-12 Nutrient Mixture (Ham)/Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle medium (Invitrogen), 5 % fetal bovine serum, 0.4 &#x003bc;g/mL hydrocortisone (Sigma-Aldrich), 5 &#x003bc;g/mL insulin (Sigma-Aldrich), 8.4 ng/mL cholera toxin (Sigma-Aldrich), and 10 ng/mL epidermal growth factor (Invitrogen)] with the addition of 5 &#x003bc;mol/L Y-27632 (Enzo Life Sciences) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. Cells were grown in a humidified incubator at 37 &#x000b0;C with 5 % carbon dioxide for several passages to ensure the stability of cultures. For knockdown experiments, 200,000 GSC cells were plated in a collagen-coated six-well plate along with 2000 irradiated human mesenchymal stem cells in conditionally reprogrammed cell media containing FY medium. The next day, 25 nM of either scrambled or <italic>SNRPB</italic> siRNA suspended in RNAiMAX was added to the wells. Subsequently, each well was washed twice with phosphate-buffered saline and 500 &#x003bc;L of OPTIMEM was added. After 5&#x02013;6 hours, 2 mL of conditionally reprogrammed media was incorporated into each well. After 72 hours, the floating cell fraction was collected and mixed with trypsinized attached cells from each well. Cell counting was performed using a Countess automated cell counter (Life Technologies) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Transfections were performed in triplicate and each experiment was done at least two times. Total RNA was isolated by pooling three wells from each experiment and using an RNeasy kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. The percentage normalized cell index for SNRPB-specific siRNA was calculated by normalizing the cell index with control siRNA. The standard deviation was calculated for each experiment and then averaged to obtain cumulative standard deviation.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Cell viability assay</title><p>After transfection, U251 and U343 cells were grown in 96-well cell culture plates. Cell viability was assessed by CellTiter 96 AQueous One Solution (Promega) reagent after 72 hours of incubation. Absorbance at 490 nm was quantified using the SpectraMax M5 microplate reader (Molecular Devices). Data were analyzed using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test and presented as the relative mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Proliferation assay</title><p>After transfection, U251 and U343 cells were grown in 96-well cell culture plates. The confluence percentage was monitored for 96 hours using a high-definition automated imaging system (IncuCyte; Essen BioScience). Data were evaluated using ANOVA and presented as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error.</p></sec><sec id="Sec25"><title>Caspase-3/7 apoptosis assay</title><p>U251 and U343 cells were grown in 96-well plates after transfection. After 72 hours of incubation, apoptosis levels were assessed using the Caspase-Glo 3/7 assay kit (Promega), according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Luminescence was measured using the SpectraMax M5 microplate reader (Molecular Devices). Data were analyzed using Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic>-test and presented as mean of relative light units&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard error.</p></sec><sec id="Sec26"><title>Gene expression analysis of RNA-Seq data from neural stem cells</title><p>RNA-Seq data from mouse neural stem cells and differentiated cells after 4 days [GEO: GSE67135] was used to analyze expression levels of <italic>SNRPB</italic> in both conditions. The HomoloGene database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102">102</xref>] was used to identify <italic>SNRPB</italic> orthologs between human and mouse. <italic>SNRPB</italic> gene expression in undifferentiated cells was compared to its expression in differentiated neural cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Knockdown quantification by real-time PCR</title><p>Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Reverse transcription of messenger RNAs was performed using a high-capacity cDNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems) with random priming. For mRNA analysis, quantitative PCR was performed using the primers listed in Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>: Table S6 and Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix (Applied Biosystems). Real-time PCRs were performed on the ViiA&#x02122; 7 Real-Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems). Data were acquired using the ViiA 7 RUO software (Applied Biosystems) and analyzed using the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method with GAPDH as an endogenous control.</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Knockdown quantification by western blot</title><p>Cells were resuspended and sonicated in Laemmli sample buffer, separated on a 13.5 % sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) gel, and transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes. After transfer, membranes were blocked in Tris-buffered saline with Tween 20 and 5 % milk. Membranes were probed with rabbit anti-&#x003b1;-SNRPB (GeneTex; dilution 1:500) and mouse anti-&#x003b1;-tubulin antibody (Sigma; dilution, 1:2000). Horseradish peroxidase (HRP)-conjugated goat anti-rabbit antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) or HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse antibody (Zymed Laboratories, Carlsbad, CA, USA) were used as secondary antibodies. Electrochemiluminescence was used to detect the selected proteins using Immobilon Western chemiluminescent substrate (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA).</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>RNA preparation and sequencing</title><p>U251 cells were transiently transfected with control or SNRPB siRNAs using Lipofectamine RNAiMAX (Invitrogen). The experiment was performed in triplicate. Knockdown levels of SNRPB were ~90 %, as measured by quantitative reverse transcription-PCR (qRT-PCR). Total RNA was extracted using the TRIzol reagent (Life Technologies) and further purified with RNeasy (Qiagen), according to manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions. Samples were prepared for RNA-Seq according to Illumina instructions and sequenced in a HiSeq-2000 machine by UTHSCSA Genomic Facility.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Alternative splicing analysis</title><p>To identify splicing alterations produced by <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown, raw RNA-Seq reads of control and knockdown experiments were mapped against the human reference genome (hg19/GRCh37) and a reference transcriptome (GENCODE version 19 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]) using GSNAP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91">91</xref>] (version 2014-05-15). Next, only reliable alignments (Q&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;20; Phred-scale) were selected using SAMtools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92">92</xref>]. Multivariate Analysis of Transcript Splicing (MATS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103">103</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104">104</xref>]) was used to search for splicing differences between <italic>SNRPB</italic>-knockdown and control samples. Only those isoforms differentially represented between conditions (FDR-adjusted <italic>p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 and &#x00394;PSI&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;|0.1|) were selected. Splicing variants were classified as SE, MXE, RI, alternative donor site (A5SS), or alternative acceptor site (A3SS). 3&#x02032;ss and 5&#x02032;ss strengths of the differentially spliced exons and introns were calculated using the MaxEntScan approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Statistical analysis and figures</title><p>All statistical analyses were executed using R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>]. Figures were built using R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105">105</xref>], Cytoscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101">101</xref>], Circos Plot [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106">106</xref>], Sashimi plot [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107">107</xref>], and Inkscape [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108">108</xref>].</p></sec></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="App1"><sec id="Sec32"><title>Additional files</title><p><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13059_2016_990_MOESM1_ESM.xls" id="MOESM1"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>Contains supplementary <bold>Tables S1&#x02013;S10.</bold>
<bold>Table S1.</bold> GBM RNA-Seq samples from TCGA and Normal samples from SRA and TCGA. <bold>Table S2.</bold> Differentially expressed RBPs in GBM data from TCGA. <bold>Table S3.</bold> Differentially expressed RBPs in GSCs data. <bold>Table S4.</bold> RBPs expression in GBM samples from TCGA vs. normal brain samples from GTEx. <bold>Table S5.</bold> Wilcoxon rank-sum test results: GBM vs. lower grade gliomas. <bold>Table S6.</bold> Knockdown efficiency measured by qRT-PCR. <bold>Table S7.</bold> Differentially expressed genes upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. <bold>Table S8.</bold> Functional annotation of differentially expressed genes upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. <bold>Table S9.</bold> Summary of differentially regulated splicing events upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. <bold>Table S10.</bold> Functional annotation of differentially spliced genes upon <italic>SNRPB</italic> knockdown. (XLS 822 kb)</p></caption></media><media position="anchor" xlink:href="13059_2016_990_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM2"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Contains supplementary <bold>Figures S1&#x02013;S13.</bold> (PDF 4857 kb)</p></caption></media></p></sec></app></app-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Dr Ichiro Nakano for sharing cell lines and Dr Scott Kuersten for comments. The results published here are in part based upon data generated by TCGA Research Network: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cancergenome.nih.gov/">http://cancergenome.nih.gov/</ext-link>.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p>This study was supported by a grant from the Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico (CNPq), Brazil, to PFG and LOFP and 5R21CA205475-02 to LOFP. BRC was supported by fellowships from Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo a Pesquisa do Estado de S&#x000e3;o Paulo &#x02013; FAPESP (2013/25483-4 and 2013/07159-5). PRA was supported by CPRIT Training Grant RP140105.</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>RNA sequencing data have been deposited in the European Nucleotide Archive [ENA: PRJEB10298] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109">109</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="FPar3"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>BRC performed all the computational and statistical analyses, helped with experiments, and wrote parts of the manuscript. PRA performed qRT-PCR experiments and helped with biological assays. MQ performed the majority of the biological assays. SCB prepared the RNA-Seq library and helped with biological assays. CC established patient-derived cell cultures and performed the knockdown assays on these cell lines. RS helped with the establishment of CRC lines. SA supervised, designed, and analyzed the knockdown experiments in patient-derived cell lines. PAFG designed the study, led computational analysis, and wrote parts of the manuscript. LOFP designed the study, led data interpretation, and wrote parts of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>All experimental methods comply with the Helsinki Declaration. GSC lines used in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref> were obtained by Dr Ichiro Nakano&#x02019;s laboratory (The Ohio State University) and are described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. All work relating to human tissues was performed previously at Ohio State University (Columbus, OH, USA) under an institutional review board&#x02013;approved protocol according to National Institute of Health (NIH) guidelines. Glioma neurospheres were obtained from high-grade glioma samples using protocols described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110">110</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113">113</xref>]. Drs I. Nakano and E. A. Chiocca performed the surgeries at the Department of Neurological Surgery, The Ohio State University (Columbus, OH, USA).</p></sec></ack><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Omuro</surname><given-names>AMP</given-names></name><name><surname>Faivre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lessons learned in the development of targeted therapy for malignant gliomas</article-title><source>Mol Cancer Ther.</source><year>2007</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1909</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-07-0047</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17620423?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17620423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stupp R, Mason WP, van den Bent MJ, Weller M, Fisher B, Taphoorn MJB, Belanger K, Brandes AA, Marosi C, Bogdahn U, Curschmann J, Janzer RC, Ludwin SK, Gorlia T, Allgeier A, Lacombe D, Cairncross JG, Eisenhauer E, Mirimanoff RO. Radiotherapy plus concomitant and adjuvant temozolomide for glioblastoma. N Engl J Med. 2005;352:987&#x02013;96.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holland</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glioblastoma multiforme: the terminator</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>6242</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.12.6242</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10841526?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10841526</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Furnari FB, Fenton T, Bachoo RM, Mukasa A, Stommel JM, Stegh A, Hahn WC, Ligon KL, Louis DN, Brennan C, Chin L, DePinho RA, Cavenee WK. Malignant astrocytic glioma: genetics, biology, and paths to treatment. Genes Dev. 2007;21:2683&#x02013;710.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esparza</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Azad</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Feroze</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitra</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheshier</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glioblastoma stem cells and stem cell-targeting immunotherapies</article-title><source>J Neurooncol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>449</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11060-015-1729-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25682090?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25682090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">McLendon R, Friedman A, Bigner D, Van Meir EG, Brat DJ, Mastrogianakis GM, Olson JJ, Mikkelsen T, Lehman N, Aldape K, Alfred Yung WK, Bogler O, VandenBerg S, Berger M, Prados M, Muzny D, Morgan M, Scherer S, Sabo A, Nazareth L, Lewis L, Hall O, Zhu Y, Ren Y, Alvi O, Yao J, Hawes A, Jhangiani S, Fowler G, San Lucas A, et al. Comprehensive genomic characterization defines human glioblastoma genes and core pathways. Nature. 2008;455:1061&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brennan CW, Verhaak RGW, McKenna A, Campos B, Noushmehr H, Salama SR, Zheng S, Chakravarty D, Sanborn JZ, Berman SH, Beroukhim R, Bernard B, Wu C-J, Genovese G, Shmulevich I, Barnholtz-Sloan J, Zou L, Vegesna R, Shukla SA, Ciriello G, Yung WK, Zhang W, Sougnez C, Mikkelsen T, Aldape K, Bigner DD, Van Meir EG, Prados M, Sloan A, Black KL, et al. The somatic genomic landscape of glioblastoma. Cell. 2013;155:462&#x02013;77.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonavia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Inda</surname><given-names>MDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavenee</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Furnari</surname><given-names>FB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heterogeneity maintenance in glioblastoma: a social network</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2011</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>4055</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-11-0153</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21628493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21628493</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Persano</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rampazzo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Basso</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Viola</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glioblastoma cancer stem cells: role of the microenvironment and therapeutic targeting</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bcp.2012.10.001</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23063412?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23063412</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Friedmann-Morvinski</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glioblastoma heterogeneity and cancer cell plasticity</article-title><source>Crit Rev Oncog.</source><year>2014</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/CritRevOncog.2014011777</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25404148?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25404148</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Castello A, Fischer B, Eichelbaum K, Horos R, Beckmann BM, Strein C, Davey NE, Humphreys DT, Preiss T, Steinmetz LM, Krijgsveld J, Hentze MW. Insights into RNA biology from an atlas of mammalian mRNA-binding proteins. Cell. 2012;149:1393&#x02013;406.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Castello A, Horos R, Strein C, Fischer B, Eichelbaum K, Steinmetz LM, Krijgsveld J, Hentze MW. System-wide identification of RNA-binding proteins by interactome capture. Nat Protoc. 2013;8:491&#x02013;500.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheibe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Butter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hogan</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative proteomic analysis reveals concurrent RNA-protein interactions and identifies new RNA-binding proteins in Saccharomyces cerevisiae</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2013</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1028</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.153031.112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23636942?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23636942</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerstberger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuschl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A census of human RNA-binding proteins</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>829</fpage><lpage>45</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg3813</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25365966?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25365966</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GENCODE Project. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gencodegenes.org/">http://www.gencodegenes.org/</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Galante PAF, Sandhu D, Abreu RDS, Gradassi M, Vogel C, De Souza SJ, Penalva LOF. A comprehensive in silico expression analysis of RNA binding proteins in normal and tumor tissue: identification of potential players in tumor formation. RNA Biol. 2009;6:426&#x02013;33.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kechavarzi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Janga</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dissecting the expression landscape of RNA-binding proteins in human cancers</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>R14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-1-r14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24410894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24410894</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Shyr</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dysregulated transcription across diverse cancer types reveals the importance of RNA-binding protein in carcinogenesis</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2015</year><volume>16</volume><issue>Suppl 7</issue><fpage>S5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-16-S7-S5</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26100984?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26100984</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelmohsen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorospe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Posttranscriptional regulation of cancer traits by HuR</article-title><source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev RNA.</source><year>2010</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>214</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wrna.4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21935886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21935886</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glazer</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Penalva</surname><given-names>LOF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Musashi1: an RBP with versatile functions in normal and cancer stem cells</article-title><source>Front Biol (Beijing)</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bielli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bus&#x000e0;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Paronetto</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sette</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The RNA-binding protein Sam68 is a multifunctional player in human cancer</article-title><source>Endocr Relat Cancer.</source><year>2011</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>R91</fpage><lpage>R102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1530/ERC-11-0041</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21565971?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21565971</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jia Y, Polunovsky V, Bitterman PB, Wagner CR. Cap-dependent translation initiation factor eIF4E: an emerging anticancer drug target. Med Res Rev. 2012;32:786&#x02013;814.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Holste</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreiman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation in alternative splicing across human tissues</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>R74</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2004-5-10-r74</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15461793?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15461793</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wang ET, Sandberg R, Luo S, Khrebtukova I, Zhang L, Mayr C, Kingsmore SF, Schroth GP, Burge CB. Alternative isoform regulation in human tissue transcriptomes. Nature. 2008;456:470&#x02013;6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Castle JC, Zhang C, Shah JK, Kulkarni AV, Kalsotra A, Cooper TA, Johnson JM. Expression of 24,426 human alternative splicing events and predicted cis regulation in 48 tissues and cell lines. Nat Genet. 2008;40:1416&#x02013;25.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Muto J, Imai T, Ogawa D, Nishimoto Y, Okada Y, Mabuchi Y, Kawase T, Iwanami A, Mischel PS, Saya H, Yoshida K, Matsuzaki Y, Okano H. RNA-binding protein Musashi1 modulates glioma cell growth through the post-transcriptional regulation of Notch and PI3 Kinase/Akt signaling pathways. PLoS One. 2012;7:e33431.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Vo DT, Abdelmohsen K, Martindale JL, Qiao M, Tominaga K, Burton TL, Gelfond JAL, Brenner AJ, Patel V, Trageser D, Scheffler B, Gorospe M, Penalva LOF. The oncogenic RNA-binding protein Musashi1 is regulated by HuR via mRNA translation and stability in glioblastoma cells. Mol Cancer Res. 2012;10:143&#x02013;55.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Uren PJ, Vo DT, de Araujo PR, P&#x000f6;tschke R, Burns SC, Bahrami-Samani E, Qiao M, de Sousa Abreu R, Nakaya HI, Correa BR, K&#x000fc;hn&#x000f6;l C, Ule J, Martindale JL, Abdelmohsen K, Gorospe M, Smith AD, Penalva LOF. RNA-binding protein Musashi1 is a central regulator of adhesion pathways in glioblastoma. Mol Cell Biol. 2015;35:2965&#x02013;78.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clower</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantley</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vander Heiden</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Krainer</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The alternative splicing repressors hnRNP A1/A2 and PTB influence pyruvate kinase isoform expression and cell metabolism</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A.</source><year>2010</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>1894</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0914845107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20133837?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20133837</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">LeFave CV, Squatrito M, Vorlova S, Rocco GL, Brennan CW, Holland EC, Pan Y-X, Cartegni L. Splicing factor hnRNPH drives an oncogenic splicing switch in gliomas. EMBO J. 2011;30:4084&#x02013;97.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Golan-Gerstl R, Cohen M, Shilo A, Suh SS, Bak&#x000e0;cs A, Coppola L, Karni R. Splicing factor hnRNP A2/B1 regulates tumor suppressor gene splicing and is an oncogenic driver in glioblastoma. Cancer Res. 2011;71:4464&#x02013;72.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Deng J, Chen S, Wang F, Zhao H, Xie Z, Xu Z, Zhang Q, Liang P, Zhai X, Cheng Y. Effects of hnRNP A2/B1 knockdown on inhibition of glioblastoma cell invasion. Mol Neurobiol. 2016;53:1132&#x02013;44.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>McCutcheon</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibroblast growth factor receptor-1 alpha-exon exclusion and polypyrimidine tract-binding protein in glioblastoma multiforme tumors</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2000</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>1221</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10728679?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10728679</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCutcheon</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hentschel</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cote</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of the splicing regulator polypyrimidine tract-binding protein in normal and neoplastic brain</article-title><source>Neuro Oncol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1215/S1152851703000218</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14769136</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Germano</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Binello</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stem cells and gliomas: past, present, and future</article-title><source>J Neurooncol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>547</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11060-014-1498-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25081973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25081973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bao S, Wu Q, McLendon RE, Hao Y, Shi Q, Hjelmeland AB, Dewhirst MW, Bigner DD, Rich JN. Glioma stem cells promote radioresistance by preferential activation of the DNA damage response. Nature. 2006;444:756&#x02013;60.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu G, Yuan X, Zeng Z, Tunici P, Ng H, Abdulkadir IR, Lu L, Irvin D, Black KL, Yu JS. Analysis of gene expression and chemoresistance of CD133+ cancer stem cells in glioblastoma. Mol Cancer. 2006;5:67.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen J, Li Y, Yu T-S, McKay RM, Burns DK, Kernie SG, Parada LF. A restricted cell population propagates glioblastoma growth after chemotherapy. Nature. 2012;488:522&#x02013;6.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mao P, Joshi K, Li J, Kim S-H, Li P, Santana-Santos L, Luthra S, Chandran UR, Benos P V, Smith L, Wang M, Hu B, Cheng S-Y, Sobol RW, Nakano I. Mesenchymal glioma stem cells are maintained by activated glycolytic metabolism involving aldehyde dehydrogenase 1A3. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2013;110:8644&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Adjei</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeting oncogenic drivers</article-title><source>Prog Tumor Res.</source><year>2014</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000355895</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24727983?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24727983</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shamu</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Neum&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNAi screening comes of age: improved techniques and complementary approaches</article-title><source>Nat Publ Gr.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>591</fpage><lpage>600</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">REMBRANDT: Repository for Molecular Brain Neoplasia Data. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://caintegrator.nci.nih.gov/rembrandt/">https://caintegrator.nci.nih.gov/rembrandt/</ext-link>]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">GTEx Portal. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gtexportal.org/">http://www.gtexportal.org/</ext-link>]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hermansen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristensen</surname><given-names>BW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA biomarkers in glioblastoma</article-title><source>J Neurooncol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11060-013-1155-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23700324?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23700324</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cerami E, Gao J, Dogrusoz U, Gross BE, Sumer SO, Aksoy BA, Jacobsen A, Byrne CJ, Heuer ML, Larsson E, Antipin Y, Reva B, Goldberg AP, Sander C, Schultz N. The cBio Cancer Genomics Portal: an open platform for exploring multidimensional cancer genomics data. Cancer Discov. 2012;2:401&#x02013;4.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gao J, Aksoy BA, Dogrusoz U, Dresdner G, Gross B, Sumer SO, Sun Y, Jacobsen A, Sinha R, Larsson E, Cerami E, Sander C, Schultz N. Integrative analysis of complex cancer genomics and clinical profiles using the cBioPortal. Sci Signal. 2013;6:pl1.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Liu X, Ory V, Chapman S, Yuan H, Albanese C, Kallakury B, Timofeeva OA, Nealon C, Dakic A, Simic V, Haddad BR, Rhim JS, Dritschilo A, Riegel A, McBride A, Schlegel R. ROCK inhibitor and feeder cells induce the conditional reprogramming of epithelial cells. Am J Pathol. 2012;180:599&#x02013;607.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ben-Porath I, Thomson MW, Carey VJ, Ge R, Bell GW, Regev A, Weinberg RA. An embryonic stem cell-like gene expression signature in poorly differentiated aggressive human tumors. Nat Genet. 2008;40:499&#x02013;507.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogelstein</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Papadopoulos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Velculescu</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>LA</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Kinzler</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cancer genome landscapes</article-title><source>Science.</source><year>2013</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>1546</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1235122</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23539594?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23539594</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tamborero D, Gonzalez-Perez A, Perez-llamas C, Deu-Pons J, Kandoth C, Reimand J, Lawrence MS, Getz G, Bader GD, Ding L, Lopez-Bigas N. Comprehensive identification of mutational cancer driver genes across 12 tumor types. Sci Rep. 2013;3:2650.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lawrence MS, Stojanov P, Mermel CH, Robinson JT, Garraway LA, Golub TR, Meyerson M, Gabriel SB, Lander ES, Getz G. Discovery and saturation analysis of cancer genes across 21 tumour types. Nature. 2014;505:495&#x02013;501.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Burge</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximum entropy modeling of short sequence motifs with applications to RNA splicing signals</article-title><source>J Comput Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/1066527041410418</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15285897?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15285897</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lawrence MS, Stojanov P, Polak P, Kryukov GV, Cibulskis K, Sivachenko A, Carter SL, Stewart C, Mermel CH, Roberts S a, Kiezun A, Hammerman PS, McKenna A, Drier Y, Zou L, Ramos AH, Pugh TJ, Stransky N, Helman E, Kim J, Sougnez C, Ambrogio L, Nickerson E, Shefler E, Cort&#x000e9;s ML, Auclair D, Saksena G, Voet D, Noble M, DiCara D, et al. Mutational heterogeneity in cancer and the search for new cancer-associated genes. Nature. 2013;499:214&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silber J, Lim DA, Petritsch C, Persson AI, Maunakea AK, Yu M, Vandenberg SR, Ginzinger DG, James CD, Costello JF, Bergers G, Weiss WA, Alvarez-Buylla A, Hodgson JG. miR-124 and miR-137 inhibit proliferation of glioblastoma multiforme cells and induce differentiation of brain tumor stem cells. BMC Med. 2008;6:14.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>miR-124 inhibits the growth of glioblastoma through the downregulation of SOS1</article-title><source>Mol Med Rep.</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23817964?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23817964</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chen Q, Lu G, Cai Y, Li Y, Xu R, Ke Y, Zhang S. MiR-124-5p inhibits the growth of high-grade gliomas through posttranscriptional regulation of LAMB1. Neuro Oncol. 2014;16:637&#x02013;51.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Cai J-J, Qi Z-X, Chen L-C, Yao Y, Gong Y, Mao Y. miR-124 suppresses the migration and invasion of glioma cells in vitro via Capn4. Oncol Rep. 2016;35:284&#x02013;90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bahrami-Samani E, Vo DT, de Araujo PR, Vogel C, Smith AD, Penalva LOF, Uren PJ. Computational challenges, tools, and resources for analyzing co- and post-transcriptional events in high throughput. Wiley Interdiscip Rev RNA. 2015;6:291&#x02013;310.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dominguez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-wide identification and study of cancer-specific splicing events across multiple tumors</article-title><source>Oncotarget.</source><year>2015</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>6825</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18632/oncotarget.3145</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25749525?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25749525</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sebesty&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zawisza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Eyras</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zawisza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recurrent alternative splicing isoform switches in tumor samples provide novel signatures of cancer</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res.</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>1345</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gku1392</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25578962?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25578962</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dvinge</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradley</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Widespread intron retention diversifies most cancer transcriptomes</article-title><source>Genome Med.</source><year>2015</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13073-015-0168-9</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25606059</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chesnais V, Kosmider O, Damm F, Itzykson R, Bernard OA, Solary E, Fontenay M. Spliceosome mutations in myelodysplastic syndromes and chronic myelomonocytic leukemia. Oncotarget. 2012;3:1284&#x02013;93.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramsay</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;nez-Trillos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jares</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwarciak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Quesada</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Next-generation sequencing reveals the secrets of the chronic lymphocytic leukemia genome</article-title><source>Clin Transl Oncol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12094-012-0922-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22911550?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22911550</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebel</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acquired mutations that affect pre-mRNA splicing in hematologic malignancies and solid tumors</article-title><source>J Natl Cancer Inst.</source><year>2013</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>1540</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/djt257</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24052622?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24052622</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Manley</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Misregulation of pre-mRNA alternative splicing in cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Discov.</source><year>2013</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1228</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-13-0253</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24145039?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24145039</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jin DI, Lee SW, Han ME, Kim HJ, Seo SA, Hur GY, Jung S, Kim BS, Oh SO. Expression and roles of Wilms&#x02019; tumor 1-associating protein in glioblastoma. Cancer Sci. 2012;103:2102&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ferrarese R, Harsh IV GR, Yadav AK, Bug E, Maticzka D, Reichardt W, Dombrowski SM, Miller TE, Masilamani AP, Dai F, Kim H, Hadler M, Scholtens DM, Yu ILY, Beck J, Srinivasasainagendra V, Costa F, Baxan N, Pfeifer D, Von Elverfeldt D, Backofen R, Weyerbrock A, Duarte CW, He X, Prinz M, Chandler JP, Vogel H, Chakravarti A, Rich JN, Carro MS, et al. Lineage-specific splicing of a brain-enriched alternative exon promotes glioblastoma progression. J Clin Invest. 2014;124:2861&#x02013;76.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali-Osman</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A novel splice variant of GLI1 that promotes glioblastoma cell migration and invasion</article-title><source>Cancer Res.</source><year>2009</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>6790</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/0008-5472.CAN-09-0886</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19706761?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19706761</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hirvonen HE, Salonen R, Sandberg MM, Vuorio E, V&#x000e4;strik I, Kotilainen E, Kalimo H. Differential expression of myc, max and RB1 genes in human gliomas and glioma cell lines. Br J Cancer. 1994;69:16&#x02013;25.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Camacho-Vanegas O, Narla G, Teixeira MS, DiFeo A, Misra A, Singh G, Chan AM, Friedman SL, Feuerstein BG, Martignetti JA. Functional inactivation of the KLF6 tumor suppressor gene by loss of heterozygosity and increased alternative splicing in glioblastoma. Int J Cancer. 2007;121:1390&#x02013;5.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hieter</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Stirling</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of genome instability induced by RNA processing defects</article-title><source>Trends Genet.</source><year>2014</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tig.2014.03.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24794811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24794811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papasaikas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tejedor</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vigevani</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Valc&#x000e1;rcel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional splicing network reveals extensive regulatory potential of the core spliceosomal machinery</article-title><source>Mol Cell.</source><year>2015</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2014.10.030</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25482510?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25482510</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saltzman</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Blencowe</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of alternative splicing by the core spliceosomal machinery</article-title><source>Genes Dev.</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.2004811</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21325135?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21325135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Murigneux</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Le Hir</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome-wide modulation of splicing by the exon junction complex</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2014-15-1-r1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shao C, Yang B, Wu T, Huang J, Tang P, Zhou Y, Zhou J, Qiu J, Jiang L, Li H, Chen G, Sun H, Zhang Y, Denise A, Zhang D-E, Fu X-D. Mechanisms for U2AF to define 3&#x02032; splice sites and regulate alternative splicing in the human genome. Nat Struct Mol Biol. 2014;21:997&#x02013;1005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lynch DC, Revil T, Schwartzentruber J, Bhoj EJ, Innes AM, Lamont RE, Lemire EG, Chodirker BN, Taylor JP, Zackai EH, McLeod DR, Kirk EP, Hoover-Fong J, Fleming L, Savarirayan R, Majewski J, Jerome-Majewska L a, Parboosingh JS, Bernier FP. Disrupted auto-regulation of the spliceosomal gene SNRPB causes cerebro-costo-mandibular syndrome. Nat Commun. 2014;5:4483.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bacrot S, Doyard M, Huber C, Alibeu O, Feldhahn N, Lehalle D, Lacombe D, Marlin S, Nitschke P, Petit F, Vazquez M-P, Munnich A, Cormier-Daire V. Mutations in <italic>SNRPB</italic>, encoding components of the core splicing machinery, cause cerebro-costo-mandibular syndrome. Hum Mutat. 2015;36:187&#x02013;90.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lehalle D, Wieczorek D, Zechi-Ceide RM, Passos-Bueno MR, Lyonnet S, Amiel J, Gordon CT. A review of craniofacial disorders caused by spliceosomal defects. Clin Genet. 2015;88:405&#x02013;15.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kittler R, Putz G, Pelletier L, Poser I, Heninger A-K, Drechsel D, Fischer S, Konstantinova I, Habermann B, Grabner H, Yaspo M-L, Himmelbauer H, Korn B, Neugebauer K, Pisabarro MT, Buchholz F. An endoribonuclease-prepared siRNA screen in human cells identifies genes essential for cell division. Nature. 2004;432:1036&#x02013;40.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valles</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Pajares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Segura</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Guruceaga</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Roman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Montuenga</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of novel deregulated RNA metabolism-related genes in non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>e42086</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0042086</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22876301?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876301</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yi Y, Nandana S, Case T, Nelson C, Radmilovic T, Matusik RJ, Tsuchiya KD. Candidate metastasis suppressor genes uncovered by array comparative genomic hybridization in a mouse allograft model of prostate cancer. Mol Cytogenet. 2009;2:18.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Romero A, Garc&#x000ed;a-Garc&#x000ed;a F, L&#x000f3;pez-Perolio I. Ruiz de Garibay G, Garc&#x000ed;a-S&#x000e1;enz JA, Garre P, Ayll&#x000f3;n P, Benito E, Dopazo J, D&#x000ed;az-Rubio E, Cald&#x000e9;s T, de la Hoya M. BRCA1 Alternative splicing landscape in breast tissue samples. BMC Cancer. 2015;15:1&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li L, Cohen M, Wu J, Sow MH, Nikolic B, Bischof P, Irminger-Finger I. Identification of BARD1 splice-isoforms involved in human trophoblast invasion. Int J Biochem Cell Biol. 2007;39:1659&#x02013;72.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lastella</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Surdo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Resta</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guanti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stella</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In silico and in vivo splicing analysis of MLH1 and MSH2 missense mutations shows exon- and tissue-specific effects</article-title><source>BMC Genomics.</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>243</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2164-7-243</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16995940?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16995940</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Kim KK, Shin BA, Seo KH, Kim PN, Koh JT, Kim JH, Park BR. Molecular cloning and characterization of splice variants of human RAD50 gene. Gene. 1999;235:59&#x02013;67.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR86"><label>86.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pabla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Checkpoint kinase 1 (Chk1)-short is a splice variant and endogenous inhibitor of Chk1 that regulates cell cycle and DNA damage checkpoints</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>202</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1104767109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22184239?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22184239</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR87"><label>87.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">The Cancer Genome Atlas. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cancergenome.nih.gov/">http://cancergenome.nih.gov/</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR88"><label>88.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">CGHub: The Cancer Genomics Hub. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cghub.ucsc.edu/">https://cghub.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR89"><label>89.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">SRA: Sequence Read Archive. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR90"><label>90.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UCSC Genome Browser. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genome.ucsc.edu/">https://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR91"><label>91.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nacu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fast and SNP-tolerant detection of complex variants and splicing in short reads</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2010</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>873</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btq057</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20147302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20147302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR92"><label>92.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Li H, Handsaker B, Wysoker A, Fennell T, Ruan J, Homer N, Marth G, Abecasis G, Durbin R. The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics. 2009;25:2078&#x02013;9.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR93"><label>93.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyl</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HTSeq--a Python framework to work with high-throughput sequencing data</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2015</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>166</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu638</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25260700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25260700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR94"><label>94.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2</article-title><source>Genome Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>550</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25516281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR95"><label>95.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gautier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cope</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bolstad</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Affy - analysis of Affymetrix GeneChip data at the probe level</article-title><source>Bioinformatics.</source><year>2004</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btg405</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14960456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR96"><label>96.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ritchie ME, Phipson B, Wu D, Hu Y, Law CW, Shi W, Smyth GK. Limma powers differential expression analyses for RNA-sequencing and microarray studies. Nucleic Acids Res. 2015;43:e47&#x02013;7.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR97"><label>97.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>CDGS-R Package - R-based API for accessing the MSKCC Cancer Genomics Data Server (CGDS)</source><year>2015</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR98"><label>98.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chou C-H, Chang N-W, Shrestha S, Hsu S-D, Lin Y-L, Lee W-H, Yang C-D, Hong H-C, Wei T-Y, Tu S-J, Tsai T-R, Ho S-Y, Jian T-Y, Wu H-Y, Chen P-R, Lin N-C, Huang H-T, Yang T-L, Pai C-Y, Tai C-S, Chen W-L, Huang C-Y, Liu C-C, Weng S-L, Liao K-W, Hsu W-L, Huang H-D. miRTarBase 2016: updates to the experimentally validated miRNA-target interactions database. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016;2016(44):D239&#x02013;47.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR99"><label>99.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dennis G, Sherman BT, Hosack DA, Yang J, Gao W, Lane H, Lempicki RA. DAVID: database for annotation, visualization, and integrated discovery. Genome Biol. 2003;4:R60.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR100"><label>100.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Supek</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bo&#x00161;njak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;kunca</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;muc</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>REVIGO summarizes and visualizes long lists of gene ontology terms</article-title><source>PLoS One.</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e21800</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0021800</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21789182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21789182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR101"><label>101.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoscape: A software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks</article-title><source>Genome Res.</source><year>2003</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2498</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.1239303</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14597658?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14597658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR102"><label>102.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">HomoloGene. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/homologene">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/homologene</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR103"><label>103.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shen S, Park JW, Huang J, Dittmar KA, Lu ZX, Zhou Q, Carstens RP, Xing Y . MATS: a Bayesian framework for flexible detection of differential alternative splicing from RNA-Seq data. Nucleic Acids Res. 2012;40:1&#x02013;13.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR104"><label>104.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shen S, Park JW, Lu Z, Lin L, Henry MD, Wu YN, Zhou Q, Xing Y. rMATS: Robust and flexible detection of differential alternative splicing from replicate RNA-Seq data. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2014;111:E5593&#x02013;601.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR105"><label>105.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Project. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">http://www.r-project.org/</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR106"><label>106.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Krzywinski M, Schein J, Birol I, Connors J, Gascoyne R, Horsman D, Jones SJ, Marra MA. Circos: an information aesthetic for comparative genomics. Genome Res. 2009;19:1639&#x02013;45.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR107"><label>107.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Katz Y, Wang ET, Stilterra J, Schwartz S, Wong B, Thorvaldsdottir H, Robinson JT, Mesirov JP, Airoldi EM, Burge CB. Sashimi plots: quantitative visualization of alternative isoform expression from RNA-seq data. Bioinformatics. 2015;31:2400&#x02013;2.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR108"><label>108.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Inkscape. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://inkscape.org/">https://inkscape.org/</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR109"><label>109.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European Nucleotide Archive - ENA. [<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/ena</ext-link>]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR110"><label>110.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jijiwa M, Demir H, Gupta S, Leung C, Joshi K, Orozco N, Huang T, Yildiz VO, Shibahara I, de Jesus JA, Yong WH, Mischel PS, Fernandez S, Kornblum HI, Nakano I. CD44v6 regulates growth of brain tumor stem cells partially through the AKT-mediated pathway. PLoS One. 2011;6:e24217.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR111"><label>111.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Guvenc H, Pavlyukov MS, Joshi K, Kurt H, Banasavadi-Siddegowda YK, Mao P, Hong C, Yamada R, Kwon C-H, Bhasin D, Chettiar S, Kitange G, Park I-H, Sarkaria JN, Li C, Shakhparonov MI, Nakano I. Impairment of glioma stem cell survival and growth by a novel inhibitor for survivin-ran protein complex. Clin Cancer Res. 2013;19:631&#x02013;42.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR112"><label>112.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nakano I, Masterman-Smith M, Saigusa K, Paucar AA, Horvath S, Shoemaker L, Watanabe M, Negro A, Bajpai R, Howes A, Lelievre V, Waschek JA, Lazareff JA, Freije WA, Liau LM, Gilbertson RJ, Cloughesy TF, Geschwind DH, Nelson SF, Mischel PS, Terskikh A V, Kornblum HI. Maternal embryonic leucine zipper kinase is a key regulator of the proliferation of malignant brain tumors, including brain tumor stem cells. J Neurosci Res. 2008;86:48&#x02013;60.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR113"><label>113.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dougherty JD, Garcia ADR, Nakano I, Livingstone M, Norris B, Polakiewicz R, Wexler EM, Sofroniew M V, Kornblum HI, Geschwind DH. PBK/TOPK, a proliferating neural progenitor-specific mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase. J Neurosci. 2005;25:10773&#x02013;85.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR114"><label>114.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Will</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000fc;hrmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spliceosome structure and function</article-title><source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a003707</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>