<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Br J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Br J Ophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">bjophthalmol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">bjo</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The British Journal of Ophthalmology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0007-1161</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1468-2079</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BMJ Publishing Group</publisher-name><publisher-loc>BMA House, Tavistock Square, London, WC1H 9JR</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5754869</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">29122821</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">bjophthalmol-2017-311151</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjophthalmol-2017-311151</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Innovations</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="hwp-journal-coll"><subject>1506</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Metagenomic deep sequencing of aqueous fluid detects intraocular lymphomas</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-44228286" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-53882033" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>Thuy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-45170880" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shantha</surname><given-names>Jessica G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-57210362" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bloomer</surname><given-names>Michele</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-57210411" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>Michael R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-57210535" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>DeRisi</surname><given-names>Joseph L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-21760078" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>Nisha</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution content-type="department">Francis I Proctor Foundation</institution>, <institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Ophthalmology</institution>, <institution>University of California San Francisco</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<label>3</label>
<institution content-type="department">Weill Institute for Neurosciences</institution>, <institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<label>4</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Neurology</institution>, <institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<label>5</label>
<institution content-type="department">Department of Biochemistry and Biophysics</institution>, <institution>University of California</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><aff id="aff6">
<label>6</label>
<institution>Chan Zuckerberg Biohub</institution>, <addr-line content-type="city">San Francisco</addr-line>, <addr-line content-type="state">California</addr-line>, <country>USA</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp><label>Correspondence to</label> Dr Thuy Doan, Francis I. Proctor Foundation, University of California, San Francisco, CA, USA; <email>Thuy.Doan@ucsf.edu</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other"><p>JG and TD are co-first authors.</p></fn><fn id="fn8"><p>Presented at the American Uveitis Society (AUS) meeting at the Association for Research Vision and Ophthalmology (ARVO) meeting, 2017.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>11</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>102</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>6</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>8</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>10</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; Article author(s) (or their employer(s) unless otherwise stated in the text of the article) 2018. All rights reserved. No commercial use is permitted unless otherwise expressly granted.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed in accordance with the Creative Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC) license, which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and the use is non-commercial. See: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/</ext-link></license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="bjophthalmol-2017-311151.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Currently, the detection of pathogens or mutations associated with intraocular lymphomas heavily relies on prespecified, directed PCRs. With metagenomic deep sequencing (MDS), an unbiased high-throughput sequencing approach, all pathogens as well as all mutations present in the host&#x02019;s genome can be detected in the same small amount of ocular fluid.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In this cross-sectional case series, aqueous fluid samples from two patients were submitted to MDS to identify pathogens as well as common and rare cancer mutations.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>MDS of aqueous fluid from the first patient with vitreal lymphoma revealed the presence of both Epstein-Barr virus (HHV-4/EBV) and human herpes virus 8 (HHV-8) RNA. Aqueous fluid from the second patient with intraocular B-cell lymphoma demonstrated a less common mutation in the <italic>MYD88</italic> gene associated with B-cell lymphoma.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>MDS detects pathogens that, in some instances, may drive the development of intraocular lymphomas. Moreover, MDS is able to identify both common and rare mutations associated with lymphomas.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>aqueous humour</kwd><kwd>immunology</kwd><kwd>infection</kwd><kwd>inflammation</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>National Eye Institute of the National Institutes of Health (NIH)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Silicon Valley Community Foundation/Huang Pacific Foundation</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-3"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Research to Prevent Blindness Career Development Award</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-4"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>UCSF Resource Allocation Program for Junior Investigators in Basic and Clinical/Translational Science</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group id="funding-5"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Chan Zuckerberg Biohub</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>special-feature</meta-name><meta-value>unlocked</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Molecular diagnostics such as pathogen-directed PCRs previously revolutionised the field of ophthalmology by accurately providing diagnoses for ocular infections using minute amounts of ocular samples.<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1 2</xref> A major limitation with these assays is that only prespecified pathogens can be detected leading to potential missed pathogens. Additionally, directed PCR or DNA microarray may overlook less common mutations associated with lymphoproliferative disorders. Metagenomic deep sequencing (MDS) is an unbiased high-throughput sequencing approach that can theoretically detect all pathogens in a clinical sample. Further, it simultaneously provides genetic information that may be useful for evaluating the host&#x02019;s immune system. Distinguishing uveitis as infectious or non-infectious is vital as such knowledge guides appropriate treatment. It is also important to identify uveitic masqueraders such as intraocular malignancies as the treatment is likewise impacted by this knowledge. Herein, we present two cases of intraocular lymphoproliferative disorders that were identified using MDS.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Study design</title><p>Cross-sectional case studies in which patients&#x02019; aqueous fluid samples were submitted to MDS to identify infectious pathogens as well as host genome sequencing to identify mutations associated with lymphoproliferative disorders. Our research adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki. Informed consent was obtained from all participants.</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Sequencing library preparation</title><p>Samples were prepared for MDS as previously described.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 4</xref> Briefly, RNA was extracted from 20 to 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;L of aqueous fluid with the Direct-zol RNA Microprep (Zymo Research, California, USA) per manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations and eluted in 20&#x02009;&#x000b5;L nuclease-free water. Five microlitres of the extracted RNA were used to prepare libraries using the New England Biolabs&#x02019; (NEB) NEBNext RNA First Strand Synthesis Module (E7525) and NEBNext Ultra Directional RNA Second Strand Synthesis Module (E7550) to generate double-stranded cDNA. The cDNA was converted to Illumina libraries using the NEBNext Ultra II DNA Library Prep Kit (E7645) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendation and then amplified with 14 PCR cycles. Samples were sequenced on the Illumina HiSeq 4000 using 125-nucleotide (nt) paired-end sequencing.</p></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Bioinformatics</title><p>Analysis of sequenced data was made using a rapid computational pipeline developed in-house to classify sequencing reads and identify potential pathogens against the entire National Center for Biotechnology Information (NCBI) nt reference database.<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3 4</xref> To identify the somatic mutations in the myeloid differentiation primary response 88 (<italic>MYD88</italic>) gene (NC_000003.12), we aligned the filtered human sequences against the <italic>MYD88</italic> gene using HISAT2 (V.2.0.5).<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>
</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>The first patient was a middle-aged Caucasian man who presented with &#x02018;foggy vision&#x02019; in the left eye. His medical history included Kaposi sarcoma of the chest and thigh 30 years ago and now in remission, and a diagnosis of HIV 15 years prior, currently on antiretroviral treatment. His most recent absolute CD4 count was 800&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup>/L. Examination of the right eye was unremarkable. Notably, the left eye exhibited &#x000bd;+ anterior&#x02009;chamber cells and 1+ flare, 3+ vitreous cells and &#x000bd;+ vitreous&#x02009;haze (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1A</xref>). There were no retinal or choroidal lesions. Anterior chamber paracentesis was performed as well as a diagnostic and therapeutic vitrectomy of the left eye. Pathogen-directed PCR analysis of the aqueous fluid was negative for herpes simplex virus (HSV), varicella zoster virus (VZV) and cytomegalovirus (CMV). MDS of the aqueous fluid identified the presence of both Epstein-Barr virus (HHV-4/EBV) and human herpes virus 8 (HHV-8) RNA (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1B</xref>). The vitrectomy fluid yielded rare, small lymphocytes on cytopathology, no B-cells on flow cytometry, but <italic>Ig-kappa</italic> gene rearrangement suggestive of lymphoma. In the context of a patient with HIV, the finding of lymphoma with a coinfection with HHV-8 and EBV can be associated with a phenotype most similar to primary effusion lymphoma (PEL).<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref> Interestingly, phylogenetic analysis of the patient&#x02019;s HHV-8 strain indicated that it was most similar to a PEL-associated strain isolated from a patient in the USA (NCBI GenBank AF1330391.1, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1E</xref>).</p><fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Clinical, histopathology and metagenomic deep sequencing (MDS) findings of patient #1 and #2. (A) Anterior vitreous cells on slit lamp examination, and (B) HHV-8 and HHV-4 (also known as EBV) genomes were detected in the aqueous fluid by MDS for patient #1; (C) photomicrograph of H&#x00026;E-stained specimen from the anterior chamber biopsied material disclosing the presence of numerous intermediate to large cells with irregular nuclei. Immunohistochemistry of these cells showed diffusely positive staining with B-lymphocyte antigen CD20 and most of the large cells stained positively with BCL-2 (not shown), and (D) analysis of the <italic>MYD88</italic> gene indicated the presence of a serine to asparagine mutational change at amino acid position 243 for patient #2. (E) Phylogenetic analysis of the HHV-8 sequence obtained from MDS for patient #1 using the ORF K1 hypervariable region with HHV-8 isolates from different diseases and geographic origins using multiple sequence comparison by log-expectation (MUSCLE).<xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref> HHV-8, human herpes virus-8; HHV-4, human herpes virus-4; EBV, Epstein-Barr virus; BCL-2, B-cell lymphoma 2; MYD88, myeloid differentiation primary response 88; ORF, open reading frame; BCBL, body cavity-based lymphoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="bjophthalmol-2017-311151f01"/></fig><p>The second patient was a mid-30s Caucasian man with bilateral intermediate uveitis of 5 years&#x02019; duration who presented for initiation of systemic immunomodulatory therapy. A vitrectomy performed 1&#x02009;year after onset of disease showed mixed lymphocytes, but was read as negative for lymphoma. On presentation in our clinic, the patient exhibited 1+ anterior&#x02009;chamber cells, 3+ anterior&#x02009;vitreous cells and 1+ vitreous&#x02009;haze in the right eye. The left eye had no anterior chamber cell or flare, but with 3+ anterior&#x02009;vitreous cells and no vitreous haze. There were no retinal or choroidal lesions in either eye. An anterior chamber paracentesis was negative on directed PCR for HSV, VZV, CMV and <italic>Toxoplasma gondii</italic>. Likewise, MDS was negative for infectious agents. Given that MDS captures mostly host sequence, we were able to use the same data set to interrogate the <italic>MYD88</italic> gene for both common and rare mutations associated with lymphoma. Indeed, the patient exhibited the S243N mutation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1D</xref>), which has been associated with the activated B-cell (ABC) subtype of diffuse large B-cell lymphoma. S243N is a recognised gain of function mutant that can contribute to constitutive NF-kB expression.<xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref> This finding was intriguing as 50%&#x02013;70% of primary vitreoretinal lymphomas exhibit the L265P mutation.<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Thus, routine screening using directed PCR for the most common mutation would not have identified this patient&#x02019;s lymphoma. A definitive diagnosis of lymphoma was provided when biopsy of material in the anterior chamber revealed large B-cell lymphoma on histopathology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">figure 1C</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Intraocular lymphomas are challenging to diagnose given the small amounts of tissue that can be obtained on biopsy. Lymphomatous cells are fragile and may appear as non-diagnostic &#x02018;smudge cells&#x02019; on cytopathological inspection.<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9 10</xref> Further, the time of disease onset to diagnosis is often prolonged because its clinical signs may be attributed to undifferentiated uveitis.<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref> The cases described here demonstrated that MDS can accurately detect pathogen-related causes of inflammation that drive intraocular lymphomas as well as common and rare cancer-associated mutations in as little as 20 to 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;L of aqueous fluid. MDS, therefore, has the potential to improve the diagnostic rates of intraocular lymphomas as the diagnosis may be possible with a single outpatient anterior chamber paracentesis as the initial work-up.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Derek Bogdanoff and Eric Chow in the UCSF Center for Advanced Technology for their expertise and assistance operating the Illumina sequencer and Armin Hinterwirth for his assistance with bioinformatics. Lastly, we thank our patients for their participation in this research program.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Contributors:</bold> Conception and design of study: JAG, TD, MRW, JLD, NA. Acquisition of data: JAG, TD, JGS, MB, NRA. Analysis and/or interpretation of data: TD, JAG, MB, MRW, JLD, NRA. Drafting the manuscript: JAG, TD, JGS, MB, MRW, JLD, NRA. Revising the manuscript critically for important intellectual content: JAG, TD, MRW, JLD, NRA. Approval of the version of the manuscript to be published: JAG, TD, JGS, MB, MRW, JLD, NRA.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Funding:</bold> Research reported in this publication was supported by the UCSF Resource Allocation Program for Junior Investigators in Basic and Clinical/Translational Science (TD); Research to Prevent Blindness Career Development Award (TD); the National Eye Institute of the National Institutes of Health (NIH) under Award Number K08EY026986 (TD); Silicon Valley Community Foundation/Huang Pacific Foundation (TD), and the Chan Zuckerberg Biohub (JLD).</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing interests:</bold> None declared.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Ethics approval:</bold> The Institutional Review Board of the University of California, San Francisco approved the study (16&#x02013;19151).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Provenance and peer review:</bold> Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Taravati</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Gelder</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Role of molecular diagnostics in ocular microbiology</article-title>. <source>Curr Ophthalmol Rep</source>
<year>2013</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40135-013-0025-1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>de Groot-Mijnes</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de Visser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zuurveen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of new pathogens in the intraocular fluid of patients with uveitis</article-title>. <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
<year>2010</year>;<volume>150</volume>:<fpage>628</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ajo.2010.05.015</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20691420</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Doan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Illuminating uveitis: metagenomic deep sequencing identifies common and rare pathogens</article-title>. <source>Genome Med</source>
<year>2016</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>90</fpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13073-016-0344-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27562436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shanbhag</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reid</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Diagnosing Balamuthia mandrillaris Encephalitis With Metagenomic Deep Sequencing</article-title>. <source>Ann Neurol</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>722</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ana.24499</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26290222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>HISAT: a fast spliced aligner with low memory requirements</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.3317</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25751142</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Horenstein</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nador</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chadburn</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Epstein-Barr virus latent gene expression in primary effusion lymphomas containing Kaposi&#x02019;s sarcoma-associated herpesvirus/human herpesvirus-8</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>1997</year>;<volume>90</volume>:<fpage>1186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9242551</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ngo</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Young</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Oncogenically active MYD88 mutations in human lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<year>2011</year>;<volume>470</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09671</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21179087</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonzheim</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Giese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Deuter</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>High frequency of MYD88 mutations in vitreoretinal B-cell lymphoma: a valuable tool to improve diagnostic yield of vitreous aspirates</article-title>. <source>Blood</source>
<year>2015</year>;<volume>126</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2015-01-620518</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25900979</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solomon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nussenblatt</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Immunocytochemical staining of vitreous cells. Indications, techniques, and results</article-title>. <source>Ophthalmology</source>
<year>1992</year>;<volume>99</volume>:<fpage>250</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1553217</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Biopsy techniques and yields in diagnosing primary intraocular lymphoma</article-title>. <source>Int Ophthalmol</source>
<year>2007</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>241</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10792-007-9065-6</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17440686</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Intraocular lymphoma: update on diagnosis and management</article-title>. <source>Cancer Control</source>
<year>2004</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/107327480401100502</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15377987</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dereeper</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guignon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Phylogeny.fr: robust phylogenetic analysis for the non-specialist</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
<year>2008</year>;<volume>36</volume>:<fpage>W465</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W469</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkn180</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18424797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>