<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genome Biol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">gbe</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Genome Biology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1759-6653</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6367104</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/gbe/evz004</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">evz004</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Plastid Genomes and Proteins Illuminate the Evolution of Eustigmatophyte Algae and Their Bacterial Endosymbionts</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Tereza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evz004-FM2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yurchenko</surname><given-names>Tatiana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="evz004-FM2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>Karen P</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>Raquel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Strnad</surname><given-names>Hynek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>Lilia M A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>Marvin W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161;</surname><given-names>Marek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="evz004-aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="evz004-cor1"/><!--<email>marek.elias@osu.cz</email>--></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>Laura A</given-names></name><role>Associate Editor</role></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="evz004-aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology and Ecology Faculty of Science, University of Ostrava, Ostrava, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="evz004-aff2"><label>2</label>Faculty of Science, Institute of Environmental Technologies, University of Ostrava, Ostrava, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="evz004-aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Sciences and Mathematics, University of the Ozarks, Clarksville, Arkansas</aff><aff id="evz004-aff4"><label>4</label>Coimbra Collection of Algae (ACOI), Department of Life Sciences, University of Coimbra, Coimbra, Portugal</aff><aff id="evz004-aff5"><label>5</label>Laboratory of Genomics and Bioinformatics, Institute of Molecular Genetics of the CAS, v.v.i., Prague, Czech Republic</aff><aff id="evz004-aff6"><label>6</label>School of Mathematical and Natural Sciences, University of Arkansas at Monticello, Monticello, Arkansas</aff><author-notes><fn id="evz004-FM2"><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp id="evz004-cor1">Corresponding author: E-mail: <email>marek.elias@osu.cz</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-01-10"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>11</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>362</fpage><lpage>379</lpage><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="evz004.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>Eustigmatophytes, a class of stramenopile algae (ochrophytes), include not only the extensively studied biotechnologically important genus <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> but also a rapidly expanding diversity of lineages with much less well characterized biology. Recent discoveries have led to exciting additions to our knowledge about eustigmatophytes. Some proved to harbor bacterial endosymbionts representing a novel genus, <italic>Candidatus</italic> Phycorickettsia, and an operon of unclear function (<italic>ebo</italic>) obtained by horizontal gene transfer from the endosymbiont lineage was found in the plastid genomes of still other eustigmatophytes. To shed more light on the latter event, as well as to generally improve our understanding of the eustigmatophyte evolutionary history, we sequenced plastid genomes of seven phylogenetically diverse representatives (including new isolates representing undescribed taxa). A phylogenomic analysis of plastid genome-encoded proteins resolved the phylogenetic relationships among the main eustigmatophyte lineages and provided a framework for the interpretation of plastid gene gains and losses in the group. The <italic>ebo</italic> operon gain was inferred to have probably occurred within the order Eustigmatales, after the divergence of the two basalmost lineages (a newly discovered hitherto undescribed strain and the <italic>Pseudellipsoidion</italic> group). When looking for nuclear genes potentially compensating for plastid gene losses, we noticed a gene for a plastid-targeted acyl carrier protein that was apparently acquired by horizontal gene transfer from <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic>. The presence of this gene in all eustigmatophytes studied, including representatives of both principal clades (Eustigmatales and Goniochloridales), is a genetic footprint indicating that the eustigmatophyte&#x02013;<italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> partnership started no later than in the last eustigmatophyte common ancestor.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>acyl carrier protein</kwd><kwd>Eustigmatophyceae</kwd><kwd>horizontal gene transfer</kwd><kwd>Ochrophyta</kwd><kwd>Phycorickettsia</kwd><kwd>plastid genome</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program</named-content></funding-source><award-id>642575</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">Czech Science Foundation</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/501100001824</named-content></funding-source><award-id>18-13458S</award-id></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Feasibility Programme</named-content></funding-source></award-group><award-group award-type="grant"><funding-source><named-content content-type="funder-name">National Science Foundation</named-content><named-content content-type="funder-identifier">10.13039/100000001</named-content></funding-source><award-id>DEB1145414</award-id></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="18"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Eustigmatophytes are an interesting group of unicellular, primarily freshwater algae. These organisms generally have a simple coccoid morphology, yet they exhibit a suite of cytological and biochemical features making them unlike any other algal taxon (<xref rid="evz004-B10" ref-type="bibr">Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161; et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Phylogenetically they constitute a well-delineated lineage, typically classified as an independent class of ochrophytes, a prominent algal phylum that emerged within the stramenopiles by acquisition of a plastid (pt) through a higher-order endosymbiotic event (<xref rid="evz004-B69" ref-type="bibr">Dorrell et al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dorrell and Bowler 2017</xref>). Although recognized as a separate phylogenetic unit nearly five decades ago, eustigmatophytes were long considered a relatively insignificant taxon with limited species diversity and minor ecological importance (<xref rid="evz004-B19" ref-type="bibr">Graham et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>). Hence, until recently, research on fundamental aspects of eustigmatophyte biology was essentially limited to taxonomic studies that slowly expanded the number of eustigmatophyte taxa, combined with basic characterization of eustigmatophyte morphology, ultrastructure, and composition of photosynthetic pigments (reviewed in <xref rid="evz004-B10" ref-type="bibr">Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161; et&#x000a0;al. [2017</xref>]).</p><p>More recently, a renewed interest in algae as resources for biotechnologies has sparked an extensive research program on eustigmatophytes, but attention has been given almost exclusively to a single eustigmatophyte lineage traditionally classified as the genus <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> (e.g., <xref rid="evz004-B37" ref-type="bibr">Ma et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). These studies include not only physiological, biochemical, and cell biological investigations but also application of genomic approaches yielding complete or draft genome sequences for nearly all species of the genus (<xref rid="evz004-B42" ref-type="bibr">Pan et&#x000a0;al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B46" ref-type="bibr">Radakovits et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B57" ref-type="bibr">Vieler et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B7" ref-type="bibr">Corteggiani Carpinelli et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B58" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). For the sake of taxonomic accuracy, it should be stressed that two <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> species have recently been segregated into a separate (yet related) genus <italic>Microchloropsis</italic> (<xref rid="evz004-B15" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), so the whole group will hereafter be referred to as the <italic>Nanno-</italic>/<italic>Microchloropsis</italic> clade.</p><p>In this article, we are primarily concerned with pt genomes. The first eustigmatophyte pt genomes were sequenced as part of the genome project for <italic>Microchloropsis</italic> (then <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic>) <italic>gaditana</italic> (<xref rid="evz004-B46" ref-type="bibr">Radakovits et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>), but more detailed analyses came only with two subsequent studies that collectively provided pt genome sequences from nearly all known species of the <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> group (<xref rid="evz004-B60" ref-type="bibr">Wei et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B54" ref-type="bibr">Starkenburg et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). These investigations yielded a number of important findings concerning the gene repertoire of pt genomes in eustigmatophytes and indicated the degree of variation in their pt genome architecture and coding capacity across different species of the single eustigmatophyte lineage. However, a question remained as to what extent the findings from the <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> clade are representative of eustigmatophytes across their actual phylogenetic breadth.</p><p>Eustigmatophytes are indeed much more than <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic>. Presently, the class comprises &#x0223c;30 species classified in 15 different genera, but molecular markers obtained from a number of unidentified isolates revealed a much higher taxonomic diversity that yet needs to be properly studied (<xref rid="evz004-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B10" ref-type="bibr">Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161; et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). Phylogenetically, the class is deeply divided into two major monophyletic clades, one of them being the order Eustigmatales and the other presently referred to as the clade <italic>Goniochloridales.</italic> This clade was defined according to the PhyloCode but (for technical taxonomic reasons) so far lacks a standing in the traditional Linnaean taxonomy governed by the International Code of Nomenclature for algae, fungi, and plants (<xref rid="evz004-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). However, for the purpose of this study, we will consider the group having the same rank as the order Eustigmatales and will refer to it simply to as Goniochloridales (not italicized).</p><p>The order Eustigmatales includes all eustigmatophytes defined by the pioneering work of <xref rid="evz004-B22" ref-type="bibr">Hibberd (1981)</xref>, whereas Goniochloridales comprise more recently recognized eustigmatophytes, including taxa transferred to eustigmatophytes from xanthophytes based on molecular and other supporting evidence (e.g., <xref rid="evz004-B45" ref-type="bibr">P&#x00159;ibyl et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B14" ref-type="bibr">Fawley and Fawley 2017</xref>) or described anew (<xref rid="evz004-B40" ref-type="bibr">Nakayama et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). However, the majority of known Goniochloridales representatives are unidentified algal isolates, many of which probably represent species and genera yet to be described (<xref rid="evz004-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses based on 18S rRNA and <italic>rbcL</italic> gene sequences led to the recognition of four main (generally well supported) Goniochloridales lineages, specifically the genus <italic>Pseudostaurastrum</italic> and clades IIa, IIb, and IIc, but their relationships remain unresolved (<xref rid="evz004-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B14" ref-type="bibr">Fawley and Fawley 2017</xref>). Eustigmatales include three robustly supported main clades. One of them corresponds to the family Monodopsidaceae (which includes the <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> group and other taxa), whereas the other two lineages are not yet recognized in the formal taxonomy of the group and are informally referred to as the Eustigmataceae group and the <italic>Pseudellipsoidion</italic> group (<xref rid="evz004-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). 18S rDNA phylogenies suggest that the <italic>Pseudellipsoidion</italic> group is basal to the other two lineages, but this branching order is only moderately supported (<xref rid="evz004-B10" ref-type="bibr">Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161; et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B14" ref-type="bibr">Fawley and Fawley 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), whereas the <italic>rbcL</italic> marker suggests the basal position of Monodopsidaceae (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Phylogenetic analyses based on more markers are clearly needed to resolve the relationships within both Eustigmatales and Goniochloridales.
</p><fig id="evz004-F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 1.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Eustigmatophyte phylogeny inferred from pt genome data. The tree shown was inferred using PhyloBayes-MPI v1.7 and the site-heterogeneous substitution model CAT + GTR from an alignment of 18,378 amino acid positions (derived from 68 conserved pt genome-encoded proteins). All branches received maximal support (posterior probability of 1.0). For simplicity, only the ochrophyte subtree is shown (omitting thus the outgroup comprising cryptophytes and haptophytes) and classes (other than eustigmatophytes) with multiple representatives are collapsed as triangles. Species (strains) with pt genomes sequenced in this study are highlighted in bold. <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary figure S10</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online, shows a full version of the essentially identical ML tree inferred from the same supermatrix using IQ-TREE v1.6.5. GenBank accession numbers of pt genomes employed in the phylogenomic analysis are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref> and in the legend to <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary figure S10</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online. Light microphotographs are provided for the four sequenced strains whose appearance has been previously documented in the literature; scale bar: 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;m.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz004f1"/></fig><p>The broad phylogenetic diversity of eustigmatophytes and the availability of many representative cultures provide opportunities for genomic explorations beyond the well-studied <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> group. As part of a such an endeavor, we recently reported on both pt and mitochondrial (mt) genomes of three eustigmatophytes representing three lineages progressively more distantly related to the <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> group, namely the genus <italic>Monodopsis</italic>, the Eustigmataceae group, and the Goniochloridales clade IIa (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref><xref rid="evz004-B50" ref-type="bibr">, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). These data enabled us to obtain various additional interesting insights into the evolution of the eustigmatophyte organellar genomes as such, as well as of eustigmatophytes themselves. For example, by carrying out a phylogenomic analysis utilizing pt genome data from three eustigmatophytes representing both principal clades of the group, that is, Eustigmatales (<italic>Nannochloropsis oceanica</italic> and <italic>Microchloropsis gaditana</italic>) and Goniochloridales (<italic>Trachydiscus minutus</italic>), we could solidify the phylogenetic relationship of eustigmatophytes to other ochrophytes, supporting their classification within the group Limnista together with chrysophytes (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>).</p><p>The most striking discovery came, however, with sequencing the pt genomes of <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202 and <italic>Monodopsis</italic> sp. MarTras21. Both turned out to harbor a unique six-gene cluster never seen before in any pt genome, yet homologous to a novel operon, denoted <italic>ebo</italic>. The operon occurs in diverse bacteria and encodes enzymes of an uncharacterized biochemical pathway that was hypothesized to produce a specific secondary metabolite (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Phylogenetic analyses suggested that the <italic>ebo</italic> operon was introduced via a single horizontal transfer event into the pt genome of a common ancestor of <italic>Vischeria</italic> and <italic>Monodopsis</italic>, implying its secondary loss from the <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> lineage (<italic>Monodopsis</italic> is more closely related to this lineage than to <italic>Vischeria</italic>). Furthermore, the putative donor of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon was suggested to be a bacterium belonging to the phylum Bacteroidetes (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>).</p><p>An interesting new twist in this story came with our recent discovery of a novel bacterial endosymbiont of <italic>T. minutus</italic> and characterization of its genomes (<xref rid="evz004-B65" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). The endosymbiont, described as <italic>Candidatus</italic> Phycorickettsia trachydisci (<italic>P. trachydisci</italic> for short), represents a new genus-level lineage of the family Rickettsiaceae, a group of obligate intracellular endosymbionts, primarily parasites, of various eukaryotes. Close relatives of <italic>P. trachydisci</italic> were detected in several other eustigmatophytes, representing both Goniochloridales and Eustigmatales, suggesting a widespread and possibly specific association of the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage with eustigmatophytes. Most strikingly, the <italic>P. trachydisci</italic> genome also harbors a copy of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon (uniquely among the whole order Rickettsiales) and phylogenetic analyses demonstrated that the <italic>ebo</italic> operons from <italic>P. trachydisci</italic> and eustigmatophyte pt genomes are specifically related. We proposed that eustigmatophytes gained the <italic>ebo</italic> operon from their rickettsiacean endosymbiont, which was the actual recipient of the operon from a Bacteroidetes-related donor. Given the presumed antiquity of the transfer event from <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> to the pt genome of the <italic>Vischeria</italic> and <italic>Monodopsis</italic> ancestor, we hypothesized that <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> and eustigmatophytes have been engaged in a long-term evolutionary partnership (<xref rid="evz004-B65" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>).</p><p>Further studies are obviously required to test this hypothesis. One of the key questions is how widespread the <italic>ebo</italic> operon is in eustigmatophyte pt genomes. Knowing this is critical for pinpointing the operon transfer event in eustigmatophyte phylogeny and may also give insights into the functional significance of the presence of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon. To answer this question, pt genome data from a wider array of phylogenetically diverse eustigmatophyte lineages are needed. With this in mind, we used the Illumina technology to generate large volumes of DNA sequence data from several phylogenetically diverse eustigmatophytes, which allowed us to extract and assemble complete sequences of their pt genomes. We exploited the new sequences to build a robust &#x0201c;backbone&#x0201d; phylogeny of the group and to address salient questions of pt genome evolution, including but not restricted to the origin and distribution of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon. In addition, analyses of partial nuclear genome data generated alongside the pt genome sequences enabled us to shed light on specific aspects of coevolution of the pt and nuclear genomes in eustigmatophytes, providing an unexpected new insight into the history of <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic>&#x02013;eustigmatophyte interaction.</p></sec><sec><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Algal Cultures</title><p>Six algal cultures were grown for the purpose of this study (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). <italic>Pseudellipsoidion edaphicum</italic> strain CAUP Q 401 was obtained from the Culture Collection of Algae of Charles University in Prague (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://botany.natur.cuni.cz/algo/caup.html">https://botany.natur.cuni.cz/algo/caup.html</ext-link>; last accessed January 22, 2019), spread out onto three agar plates (2% agar in Z-medium) of 90&#x02009;mm diameter, sealed with Parafilm, and grown at the incident light intensity of 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and at room temperature for 3 weeks. The algal culture ACOI 456 came from the Coimbra Collection of Algae (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://acoi.ci.uc.pt/spec_detail.php?cult_id=520">http://acoi.ci.uc.pt/spec_detail.php? cult_id=520</ext-link>; last accessed January 22, 2019) and cultivated up to a volume of 200&#x02009;ml in liquid Desmideacean Medium (<xref rid="evz004-B48" ref-type="bibr">Schl&#x000f6;sser 1994</xref>) pH 6.4&#x02013;6.6, at 23&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, a 16:8&#x02009;h photoperiod and under light intensity of 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;mol photons m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;</sup><sup>1</sup> provided by cool white fluorescent lamps. The previously reported unidentified eustigmatophyte strain Chic 10/23 P-6w (<xref rid="evz004-B13" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>) and three newly characterized eustigmatophyte strains Bat 8/9-7w, NDem 8/9 T-3m6.8, and Mont 10/10-1w (for their origin see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) were grown in liquid WH+ medium (<xref rid="evz004-B71" ref-type="bibr">Fawley et al. 2013</xref>) at 20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with a 14&#x02009;h:10&#x02009;h light:dark cycle using cool white fluorescent lights. Light intensity used was 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> for strains Chic 10/23 P-6w, Bat 8/9-7w and NDem 8/9 T-3m6.8, whereas Mont 10/10-1w was grown at &#x0223c;20&#x02009;&#x000b5;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. To confirm the phylogenetic position of the three previously uncharacterized strains, complete 18S rRNA gene sequences were identified in the respective genome assemblies (see below) and added to a manually curated alignment of all available eustigmatophyte 18S rRNA gene sequences. The ML tree was inferred from the alignment using RAxML v8.2.10 (<xref rid="evz004-B53" ref-type="bibr">Stamatakis 2014</xref>) and the GTR + &#x00393; + I substitution model, and branch support was assessed by the rapid bootstrapping algorithm implemented in the program.</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Isolation</title><p>Cells of the ACOI 456 culture were collected by centrifugation and disrupted using glass beads and a mixer mill (MM200, Retsch, Haan, Germany) for 5&#x02009;min. Genomic DNA was extracted from the homogenate using Invisorb Spin Plant Mini Kit (Stratec). DNA from the strains Chic 10/23 P-6w, Bat 8/9-7w, NDem 8/9 T-3m6.8, and Mont 10/10-1w was isolated using the procedure of <xref rid="evz004-B70" ref-type="bibr">Fawley and Fawley (2004)</xref> with minor modifications. Briefly, cells from rapidly growing cultures were harvested by centrifugation in 1.5&#x02009;ml screw-top tubes and washed with 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;l DNA extraction buffer (1&#x02009;M NaCl, 70&#x02009;mM Tris, 30&#x02009;mM disodium salt of ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid, pH 8.6). Strain Mont 10/10-1w, which grows in large clumps, was agitated without glass beads for about 2&#x02009;s with a MiniBeadBeater (BioSpec Products, Bartlesville, OK) before proceeding. Samples were then centrifuged and the extraction buffer was removed. Two hundred microliters of extraction buffer, 25&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of 10% DTAB, glass beadsl and 200&#x02009;&#x000b5;l of fresh molecular biology grade chloroform were added to each sample. Samples were shaken using a MiniBeadBeater for 30&#x02009;sec at highest cycle rate. After centrifugation for 4&#x02009;min at 5,000 rpm, the aqueous phase was removed and the DNA prepared using GenCleanTurbo Cartridges (MP Biomedicals North America, Solon, OH) following the manufacturers protocol using the genomic salt solution. DNA was quantified with the Qubit HE system (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>DNA Sequencing and Assembly</title><p>DNA from <italic>P. edaphicum</italic> CAUP Q 401 was sequenced using the HiSeq 2500 technology by the Genomics Core Facility, EMBL, Germany (insert length 300&#x02009;bp, read length 100&#x02009;bp). Reads were processed using Trimmomatic v0.32 (<xref rid="evz004-B5" ref-type="bibr">Bolger et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), adjusted using FLASH v1.2.9 (<xref rid="evz004-B38" ref-type="bibr">Mago&#x0010d; and Salzberg 2011</xref>), and assembled using SOAPdenovo-127mer v2.04 from the SOAP package (<xref rid="evz004-B36" ref-type="bibr">Luo et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>) with the Kmer size set to 77. The assembly was further improved using GapCloser v1.12 from the SOAP package. The remaining five DNA samples were sequenced using the HiSeq 2500 technology by Macrogen Inc. (Seoul, South Korea), with additional deep sequencing of the ACOI 456 culture performed using HiSeq X technology also at Macrogen. Reads were processed by Trimmomatic v0.36, and assembled using Spades v3.11.1 (<xref rid="evz004-B4" ref-type="bibr">Bankevich et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). The resulting assemblies were searched using Blast (<xref rid="evz004-B2" ref-type="bibr">Altschul et&#x000a0;al. 1997</xref>) with conserved pt genes as queries, and scaffolds or contigs corresponding to pt genomes were identified. In the case of the ACOI 456 culture, pt scaffolds of two very different read coverage values were assigned to the two different species, <italic>Characiopsis acuta</italic> (the only algal component of the culture observed in a light microscope) and an unidentified <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. (based on the high sequence similarity to the previously sequenced pt genome from <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202), although this alga was not seen in the culture and apparently represents a very minor fraction of the cells. Full assemblies of seven pt genome sequences were obtained manually with the aid of iterative read mapping with Bowtie2 v2.3.4.1 (<xref rid="evz004-B31" ref-type="bibr">Langmead and Salzberg 2012</xref>) onto intermediate and final assemblies. The presence of two copies of inverted repeats was considered, supported by the coverage of the respective scaffolds being two times higher than scaffolds representing single-copy regions of the same pt genome. Finally, all assemblies were validated by visual inspection of mapped reads in Tablet 1.14.04.10 (<xref rid="evz004-B39" ref-type="bibr">Milne et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Annotation of pt Genome Sequences</title><p>Initial annotation of the pt genomes was obtained using MFannot (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://megasun.bch.umontreal.ca/cgi-bin/mfannot/mfannotInterface.pl">http://megasun.bch.umontreal.ca/cgi-bin/mfannot/mfannotInterface.pl</ext-link>; last accessed January 22, 2019). Identification and delimitation of the genes provided by the program was checked manually by building multiple alignments of the newly annotated genes with homologs from previously sequenced eustigmatophyte and other ochrophyte organellar genomes. Modifications to the initial annotation, particularly concerning the definition of the initiation codon, were introduced when supported by sequence conservation in homologous sequences. Possible remote homologies of proteins encoded by eustigmatophyte-specific organellar open-reading frames (ORFs) were searched using HHpred (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/#/tools/hhpred">https://toolkit.tuebingen.mpg.de/#/tools/hhpred</ext-link>; last accessed January 22, 2019; <xref rid="evz004-B68" ref-type="bibr">Zimmermann et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). The presence of transmembrane helices in proteins was assessed using the TMHMM Server v. 2.0 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/">http://www.cbs.dtu.dk/services/TMHMM/</ext-link>; last accessed January 22, 2019; <xref rid="evz004-B28" ref-type="bibr">Krogh et&#x000a0;al. 2001</xref>). Short conserved protein-coding genes (e.g., <italic>secG</italic> or <italic>psaM</italic>), the conserved intron-containing <italic>trnL</italic>(uaa) gene, and the <italic>ssrA</italic> gene specifying tmRNA, missed by MFannot, were identified and manually integrated into the genome annotation. Putative intergenic regions were further systematically checked by BlastN and BlastX to detect possible additional genes that escaped automated annotation. MFannot does not distinguish genes specifying initiator fMet-tRNA, elongator Met-tRNA, and Ile-tRNA cognate to the AUA codon, which all exhibit the anticodon CAU (with the cytosine post-transcriptionally modified to lysidine in case of Ile-tRNA<sub>CAU</sub>). The proper annotation of these genes was achieved by careful comparison to homologs in previously annotated organellar genomes. All seven newly sequenced and annotated pt genome sequences were deposited at GenBank with accession numbers listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online.</p></sec><sec><title>Plastid Phylogenomic Analysis</title><p>Based on preliminary analyses, 68 pt protein-coding genes were selected to construct a supermatrix for a phylogenomic analysis. Specifically, for each conserved pt gene, the respective protein sequences were collected from the newly sequenced species, previously reported eustigmatophyte genomes (selecting only a single representative for each <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> and <italic>Microchloropsis</italic> species), a selection of other ochrophytes (maximizing the representation of different classes), and a selection of nonochrophyte taxa (cryptophytes and haptophytes) and the outgroup. The protein sequences were aligned using MAFFT v7 (<xref rid="evz004-B25" ref-type="bibr">Katoh and Standley 2013</xref>), the alignments were trimmed using TrimAl v. 1.3 (<xref rid="evz004-B6" ref-type="bibr">Capella-Gutierrez et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>), with the &#x0201c;Gappyout&#x0201d; setting to remove poorly conserved regions, and the trimmed alignments were concatenated using FASconCAT v1.04 (<xref rid="evz004-B30" ref-type="bibr">K&#x000fc;ck and Meusemann 2010</xref>). All alignments are available upon request. Phylogenetic trees were inferred from the supermatrices using the maximum likelihood (ML) method implemented in IQ-TREE v1.5 (<xref rid="evz004-B41" ref-type="bibr">Nguyen et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) and Bayesian inference implemented in PhyloBayes-MPI v1.7 (<xref rid="evz004-B32" ref-type="bibr">Lartillot et&#x000a0;al. 2013</xref>). The ML tree was inferred using the most complex approach available for modeling the substitution process, that is, employing the posterior mean site frequency (PMSF) model (<xref rid="evz004-B59" ref-type="bibr">Wang et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), specifically the cpREV + C20 + F&#x02009;+&#x02009;&#x00393;-PMSF model, and ultrafast bootstrapping (based on 1,000 replicates) was used for assessing branch support. Two chains of PhyloBayes were run for 4,002 and 4,042 generations, respectively, reaching convergence (maxdiff of 0.0). Eight hundred generations were removed as burn-in, and the consensus tree was calculated by summing every tenth generation from the rest. Trees were visualized using iTOL (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://itol.embl.de/upload.cgi">http://itol.embl.de/upload.cgi</ext-link>; last accessed January 22, 2019) and adjusted in a graphical editor.</p></sec><sec><title>Analyses of Nuclear Genes for pt-Targeted Proteins</title><p>Using BlastP or TBlastN, nuclear homologs of selected pt genes were searched in available eustigmatophyte nuclear genome data, including the previously published genome assemblies from <italic>Nanno-</italic>/<italic>Microchloropsis</italic> species, partial nuclear genome sequences present in assemblies of Illumina sequencing data obtained for this study, and incomplete nuclear genome and transcriptome data generated in frame of our on-going sequencing projects for <italic>T. minutus</italic>, <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202, and <italic>Monodopsis</italic> sp. MarTras21 (which also yielded the previously published organellar genomes from these species; see <xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref><xref rid="evz004-B50" ref-type="bibr">, 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Significantly similar hits (e-value &#x02264;0.01) were evaluated and coding sequences (exon-intron structures) were manually validated or deduced de novo based on transcriptome data (if available) or sequence conservation among homologs. For phylogenetic analyses of the FtrB, Rpl26 and acyl carrier protein (ACP) families, a selection of homologs was gathered by searching the NCBI nonredundant protein sequence database and, in order to sample ochrophyte classes not represented in the NCBI database, transcriptome assemblies generated by the MMETSP project (<xref rid="evz004-B26" ref-type="bibr">Keeling et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). Sequences were aligned using MAFFT, the alignments were trimmed manually to remove poorly conserved regions, and trees were inferred using IQ-TREE, with the most appropriate substitution models selected by the program. N-terminal presequences in nucleus-encoded putatively pt-targeted proteins were evaluated using ASAFind (<xref rid="evz004-B20" ref-type="bibr">Gruber et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) for proteins from ochrophytes, haptophytes, and chrompodellids; a combination of PredSL (<xref rid="evz004-B43" ref-type="bibr">Petsalaki et&#x000a0;al. 2006</xref>) and ChloroP 1.1 (<xref rid="evz004-B12" ref-type="bibr">Emanuelsson et&#x000a0;al. 1999</xref>) for proteins from other algae with secondary plastids; and ChloroP for proteins from eukaryotes with the primary plastid. The presence of mt transit peptides in the putative mitochondrion-targeted ACP proteins was confirmed using TargetP 1.1 (<xref rid="evz004-B11" ref-type="bibr">Emanuelsson et&#x000a0;al. 2000</xref>). Sequences of relevant nuclear genes extracted from our unpublic genome and transcriptome assemblies were deposited at GenBank with accession numbers provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary tables S3&#x02013;S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online. The present working assemblies are available upon request, whereas full publication of these data is planned after critical improvements (including removal of contaminations) and more systematic analyses have been carried out.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Eustigmatophyte Phylogeny Resolved by pt Phylogenomic Analyses</title><p>In total, we obtained complete pt genome sequences from seven eustigmatophytes. The sequencing targets were selected based on their phylogenetic position inferred from the 18S rRNA gene sequences (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) to sample across the eustigmatophyte phylogenetic diversity. Thus, we report on the first organellar genomes from the clades IIc in Goniochloridales (strain Chic 10/23&#x02009;P-6w) and from the <italic>Pseudellipsoidion</italic> group in Eustigmatales (<italic>P. edaphicum</italic> CAUP Q 401). Particularly notable is the inclusion of the newly characterized strain Mont 10/10-1w in the analysis. This strain proved to represent a novel eustigmatophyte lineage sister to the known Eustigmatales (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). Sequencing the pt genomes of <italic>C</italic><italic>.</italic><italic>acuta</italic> ACOI 456 improved sampling of the highly diverse Eustigmataceae group, whereas inclusion of the strains Bat 8/9-7w and NDem 8/9&#x02009;T-3m6.8 allowed us to evaluate the pt genome variation within the Goniochloridales clade IIa.</p><p>The seventh pt genome was sequenced accidentally as a result of microscopically unnoticed minor component of the ACOI 456 culture. Based on sequences of the 18S rRNA gene (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), <italic>rbcL</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) and the pt genome (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>), it was identified as a representative of the genus <italic>Vischeria</italic>, hereafter referred to as of <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. ACOI 3415. This was a welcome addition to our sampling, as it enabled us to assess the conservation of unusual features of previously sequenced pt genome of <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202, particularly the presence of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon, among the relatives of this alga. The degree of sequence divergence between the two <italic>Vischeria</italic> strains (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>) is comparable to that exhibited by different formally recognized species of the genera <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> and <italic>Microchloropsis</italic>, so for the purpose of this study we consider the two <italic>Vischeria</italic> strains as representatives of two different species. Whether they can be identified as some of the formally described <italic>Vischeria</italic> species or whether any of them represent a new species remains to be resolved, together with the very much needed critical taxonomic revision of the genus as a whole (see <xref rid="evz004-B29" ref-type="bibr">Kryvenda et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>).</p><p>All sequenced pt genomes are conventional circular-mapping molecules (supplementary figs. S3&#x02013;S9, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The size and the gene content of the newly sequenced genomes are comparable to the previously sequenced ones (<xref rid="evz004-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). All seven genomes include the typical inverted repeat regions separated by short and long single-copy regions, with the number of genes in the inverted repeat slightly varying between taxa (<xref rid="evz004-T1" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="evz004-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Basic Characteristics of the Newly Sequenced Plastid Genomes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/><col valign="top" align="char" char="." span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="3" style="#5B9BD5" colspan="1"/><th colspan="4" style="#5B9BD5" align="center" rowspan="1">Eustigmatales<hr/></th><th colspan="3" style="#5B9BD5" align="center" rowspan="1">Goniochloridales<hr/></th></tr><tr><th colspan="2" style="#D2DEEF" align="center" rowspan="1">Eustigmataceae Group<hr/></th><th style="#D2DEEF" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudellipsoidion</italic> Group<hr/></th><th style="#D2DEEF" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">New Lineage<hr/></th><th colspan="2" style="#D2DEEF" align="center" rowspan="1">Clade IIa<hr/></th><th style="#D2DEEF" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clade IIc<hr/></th></tr><tr><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. ACOI 3415</th><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Characiopsis acuta</italic> ACOI 456</th><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudellipsoidion edaphicum</italic> CAUP Q 401</th><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain Mont 10/10-1w</th><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain Ndem 8/9T-3m6.8</th><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain Bat 8/9-7w</th><th style="#EAEFF7" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain Chic 10/23 P-6w</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Size (bp)</bold></td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126,352</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121,124</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123,658</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">117,466</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120,715</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120,042</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125,946</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>inverted repeat (bp)</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,783</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,379</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,777</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,323</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,434</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9,446</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10,072</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>LSC region (bp)</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62,223</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,382</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,318</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54,099</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56,274</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,928</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55,586</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>SSC region (bp)</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,563</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,984</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48,786</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44,721</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,573</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45,232</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50,216</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Total GC content (%)</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.43</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.51</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.18</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.35</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.83</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.66</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.59</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Gene content (total)</bold></td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">161</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">166</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">170</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Common conserved plastid protein-coding genes</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">125</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">128</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Conserved group-specific genes (<italic>ycf95</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>orf1_gon</italic></bold>, <bold><italic>orf1_eust</italic>)</bold></td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>ebo</italic> operon genes</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>ORFs without homologs</bold></td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>rRNA genes</bold></td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>tRNA genes</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Other noncoding RNA genes (only <italic>ssrA</italic>)</bold></td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td style="#D2DEEF" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td style="#5B9BD5" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Number of genes in inverted repeat</bold></td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td style="#EAEFF7" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn1"><p><sc>Note</sc>.&#x02014;Genes present in inverted repeats are counted only once for the gene counts provided in the table. Abbreviations used: LSC, long single-copy region; SSC, short single-copy region; ORFs, open-reading frames.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Plastid genomes have proven to be a particularly useful source of data to reconstruct the phylogenetic relationships of plants and algae at various phylogenetic scales (e.g., <xref rid="evz004-B16" ref-type="bibr">Fu&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B34" ref-type="bibr">Leliaert et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B23" ref-type="bibr">Jackson et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B18" ref-type="bibr">Gitzendanner et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), and also provided insights into the phylogeny of ochrophytes (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) and their specific sublineages, especially diatoms (<xref rid="evz004-B64" ref-type="bibr">Yu et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). Hence, we exploited the newly obtained sequences to improve our understanding of the phylogeny of eustigmatophytes. To this end, we built a supermatrix of 68 conserved proteins encoded by the pt genomes of eustigmatophytes, other ochrophytes, and selected other algal lineages (comprising 18,378 reliably aligned amino acid positions), and inferred trees using two different methods (Bayesian inference and ML) and different substitution models (CAT + GTR and cpREV + C20 + F &#x02009; + &#x02009;&#x00393;-PMSF, respectively). Both analyses arrived at essentially the same topology (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F1">fig.&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S10</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), with the only difference concerning a position of the diatom <italic>Thalassiosira pseudonana</italic> (sister to all other diatoms in the PhyloBayes tree or to <italic>Trieres sinensis</italic> in the ML tree). All branches in the PhyloBayes tree and most branches in the ML tree (including the stem and internal branches of the eustigmatophyte subtree), received maximal support. The inferred relationships among the main ochrophyte lineages are congruent with previous analyses of pt genome data (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B55" ref-type="bibr">TajiMa et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Eustigmatophytes are resolved sister to the lineage represented by the chrysophyte <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393 (and presumably including other ochrophyte taxa so far lacking pt genome data, such as synchromophytes; see <xref rid="evz004-B63" ref-type="bibr">Yang et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>The topology of the eustigmatophyte subtree is generally in accord with the analysis of the 18S rRNA gene (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The added value of the pt genome analysis is primarily complete resolution of the internal topology of the Eustigmatales. Thus, the strain Mont 10/10-1w is resolved with maximal support as the new sister branch of Eustigmatales as currently circumscribed. This confirms that Mont 10/10-1w represents a novel lineage that is best classified as a separate family of Eustigmatales. The full support in the pt phylogenomic analysis for <italic>P. edaphicum</italic> (representing the <italic>Pseudellipsodion</italic> group) as a sister group of Eustigmataceae group plus Monodopsidaceae, and for the strain NDem 8/9&#x02009;T-3m6.8 as being sister to the other clade IIa representatives, resolves conflicting positions of these taxa in the 18S rRNA-based tree (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) and the <italic>rbcL</italic>-based tree (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p></sec><sec><title>Defining the Ancestral pt Gene Set of Eustigmatophytes</title><p>The highly improved sampling of eustigmatophyte pt genomes and the robustly resolved phylogeny of the group enabled us to reconstruct the evolutionary history of the changes of the pt gene content in the eustigmatophyte lineage in an unprecedented detail. We start with a description of the inference of the ancestral eustigmatophyte pt gene complement. A gene was considered ancestral if it was present in at least some representatives of both principal eustigmatophyte groups (Eustigmatales and Goniochloridales) or if it was shared by pt genomes of at least some eustigmatophytes and another algal group.</p><p>This reasoning yielded at least 167 genes, including 135 protein-coding genes (counting the split <italic>clpC</italic> gene as two separate genes, see below) and 32 genes specifying noncoding RNAs evidently present in the pt genome of the last eustigmatophyte common ancestor (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The vast majority of them are typical conserved genes with readily identifiable orthologs in other taxa, whereas establishing orthology of a few genes required a more careful analysis. Specifically, the expanded sampling now enabled us to recognize that the eustigmatophyte gene previously referred to as <italic>orf60</italic> (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) is in fact an ortholog of <italic>secG</italic>. The assignment is supported by an HHpred search and a position of the gene just downstream of <italic>petM</italic> that is shared with many other ochrophyte pt genomes. Considering synteny as a clue we were able to identify a previously missed (unannotated) <italic>secG</italic> gene in the pt genomes of pelagophytes, <italic>Heterosigma akashiwo</italic>, and <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393 (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S11</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The <italic>secG</italic> gene thus belongs to the core of ubiquitous ochrophyte pt genes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p><p>Another update concerns the eustigmatophyte gene previously referred to as <italic>orf403</italic>/<italic>457</italic> (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). The gene is rapidly evolving, as evident from the fact that simple BlastP searches are not sensitive enough to reveal homology of the respective sequences from distantly related eustigmatophytes, and no candidate homologs outside eustigmatophytes could previously be identified even when using more sensitive methods. However, the substantially expanded sampling of <italic>orf403</italic>/<italic>457</italic> sequences improved the sensitivity of an HHpred search, which suggested homology of the C-terminal half of the Orf403/457 protein to the Pfam TIC20 family (PF16166) with the probability value &#x0003e;90. The TIC20 family includes not only the key component of the TIC translocon at the inner plastidial membrane but also the Ycf60 protein encoded by pt genomes of several algal groups including rhodophytes, haptophytes, and, notably, some ochrophytes, namely phaeophytes and xanthophytes (<xref rid="evz004-B33" ref-type="bibr">Le Corguill&#x000e9; et&#x000a0;al. 2009</xref>), but arguably not eustigmatophytes (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). To better understand the distribution of the <italic>ycf60</italic> gene in ochrophytes, we employed the known Ycf60 sequence from the brown alga <italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus</italic> as a query for a PSI-Blast search, which led to the identification of previously unrecognized <italic>ycf60</italic> genes in pt genomes of pelagophytes and the bolidophyte <italic>Triparma laevis</italic>. Interestingly, the <italic>ycf60</italic> gene in the <italic>T. laevis</italic> pt genome is positioned (in the head-to-head orientation) next to the <italic>secA</italic> gene, exactly as the &#x0201c;<italic>orf403</italic>/<italic>457</italic>&#x0201d; gene in strain Mont 10/10-1w and <italic>P. edaphicum</italic> CAP Q 401; the relative position of <italic>secA</italic> and &#x0201c;<italic>orf403</italic>/<italic>457</italic>&#x0201d; in other eustigmatophytes differs only by an insertion of an extra gene (<italic>orf1_eust</italic> and <italic>orf1_gon</italic>, see below) between them (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S12</xref><italic>A</italic>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). In addition, the pt genome from <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393 includes an unannotated gene (<italic>orf215</italic>) occupying the same position with respect to <italic>secA</italic> as the <italic>ycf60</italic> gene in <italic>T. laevis</italic> and eustigmatophytes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S12</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) yet lacking any significant hits when investigated by BlastP. We aligned it with homologs identified in chrysophyte transcriptome assemblies and carried out an HHpred search, which indicated homology to the TIC20 family with the probability value &#x0003e;94. The respective eustigmatophyte and chrysophyte proteins all include multiple predicted transmembrane helices, similar to known Ycf60 proteins (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S12</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The most parsimonious interpretation of these observations is that the eustigmatophyte &#x0201c;<italic>orf403</italic>/<italic>457</italic>&#x0201d; and the chrysophyte &#x0201c;<italic>orf215</italic>&#x0201d; genes are highly divergent forms of the ancestrally present <italic>ycf60</italic> gene; hence, we reannotated them accordingly. The functional significance of the N-terminal extension acquired by the eustigmatophyte Ycf60 proteins (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S12</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) remains unknown.</p><p>We previously reported that the eustigmatophytes are the only ochrophyte lineage that has retained the <italic>ycf49</italic> gene in their pt genome (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). Here, we not only document that this still holds true despite the substantially improved sampling of the ochrophyte pt genomes, but we unveil one more such gene. The <italic>trnL</italic>(caa) gene, so far known only from the <italic>T. minutus</italic> pt genome (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), has orthologs in other Goniochloridales as well as two of the newly sequenced Eustigmatales species (<italic>P. edaphicum</italic> and <italic>C. acuta</italic>), so we can infer that it was present in the ancestral eustigmatophyte pt genome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Furthermore, despite being absent from all other ochrophyte pt genomes sequenced so far, it has homologs in pt genomes from some other algal groups, including red algae and cryptophytes. The similarly patchy distribution of <italic>ycf49</italic> led <xref rid="evz004-B9" ref-type="bibr">Dorrell and Bowler (2017)</xref> to propose that the gene was introduced into the eustigmatophyte lineage by a horizontal gene transfer (HGT) event, so the same explanation is analogously applicable to the <italic>trnL</italic>(caa) gene. However, as previously discussed for <italic>ycf49</italic> (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>) and as pointed to here for <italic>trnL</italic>(caa), both genes in eustigmatophyte pt genomes occupy positions that are syntenic with the location of the genes in pt genomes of other algae. Specifically, <italic>ycf49</italic> is flanked by <italic>petL</italic> and <italic>ycf4</italic> in both eustigmatophytes and cyanidiophytes, and <italic>trnL</italic>(caa) is upstream of the <italic>sufB</italic> gene in both eustigmatophytes and cryptophytes. In our view, this favors the scenario invoking vertical inheritance of these genes in the eustigmatophyte lineage (and multiple losses in other ochrophytes) over the alternative explanation employing HGT.</p><p>Nevertheless, the eustigmatophyte pt genomes do include genes that seem to have been created or acquired more recently. We previously documented stepwise additions to the pt gene number in the Limnista lineage by fragmentation of the ancestral <italic>clpC</italic> gene, initiated by separation of regions encoding the N- and C-terminal parts of the ClpC protein before the divergence of chrysophytes and eustigmatophytes, followed by separation of the region encoding the very N-terminal domain of the ClpC protein in the eustigmatophyte stem lineage (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). Our expanded sampling documents that the state with the three separate genes encoding different parts of the ClpC protein is common to all eustigmatophytes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p><p>Further potential novelties of the eustigmatophyte pt genome are found among some of the remaining unidentified ORFs. One encodes a protein of &#x0223c;120 amino acids conserved in all eustigmatophyte pt genomes sequenced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S13</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), but we could not identify any candidate homologs outside of this group even when using HHpred or when considering its position relative to other genes as a clue. Following the convention for naming conserved pt genes of unknown function (<xref rid="evz004-B21" ref-type="bibr">Hallick and Bairoch 1994</xref>) and considering <italic>ycf94</italic> being the most recently described gene in this category (<xref rid="evz004-B52" ref-type="bibr">Song et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), we designate the respective ORF as <italic>ycf95</italic>. It is possible that the encoded Ycf95 mediates some eustigmatophyte-specific pt function, but we cannot rule out the possibility that <italic>ycf95</italic> is a highly divergent ortholog of some of the standard pt genes apparently missing from eustigmatophytes (such as some of the broadly conserved <italic>ycf</italic> genes; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).</p><p>All eustigmatophytes, except for <italic>P. edaphicum</italic> and the strain Mont 10/10-1w, additionally exhibit an unidentified ORF located at the syntenic position upstream of the <italic>ycf60</italic> gene (supplementary figs. S3&#x02013;S9, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Comparison of the encoded protein sequences supports homology of the ORFs within Goniochloridales and within Eustigmatales, but there is no indication (other than synteny) that the proteins would be homologous across eustigmatophytes as a whole. Hence, it remains unclear whether this is an ancestral eustigmatophyte gene that has followed very different evolutionary trajectories in the two main eustigmatophyte lineages, or whether the ORFs emerged independently in Goniochloridales and Eustigmatales. Given this uncertainty, these genes are provisionally annotated as <italic>orf1_gon</italic>&#x000a0;and <italic>orf1_eust</italic>, depending on which undeniable group of homologs they belong to.</p></sec><sec><title>Pinpointing the Acquisition of the <italic>e</italic><italic>bo</italic> Operon in Eustigmatophyte Evolution</title><p>In addition to contributing to the ancestral pt gene set of eustigmatophytes as a whole, gene acquisition has been one of the sources of variation of pt genomes among different eustigmatophytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). Two different eustigmatophyte lineages have their pt gene complements potentially expanded by ORFs lacking discernible orthologs in other eustigmatophytes or other organisms, including <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic>. Six such ORFs (in two clusters comprising two and four ORFs, respectively) occur in the pt genome of the Chic 10/23 P-6w strain, and five ORFs (in three unique genomic regions including one, two, and two ORFs, respectively) are found in the <italic>P. edaphicum</italic> pt genome (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref> and supplementary figs. S3 and S7, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Whether these ORFs are translated to produce functional proteins or not, what might be the function of the encoded proteins, and what is the origin of the respective DNA regions remains presently unknown.
</p><fig id="evz004-F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 2.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Major events in the evolution of the pt genomes in eustigmatophytes. The scheme shows inferred events of gene loss and gain along the eustigmatophyte phylogeny. The pt genome of the chrysophyte <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393 (a representative of the presumed sister lineage of eustigmatophytes) is included to provide a broader phylogenetic context. Genes lost are in red, genes gained are in blue (&#x0201c;<italic>ebo</italic>&#x0201d; refers to gain or loss of the whole operon). Losses mapped before divergence of <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. and eustigmatophytes may have happened at various deep branches of the ochrophyte phylogeny. Possible homology of <italic>orf1_gon</italic> and <italic>orf1_eust</italic> genes is discussed and detail concerning the split <italic>sufB</italic> gene (or pseudogene?) are provided in the main text. Note labels of some genes (e.g., <italic>acpP</italic>) at multiple branches in the tree, indicating multiple independent losses during the eustigmatophyte evolution. Taxa printed in bold are those for which the pt genome sequence is reported in this study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz004f2"/></fig><p>More obvious is the origin and functional significance of the acquisition of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon. As mentioned in Introduction, we previously identified this novel six-gene cluster in pt genomes of two eustigmatophytes, <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202 and <italic>Monodopsis</italic> sp. MarTras21 (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Of the seven newly sequenced pt genomes, only one&#x02014;the one from the second <italic>Vischeria</italic> representative&#x02014;proved to contain a copy of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S9</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), whereas all six <italic>ebo</italic> genes are missing from the remaining six pt genomes. Considering the occurrence of the operon and phylogenetic relationships in eustigmatophytes, the most parsimonious scenario implies gain of the operon, most likely from a bacterial endosymbiont representing the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage (<xref rid="evz004-B65" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), in an exclusive ancestor of the Eustigmataceae group and Monodopsidaceae (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The lack of the operon from pt genomes of <italic>C. acuta</italic> (in the Eustigmataceae group) and the <italic>Nanno-/Microchloropsis</italic> clade (in Monodopsidaceae) must then reflect at least two independent losses of the operon. An alternative scenario would be independent acquisition of the operon in the <italic>Vischeria</italic> and <italic>Monodopsis</italic> lineages. However, gene gain by HGT seem to be a priori a less likely event than gene loss, and the syntenic position of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon in the pt genomes of both <italic>Vischeria</italic> strains and <italic>Monodopsis</italic> sp. MarTras21 (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S9</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online, and <xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) strongly favors a single gain event.</p><p>Answering the question as to why the <italic>ebo</italic> operon has been retained by some eustigmatophytes but lost by others awaits identification and functional characterization of the metabolite putatively synthesized by the suite of enzymes encoded by the <italic>ebo</italic> operon. Very recently, a genetic study of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon in the cyanobacterium <italic>Nostoc punctiforme</italic> indicated that the product of the Ebo proteins-mediated pathway is critical for the export of a precursor of the natural sunscreen scytonemin from the cytoplasm into the periplasm (<xref rid="evz004-B27" ref-type="bibr">Klicki et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>). However, the identity of the product and the mechanism of its action have not been clarified, and it is presently unclear how the findings from the cyanobacterium relate to the role of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon in other taxa, including eustigmatophytes, which do not make scytonemin.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene Loss in Eustigmatophyte pt Genome Evolution</title><p>Like organellar genomes in general, the dominant process that has sculpted the content of eustigmatophyte pt genomes is gene loss. Twenty conserved pt genes present in various ochrophyte lineages are missing from all eustigmatophyte pt genomes sequenced (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Of these, the most intriguing is the absence of the gene <italic>rpl24</italic>, which is retained in all other ochrophyte pt genomes sequenced so far. All other conserved pt genes universally missing from eustigmatophytes are also absent from at least some other ochrophytes. Three of them, <italic>ilvH</italic>, <italic>ftrB</italic>, and <italic>syfB</italic>, are present in the pt genome of the chrysophyte <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393 representing the putative sister lineage of eustigmatophytes, suggesting that they were lost in the eustigmatophyte stem lineage independently of various other ochrophytes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The absence of 16 genes (<italic>dnaB</italic>, <italic>hlip</italic>, <italic>rpl9</italic>, <italic>rpoZ</italic>, <italic>rps1</italic>, <italic>ycf26</italic>, <italic>ycf27</italic>, <italic>ycf33</italic>, <italic>ycf35</italic>, <italic>ycf37</italic>, <italic>ycf39</italic>, <italic>ycf41</italic>, <italic>ycf42</italic>, <italic>ycf45</italic>, <italic>ycf65</italic>, and <italic>ffs</italic>) is shared with the pt genome of <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393 and usually some other ochrophytes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online), so these might have been dispensed with prior to the radiation of the Limnista clade (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>It remains theoretically possible that some of the apparent gene absences are due to their extreme divergence obscuring their identity rather than their genuine loss. This was particularly pertinent in the case of the <italic>ffs</italic> gene specifying the RNA component (4.5S RNA) of the plastidial signal recognition particle (cpSRP), because genes for noncoding RNAs are often poorly conserved and difficult to recognize. However, differential occurrence of 4.5S RNA in ochrophyte plastids (with eustigmatophytes not considered) was noticed previously and the absences were linked to specific mutations in the protein SRP component, the protein cpSRP54, that presumably abolish the ability of the protein to bind the RNA partner (<xref rid="evz004-B56" ref-type="bibr">Tr&#x000e4;ger et&#x000a0;al. 2012</xref>). Here, we report that eustigmatophytes and representatives of some other previously unstudied ochrophyte groups (the chrysophyte <italic>Ochromonas</italic> sp. CCMP 1393, the xanthophyte <italic>Vaucheria litorea</italic>, and the raphidophyte <italic>Heterosigma akashiwo</italic>) all exhibit mutations in the two motifs of their cpSRP54 critical for 4.5S RNA binding (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F3">fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>), and in perfect correlation with these changes they all lack discernible <italic>ffs</italic> gene in their pt genomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This supports the notion that the <italic>ffs</italic> gene is truly absent from eustigmatophytes and many other ochrophytes rather than being difficult to detect.
</p><fig id="evz004-F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 3.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Recurrent loss of 4.5S RNA (the RNA component of the plastidial SRP specified by the <italic>ffs</italic> gene) in ochrophytes. The figure shows a segment of a multiple sequence alignment of cpSRP54 (the protein component of the plastidial SRP) including two motifs critical for binding of the 4.5S RNA molecule. The presence of a discernible <italic>ffs</italic> gene in the pt genome of the respective species is indicated on the left by a red square. Note the perfect correlation between the conservation of the 4.5S RNA-binding motif in cpSRP54 (shown in red beneath the alignment) and the presence of the <italic>ffs</italic> gene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz004f3"/></fig><p>Further losses have differentially affected individual eustigmatophyte lineages, thus contributing to the variation in the pt genome content of different species (<xref rid="evz004-T2" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S2</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Two genes, <italic>rbcR</italic> and <italic>tsf</italic>, have been retained by Goniochloridales but lost in all Eustigmatales (incl. strain Mont 10/10-1w), whereas <italic>ycf36</italic> is missing from all Goniochloridales and from the strain Mont 10/10-1w, indicating two independent loss events. Some Eustigmatales lack the <italic>trnL(caa)</italic> gene as a result of at least three independent loss events, and the genus <italic>Microchloropsis</italic> has further lost the <italic>trnR(ccg)</italic> gene. The <italic>acpP</italic> gene exhibits sporadic distribution in Eustigmatales due to four inferred independent losses (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The previously reported absence of the <italic>psbZ</italic> gene in <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202 (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>) seems to be shared by not only the second <italic>Vischeria</italic> species sequenced but also <italic>C. acuta</italic> ACOI 456, so it may be a specific feature of the whole Eustigmataceae group.
<table-wrap id="evz004-T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Plastid Gene Loss and Compensatory Mechanisms or Adaptations in Eustigmatophytes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/><col valign="top" align="left" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Monodopsis</italic> sp. MarTras21</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microchloropsis</italic> spp.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> spp.</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. ACOI 3415</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Characiopsis. acuta</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Pseudellipsoidion edaphicum</italic></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strain Mont 10/10-1w</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goniochloridales</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Compensatory Mechanism/Adaptation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ilvH</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None apparent (&#x02192; changed way of regulation of acetohydroxyacid synthase)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ycf36</italic></td><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None apparent (&#x02192; functional consequences unknown)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rbcR</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None apparent (&#x02192; changed way of regulation of <italic>rbcL</italic> gene expression)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>tsf</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None apparent (&#x02192; changed way of regulation of the plastidial EF-Tu)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>psb28</italic></td><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003a8;</td><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None apparent (&#x02192; simplified composition of the photosystem II)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>psbZ</italic></td><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">None apparent (&#x02192; change in the antenna&#x02013;core interface of the photosystem II)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trnL(caa)</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Functional redundancy with the <italic>trnL(uaa)</italic> gene product (wobble pairing at the third codon position)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>trnR(ccg)</italic></td><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Potential redundancy with a modified (deaminated) product of the <italic>trnR(acg)</italic> gene<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn3"><sup>a</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>syfB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dual targeting of monomeric mitochondrial phenylalanyl-tRNA synthetase?<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn4"><sup>b</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>ftrB</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleus-encoded plastid-targeted homolog (presumably derived from EGT)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn5"><sup>c</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>rpl24</italic></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleus-encoded plastid-targeted paralog of the L26 subunit of the cytosolic ribosome<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn6"><sup>d</sup></xref></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>acpP</italic></td><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td style="#99CCFF" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nucleus-encoded plastid-targeted homolog obtained by HGT (from the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tblfn7"><sup>e</sup></xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tblfn2"><p><sc>Note</sc>.&#x02014;The table lists all conserved plastid genes inferred to have been lost at any point of the eustigmatophyte phylogeny (including the stem branch). Presence/absence of the genes in individual taxa is indicated by blue and white squares, respectively (for simplicity, related species or strains with the same gene occurrence pattern were grouped into broader taxa). The Greek letter &#x003a8; indicates that the <italic>psb28</italic> gene in <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202 is likely a pseudogene. For each gene, a mechanism or adaptation that seems to compensate for the respective gene loss in the taxa concerned is indicated; if none is apparent, putative functional consequences of the gene loss are specified.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn3"><label>a</label><p>See <xref rid="evz004-B44" ref-type="bibr">Pfitzinger et&#x000a0;al. (1990)</xref> and <xref rid="evz004-B1" ref-type="bibr">Alkatib et&#x000a0;al. (2012)</xref>.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn4"><label>b</label><p>See <xref rid="evz004-B17" ref-type="bibr">Gile et&#x000a0;al. (2015)</xref> for an analogous situation is some other ochrophytes.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn5"><label>c</label><p>See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary figure S15</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn6"><label>d</label><p>See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F4">figure&#x000a0;4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online.</p></fn><fn id="tblfn7"><label>e</label><p>See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F5">figure&#x000a0;5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><p>Some eustigmatophyte pt genomes record an intermediate stage of gene loss. We previously observed apparent pseudogenization of the <italic>psb28</italic> (<italic>psbW</italic>) gene in <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202 (<xref rid="evz004-B66" ref-type="bibr">Yurchenko et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Apparently, this is a recent event, not shared by the newly sequenced <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. ACOI 3415. The <italic>sufB</italic> gene in the pt genome of <italic>P. edaphicum</italic> may represent another case of ongoing pseudogenization. The <italic>sufB</italic> coding sequence has been interrupted by a frame-shift mutation due to a single-nucleotide insertion (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S14</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The insertion is not an artifact of the sequence assembly, as it is unambiguously supported by visual inspection of mapped raw reads and is present also in a contig found in the transcriptome assembly and representing a partial transcript derived from the <italic>P. edaphicum sufB</italic> gene. The apparent <italic>sufB</italic> disruption does not seem to be compensated for by the existence of a nuclear copy of the gene (based on our searches of genome and transcriptome data from <italic>P. edaphicum</italic>), which is surprising, because the SufB protein is an essential component of the plastidial SUF system for the assembly of Fe&#x02013;S clusters (<xref rid="evz004-B35" ref-type="bibr">Lu 2018</xref>). However, as detailed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary figure S14</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online, and the associated legend, it is possible that the gene is still functional, producing an N-terminally truncated SufB protein alone or together with a separately translated short protein representing the &#x003b1;-helical N-terminus of the full-length SufB. Sequencing of pt genomes of additional members of the <italic>Pseudellipsoidion</italic> group will help to clarify the functionality of the <italic>sufB</italic> gene in <italic>P. edaphicum</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Different Modes of Functional Compensation of pt Gene Loss in Eustigmatophyte Evolution</title><p>Gene loss from organellar genomes is a pervasive phenomenon, but each individual loss raises a question whether and how it is functionally compensated. Some losses may manifest a degree of inherent redundancy of the system. For example, the loss of the <italic>trnL(caa)</italic> gene from several Eustigmatales probably reflects the ability of the product of the <italic>trnL(uaa)</italic> gene (common in eustigmatophyte pt genomes) to decode the UUG codon thanks to wobble pairing of the first anticodon position with the third codon position. Other losses of pt genes perhaps signify true loss of the respective functionality, entailing simplification of metabolic or regulatory functions in the organelle. Finally, specific adaptations providing direct or alternative functional complementation are associated with still other organellar gene losses. These are typically ensured by targeting into the organelle specific proteins encoded by nuclear genes, often homologous to the missing pt genes. We exploited available nuclear genomic data from diverse representatives of the group (both published genome assemblies from <italic>Nanno-</italic>/<italic>Microchloropsis</italic> species and the partial data obtained by us as part of the pt genome sequencing) to illuminate the functional significance of the gene losses that have impacted eustigmatophyte pt genomes. For the sake of focus, we ignored losses that seem to predate the divergence of eustigmatophytes from other ochrophyte classes. We searched for homologs of the missing pt genes and evaluated the presence of the characteristic N-terminal bipartite presequence that would indicate plastid targeting. The results are summarized in <xref rid="evz004-T2" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;2</xref> and the most interesting cases are discussed below.</p><p>In most cases, no functional compensation is readily apparent in the eustigmatophyte genomic data. One example is the <italic>ilvH</italic> gene inferred to have been lost in the eustigmatophyte stem lineage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The IlvH protein is a regulator of acetohydroxyacid synthase, an enzyme coded for by the <italic>ilvB</italic> gene (present in eustigmatophyte pt genomes) and catalysing the committed step of the branched amino acid biosynthesis. It was previously noted that the <italic>ilvH</italic> gene is likewise absent from the <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> nuclear (and mt) genomes (<xref rid="evz004-B54" ref-type="bibr">Starkenburg et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>), and we now extend this observation to eustigmatophytes as a whole. Similarly, neither of the losses specific for different eustigmatophyte subgroups, except for <italic>acpP</italic> (see the next section), seem to have been compensated by emergence of nucleus-encoded pt-targeted versions of the respective proteins, suggesting genuine lineage-specific simplification of the plastidial functioning. For example, the loss of the <italic>psbZ</italic> gene in the Eustigmataceae group indicates a change in the antenna&#x02013;core interface of the photosystem II (see <xref rid="evz004-B61" ref-type="bibr">Wei et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>). Another case of photosystem II simplification likely occurred due to apparent pseudogenization of the <italic>psb28</italic> gene in <italic>Vischeria</italic> sp. CAUP Q 202 and the lack of a homologous gene in the nuclear genome of this organism (see <xref rid="evz004-B62" ref-type="bibr">Weisz et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). This is in contrast to some diatoms, which have been reported to exhibit a nuclear gene encoding a pt-targeted Psb28 homolog, in addition to the standard Psb28 encoded by the pt genome (<xref rid="evz004-B24" ref-type="bibr">Jiroutov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2010</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>syfB</italic> gene, another gene probably lost in the eustigmatophyte stem lineage, encodes the beta subunit of a dimeric plastidial phenylalanyl-tRNA synthetase, that is, a protein mediating a function essential for plastidial translation. However, it has been retained in only some ochrophytes, together with the alpha subunit encoded by a nuclear cyanobacteria-derived <italic>syfH</italic> gene (<xref rid="evz004-B47" ref-type="bibr">Ruck et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="evz004-B17" ref-type="bibr">Gile et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>). A possible transfer of the <italic>syfB</italic> gene into the eustigmatophyte nuclear genome was ruled out by our searches of available genome and transcriptome data, which also demonstrated the lack of the nuclear <italic>syfH</italic> gene in this group. We thus predict that like in plants or <italic>syfB</italic>/<italic>H</italic>-lacking diatoms (<xref rid="evz004-B17" ref-type="bibr">Gile et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), the production of phe-tRNA in the eustigmatophyte plastid is ensured by dual targeting of the monomeric mitochondrial phenylalanyl-tRNA synthetase (<xref rid="evz004-T2" ref-type="table">table&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>In contrast to the missing pt genes discussed so far, several others do have equivalents in eustigmatophyte nuclear genomes that encode proteins evidently dedicated to function in the pt as likely compensatory devices. Thus, all eustigmatophytes investigated complement the missing pt gene for the catalytic (beta) subunit of ferredoxin-thioredoxin reductase (<italic>ftrB</italic>) by a nucleus-encoded isoform exhibiting a clear N-terminal bipartite pt-targeting signal (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). To understand the origin of this nuclear gene, we inferred a tree of the FtrB family using a broad sample of sequences from eukaryotes and their most similar bacterial homologs (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S15</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). FtrB sequences are short (providing only 94 reliably aligned amino acid positions), so the inferred phylogeny of the family needs to be interpreted with caution. However, the tree suggests that the nuclear FtrB genes in ochrophytes are likely derived from two different sources. One group, including genes from diatoms, bolidophytes, pelagophytes, and dictyochophytes, that is, Diatomista (see <xref rid="evz004-B8" ref-type="bibr">Derelle et&#x000a0;al. 2016</xref>), is contained in a well-supported clade together with nuclear FtrB genes from a variety of algal (and plant) lineages with both primary and secondary plastids. This suggests that the pt <italic>ftrB</italic> gene missing from all Diatomista studied (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary tables S2 and S3</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) was replaced by a nuclear version gained by HGT from another algal lineage (although its exact identity cannot be resolved at present). The second ochrophyte nuclear <italic>ftrB</italic> gene group is restricted to eustigmatophytes, but it seems to be specifically related to nuclear genes from the &#x0201c;chrompodellid&#x0201d; algae <italic>Chromera velia</italic> and <italic>Vitrella brassicaformis</italic> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S15</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This is curious in light of a previous hypothesis that these algae obtained their plastid via a higher-order endosymbiosis of an ochrophyte alga (<xref rid="evz004-B49" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2015</xref>), possibly a specific relative of eustigmatophytes (<xref rid="evz004-B51" ref-type="bibr">Sobotka et&#x000a0;al. 2017</xref>). The origin of the nuclear eustigmatophyte (and secondarily chrompodellid) <italic>ftrB</italic> gene cannot be decided with confidence from the data available, but its branching next to the pt <italic>ftrB</italic> from <italic>Phaeomonas parva</italic> (a pinguiophyte) suggests that it may simply result from endosymbiotic gene transfer (EGT) of the pt <italic>ftrB</italic> into the nucleus in the eustigmatophyte lineage.</p><p>An interesting situation was encountered when we investigated the case of the <italic>rpl24</italic> gene, which was lost by eustigmatophytes uniquely among all ochrophytes studied so far. This gene encodes the L24 protein, a conserved component of the large ribosomal subunit likely important for the functionality of the plastidial ribosome. However, searches of the eustigmatophyte nuclear genomic data returned only an L24 homolog that carries an apparent mitochondrion-localization signal (data not shown), ruling out the possibility that the <italic>rpl24</italic> absence is compensated for by a nuclear copy of the gene. We instead noticed that all eustigmatophytes investigated encode in their nuclear genome two different paralogs of the ribosomal L26 protein that is a part of the cytosolic large ribosomal subunit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F4">fig.&#x000a0;4</xref>). Significantly, one of the paralogs carries an N-terminal extension with characteristics of the typical ochrophyte bipartite pt-targeting signal and hence is likely localized in the eustigmatophyte plastid (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). The eukaryotic L26 protein is in fact an evolutionary and functional equivalent of the eubacterial (and hence plastidial and mt) L24 protein, as they both represent the same ortholog family (called uL24 according to the unified nomenclature of ribosomal proteins; <xref rid="evz004-B3" ref-type="bibr">Ban et&#x000a0;al. 2014</xref>). We thus propose that in eustigmatophytes the original plastid-encoded eubacterial L24 protein was functionally replaced by a newly evolved nucleus-encoded copy of the eukaryotic L26 protein. Interestingly, a similar replacement was recently observed in the plastid of euglenophytes (<xref rid="evz004-B67" ref-type="bibr">Z&#x000e1;honov&#x000e1; et&#x000a0;al. 2018</xref>), suggesting that there are no serious mechanical obstacles to accommodate the eukaryotic L26 protein into the context of the eubacterial ribosome.
</p><fig id="evz004-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 4.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;A novel pt-targeted paralog of the ribosomal protein L26 in eustigmatophytes. The ML tree was inferred from an alignment of 115 amino acid position using IQ-TREE v1.6.5 and the optimal substitution model selected by the program (LG + I + &#x00393;4). Bootstrap values &#x0003c;75 are omitted from the figure. The tree displayed unveils the existence of a separate clade of L26-related sequences encoded by nuclear genomes of all eustigmatophytes investigated and possessing an N-terminal extension fitting the structure of a bipartite pt-targeting presequence (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S4</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This clade is clearly separated from conventional L26 proteins lacking the N-terminal targeting sequence and expected to function as components of the cytosolic ribosomes, as well as from the presumably independently evolved group of pt-targeted L26 proteins from euglenophytes. The tree was arbitrarily rooted between sequences from Archaea and eukaryotes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz004f4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>A plastid-Targeted Protein Encoded by a <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic>-Derived Gene in Eustigmatophytes</title><p>Based on the survey of eustigmatophyte pt genomes reported in this study, the current best estimate of the timing of the <italic>ebo</italic> operon gain by the eustigmatophyte pt genome lineage is an exclusive common ancestor of the Eustigmataceae group and Monodopsidaceae (see above). This would mean that bacteria of the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage might have started to infect eustigmatophytes only after the emergence and initial diversification of the host algal group. However, a new exciting finding suggests a different scenario. We came across it when trying to explain what allowed most Eustigmatales to lose the <italic>acpP</italic> gene, which encodes ACP essential for plastidial fatty acid biosynthesis. It turned out that not only the species devoid of the pt <italic>acpP</italic> gene but all eustigmatophytes possess a nucleus-encoded ACP homolog with an obvious N-terminal bipartite pt-targeting signal (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). This suggests functional redundancy conducive to the loss of the pt-encoded copy in eustigmatophytes (which happened at least four times independently; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F2">fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>Strikingly, when used as queries against the nr protein sequence database at NCBI, the eustigmatophyte nuclear plastid-targeted ACP (ptACP) proteins gave as their best hit an ACP protein from <italic>P. trachydisci</italic>. We therefore carried out a phylogenetic analysis of a broad selection of ACP sequences, which showed that the eustigmatophyte ptACP and the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> ACP indeed form a clade well separated from other ACP sequences (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S16</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online). Specific relationship between the eustigmatophyte ptACP and the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> ACP is further supported by a shared unique insertion absent from any other ACP homologs (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>), making it unlikely that the eustigmatophyte ptACP and the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> ACP branch together due to an artifact caused by their admittedly divergent nature. None of the ACP proteins encoded by nuclear genomes of other ochrophyte classes are related to the eustigmatophyte/<italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> clade. Some of them belong to a group represented in many other eukaryotes and comprising ACP presumably targeted to the mitochondrion, whereas others also bear predicted plastid-targeting presequences (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary table S5</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online) but correspond to apparently independent acquisitions from different bacterial groups or (in the case of phaeophytes) are likely derived by EGT from the original pt <italic>acpP</italic> gene (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="evz004-F5">fig.&#x000a0;5</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary fig. S16</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online).
</p><fig id="evz004-F5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label><sc>Fig</sc>. 5.</label><caption><p>&#x02014;Phylogenetic analysis of ACP sequences. The ML tree was inferred from an alignment of 70 amino acid position using IQ-TREE v1.6.5 and the optimal substitution model selected by the program (LG + I + &#x00393;4). Bootstrap values &#x0003c;75 are omitted from the figure. Four ACP types are distinguished by different abbreviations: ACP, bacterial; AcpP, plastid genome encoded; ptACP, nucleus-encoded plastid targeted; mtACP, nucleus-encoded mitochondrion targeted. For simplicity, several clades were collapsed and their composition is shown on the right. Tip labels of sequences from bacteria, except those from Rickettsiales, are omitted for simplicity, the respective branches are rendered in gray. Note the strongly supported relationship between ACP from <italic>P. trachydisci</italic> and the eustigmatophyte ptACP. Full version of the tree is provided as <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">supplementary figure S16</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Material</xref> online. The right part of the figure shows a segment of a multiple alignment of the ACP sequences included into the phylogenetic analysis (listed in the same vertical order as they appear in the tree) that includes a characteristic insertion shared by ACP from <italic>P. trachydisci</italic> and ptACP from eustigmatophytes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="evz004f5"/></fig><p>Thus, it is highly likely that the ptACP gene in the eustigmatophyte nucleus and the ACP gene in <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> share a specific ancestor, implying an HGT event between the two organismal lineages. Three observations lead us to favor the transfer being from the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage to eustigmatophytes. First, the eustigmatophyte nuclear ACP genes possess introns, so invoking eustigmatophytes as the donor lineage necessitate to postulate that the transfer into the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage must have happened before the acquisition of introns or that the transfer was mediated by a retrotranscribed intron-less copy of the eustigmatophyte gene. Second, the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage must have always possessed an ACP gene (encoding an essential component of the fatty acid biosynthesis machinery), whereas the eustigmatophyte nuclear ptACP gene, whatever its origin, is an evolutionary innovation initially redundant with the pt <italic>acpP</italic> gene. Third, the genomic context of the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> ACP gene is conserved with other Rickettsiales. Specifically, the ACP gene in these organisms is flanked by two genes encoding enzymes also involved in fatty acid biosynthesis, FabB (3-oxoacyl-[acyl-carrier-protein] synthase II) upstream and FabG (3-oxoacyl-[acyl-carrier protein] reductase) downstream. The <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> FabB and FabG genes are undeniably of rickettsiacean origin, so despite its considerable divergence, the ACP gene in between was also most likely vertically inherited by <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> from its bacterial ancestors rather than acquired horizontally from an external source. It is worth noting that the eustigmatophyte FabB and FabG proteins are encoded by genes unlinked to the ptACP gene and not specifically related to the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> homologs (data not shown).</p><p>Altogether, there is sufficient evidence to propose that the eustigmatophyte ptACP gene has been acquired from a relative of extant <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic>. The presence of the ptACP gene in all eustigmatophytes examined, including representatives of both principal eustigmatophyte clades (Eustigmatales and Goniochloridales) further implies that the transfer event must have happened before the radiation of extant eustigmatophytes. The apparent absence of this gene from noneustigmatophyte ochrophytes (judging admittedly from an incomplete sampling of the ochrophyte diversity) further suggests that the HGT event occurred only after the eustigmatophyte lineage had diverged from other ochrophytes, that is, that the recipient was a stem eustigmatophyte. This means that the affair between eustigmatophytes and <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> must have started earlier than evidenced so far, and that the whole crown eustigmatophyte group is evolutionarily influenced by the interaction with the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> endosymbiont.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The seven new plastid genome sequences reported in this study make eustigmatophytes one of the best sampled algal classes in terms of pt genomics. This is remarkable, given the fact that eustigmatophytes were for long considered an insignificant taxon and the knowledge of their biology still suffers from fundamental gaps. The wealth of the pt genome data enabled us to resolve phylogenetic relationships among main eustigmatophyte lineages, providing a useful framework for interpretation of the evolution of different eustigmatophyte traits. The improved sampling also enabled us to recognize some of the previously enigmatic eustigmatophyte genes as divergent homologs of known genes conserved in other taxa. The detailed reconstruction of the evolution of the eustigmatophyte pt gene complement provided interesting examples illustrating different events accompanying the organellar genome evolution: sequence divergence (nearly) beyond recognition, gene splitting, pseudogenization, complete gene loss, gene gain from external sources, and possibly de novo formation of truly novel genes. We also discovered examples of different configurations associated with loss of particular genes from the eustigmatophyte pt genomes&#x02014;apparent loss of the respective functionality as well as functional compensation by employing nuclear genes. The latter may have various origins, including EGT, duplication of pre-existing nuclear genes and HGT from external sources. The latter case, concerning the nuclear ACP gene, is particularly interesting, as it points to a very early beginning of coevolution of eustigmatophytes and bacteria of the <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> lineage. A systematic survey of eustigmatophyte nuclear genomes and of diverse <italic>Phycorickettsia</italic> representatives is now in order to understand the actual magnitude and significance of gene traffic between these two organismal groups.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>
<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary data</xref> are available at <italic>Genome Biology and Evolution</italic> online.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Data</label><media xlink:href="evz004_supp.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Pavel P&#x00159;ibyl (Institute of Botany, Czech Academy of Sciences) for growing the culture of <italic>Pseudellipsoidion edaphicum</italic> CAUP Q 401 for DNA isolation. This work was supported by the European Union&#x02019;s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program under the Marie Sklodowska-Curie grant agreement no. 642575; ERD Funds, project OPVVV CZ.02.1.01/0.0/0.0/16_019/0000759 (Centre for research of pathogenicity and virulence of parasites); Czech Science Foundation grant 18-13458S; the infrastructure grant &#x0201c;P&#x00159;&#x000ed;stroje IET&#x0201d; (CZ.1.05/2.1.00/19.0388); the project LO1208 of the National Feasibility Programme I of the Czech Republic; the National Science Foundation (grant no. DEB1145414); and the Arkansas INBRE program through a grant (P20 GM103429) from the National Institute of General Medical Sciences of the National Institutes of Health.</p></ack><sec><title>Footnote</title><p>
<bold>Data deposition:</bold> All newly reported nucleotide sequences were deposited at GenBank under the accessions <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="MK281411">MK281411</ext-link>&#x02013;<ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="MK281458">MK281458</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>Literature Cited</title><ref id="evz004-B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Alkatib</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>The contributions of wobbling and superwobbling to the reading of the genetic code</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e1003076.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166520</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Altschul</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein database search programs</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <volume>25</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>3389</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3402</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ban</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A new system for naming ribosomal proteins</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Struct Biol</source>. <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>169</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24524803</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bankevich</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>SPAdes: a new genome assembly algorithm and its applications to single-cell sequencing</article-title>. <source>J Comput Biol</source>. <volume>19</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>455</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>477</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22506599</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bolger</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Usadel</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2120</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capella-Gutierrez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silla-Martinez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gabaldon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>trimAl: a tool for automated alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>25</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1972</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1973</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19505945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Corteggiani Carpinelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Chromosome scale genome assembly and transcriptome profiling of <italic>Nannochloropsis gaditana</italic> in nitrogen depletion</article-title>. <source>Mol Plant</source><volume>7</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23966634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Derelle</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Timpano</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>A phylogenomic framework to study the diversity and evolution of Stramenopiles (=Heterokonts)</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>33</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2898</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27512113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Secondary plastids of stramenopiles</article-title>. <source>Adv Bot Res</source>. <volume>84</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B09"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>,</person-group> et al. 2017. Chimeric origins of ochrophytes and haptophytes revealed through an ancient plastid proteome. Elife 6:e23717.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<chapter-title>Eustigmatophyceae</chapter-title> In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slamovits</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name></person-group>, editors. <source>Handbook of the protists</source>.
<publisher-name>New York: Springer International Publishing</publisher-name> p. <fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>406</lpage>. </mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Predicting subcellular localization of proteins based on their N-terminal amino acid sequence</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <volume>300</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1005</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1016</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10891285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Emanuelsson</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>ChloroP, a neural network-based method for predicting chloroplast transit peptides and their cleavage sites</article-title>. <source>Protein Sci</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>978</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>984</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10338008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The diversity and phylogeny of the commercially important algal class Eustigmatophyceae including the new clade Goniochloridales</article-title>. <source>J Appl Phycol</source>. <volume>26</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1782</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Rediscovery of <italic>Tetra&#x000eb;driella subglobosa</italic> Pascher a member of the Eustigmatophyceae</article-title>. <source>Fottea</source><volume>17</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>96</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP.</given-names></name></person-group> 2004. A simple and rapid technique for the isolation of DNA from microalgae. J Phycol. 40(1):223&#x02013;225</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP.</given-names></name></person-group>, Hegewald E. 2013. <italic>Desmodesmus baconii</italic> (Chlorophyta), a new species with double rows of arcuate spines. Phycologia 52(6):565&#x02013;572.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>The phylogeny of the genus <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> (Monodopsidaceae, Eustigmatophyceae) with descriptions of <italic>N. australis</italic> sp. nov. and <italic>Microchloropsis</italic> gen. nov</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source><volume>54</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>552</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fu&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>LA.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Chloroplast phylogenomic data from the green algal order Sphaeropleales (Chlorophyceae, Chlorophyta) reveal complex patterns of sequence evolution</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>98</volume>:<fpage>176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>183</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26903036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gile</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moog</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Slamovits</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>UG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Archibald</surname><given-names>JM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Dual organellar targeting of aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases in diatoms and cryptophytes</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1728</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1742</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25994931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gitzendanner</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruhfel</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Plastid phylogenomic analysis of green plants: a billion years of evolutionary history</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source>. <volume>105</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>291</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29603143</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilcox</surname><given-names>LW.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<source>Algae</source>. <edition>2nd ed</edition>
<publisher-loc>San Francisco (CA</publisher-loc>):
<publisher-name>Benjamin Cummings</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocap</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kroth</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Armbrust</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mock</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Plastid proteome prediction for diatoms and other algae with secondary plastids of the red lineage</article-title>. <source>Plant J</source>. <volume>81</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>528</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25438865</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hallick</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bairoch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Proposals for the naming of chloroplast genes III. Nomenclature for open reading frames encoded in chloroplast genomes</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol Rep</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>S29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>S30</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hibberd</surname><given-names>DJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>Notes on the taxonomy and nomenclature of the algal classes Eustigmatophyceae and Tribophyceae (synonym Xanthophyceae)</article-title>. <source>Bot J Linn Soc</source>. <volume>82</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>119</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Knoll</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>CX</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Verbruggen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Plastid phylogenomics with broad taxon sampling further elucidates the distinct evolutionary origins and timing of secondary green plastids</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1523.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29367699</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jiroutov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ko&#x00159;en&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bowler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oborn&#x000ed;k</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>A gene in the process of endosymbiotic transfer</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source><volume>5</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e13234.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20949086</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Standley</surname><given-names>DM.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: improvements in performance and usability</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>772</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23329690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>The Marine Microbial Eukaryote Transcriptome Sequencing Project (MMETSP): illuminating the functional diversity of eukaryotic life in the oceans through transcriptome sequencing</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e1001889.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24959919</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Klicki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>The widely conserved <italic>ebo</italic> cluster is involved in precursor transport to the periplasm during scytonemin synthesis in <italic>Nostoc punctiforme</italic></article-title>. <source>MBio</source><volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e02266</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>e02218</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30482833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden Markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <volume>305</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kryvenda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rybalka</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friedl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Species distinctions among closely related strains of Eustigmatophyceae (Stramenopiles) emphasizing ITS2 sequence-structure data: <italic>eustigmatos</italic> and <italic>Vischeria</italic></article-title>. <source>Eur J Phycol</source>. <volume>53</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>491</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>K&#x000fc;ck</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meusemann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>FASconCAT: convenient handling of data matrices</article-title>. <source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source>. <volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1118</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20416383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langmead</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods.</source><volume>9</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388286</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lartillot</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rodrigue</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stubbs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richer</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>PhyloBayes MPI: phylogenetic reconstruction with infinite mixtures of profiles in a parallel environment</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>62</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>615</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23564032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Corguill&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Plastid genomes of two brown algae <italic>Ectocarpus siliculosus</italic> and <italic>Fucus vesiculosus</italic>: further insights on the evolution of red-algal derived plastids</article-title>. <source>BMC Evol Biol</source>. <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>253.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19835607</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Leliaert</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Chloroplast phylogenomic analyses reveal the deepest-branching lineage of the Chlorophyta, Palmophyllophyceae class. nov</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>25367.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27157793</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Assembly and transfer of iron-sulfur clusters in the plastid</article-title>. <source>Front Plant Sci</source>. <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>336.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29662496</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>SOAPdenovo2: an empirically improved memory-efficient short-read de novo assembler</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source><volume>1</volume>:<fpage>18</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23587118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>XN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Lipid production from <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic></article-title>. <source>Mar Drugs</source><volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>61.</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mago&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Salzberg</surname><given-names>SL.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>FLASH: fast length adjustment of short reads to improve genome assemblies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>27</volume>(<issue>21</issue>):<fpage>2957</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2963</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21903629</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Milne</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Using tablet for visual exploration of second-generation sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinformatics</source><volume>14</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>193</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>202</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22445902</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Taxonomic study of a new eustigmatophycean alga, <italic>Vacuoliviride crystalliferum</italic> gen. et sp. nov</article-title>. <source>J Plant Res</source>. <volume>128</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>257</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>von Haeseler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>IQ-TREE: a fast and effective stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Mol Biol Evol</source>. <volume>32</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>268</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25371430</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Nuclear monoploidy and asexual propagation of <italic>Nannochloropsis oceanica</italic> (Eustigmatophyceae) as revealed by its genome sequence</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source>. <volume>47</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1432</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27020366</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petsalaki</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bagos</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Litou</surname><given-names>ZI</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamodrakas</surname><given-names>SJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>PredSL: a tool for the N-terminal sequence-based prediction of protein subcellular localization</article-title>. <source>Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics</source><volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>48</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16689702</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pfitzinger</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weil</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pillay</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillemaut</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Codon recognition mechanisms in plant chloroplasts</article-title>. <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>. <volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>814</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2102858</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>P&#x00159;ibyl</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cep&#x000e1;k</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lukavsk&#x000fd;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ka&#x00161;t&#x000e1;nek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Zoosporogenesis morphology ultrastructure pigment composition and phylogenetic position of <italic>Trachydiscus minutus</italic> (Eustigmatophyceae Heterokontophyta)</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source>. <volume>48</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27009667</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Radakovits</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Draft genome sequence and genetic transformation of the oleaginous alga <italic>Nannochloropis gaditana</italic></article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>686.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22353717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ruck</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakov</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Theriot</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alverson</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Serial gene losses and foreign DNA underlie size and sequence variation in the plastid genomes of diatoms</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>6</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>654</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24567305</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schl&#x000f6;sser</surname><given-names>UG.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>SAG&#x02014;Sammlung von Algenkulturen at the University of G&#x000f6;ttingen Catalogue of strains</article-title>. <source>Bot Acta</source><volume>107</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>186</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Updating algal evolutionary relationships through plastid genome sequencing: did alveolate plastids emerge through endosymbiosis of an ochrophyte?</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>10134.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26017773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>A comparative analysis of mitochondrial genomes in eustigmatophyte algae</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>705</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>722</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26872774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sobotka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Extensive gain and loss of photosystem I subunits in chromerid algae photosynthetic relatives of apicomplexans</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>13214.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29038514</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Song</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>A novel chloroplast gene reported for flagellate plants</article-title>. <source>Am J Bot</source>. <volume>105</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>121</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29532931</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stamatakis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>RAxML version 8: a tool for phylogenetic analysis and post-analysis of large phylogenies</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source><volume>30</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>1312</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1313</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451623</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Starkenburg</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>A pangenomic analysis of the <italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> organellar genomes reveals novel genetic variations in key metabolic genes</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>212.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24646409</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Sequencing and analysis of the complete organellar genomes of Parmales, a closely related group to Bacillariophyta (diatoms)</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source>. <volume>62</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>896</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27091756</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tr&#x000e4;ger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Evolution from the prokaryotic to the higher plant chloroplast signal recognition particle: the signal recognition particle RNA is conserved in plastids of a wide range of photosynthetic organisms</article-title>. <source>Plant Cell</source><volume>24</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>4819</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4836</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23275580</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vieler</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Genome functional gene annotation and nuclear transformation of the heterokont oleaginous alga <italic>Nannochloropsis oceanica</italic> CCMP1779</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e1003064</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23166516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title><italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> genomes reveal evolution of microalgal oleaginous traits</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1004094.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24415958</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minh</surname><given-names>BQ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Susko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>AJ.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Modeling site heterogeneity with posterior mean site frequency profiles accelerates accurate phylogenomic estimation</article-title>. <source>Syst Biol</source>. <volume>67</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>216</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28950365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title><italic>Nannochloropsis</italic> plastid and mitochondrial phylogenomes reveal organelle diversification mechanism and intragenus phylotyping strategy in microalgae</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>534.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23915326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Structure of spinach photosystem II-LHCII supercomplex at 3.2&#x02009;&#x000c5; resolution</article-title>. <source>Nature</source><volume>534</volume>(<issue>7605</issue>):<fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27251276</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weisz</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Mass spectrometry-based cross-linking study shows that the Psb28 protein binds to cytochrome b559 in Photosystem II</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <volume>114</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2224</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2229</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28193857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Supermatrix data highlight the phylogenetic relationships of photosynthetic stramenopiles</article-title>. <source>Protist</source><volume>163</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>231</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22001261</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Evolution of the plastid genomes in diatoms</article-title>. <source>Adv Bot Res</source>. <volume>85</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>155</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yurchenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>A gene transfer event suggests a long-term partnership between eustigmatophyte algae and a novel lineage of endosymbiotic bacteria</article-title>. <source>ISME J</source>. <volume>12</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29880910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yurchenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;ev&#x0010d;&#x000ed;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strnad</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eli&#x000e1;&#x00161;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>The plastid genome of some eustigmatophyte algae harbours a bacteria-derived six-gene cluster for biosynthesis of a novel secondary metabolite</article-title>. <source>Open Biol</source>. <volume>6</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>160249.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27906133</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Z&#x000e1;honov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>Peculiar features of the plastids of the colourless alga <italic>Euglena longa</italic> and photosynthetic euglenophytes unveiled by transcriptome analyses</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>17012.</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30451959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<article-title>A completely reimplemented MPI Bioinformatics Toolkit with a new HHpred server at its core</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <volume>430</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2237</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2243</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29258817</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dorrell</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>,
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>Chimeric origins of ochrophytes and haptophytes revealed through an ancient plastid proteome</article-title>. <source>Elife</source><volume>6</volume>:<fpage>e23717</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28498102</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>A simple and rapid technique for the isolation of DNA from microalgae</article-title>. <source>J Phycol</source>. <volume>40</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>225</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="evz004-B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fawley</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hegewald</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Desmodesmus baconii (Chlorophyta), a new species with double rows of arcuate spines</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source>. <volume>52</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>565</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>572</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>